<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The operator for the teeth shewing how to preserve the teeth and gums from all the accidents they are subject to : with particular directions for childrens teeth : as also the description and use of the polican, never published before / by Charles Allen.</title>
            <author>Allen, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-06">2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08038068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08038068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A23630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1221:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The operator for the teeth shewing how to preserve the teeth and gums from all the accidents they are subject to : with particular directions for childrens teeth : as also the description and use of the polican, never published before / by Charles Allen.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Crook and Samuel Helsham for the author and are to be sold by Robert Thornton and by the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1686?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To which is annexed a physical discourse, wherein the reasons of the beating of the pulse, or pulsation of the arteries, together with those of the circulation of the blood are mechanically explained, which was never done before / by an unknown hand."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dentistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE OPERATOR For The TEETH: SHEWING How to Pre<U+017F>erve the Teeth and Gums from all the Accidents they are <U+017F>ubject to: With par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Directions for Childrens Teeth. As al<U+017F>o the De<U+017F>cription and U<U+017F>e of the <hi>POLICAN,</hi> Never Publi<U+017F>hed before. By <hi>CHARLES ALLEN;</hi> Profe<U+017F><U+017F>or of the <U+017F>ame.</p>
            <p>To which is Annexed A Phy<U+017F>ical Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, wherein the rea<U+017F>ons of the Beating of the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> or <hi>Pul<U+017F>ation</hi> of the <hi>Arteries,</hi> together with tho<U+017F>e of the circulation of the <hi>Blood,</hi> are mechanically Explained; which was never done before. By an Unknown Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Crook</hi> and <hi>Samuel Hel<U+017F>ham</hi> for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>Robert Thornton</hi> Book<U+017F>eller, at the <hi>Leather-Bottel</hi> in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> and by the Author at his own Lodging at Mr. <hi>Bani<U+017F>ter</hi>'s at the <hi>Smiths-Arms</hi> in <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ex-<U+017F>treet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:40751:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc><…></desc>
               </gap> Chri<U+017F>to P. D. Franc. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc><…></desc>
               </gap> Dom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40751:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HONOURABLE AND TRULY LEARNED The Phy<U+017F>itians, Chirurgions and Apothecaries Of the City of DUBLIN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen I <U+017F>ee your INDEFATIGABLE Care in procuring men (that without which all the World is nothing) HEALTH, the PRIMARY cau<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ole Foundation and Prop of Humane FELICITY; and how the experience of <U+017F>o many years manife<U+017F>ts to all men, by the happy <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of your Undertakings, and your great Charity to the Poor, that your private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions do corre<U+017F>pond admirably well with your external actions; and that all your indeavours are real and unfeigned: I am per<U+017F>waded, that whatever can in any wi<U+017F>e contribute to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of your mo<U+017F>t Noble and Generous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign, can't but be acceptable to you. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having with the <U+017F>ame pas<U+017F>ion, for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb facs="tcp:40751:3"/>
Advantage, compo<U+017F>ed the following <U+017F>mall Treati<U+017F>e, I take the liberty mo<U+017F>t humbly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent it You; that (as You are the be<U+017F>t JUDGES of the thing) <U+017F>o You may by Your Judicious and Impartial Cen<U+017F>ure of it, inform the World of its worth; that no per<U+017F>on may be deceiv'd in it. For my intentions in publi<U+017F>hing it, being to advance the common Good; if I thought it did contain any thing contrary to that DESIGN, I <U+017F>hou'd be the fir<U+017F>t that wou'd indeavour its <U+017F>uppres<U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p>But, GENTLEMEN, be<U+017F>ides the foregoing rea<U+017F>ons, which I had of offering You this fir<U+017F>t E<U+017F><U+017F>ay of mine, I did it al<U+017F>o to acquit my <U+017F>elf in <U+017F>ome mea<U+017F>ure of my Duty towards You; and to a<U+017F><U+017F>ure You further, that I am in all re<U+017F>pects,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
               <signed> Your Mo<U+017F>t Humble, Mo<U+017F>t Obedient, And Mo<U+017F>t Obliged Servant CHARLES ALLEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:40751:3"/>
            <head>THE OPERATOR FOR THE TEETH.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The PROEM.</head>
               <p>KNowing that it is the duty of every man, and e<U+017F>pecially of <U+017F>u h as live under a Civil Government, (where the general Intere<U+017F>t always includes the particular) to contribute as much as he can (in his own <U+017F>tation) to the publick Good<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and al<U+017F>o of what Importance it is to all men to be informed of tho<U+017F>e Benefits which by my Art they may enjoy; I am re<U+017F>ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to <U+017F>et down here what I think mo<U+017F>t convenient for every one to under<U+017F>tand concerning the pre<U+017F>ervation, and melioration of his own Teeth; A thing indeed of little e<U+017F>teem among mo<U+017F>t people, but in truth, of ine<U+017F>timable value for its many and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant con<U+017F>equences. However, in <U+017F>o doing, I <U+017F>hall acquit my <U+017F>elf of my duty towards God and Man: And provided my Indeavors prove but beneficial to others, (as certainly they will, if put in practice) it is all I de<U+017F>ire, caring very little what opinion the Criticks of <hi>Words</hi> and artificial <hi>Logick</hi> may have of me.</p>
               <p>Of what <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>tility this <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ndertaking of mine may be to every body, will appear by the <U+017F>equel of this Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e; whereof the
<pb facs="tcp:40751:4"/>
<U+017F>cope is to prevent the lo<U+017F>s of <hi>Teeth;</hi> the u<U+017F>e of which is <U+017F>o nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in the preparing of food, that the want of <U+017F>uch a help (if not <U+017F>upplied by <U+017F>trong di<U+017F><U+017F>olvents) hinders a true concoction of the Aliments in the Stomach; whence do proceed Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<U+017F>tions, and abundance of Crudities very noxious to the body of man; as being the <U+017F>eed of most of tho<U+017F>e innumerable Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and Infirmities, whereby life is not only made trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome to us, but al<U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderably <U+017F>horter than it would otherwi<U+017F>e be, which is <U+017F>o con<U+017F>onant to truth, that vulgar ob<U+017F>ervation it <U+017F>elf has turned it into a common Proverb: For they u<U+017F>e to <U+017F>ay of one who<U+017F>e Teeth are naturally thin, that he is <U+017F>hort-lv'd, whereof the rea<U+017F>on is, that <U+017F>uch per<U+017F>ons do not chew their meat well. Moreover, the lo<U+017F>s of Teeth renders the pronounciation both trouble<U+017F>ome to ones <U+017F>elf, and unintelligible to others. In a word, the corruption, and want of them, is as great a defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and of as much prejudice to one, as any thing what<U+017F>oever can be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:40751:4"/>
               <head>SECTION I. Of the Nature of the TEETH.</head>
               <p>WHat men are wont to call Science, or the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of any being, is by them commonly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into two <U+017F>everal parts: one whereof is termed <hi>Theoretical,</hi> and the other <hi>Practical.</hi> The fir<U+017F>t includes the rea<U+017F>ons and cau<U+017F>es of things, with the order and manner of their progre<U+017F>s in coming to be what they are. The <U+017F>econd regards only their Properties and Effects, and what they are actually in them<U+017F>elves, without inquiring how they come to be <U+017F>o made, or thus qualify'd. As for example of tho<U+017F>e two branches of Humane Learning, (in re<U+017F>pect to Phy<U+017F>ical matters) when Philo<U+017F>ophers go about to in<U+017F>pect the nature of the <hi>Load<U+017F>tone,</hi> they <U+017F>earch into its <hi>Origine,</hi> tracing out the <U+017F>everal cau<U+017F>es of its Formation, even to their <U+017F>ource or <U+017F>pring-head; from whence they draw arguments for the <U+017F>olution of all the <hi>Phenomena</hi> thereof; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Mariners con<U+017F>ider it only as a certain Stone that draws Iron to it <U+017F>elf, having the power of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating its properties to the <U+017F>aid Iron; and which, if not hindred (by its own gravity, or any other impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment) will always turn one of its <U+017F>ides towards the North, and another diametrically oppo<U+017F>ite to the fir<U+017F>t towards the South; which <U+017F>ufficeth them for the u<U+017F>e they make on't, in directing their cour<U+017F>es through the Sea, without caring what may be the cau<U+017F>e of <U+017F>o ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40751:5"/>
vertues in the <hi>Magnet.</hi> Either of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tituent parts of Knowledge being <U+017F>eparated from the other, cannot afford a full and <U+017F>atisfactory account of a thing: And therefore being about to treat of my Art, I <U+017F>hould by con<U+017F>equence begin with its <hi>Theory,</hi> and di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of the <hi>Elements, Principles,</hi> and fir<U+017F>t <hi>Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>Teeth;</hi> which make the Subject thereof, unfolding the rea<U+017F>ons of their con<U+017F>titution and frame, and how they come to have <U+017F>everal Roots, and to grow above the Gums; with what ever el<U+017F>e may be the cau<U+017F>e of their <U+017F>pecifical being; and thence pa<U+017F>s to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. But <U+017F>ome Con<U+017F>iderations obliging me to defer treating of the former <hi>Part,</hi> or <hi>Theorick,</hi> till a better opportunity, I de<U+017F>ign only to lay down in this Paper <U+017F>ome of the mo<U+017F>t principal <hi>Points</hi> relating to the other; namely, the Practical part of my <hi>Profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</hi> In doing which, although it would be enough for us to <U+017F>peak of things, as in the <U+017F>tate wherein we find them: yet for the <U+017F>atisfaction of the Reader, and out of a real de<U+017F>ire to <U+017F>erve him; we <U+017F>hall not de<U+017F>titute our Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of <U+017F>uch Rea<U+017F>ons as are nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for the well under<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ay. So that although this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate will be imperfect, as wanting many things, yet what it <U+017F>hall contain, will be as u<U+017F>eful and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous as if it were accompanied with all the re<U+017F>t. However, according to the method we have pre<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed our <U+017F>elves here, we are to proceed next to the con<U+017F>ideration of the Structure, and con<U+017F>titution or nature of the Tooth.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Analy<U+017F>ing</hi> the Tooth, its <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance is not found to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40751:5"/>
be uniform every where, but manife<U+017F>tly di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able into two different <U+017F>orts of make: one of them being harder, whiter, and of a finer texture; and the other <U+017F>ofter, more ob<U+017F>cure, and of a cour<U+017F>er compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ition. The fir<U+017F>t makes up the head of the Tooth, or that part of it that <U+017F>tands out naked above the Gums<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and the other its <U+017F>tump, or that part on't which is hidden within the <U+017F>aid Gums. The expo<U+017F>ed part of the Tooth con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts al<U+017F>o of two different Parts: To wit, its <U+017F>tony Cover or Ca<U+017F>e, and its inward <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the fir<U+017F>t is as it were an hard <hi>Perio<U+017F>teum,</hi> that inve<U+017F>ts the head of the Tooth on all <U+017F>ides, lying on it much after the <U+017F>ame manner that Enamel does upon Gold, or any other thing. This natural Enamel which I call the glo<U+017F>s of the Tooth, is of a far harder, whiter, more den<U+017F>e and lucid nature than the inward <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance lying under it: which for its <U+017F>everal u<U+017F>es may properly be compared to the <hi>Cuticula,</hi> or Scarf-skin, for like unto this it is bloodle<U+017F>s, and altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>titute of <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, <U+017F>erving to cover and defend the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, contained within the inward <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, from external injuries, and to render the Tooth more beautiful and <U+017F>trong. It has pores for the per<U+017F>piration of the excrements of the Tooth, which pores are not always of the <U+017F>ame figure, nor magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but vary almo<U+017F>t in every body. The <U+017F>aid glo<U+017F>s or <U+017F>tony <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance is likewi<U+017F>e very various in point of thickne<U+017F>s: from which differences, do ari<U+017F>e the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ity of its colour in <U+017F>everal men.</p>
               <p>The inward part of the head of the Tooth, though
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40751:6"/>
inferior to its cover or glo<U+017F>s in brightne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>olidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet its <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance is neverthele<U+017F>s much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, and clearer than that of the <U+017F>tump: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains two <U+017F>everal <U+017F>orts of pores, or <U+017F>mall channels, both of a conical figure, having their <hi>Ba<U+017F>es</hi> in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave <U+017F>uperficies</hi> of the Tooth, and their <hi>Apexes</hi> in the <hi>convex <U+017F>uperficies</hi> of the inward <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, immediately under its gla<U+017F><U+017F>y integument. Through <U+017F>ome of which channels the blood is carried by many and very <U+017F>mall <hi>Arterial</hi> Sprigs, from the middle of the Tooth to its extremity: and through the others the <U+017F>ame blood is <U+017F>ent back again from the <U+017F>aid extremity towards its middle, by <U+017F>ome <hi>capillary</hi> veins, as <U+017F>hall be <U+017F>aid here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>As to the root or <U+017F>tump of the Tooth, it is the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t, mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>oft, and porous portion of its whole <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance; and yet is clo<U+017F>er and harder than any other bone of the body, having al<U+017F>o two <U+017F>orts of channels, but of different <U+017F>ituation from one another: for <U+017F>ome of them have their Ba<U+017F>es (like tho<U+017F>e above de<U+017F>cribed) towards the cavity of the Tooth, and contain the branches of the Artery, that carry the blood quite through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Tooth, to the Gums, as <U+017F>hall be explained in its place; but the others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to any of tho<U+017F>e already mentioned, have their Ba<U+017F>es towards the external <U+017F>uperficies of the Tooth; the u<U+017F>e of which la<U+017F>t conduits, is to tran<U+017F>mit to the Gums the blood that is returned to the heart from the <hi>membrane</hi> that inve<U+017F>ts the cavity of the Tooth. This rooty part of the Tooth con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in the <U+017F>mall Teeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40751:6"/>
of a <U+017F>ingle body, and in the big ones is divided into two, three, or four branches, called roots or fangs: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the middle of each of the<U+017F>e fangs, there is a little channel that goes up to the head of the Tooth, where they are united together, and make but a <U+017F>ingle ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, whereinto are carried the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the Tooth, pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing fir<U+017F>t through the hollowne<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>tumps. Every Tooth has its particular cell or <U+017F>ocket within the <hi>Mandible,</hi> di<U+017F>tinct from all the re<U+017F>t (by a thin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the jaw-bone pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing between the Teeth, from one <U+017F>ide of the <U+017F>aid bone to the other) wherein mo<U+017F>t of its <U+017F>tump is comprehended, the re<U+017F>t being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compa<U+017F><U+017F>ed about with the Gums.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. Of the Alteration of the <hi>Teeth,</hi> with their <hi>Remedies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the con<U+017F>ideration of the nature of the Teeth, let us now pa<U+017F>s to that of the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>tep of their degenerating, or mutation. For the better under<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, we <U+017F>hall take notice, that as our body is <U+017F>o made by nature, that it wa<U+017F>ts continually by the dis<U+017F>ipation of <U+017F>ome Particles, <U+017F>eparating them<U+017F>elves from its Ma<U+017F>s, without intermis<U+017F>ion; (tran<U+017F>piring for the mo<U+017F>t part through the pores of the skin) and that if the<U+017F>e particles (which being divided from the whole, become <hi>Excrementitious)</hi> are kept too long within the body, (by rea<U+017F>on of the <hi>Opilation</hi> of the <U+017F>aid pores) it cau<U+017F>es Fevors, and great di<U+017F>orders in our blood, and vital as well as animal Functions: So likewi<U+017F>e from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40751:7"/>
the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Teeth are emitted certain <hi>Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viums</hi> through their pores, the tran<U+017F>piration of which being hindred, (by the ob<U+017F>truction of tho<U+017F>e invi<U+017F>ible pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages) the Teeth become liable to all tho<U+017F>e infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hereafter to be mentioned.</p>
               <p>The <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Tooth being rigid and inflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible, it cannot be <hi>Opilated</hi> by contraction, or a<U+017F>triction: as the skin u<U+017F>ually is but only by the intru<U+017F>ion of <U+017F>ome extraneous matter into its pores, or the incru<U+017F>tation of <U+017F>ome <U+017F>limy <U+017F>tuff upon its <U+017F>uperficies; which is done when we eat any thing of a glutinous nature, for then <U+017F>ome of its mo<U+017F>t vi<U+017F>cous parts do <U+017F>tick, and cleave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Teeth;</hi> and by the mixture of <U+017F>ome tartarious particles coming from the Lungs, the heat of the mouth, and a certain petrifick juice di<U+017F>tilling into the mouth, out of the <hi>Salival Ducts,</hi> is turned into a <U+017F>tone-like <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, commonly called the <U+017F>cales or <U+017F>curf of the <hi>Teeth:</hi> the<U+017F>e <U+017F>cales grow thicker and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er continually, and if let alone, will cover the <hi>Teeth</hi> all over, except ju<U+017F>t at the top were they grind one again<U+017F>t another.</p>
               <p>Having thus taken notice of the production of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>cales, let us now con<U+017F>ider of what ill con<U+017F>equences they may be to the <hi>Teeth.</hi> The fir<U+017F>t whereof is the <hi>Opilation</hi> of their pores, from whence proceed all the re<U+017F>t: for by that the exit of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Excrementitious</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles before mentitioned being hindred, it cau<U+017F>es them to <U+017F>tagnate within the body of the <hi>Tooth,</hi> and there corrupting, do corrode it by degrees; beginning fir<U+017F>t by the alteration of its colour from white to yellow,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40751:7"/>
and from yellow to black; and then follows the real decay of its <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <U+017F>aid humor is not only de<U+017F>tructive to the <hi>Teeth,</hi> but extends al<U+017F>o its malignity to the Gums; <U+017F>ome of its particles being <U+017F>ubtil enough (after a due <hi>fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)</hi> to pa<U+017F>s through the <U+017F>cales, and thence <U+017F>liding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Gums and the <hi>Teeth,</hi> they eat clear away the ligaments that tye them together, dividing them one from another to the very jaw-bone: which is <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proved by the <hi>excoriation</hi> and rawne<U+017F>s of the Gums, and their being <U+017F>o tender and loo<U+017F>e from the <hi>Teeth</hi> where ever <U+017F>uch <U+017F>cales are found; and e<U+017F>pecially if they be grown to a con<U+017F>iderable thickne<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>It happens <U+017F>ometimes that the u<U+017F>ual pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of this corrupted humor being <U+017F>topt by the <U+017F>cales, (when they are hard, and clo<U+017F>e enough) is thereby repercu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed, and made to take its cour<U+017F>e towards the middle of the <hi>Tooth,</hi> di<U+017F>charging it <U+017F>elf therein between the <hi>Concave <U+017F>uper<U+017F>icies</hi> of the <hi>Tooth,</hi> and the <hi>Tunicle</hi> inve<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <U+017F>ame; where it occa<U+017F>ions very great pains, and at la<U+017F>t by its fretting, and corro<U+017F>ive quality, gnaws and con<U+017F>umes quite away the <U+017F>aid <hi>membrane,</hi> as al<U+017F>o the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the <hi>Tooth;</hi> and then pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing out of the <U+017F>aid <hi>Tooth,</hi> it diffu<U+017F>es it <U+017F>elf through the <hi>Alveolus</hi> or <U+017F>ocket, where exerting its dangerous faculty, it de<U+017F>troys utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whatever cau<U+017F>es any <hi>connexion</hi> between the <hi>Teeth,</hi> the jaw-bone and the Gums, as the <hi>Perio<U+017F>teum,</hi> &amp;c. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which the <hi>Teeth</hi> do con<U+017F>equently fall out for the mo<U+017F>t part <U+017F>ound, and unaltered, except only in their colour, (which becomes yellowi<U+017F>h) by rea<U+017F>on that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40751:8"/>
afore<U+017F>aid <hi>Excrementitious</hi> Humour being at fir<U+017F>t diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted another way, did not <U+017F>tay long enough under the <U+017F>cales to occa<U+017F>ion in them a greater detriment: All which incommodities to obviate, keep only your Teeth clean from <U+017F>curf, or any foulne<U+017F>s; and if they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready clean, you need but to pre<U+017F>erve them as they are; but if not, get them to be made <U+017F>o by <U+017F>ome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>t in that Function; for otherwi<U+017F>e if you employ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body that is unskilful in it, you may chance to find the Remedy wor<U+017F>e than the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e; by rea<U+017F>on that not knowing the dangers attending <U+017F>uch an Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he may commit a great many and pernicious Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as the breaking of the <hi>Film</hi> that unites the Gums to the Teeth, the taking away of the glo<U+017F>s of the Teeth, &amp;c. Soon after which, the Tooth will lo<U+017F>e its natural lu<U+017F>tre, and become yellowi<U+017F>h, <U+017F>ubject to ake, and at la<U+017F>t wholly peri<U+017F>h away, the Gums being loo<U+017F>e and broken, will likewi<U+017F>e decay, and fall away from the Teeth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Your Teeth being once clean, you may pre<U+017F>erve them with this compo<U+017F>ition; Take <hi>Magi<U+017F>tery of Pearls, Powder of Coral,</hi> and <hi>Dragons-Blood,</hi> of each equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and as much <hi>Red-Ro<U+017F>e-water</hi> as will incorporate them together; and make the Compound of a mean con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, between hard and <U+017F>oft. I have to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a very excellent <hi>Dentifrice,</hi> which being u<U+017F>ed only once a week will keep the <hi>Teeth</hi> clean and white; and by the con<U+017F>tant u<U+017F>ing of it, fetch up their colour, if lo<U+017F>t; (tho in a con<U+017F>iderable mea<U+017F>ure) this is the <U+017F>ame that in my <hi>Bills</hi> (to keep my Ma<U+017F>ters term, tho improper,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40751:8"/>
as he well knows him<U+017F>elf,) I call an <hi>Opiat<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. Of the Corruption of the <hi>Teeth,</hi> with their Remedies<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is Annexed the De<U+017F>cription and <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>e of the <hi>Polican.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving in the former Section con<U+017F>idered the <hi>Teeth,</hi> as at the beginning of their decay, in <U+017F>uch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as tho they <U+017F>uffer <U+017F>ome light change in their accidents, yet their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, form and proportion remaining <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame, is only called alteration; that is, in a <U+017F>tate wherein indeed they are invironed, and a<U+017F><U+017F>aulted by their greate<U+017F>t enemies, but yet in a capacity of being re<U+017F>cued and pre<U+017F>erved from their harms. But now we <U+017F>hall con<U+017F>ider them as overcome by all tho<U+017F>e threatning evils, and really corrupted; in which ca<U+017F>e, all that can be done, is to prevent their total ruine.</p>
               <p>And as there are <U+017F>ome not <U+017F>o far gone, but that they may <U+017F>till do good <U+017F>ervice, if timely helped, we are to u<U+017F>e our utmo<U+017F>t indeavours to do it; which to effect, we <U+017F>hall in the fir<U+017F>t place clear their out<U+017F>ide from all foulne<U+017F>s, and then with a proper In<U+017F>trument <U+017F>crape off whatever is rotten within, wa<U+017F>hing them very well afterwards with <U+017F>ome convenient liquid, to <U+017F>cour and <U+017F>mooth away what the In<U+017F>trument may leave behind: and then if the Tooth be <U+017F>o hollow that it may be <U+017F>topt, it mu<U+017F>t be fill'd up with <U+017F>uch ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients as are neither corro<U+017F>ive, nor ill ta<U+017F>ted, and of a con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence firm enough to be u<U+017F>ed in the <U+017F>ame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40751:9"/>
as the <hi>Teeth</hi> are, and to keep from wa<U+017F>ting for a con<U+017F>iderable time; but if the <hi>Tooth</hi> rots every way equally, <U+017F>o that there is no cavity left, wherein any thing can keep fa<U+017F>t, it mu<U+017F>t only be kept clean, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care after every meal to pick out any meat that may get into it, and then wa<U+017F>h it very well with fair water; for if you neglect <U+017F>o to do, the corruption of the rotten <hi>Tooth</hi> will fall upon the others, and <U+017F>o infect all the re<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>With the<U+017F>e precautions, I would advi<U+017F>e every one to keep his <hi>Teeth</hi> as long as he can, although they were rotten to the very Gums, provided only they do not ake, by rea<U+017F>on that their <U+017F>tumps filling up their <U+017F>ock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, <U+017F>erve (like <U+017F>o many wedges) to keep the others <U+017F>treight and firm in their places; but if they are very bad, and withal <U+017F>ubject to ake, it is better to have them out, le<U+017F>t they <U+017F>hould occa<U+017F>ion an ill habit in the Gums, that might be hurtful to the <U+017F>ound ones.</p>
               <p>The Drawing out of <hi>Teeth</hi> is practi<U+017F>ed by a great many, but perhaps under<U+017F>tood but of very few; and I am <U+017F>ure that there is a great deal more danger in the Drawing of a <hi>Tooth,</hi> (e<U+017F>pecially out of the lower Jaw, than mo<U+017F>t people are commonly aware of. It is an Operation that requires to be performed with great care and circum<U+017F>pection, and not <U+017F>o ra<U+017F>hly as it is commonly done.</p>
               <p>But as the greate<U+017F>t difficulty of this Bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s lies in under<U+017F>tanding the make, and application of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truments that are imploy'd about the Drawing of <hi>Teeth;</hi> I <U+017F>hall (for the benefit of <hi>Practitioners,</hi> as well
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40751:9"/>
as of tho<U+017F>e that will be their <hi>Patients)</hi> <U+017F>ubjoyn here, the de<U+017F>cription and u<U+017F>e of the <hi>Polican;</hi> which is one of the be<U+017F>t of them.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The De<U+017F>cription and <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>e of the Polican.</head>
                  <p>THe Con<U+017F>truction, and u<U+017F>ual <U+017F>hape of the <hi>Polican,</hi> is a thing <U+017F>o well known by every body, that it wou'd be needle<U+017F>s to in<U+017F>i<U+017F>t at all upon it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without lo<U+017F>ing time in <U+017F>uch <U+017F>uperfluous Di<U+017F>cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, we <U+017F>hall here take notice of <U+017F>ome other things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the <U+017F>aid In<U+017F>trument, more material and u<U+017F>eful: as the due proportion that its parts ought to have, con<U+017F>idered in them<U+017F>elves, and in re<U+017F>pect of each other.</p>
                  <p>In the fir<U+017F>t place then, (<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing that you know the <U+017F>tuff wherewithal it mu<U+017F>t be made, which ought to be a tough <U+017F>teel, or <U+017F>teel and iron together) let the tree of the <hi>Polican</hi> be about four inches long, and <U+017F>o perforated, that the di<U+017F>tance betwixt the centre of the hole (wherein goes the pin<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> upon which are fa<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the two branches) and one of the extremities, be a line greater than the other. Let one of the two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches be two lines longer than the other; let al<U+017F>o each claw be three lines long. And finally, let the di<U+017F>tance between the bol<U+017F>ter, or <U+017F>emicircle of the longe<U+017F>t <U+017F>ide of the tree, be two lines. And you will have four di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances between the claws and the bol<U+017F>ters, which is <U+017F>ufficient to draw all <U+017F>orts of <hi>Teeth.</hi> For with the fir<U+017F>t, which is of two lines, you may draw the <hi>Inci<U+017F>ores<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40751:10"/>
With the <U+017F>econd, of three lines, you may draw the <hi>Ganini.</hi> With the third, of four lines, the <hi>Double</hi> and <hi>Treble Teeth.</hi> And with the fourth, of five lines, the <hi>Quadruple</hi> ones.</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>Polican</hi> being thus made, if you have a mind to u<U+017F>e it, you mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>o apply the Claw to the in<U+017F>ide of the <hi>Tooth</hi> you intend to pull out, that its branch may <U+017F>tand exactly upon the middle of the <U+017F>aid <hi>Tooth,</hi> gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaning your Bol<U+017F>ter upon the next to it, the better to take your mea<U+017F>ures; and then draw the <hi>Tooth</hi> out. But take heed you do not draw <hi>obliquely,</hi> but in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect line from the <hi>Tooth</hi> outwardly; for in drawing laterally, you might chance <U+017F>o to force the <hi>Tooth</hi> to be drawn, upon the next to it, that you wou'd draw them both together, or at lea<U+017F>t loo<U+017F>en very much the <U+017F>ound one, and put a far greater force upon the other in drawing it, than is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary. Which wou'd occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion an infinitely greater pain to the <hi>Patient,</hi> than if you had done it rightly.</p>
                  <p>Thus much have I thought fit to tell you concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature and u<U+017F>e of the <hi>Polican;</hi> which if you ob<U+017F>erve punctually, you need never fear the Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well of any <hi>Tooth.</hi> As for the re<U+017F>t of the In<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now in u<U+017F>e, with <U+017F>everal others of my own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, I <U+017F>hall give you the particular De<U+017F>cription, and u<U+017F>e of every one of them in the next Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of this Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e; if you think this worthy of your acceptance<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40751:10"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. Of the Re<U+017F>tauration of the Teeth.</head>
               <p>WHen our decay'd <hi>Teeth</hi> are <U+017F>o far gone before we think of any Remedy for their pre<U+017F>erva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that whatever we can do, proves but fruitle<U+017F>s<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> And that notwith<U+017F>tanding all our be<U+017F>t indeavours, they peri<U+017F>h, and rot quite away; or that <U+017F>ome into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pain has made us to draw them; we are not yet to de<U+017F>pair, and e<U+017F>teem our <U+017F>elves <hi>toothle<U+017F>s</hi> for all the re<U+017F>t of our life: the lo<U+017F>s indeed is great, but not irreparable; there is <U+017F>till <U+017F>ome help for it, the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral want may be <U+017F>upplied artificially, and herein Art imitates Nature <U+017F>o <hi>naifly,</hi> that when the <hi><U+017F>uccedaneous</hi> Teeth (if I may <U+017F>o <U+017F>peak) are well <U+017F>et in, they cannot be di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>hed from the natural ones, (neither in colour, firmne<U+017F>s, nor proportion) but by them that know of it. Being thus exactly fitted to their place, they will keep the next to them, and by con<U+017F>equence all the re<U+017F>t of that Jaw abundantly firmer and <U+017F>tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than they would otherwi<U+017F>e be.</p>
               <p>The Advantages that may be attributed to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial <hi>Teeth,</hi> are many; as that they keep the others fa<U+017F>t, as we <U+017F>aid ju<U+017F>t now, that they are of a great orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and help pronounciation extremely, &amp;c. But all that is with a <hi>Provi<U+017F>o,</hi> that they be well made, and according to the be<U+017F>t Art; for otherwi<U+017F>e they might prove quite contrary.</p>
               <p>Be<U+017F>ides this Artificial way of repairing the lo<U+017F>s of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40751:11"/>
                  <hi>Teeth,</hi> there is another that may be called Natural; which is done by taking out the rotten <hi>Teeth</hi> or <U+017F>tumps, and putting in their places <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ound ones, drawn immediately after out of <U+017F>ome poor body's head: which thing (tho difficult) I know to be fea<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough, not only by my own rea<U+017F>on that tells me <U+017F>o, but by experience it <U+017F>elf, as (to <U+017F>ay no more at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent) may be in<U+017F>tanced in the ca<U+017F>e of a certain Lady, who thinking to have <hi>two Teeth</hi> growing one on the top of another, came one day to my Ma<U+017F>ter to have one of them Drawn: my Ma<U+017F>ter told her that they were not two di<U+017F>tinct <hi>Teeth,</hi> but only a double one; but the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being not <U+017F>atisfied with this, de<U+017F>ired him to take out the <hi>Tooth</hi> <U+017F>he had told him of, let it be what it would. The <hi>Tooth</hi> being drawn out, and proving as my Ma<U+017F>ter had <U+017F>aid, it was quickly <U+017F>et again into the Jaw; and with the u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome convenient and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Remedies, became in few weeks to be as firm again<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> as any of the re<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>And yet although the event of this particular had not proved <U+017F>o pro<U+017F>perous as it did; its ill <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s would not de<U+017F>troy in me the po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of <U+017F>uch a tran<U+017F>plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or <hi>Inoculation</hi> of <hi>Teeth:</hi> (if I may be permitted to u<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch terms) that was not the only motive I had to believe it; and I have not in<U+017F>erted the Story of it here as an Argument to prove invincibly what I <U+017F>ay, but only as a proper Example to render probable to others what I know to be true. However, I do not like that method of drawing <hi>Teeth</hi> out of <U+017F>ome folks heads, to put them into others, both for its being too
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40751:11"/>
inhumane, and attended with too many difficulties; and then neither could this be called the re<U+017F>taurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Teeth,</hi> <U+017F>ince the reparation of one, is the ruine of another; it is only robbing of <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul.</hi> But if in<U+017F>tead of humane <hi>Teeth,</hi> there is u<U+017F>e made of tho<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome <hi>Brutes,</hi> as <hi>Dogs, Sheep,</hi> &amp;c. In <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e I do not only approve of it as lawful and facile, but do al<U+017F>o e<U+017F>teem it as very profitable and advantageous; only care is to be had, that the thing be undertaken, and carried on by one that at lea<U+017F>t knows <U+017F>omething of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and has a right <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of the thing to be done, being furni<U+017F>hed with whatever is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in an Operation of that nature.</p>
               <p>And that (if my Opinion may be any wi<U+017F>e <U+017F>ervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in <U+017F>uch an Attempt) I may contribute <U+017F>omething towards the improvement of <U+017F>o u<U+017F>eful an Invention; I think one is, to proceed in it <U+017F>omewhat after this manner. Fir<U+017F>t, I would chu<U+017F>e an Animal who<U+017F>e <hi>Teeth</hi> <U+017F>hould come neare<U+017F>t to tho<U+017F>e of the <hi>Patient;</hi> as a <hi>Dog,</hi> a <hi>Sheep,</hi> a <hi>Goat,</hi> or a <hi>Baboon,</hi> &amp;c. and having tied his legs together, I would fa<U+017F>ten his head in <U+017F>ome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient place, <U+017F>o that he might not <U+017F>tir in the lea<U+017F>t, and by <U+017F>ome proper means keep his mouth open as long as I <U+017F>hould have occa<U+017F>ion: that done, I would open the Gums round about the <hi>Tooth</hi> to be taken out of his head, not only to the very Jaw-bone, but as far between the <U+017F>aid Bone and the Tooth, as the fine<U+017F>t In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trument could go, leaving a very little portion of the Gums about it; and then having u<U+017F>ed the <U+017F>ame cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<U+017F>pection, in dividing the Patients Tooth from the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40751:12"/>
Gums, and the Jaw-bone, I would draw it forth, and put immediately in its place that of of the Brute; fa<U+017F>tning it very well and <U+017F>treight between the other Teeth: and then with the u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>uitable Remedies, I do not que<U+017F>tion in the lea<U+017F>t but that it would unite to the Gums and Jaw-bone, and in a little time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as fa<U+017F>t as any of the others: which performance might properly be termed the natural Re<U+017F>tauration, or <hi>Renovation</hi> of Humane Teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. Of the <hi>Tooth-ake,</hi> Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s of the <hi>Teeth,</hi> and decay of the <hi>Gums;</hi> with their Remedies.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Tooth-Ake</hi> is occa<U+017F>ioned many and very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways, but that I may render what I have to <U+017F>ay upon it, as per<U+017F>picuous and intelligible as I can; I think it very convenient we <U+017F>hould take a <U+017F>pecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that come into the Tooth, and of their re<U+017F>pective Functions. The fir<U+017F>t and chiefe<U+017F>t whereof is an Artery, who<U+017F>e Office is to bring dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly from the heart that hot and <U+017F>pirituous blood, out of which (although it is not the general Opinion) the Tooth is at fir<U+017F>t made, (as well as the re<U+017F>t of the whole body) and ever after pre<U+017F>erved and repaired by the <U+017F>upply of nouri<U+017F>hment, and vital principles it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords continually: To this effect the whole Artery divides it <U+017F>elf into an infinity of <U+017F>mall branches, which being di<U+017F><U+017F>eminated throughout the whole <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Tooth, di<U+017F>tribute to each part as much of their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40751:12"/>
blood as is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to make up the ince<U+017F><U+017F>ant lo<U+017F>s they are <U+017F>ubject to; and the re<U+017F>t is returned through innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable hair-like veins into the great ones, and thence to the heart again, but in two different manners: for the <U+017F>uperfluous part of that portion of the blood, that is carried by the <hi>Capillary</hi> Arteries to that part of the Tooth <U+017F>tanding above the Gums, is <U+017F>ent back again through <U+017F>ome <hi>Capillary</hi> veins towards the middle of the Tooth; where uniting together, they make but a <U+017F>ingle channel; and this is it we commonly call the vein of the Tooth, which we <U+017F>hall here take for its <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ve<U+017F><U+017F>el. But the remainder of the blood, that goes to the relief of that part of the Tooth that is within the Gums, pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing quite through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Tooth, is carried by the <hi>Capillary</hi> veins to the veins of the Gums, Checks, and Lips; and hence it is that whatever pain is at any time occa<U+017F>ioned in any of tho<U+017F>e parts, (either by brui<U+017F>e, exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive heat, or cold, &amp;c.) comes to be <U+017F>oon after communicated to the Teeth.</p>
               <p>The Third and La<U+017F>t Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el of the Teeth is a Nerve, one of the extremities whereof is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panded through the <hi>Membrane</hi> that inve<U+017F>ts the cavity of the Tooth, and that, that contains its Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els; and the other is rooted in the Brain, from whence it takes its <hi>Origine,</hi> and where the Animal <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> being elaborated, are thence <U+017F>ent by the Nerves to all the parts of the body, to admini<U+017F>ter <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, and the cau<U+017F>e of motion to them, &amp;c. although in <U+017F>ome, (as the Teeth) the faculty of motion is not exerci<U+017F>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40751:13"/>
From this con<U+017F>ideration of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the Tooth, we may gather the following rea<U+017F>ons of its Dolour; As fir<U+017F>t, that if either through the too great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or ebulition of the blood, the Artery is <U+017F>o dilated and <U+017F>woln, that it fills up the hole at the end of the <U+017F>tumps where it enters the <hi>Tooth,</hi> and con<U+017F>equently <U+017F>o compre<U+017F><U+017F>es the vein going out the <U+017F>ame way, that the circulation of the <hi>Blood</hi> is thereby hindred; the continual flowing in of the <hi>blood</hi> will extremely puff up, and di<U+017F>tend the <hi>membrane</hi> that contains the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and con<U+017F>equently cau<U+017F>e a great pain in the <hi>Tooth,</hi> which will la<U+017F>t till either the <hi>preternatural</hi> <U+017F>tate of the <hi>Blood</hi> be changed, or that the <hi>Arteriols</hi> which we have <U+017F>aid to pa<U+017F>s quite through the rooty part of the <hi>Tooth</hi> be <U+017F>o <U+017F>tretched and widened, that by them the <hi>Blood</hi> may be di<U+017F>charged into the Gums, Cheeks and Lips; where it will then cau<U+017F>e a <U+017F>welling, greater or le<U+017F><U+017F>er, according to the quantity of the <U+017F>uperfluous <hi>Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if at the beginning of this di<U+017F>order, when the Vein is fir<U+017F>t impeded in its <hi>Function,</hi> the motion of the <hi>Blood</hi> is <U+017F>o rapid, and its influx into the Tooth <U+017F>o im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous, that before it can make its way through the <U+017F>mall <hi>Arterial</hi> Twigs into the Gums, it does extremely extend the coats of the <hi>Artery,</hi> the <hi>Inter<U+017F>tices</hi> between their <hi>Fibres</hi> will thereby become wide enough to give pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to <U+017F>ome of the thinne<U+017F>t parts of the <hi>Blood;</hi> which gathering at the end of the root, between the out<U+017F>ide of the <hi>Artery,</hi> and the common Coat inve<U+017F>ting all the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, will there putrifie, and cau<U+017F>e a great and very la<U+017F>ting pain in the Tooth; during which,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40751:13"/>
if the Tooth be drawn, the <U+017F>aid gathering will appear at the end of its <U+017F>tump like a little Bladder.</p>
               <p>You <U+017F>hall know this <U+017F>ort of <hi>Tooth-Ake</hi> by the high beating of your Pul<U+017F>e, the fulne<U+017F>s of the Veins, and an often beating in the affected Tooth; with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, tho not very extreme pain. And then for the Cure of it, you mu<U+017F>t fir<U+017F>t bleed the Gums, and <U+017F>ometimes open a Vein in the Arm al<U+017F>o, and wa<U+017F>h your mouth with <hi>Ro<U+017F>e-water</hi> and <hi>Vinegar,</hi> of each equal quantities mixt together; putting a little Cotton dipt in <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Box</hi> into the Tooth, if it be hollow.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, if that portion of the <hi>Blood,</hi> which is diffu<U+017F>ed through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Brain for the production of the <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> is <U+017F>o depraved, that all the <U+017F>ifting it receives, through the hidden <hi>meanders,</hi> and rece<U+017F><U+017F>es of the Brain cannot clear it from its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities; and that notwith<U+017F>tanding all the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Nature it is depo<U+017F>ited into the <hi>ventricles</hi> of the Brain, (tho under another form yet) <U+017F>till impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with its ill qualities: <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ort of <hi>Animal Spirits</hi> being compounded of <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> parts, if not time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly di<U+017F>charged of their malignant and offen<U+017F>ive <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<U+017F>cles,</hi> (through the u<U+017F>ual <hi>Emunctories)</hi> will either by their fermentation in the <hi>Ventricles</hi> of the Brain, cau<U+017F>e an Head-ake; or by the <hi>oppilation</hi> of its pores, cau<U+017F>e a giddine<U+017F>s; or el<U+017F>e pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing out of the Brain into the Nerves, will by their irregular motion, and preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural extention of the coats of the Nerves, and other Tunicles, breed a di<U+017F>turbance in all the parts they go to; but more particularly in the Teeth, in which they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40751:14"/>
always excite very great pains. For di<U+017F>charging the peccant humour, between the <hi>membrane</hi> that inve<U+017F>ts the in<U+017F>ide of the Tooth, and that that inclo<U+017F>es its ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els, it occa<U+017F>ions a perpetual torment in them, till it be expelled from thence by <hi>tran<U+017F>piration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <U+017F>econd kind of Tooth-ake will be known by a di<U+017F>turbance in the head, which precedes it mo<U+017F>t com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly; a <U+017F>orene<U+017F>s in the joynts, and a certain drou<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, and lingring pain all over the body, as if one were inclined to an Ague, with a <U+017F>harp and very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ive pain in the di<U+017F>tempered Tooth, which comes by fits, <U+017F>oon cea<U+017F>ing, and often beginning a-new. As for its Cure, it may be effected by <hi>Sternutation,</hi> the <hi>friction</hi> of the <hi>nape</hi> of the Neck with warm clothes, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of <hi>aperitive</hi> Remedies, to open the <hi>pores</hi> of the Tooth: and if it be hollow, you <U+017F>hall put in't a drop of <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Camphire,</hi> whereinto has been infu<U+017F>ed <U+017F>ome <hi>Henbane-root.</hi> The<U+017F>e are the two general cau<U+017F>es of the Tooth-ake; all the re<U+017F>t proceeding from them, <U+017F>ome few excepted.</p>
               <p>There is what I had a mind to <U+017F>ay at this pre<U+017F>ent concerning the Tooth-ake. But you mu<U+017F>t note fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that as it is not enough for one that intends to travel a <hi>Countrey</hi> over, to under<U+017F>tand the <hi>Map</hi> of that <hi>Countrey;</hi> but he mu<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o inquire often of the people he meets with as he goes on his journey, for the way to <U+017F>uch and <U+017F>uch a place: <U+017F>o although I have given you a true account of the Tooth-ake, and have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered here the right method for the curing of it, yet that Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is for the mo<U+017F>t part accompanied with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40751:14"/>
<U+017F>everal circum<U+017F>tances, that can't be learnt but from <hi>experience</hi> it <U+017F>elf. Thus <U+017F>ometimes the Gums will be <hi>livid,</hi> <U+017F>ometimes <hi>pale,</hi> and <U+017F>ometimes <hi>red,</hi> and inflamed. Sometimes the Tooth is loo<U+017F>e, and ri<U+017F>en above the others. And <U+017F>ometimes its <hi>root</hi> is di<U+017F>covered, and bare of fle<U+017F>h. Sometimes its <hi>rotten,</hi> and otherwhile <hi><U+017F>ound,</hi> as to its <hi><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.</hi> In fine, <U+017F>ometimes the pain is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a great <hi>fluxion</hi> of <hi>Rhume,</hi> and <U+017F>ometimes with a dryne<U+017F>s of the <hi>mouth,</hi> &amp;c. Each of which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants</hi> requires a particular con<U+017F>ideration, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Remedies: con<U+017F>idering always the<U+017F>e things, with reference to the age, con<U+017F>titution and habit of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, it is but rarely, that a <hi>Tooth-ake</hi> is found <hi><U+017F>imple,</hi> or <hi>uncompound:</hi> (as we have <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed to be, tho<U+017F>e of which we have treated above) that is, occa<U+017F>ioned by one cau<U+017F>e only: but it proceeds mo<U+017F>t commonly from <U+017F>everal; and e<U+017F>pecially if the pain be inveterate, or of a long <U+017F>tanding. And then, the <hi><U+017F>ymptoms</hi> of this <hi>complicated</hi> Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, are mixt in the <U+017F>ame proportion as their <hi>cau<U+017F>es;</hi> which renders the Cure much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, and <U+017F>ubject to more ob<U+017F>ervations. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if any one has a mind to render him<U+017F>elf perfect in the<U+017F>e things, he mu<U+017F>t not only follow our method, that directs him to the true <hi>knowledge</hi> of them, but the <hi>dictates</hi> of his own <U+017F>en<U+017F>es al<U+017F>o; by which he will avoid all the <hi>ob<U+017F>tacles</hi> he may meet with by the way. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding all which, people being commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to undergo all the trouble attending a <hi>metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Cure,</hi> and withal apt to think, that one does them
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40751:15"/>
no good at all, unle<U+017F>s he gives them ea<U+017F>e pre<U+017F>ently; I have been forced to abandon the <hi>Art</hi> in my practice, and to invent certain general Remedies; which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thele<U+017F>s applying with <hi>circum<U+017F>pection,</hi> and as I think oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ion requires, hardly ever fail of producing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended effect: <U+017F>ometimes in an in<U+017F>tant, but mo<U+017F>t com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly within le<U+017F>s than half an hour. True it is, that were it not for my former practice, and long habit in tho<U+017F>e things, I neither cou'd have, nor expect <U+017F>o good a <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>And yet I will not deny, but that the <U+017F>aid remedies happen <U+017F>ometimes to <hi>operate</hi> a great deal <U+017F>lower than ordinary. But that comes to pa<U+017F>s by rea<U+017F>on of <U+017F>ome unexpected, or unob<U+017F>erv'd <hi>accidents:</hi> and I think it ought to <U+017F>uffice, that the Cure be at la<U+017F>t performed. Yet this does not <U+017F>atisfy every body. If the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy does not immediately Cure <U+017F>uch as are <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient</hi> or incapable of rea<U+017F>oning, they <U+017F>trait condemn it as a thing ineffectual, and altogether void of any <hi>Virtue.</hi> Upon which, believing the Stories of <U+017F>ome impertinent (tho perhaps well affectioned) friend, they make u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>uch things, as commonly hinder the effect of the Remedy. And if it happens <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that notwith<U+017F>tanding tho<U+017F>e impediments, our remedy produces its effect; they never fail of attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting the Cure to their own indeavours.</p>
               <p>However, I mu<U+017F>t ingenuou<U+017F>ly confe<U+017F>s, that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies do not take effect always. And that there are <U+017F>ome <U+017F>orts of <hi>Tooth-ake</hi> almo<U+017F>t incurable, unle<U+017F>s it be <hi>pulliatively;</hi> and that it <U+017F>elf, not without a great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40751:15"/>
deal of trouble, and a tedious while. The rea<U+017F>ons of which, I <U+017F>hall take occa<U+017F>ion to explain <U+017F>ome other time.</p>
               <p>The loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s of the Teeth, comes mo<U+017F>t commonly from the decay of the Gums, which are <U+017F>ubject to many infi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mities, proceeding for the mo<U+017F>t part from tho<U+017F>e things that occa<U+017F>ion the <hi>Tooth-ake,</hi> and putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Teeth; for <U+017F>ometimes there will be <U+017F>uch an affluence of <hi>blood</hi> from the <hi>Teeth</hi> into the Gums, that their veins being not able to contain it, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon broken; <U+017F>hedding the <hi>blood</hi> between the Gums and the <hi>Teeth:</hi> where gathering together, it corrupts, rotting away all the fle<U+017F>h from about the <hi>Teeth:</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles the <hi>excrementitious</hi> humour, that <hi>ex<U+017F>udates</hi> out of the <hi>Teeth,</hi> falling upon the Gums, eats them away by degrees, &amp;c. But above all other things, the <U+017F>cales, and foulne<U+017F>s of the <hi>Teeth</hi> are very prejudicial to them. All which infirmities to avoid, you need but to keep your Teeth and Gums neat and clean from any foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s what<U+017F>oever; as has been already <U+017F>aid in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Sections: preventing any preternatural colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Blood,</hi> or any other humours within the Gums. But if the mi<U+017F>chief is already done, that is, if your <hi>Teeth</hi> be really loo<U+017F>e, and your <hi>Gums</hi> wa<U+017F>ted, you mu<U+017F>t have recour<U+017F>e for their recovery to one well ver<U+017F>ed in tho<U+017F>e things. For to pre<U+017F>cribe you here any form of Remedies, would be to no purpo<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ince the <U+017F>ame thing cannot be equally good in all ca<U+017F>es, and that without the perfect knowledge of the cau<U+017F>e of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and a right method in applying <U+017F>uitable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments, (which commonly is under<U+017F>tood only by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40751:16"/>
Practitioners in tho<U+017F>e concerns) it is impos<U+017F>ible ever to perform the Cure of any Di<U+017F>temper.</p>
               <p>Yet, that you may not think me remi<U+017F>s in any thing belonging to my Profes<U+017F>ion, that may concern your welfare; and by rea<U+017F>on that you may chance to find your <U+017F>elves in a place where there will be no <hi>Arti<U+017F>t</hi> to help you; I will here communicate to you a general Remedy again<U+017F>t the decay of the Gums, and loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s of the <hi>Teeth;</hi> which I am <U+017F>ure, if you u<U+017F>e carefully, will often an<U+017F>wer your expectations: At lea<U+017F>t it will be <U+017F>uch, that it <U+017F>hall always do you <U+017F>ome good, and never any harm. But I mu<U+017F>t tell you before-hand, that if your body be <hi>Scorbutick,</hi> and full of ill humours, you mu<U+017F>t fir<U+017F>t be <hi>Blooded,</hi> and <hi>Purg'd,</hi> according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of a good <hi>Phy<U+017F>itian:</hi> and then you may u<U+017F>e the <U+017F>aid Remedy as followeth.</p>
               <p>Take of <hi>Ma<U+017F>tick, Myrrh, Pine-Apple, Dragons-blood,</hi> in drops, all reduced into Powder, of each equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, red <hi>Coral</hi> prepared, flowers of <hi>Pomgranats,</hi> of each double the quantity of the other <hi>Ingredients;</hi> and <U+017F>teep them all in a proportionable quantity of <hi>Spring-water</hi> upon warm <hi>Embers,</hi> for the <U+017F>pace of a natural day; and then <hi>filtrate</hi> the <hi>Infu<U+017F>ion</hi> through a woollen-cloth, and keep it clo<U+017F>e in <U+017F>ome convenient ve<U+017F><U+017F>el. And when you have a mind to u<U+017F>e it, you <U+017F>hall take two or three <U+017F>poonfuls on't a day, keeping it in your mouth a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour every time: which you mu<U+017F>t continue to do while nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity <U+017F>hall require it.</p>
               <p>I might have told you at the beginning of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, where I <U+017F>poke of the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the Teeth, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40751:16"/>
their Artery comes from the <hi>Carotids;</hi> the vein <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Jugular,</hi> and the <U+017F>inew from the fifth pair of Nerves: but if you are skilled in <hi>Anatomy,</hi> you know it better than I, and if not, my telling of it to you would <U+017F>ignify nothing at all, unle<U+017F>s I <U+017F>hould in the <U+017F>ame time, give you an accurate de<U+017F>cription of all tho<U+017F>e ve<U+017F><U+017F>els; tracing them from their <hi>Origine,</hi> even to the very la<U+017F>t of their Divi<U+017F>ions, and furthe<U+017F>t extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; which would be improper in this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. Of Childrens Teeth.</head>
               <p>HAving hitherto <U+017F>poken of the <hi>Teeth</hi> in reference to adult per<U+017F>ons, and <U+017F>uch as are pa<U+017F>t childhood: we <U+017F>hall explain in this Section, as <U+017F>uccinctly, and withal as clearly as we can, what is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to be known touching their growth, and change in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; a thing of no <U+017F>mall con<U+017F>equence, <U+017F>ince the life of Infants is therein <U+017F>o often concern'd.</p>
               <p>The Child being born, remains <hi>Toothle<U+017F>s,</hi> till he is about five or <U+017F>ix Months old: at which time his two foremo<U+017F>t Teeth in each Jaw begin to appear, without keeping any con<U+017F>tant order of Precedence: <U+017F>ometimes tho<U+017F>e above coming out fir<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>ometimes tho<U+017F>e be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. After them follow all the re<U+017F>t <U+017F>ucces<U+017F>ively in both <hi>Mandibles:</hi> <U+017F>o next to the<U+017F>e come the four other <hi>Inci<U+017F>ores,</hi> the four <hi>Canin</hi> or <hi>Dog-Teeth,</hi> and the fir<U+017F>t eight <hi>Molares,</hi> (which are properly the double <hi>Teeth)</hi> and then come the four bigge<U+017F>t <hi>Teeth</hi> of all, which may be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40751:17"/>
called <hi>Quadruple Teeth,</hi> as being about three times big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the <U+017F>mall ones: and after that the eight la<U+017F>t <hi>Teeth</hi> do follow; which in re<U+017F>pect to the <hi>Inci<U+017F>ores</hi> may be termed treble <hi>Teeth.</hi> But the<U+017F>e treble ones u<U+017F>ually vary very much in time of growth, for it is but rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they all come forth in the <U+017F>ame year, the four la<U+017F>t of them <U+017F>eldom coming out before the one or two and twentieth year of our age; for which rea<U+017F>on <U+017F>uch <hi>Teeth</hi> are called by <U+017F>ome, <hi>Teeth</hi> of <hi>Wi<U+017F>dom;</hi> becau<U+017F>e that by that time, we <U+017F>hould have a full u<U+017F>e of our rational <hi>Faculty,</hi> though God knows how often it proves to be true.</p>
               <p>The eight <hi>Inci<U+017F>ores,</hi> and the four <hi>Dog-Teeth</hi> come the fir<U+017F>t year; the eight double <hi>Teeth</hi> the <U+017F>econd<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> year; and the four <hi>Quadruples,</hi> with the four fir<U+017F>t <hi>Treble</hi> ones, the third. During the time of their eruption, and e<U+017F>pecially when the four <hi>Quadruple</hi> ones break forth out of their Sockets, children are <U+017F>ubject to Fevers, and great alterations, which weakens them extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and often puts an end to their days; which comes to pa<U+017F>s mo<U+017F>t commonly, for want of help to facilitate their i<U+017F><U+017F>ue out of the Gums.</p>
               <p>And as I look upon the knowledge of Childrens <hi>Teeth,</hi> as a <U+017F>ubject properly belonging to my Profe<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion; <U+017F>o I think my <U+017F>elf oblig'd to amend, amplifie, and render it as conducive to the pre<U+017F>ervation of the life, and health of Children, and to the preventing of all tho<U+017F>e Infirmities wherewith they are afflicted, (upon the account of the fir<U+017F>t coming, and <U+017F>hedding of their <hi>Teeth)</hi> as my weak indeavours can make it.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40751:17"/>
And therefore I will to that end deliver here in few words, what rea<U+017F>on and experience have taught me concerning the <U+017F>ame; Proceeding thus,</p>
               <p>In the fir<U+017F>t place, I would advi<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch as may be concerned in this Affair, to take a <U+017F>pecial care in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erving when the Child's <hi>Teeth</hi> begin to trouble him: which (be<U+017F>ides his frowardne<U+017F>s, and exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive crying) may be known by his <hi><U+017F>alivation</hi> or drivelling (as Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es are wont to <U+017F>tile it,) and the inflammation and <U+017F>welling of his Gums; and as <U+017F>oon as you perceive it to be <U+017F>o, you are to wa<U+017F>h his mouth now and then with the following mixture: <hi>Take</hi> <U+017F>even or eight as new <hi>Figs</hi> as you can get, and boyl them in a pint or more of <hi>Whey,</hi> till they grow very <U+017F>oft, and then <U+017F>queeze the <hi>Whey,</hi> and as much of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the <hi>Figs</hi> as you can through a cloth; of which liquor take half a pint; of Honey of Ro<U+017F>es, and Syrup of Violets, of each half an ounce; and three or four <U+017F>poonfuls of <hi>Plantain-water:</hi> mix all together, and keep it clo<U+017F>e in a Bottel. The be<U+017F>t way to u<U+017F>e it, is with a <U+017F>tick of Liquori<U+017F>h beaten at one end into <U+017F>mall threads like a Comb-bru<U+017F>h, or little Broom, with which, being dipt in <U+017F>ome of the <U+017F>aid Liquor, you <U+017F>hall wa<U+017F>h and rub the Childs Gums, (e<U+017F>pecially where they are tumified) at lea<U+017F>t five or <U+017F>ix times a day, continuing <U+017F>o to do, till you perceive the Gums to grow white above the <hi>Tooth:</hi> (which is a <U+017F>ign of great pain in that part, and that the young <hi>Tooth</hi> will in a little time break through the Gums) and then take a <hi>Lancet,</hi> or a very <U+017F>harp <hi>Pen-knife,</hi> and divide the white place, cutting it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40751:18"/>
down to the head of the <U+017F>ubjacent <hi>Tooth,</hi> with two <hi>Inci<U+017F>ions</hi> cro<U+017F><U+017F>ing one another at the centre of the white <U+017F>pot, continuing to u<U+017F>e the mixture as is afore<U+017F>aid, till the <hi>Tooth</hi> appears above the Gums; ob<U+017F>erving to u<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ame method at the coming out of every <hi>Tooth,</hi> which you may know by the foregoing tokens.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Teeth</hi> being all come out (except only <U+017F>uch as remain latent within the Jaw, till about the two and twentieth year of ones age) they keep firm and <U+017F>trong till the child is a matter of <U+017F>ix or <U+017F>even years old, and then mo<U+017F>t of them grow loo<U+017F>e, and a while after are ca<U+017F>t clear out. The <hi>treble Teeth</hi> never change, the <hi>Quadruples</hi> very rarely, but the <hi>Inci<U+017F>ores,</hi> the <hi>Dog-Teeth,</hi> and the double ones always do; <U+017F>ometimes whole, (and then the <hi><U+017F>econd Teeth,</hi> or tho<U+017F>e that are to <U+017F>ucceed them, are a long time before they grow up again;) but mo<U+017F>t commonly their head only comes off, the other part remaining <U+017F>till for the making up of the next Tooth; like unto the fir<U+017F>t production of a Vegetable Seed, or tender Sprig of a young Plant; for as the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part of this being withered in the <hi>Winter</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the rigorous cold of that Sea<U+017F>on, drops off in the next Spring: (by rea<U+017F>on that its texture being yet loo<U+017F>e, and le<U+017F>s firm, the pores or <U+017F>ap carrying ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, are over much dilated by the great affluence of the <hi>nutritive</hi> juice, and <U+017F>o give admittance to <U+017F>ome indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ted and gro<U+017F><U+017F>er <hi>particles</hi> than is convenient for the nouri<U+017F>hment of the Vegetable: which <hi>particles</hi> being irregular, and unactive, their motion is <U+017F>oon <U+017F>topt; when-as a great cold intervening, compre<U+017F><U+017F>es a little
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40751:18"/>
the young Plant round about, <U+017F>o that they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geal'd, and become fixt in their <hi>Ducts,</hi> or leading pipes, whereby that part being deprived of its due nouri<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fades away, and dries up,) and is <U+017F>ucceeded by a new Sprout <U+017F>hooting out of the <U+017F>tump, or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part. So likewi<U+017F>e the young <hi>Teeth</hi> coming into the cold air, when they are yet tender, and le<U+017F>s <U+017F>olid: tho<U+017F>e of them that are more <U+017F>u<U+017F>ceptible of alteration, and more expo<U+017F>ed to the inclemency of the weather; (as mu<U+017F>t be tho<U+017F>e before, which by rea<U+017F>on of their <U+017F>mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>ituation, cannot but be more <U+017F>ubject to <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious</hi> accidents,) are thereby chill'd and repre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, and their parts thru<U+017F>t near one another, and driven back towards their centre, from whence the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the <hi>Tooth</hi> becoming clo<U+017F>er, and the intervals between its parts narrower, and interrupted in <U+017F>everal places, by the irregular motion of <U+017F>ome of the minute<U+017F>t of tho<U+017F>e parts, (which by rea<U+017F>on of their un<U+017F>tablene<U+017F>s, and fluxibility, being di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to advance and obey the action of external Agents more than the others, do move di<U+017F>orderly, and <U+017F>poil the <U+017F>tructure of the re<U+017F>t:) the <U+017F>mall Veins and Arteries therein di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed, will become <U+017F>o extremely compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, that the bloud they contain (which in Children is mo<U+017F>t commonly gro<U+017F>s and impure, as is apparent by their <U+017F>tupidity, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <U+017F>cabs; as well as by that Feveri<U+017F>h di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition they are always inclined to; which argues a great di<U+017F>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity between the parts of their bloud,) is thereby <U+017F>topt in its cour<U+017F>e, and detained in them; where the gro<U+017F>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of its parts, and their incumbring figures will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40751:19"/>
<U+017F>oon di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e them to re<U+017F>t, and remain intangled and coagulated together.</p>
               <p>If you chance to reflect upon what I <U+017F>ay, when I a<U+017F>cribe the great agitation of Childrens Bloud, and its being quiet and fixt in their Teeth, to the <U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>e, <hi>viz.</hi> its foulne<U+017F>s, and the incongruity of its parts; you will perhaps be as angry with me, as the <hi>Satyr</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t the Traveller of the <hi>Fables,</hi> for his blowing hot and cold with the <U+017F>ame breath. But if you con<U+017F>ider it a little more attentively, you <U+017F>hall find that this, as well as the <U+017F>aid <hi>Apologue,</hi> may ea<U+017F>ily be reconciled with Rea<U+017F>on.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the Bloud coming from the live part of the Tooth, to enter the other; and being hindred thereof by the narrowne<U+017F>s of the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the conden<U+017F>ed bloud, is upon that nece<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily determined to imploy the force of its motion round about, again<U+017F>t the parts lying immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the dead portion of the Tooth, and that which is alive; the which it con<U+017F>equently loo<U+017F>ens by degrees, and at la<U+017F>t breaks them all a<U+017F>under; <U+017F>eparating thus the live body of the Tooth quite from its dead head; and the <U+017F>pace left between them permitting the <hi>trunk</hi> to grow, it <U+017F>hoots a new head; which ri<U+017F>ing above the Gums, thru<U+017F>ts out the old one, becoming a perfect Tooth in its room.</p>
               <p>But if in the mean while, through the too great adherence of the dead part to the Gums, the other is depre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, or retarded from growing, and by con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is detained under the former too long; <U+017F>ome
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40751:19"/>
of the broken <hi>particles</hi> remaining between them<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> will corrode, and eat holes in the new head of the Tooth, and <U+017F>o it comes out already peri<U+017F>hed: which to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, the fir<U+017F>t Teeth mu<U+017F>t be drawn out as <U+017F>oon as they appear any thing loo<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it happens <U+017F>ometimes, that the new head of the Tooth is nouri<U+017F>hed, and increa<U+017F>es <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t, that being ob<U+017F>tructed by the too great connexion of the old one, to the adjacent parts, from advancing in its right cour<U+017F>e; it turns a<U+017F>ide, and makes its way through either the in<U+017F>ide, or out<U+017F>ide of the Gums; and <U+017F>o it grows bia<U+017F><U+017F>ing, and out of rank. This defect is remedied by drawing out the <U+017F>uperfluous Tooth, and the u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome convenient means to bring the new Tooth into its place; which is very ea<U+017F>y to do, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken at fir<U+017F>t, but otherwi<U+017F>e a great deal more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult; and e<U+017F>pecially if the two next Teeth are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached <U+017F>o near one another, that it cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained between them, without being le<U+017F><U+017F>ened, or the others put further off from each other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> That in drawing out the old, or <U+017F>ucking Tooth, a great care is to be taken not to hurt the new one, lying under it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. Of the Acceleration of the Teeth.</head>
               <p>THe five fir<U+017F>t of the foregoing <hi>Sections</hi> have been imploy'd about mens Teeth, and the <U+017F>ixth about tho<U+017F>e of Children: but this <U+017F>eventh and la<U+017F>t Section
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40751:20"/>
of our Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e <U+017F>hall re<U+017F>pect both men and children; for it will not only teach how to ha<U+017F>ten the growth of Childrens <U+017F>econd Teeth, when it happens to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd, or retarded too long; but al<U+017F>o how to <hi>Accelerate</hi> the coming out of tho<U+017F>e in Men, that are called Teeth of Wi<U+017F>dom. Which la<U+017F>t, without the help of Art, hardly ever appear before almo<U+017F>t half of our life is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready pa<U+017F>t away; And when the time of our growth is over: during which, we have the greate<U+017F>t occa<U+017F>ion for them. But becau<U+017F>e the bare <U+017F>aying or a<U+017F><U+017F>erting of any thing without proofs, or <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>ons to render it probable, has no force to per<U+017F>wade any man of its truth, nor to make him <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of what utility it is of; We will <hi>elucidate</hi> the matter in hand, by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample drown from the motion of Seeds <U+017F>own in the Earth. Now the quick or <U+017F>low <hi>germinating</hi> of Seeds after they have been <U+017F>own, depends upon their being buried <U+017F>hallow, or deep in the ground; the light<U+017F>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s or heavine<U+017F>s of the Earth, and its good or ill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuring, and the proportion of <hi>humidity</hi> that <hi>dilutes</hi> it, as well as the heat or coldne<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on: the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral proportions of either of which accidents, alter and vary the progre<U+017F>s of the Seed, according to their prevalency in re<U+017F>pect of each other.</p>
               <p>For in a well prepar'd Soil, being cheri<U+017F>hed by the warmth of the Sun, and duly <hi>diluted</hi> with water, the Seed will budd a great deal <U+017F>ooner; the light<U+017F>ome Earth ea<U+017F>ily yielding to the <hi>expan<U+017F>ion</hi> of the <hi>Semen,</hi> when it <hi>imbibes</hi> that <hi>Succus Nutritious,</hi> which <hi>Tran<U+017F>colating</hi> through the coats of the Seed, and impregnating its
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40751:20"/>
                  <hi>Parenchyma,</hi> cau<U+017F>es by its <hi>fermentation</hi> therein, a gentle <U+017F>hake, and a <hi>vital</hi> motion in the <hi>Radicle,</hi> and <hi>Plume;</hi> (as the Learned Doctor <hi>Grer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> calls the <hi>Seminal Root,</hi> and <hi>Trunck</hi> of a Plant in <hi>Embryo)</hi> whereby they are impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Extricate</hi> them<U+017F>elves out of their <hi>Integuments,</hi> and <hi>Parenchyma;</hi> and begin to <hi>vegetate,</hi> and grow like a Plant.</p>
               <p>But the Seed being buried deep in a cold, cloggy earth; will, by the <U+017F>tubborn <hi>Cohe<U+017F>ion,</hi> and lumpi<U+017F>hne<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>aid earth, be kept from <hi>dilating</hi> it <U+017F>elf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently from receiving tho<U+017F>e <hi>particles</hi> that are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for its <hi>vivifying,</hi> and <hi>augmentation.</hi> From whence it follows, that its growth (if not hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by Art) will be check'd, and ob<U+017F>tructed till the heat of the Sun has opened the ground, and <U+017F>et its <hi>particles</hi> in <U+017F>uch motion as they ought to be, to enter the Seed, and <hi>protrude</hi> the earth upwards.</p>
               <p>So likewi<U+017F>e Childrens Gums, being yet tender, <U+017F>hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and loo<U+017F>e, and withal prepar'd, as we have taught heretofore in its place, their fir<U+017F>t Teeth come out, and grow very ea<U+017F>ily; as al<U+017F>o do their <U+017F>econd, if in <U+017F>hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the fir<U+017F>t, their heads only come off; for the others do grow up <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon, that the Gums have hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any time to clo<U+017F>e up again. But if the <U+017F>ucking-Teeth do <U+017F>hed root and all, the matter out of which the next (which I call <hi>Novel-Teeth)</hi> are to be made, will not only be a con<U+017F>iderable time in di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ing it <U+017F>elf into the requi<U+017F>ite form, but when the fir<U+017F>t linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are drawn, and Nature has accompli<U+017F>hed her fir<U+017F>t work, the Gums will be re-united together, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40751:21"/>
grown <U+017F>o hard by that time, that their re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance will oppo<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf to the growth of the<U+017F>e Teeth, till a <U+017F>tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nouri<U+017F>hment produces more and hotter Bloud, and a greater quantity of <hi>Animal Spirits;</hi> by which the Gums being made hotter, and more <U+017F>pungy, and the <hi>nutritive</hi> juice increa<U+017F>ed, the i<U+017F><U+017F>ue of the <U+017F>aid Teeth will then be <hi>facilitated,</hi> and their growth perfected.</p>
               <p>To the con<U+017F>ideration of the<U+017F>e <hi>Novel-Teeth,</hi> may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be referred that of the la<U+017F>t <hi>treble</hi> ones, or <hi>dentes <U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae.</hi> It's true, the<U+017F>e are <U+017F>tay'd a great deal longer under the Gums than the others; but al<U+017F>o they have more cau<U+017F>es that impede their growth. For, be<U+017F>ides that, the Gums are more <U+017F>inewy, and <hi>membranous</hi> about them than any where el<U+017F>e, and therefore much more difficult to <hi>penetrate:</hi> That part of the Jaw-bone that contains them, is likewi<U+017F>e much thicker, and <U+017F>tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than any other; and con<U+017F>equently, harder to be divided by the included Teeth; which being inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of making their way through it, are forced to <U+017F>tay therein till <U+017F>uch time that Nature having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected our growth, the <hi>bloud</hi> becomes hotter, <U+017F>tronger, and its <hi>energy</hi> more powerful by the firmne<U+017F>s of the Heart, (which is the Sun of our <hi>Microco<U+017F>m,</hi> or little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>world) and other principal parts, and increa<U+017F>e of tho<U+017F>e <hi>particles</hi> that were wont to be imployed in making up, and augmenting the body; mo<U+017F>t of which remain then in the ma<U+017F>s of the <hi>Bloud:</hi> whereby the <U+017F>aid <hi>bloud,</hi> being able to <U+017F>urmount the re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the Jaw and Gums, forces the <U+017F>aid Teeth to come out of their cells, and grow up.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40751:21"/>
To the efficacy of this new <U+017F>trength of the <hi>Bloud</hi> upon the arrival of Nature to its highe<U+017F>t <hi>Period,</hi> may be attributed the cau<U+017F>es of tho<U+017F>e alterations that u<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally happen in mens bodies about that time: many looking pale, and being troubled with divers infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties till then, of which they are afterwards delivered. But leaving off Digre<U+017F><U+017F>ions, let us return to our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
               <p>We have already ob<U+017F>erved, that the <hi>Novel-Teeth</hi> in Children, and <hi>Dentes Supientiae</hi> in Men, cou'd not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to their perfection, nor therefore become <U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to us without a long time, and a great <hi>Effort</hi> of Nature. It remains now, that (pur<U+017F>uant to our de<U+017F>ign, as we have declar'd it at the beginning of this Section) we indeavor to find out <U+017F>ome means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may remedy tho<U+017F>e defects; in <hi>facilitating</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's work, and rendring tho<U+017F>e <hi>tardy Teeth</hi> above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, <U+017F>erviceable to us as <U+017F>oon as we can. And as I find none more proper and expeditious, than the <hi>Rarifaction,</hi> and <hi>Dilatation</hi> of the Gums, <U+017F>o that they may lo<U+017F>e their greate<U+017F>t <U+017F>tubbornne<U+017F>s, and become more yielding to the <hi>Teeth:</hi> I conclude that all the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lies in knowing how <U+017F>uch an effect can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: which (after a due con<U+017F>ideration) I think may be performed after this manner.</p>
               <p>In the fir<U+017F>t place, there is need of an In<U+017F>trument made of Gold, or Silver, about a foot long, as big as a Tobacco-pipe, and like a <hi>Syringe;</hi> being <U+017F>o bored, that a perfectly <hi>Cilindrical embolus,</hi> or <U+017F>ucker, may fill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly nine inches of its <hi>Cavity;</hi> the re<U+017F>t being made a good
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40751:22"/>
deal <U+017F>maller, and bow'd like the Blowing-pipe of <hi>Watch-makers;</hi> which ought to end into an head re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>embling the cup of an <hi>Acorn;</hi> and <U+017F>o contriv'd, that it may imbrace the Gums exactly. Your <hi>In<U+017F>trument</hi> being ready, if you have a mind to perform the <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> you mu<U+017F>t in the next place (concerning the <hi>Dentes Sapientiae)</hi> tie all the <hi>Teeth</hi> together, (which may be done without any trouble) <U+017F>o that the two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t of them may draw the la<U+017F>t of all towards the fore-part of the <hi>mouth.</hi> By this the included Teeth will be freed from being <hi>compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed</hi> between the others, and the extremity of the Jaw-bone. And then the Gums being prepar'd by <hi>Emollients,</hi> and <hi>relaxing</hi> things, apply the end of your <hi>Syringe</hi> clo<U+017F>e upon the Gums, under which the imperfect Tooth lies; and then draw the <hi>Embolus,</hi> and the top of the Gums will follow, and ri<U+017F>e within the little <hi>Acorn-cup-like</hi> end of the Pipe, as the fle<U+017F>h u<U+017F>ually doth under <hi>Cupping-Gla<U+017F>ses.</hi> Keep it a while <U+017F>o, and then take away the <hi>Syringe,</hi> and <hi><U+017F>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie</hi> that part of the Gums that was drawn within the Pipe, in <U+017F>everal places; <hi>reiterating</hi> the <U+017F>ame <hi>Operation</hi> twice a day, for about a fortnight, omitting only the <hi>Scarification,</hi> which is to be u<U+017F>ed the fir<U+017F>t time only. By this means it appears probable to me, that the Gums yielding, the force of the <hi>Blood</hi> will compel the <hi>fibres</hi> or <hi>minute</hi> parts of the imperfect Tooth, to advance according to their natural order, and <U+017F>ituation; and <U+017F>o cau<U+017F>e the <U+017F>aid Tooth to grow.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Novel-Teeth,</hi> you <U+017F>hall follow the <U+017F>ame method, and u<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ame means in <hi>facilitating</hi> their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40751:22"/>
coming out, that you have done to the others; omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting only the tying of the Teeth, which would be <hi><U+017F>uperfluous</hi> here.</p>
               <p>Note, that every thing is not capable of the <U+017F>ame perfection, and that as there is no rule without <U+017F>ome exception; <U+017F>o when I have a<U+017F><U+017F>erted <U+017F>uch and <U+017F>uch things to be improvable to <U+017F>uch a degree, it is to be under<U+017F>tood for the mo<U+017F>t part, and in general; not denying but that it may happen otherwi<U+017F>e in <U+017F>ome particular ca<U+017F>es: but I <U+017F>hall always deal candidly with every body, never undertaking any thing but what I <U+017F>hall be able to do according to agreement. And if any one will be plea<U+017F>ed to come to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he may have my Advice (concerning any thing that belongs to my Profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion) <hi>gratis</hi> at any time.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40751:23"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough I have offered nothing in this Paper, but what is according to my own Experience, and the be<U+017F>t of my knowledge; yet I will not <U+017F>ay but that I have been deficient in many things, and have committed a great many Errors in the management of my Subject; but if you con<U+017F>ider that I am the fir<U+017F>t (as far as I know) that ever wrote any thing of this nature; and withal, what is to be expected from one in my Circum<U+017F>tances, I hope you will be the more ready to excu<U+017F>e my faults. However, if what I have done be acceptable to you, I intend in a <U+017F>econd Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of this <U+017F>mall Treati<U+017F>e, to Correct, Illu<U+017F>trate, and augment it, to its full proportion. In the mean while I would advi<U+017F>e you, to make u<U+017F>e of what is here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ented you, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very Humble Servant, CHARLES ALLEN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>Printed in the Year 1686.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40751:23"/>
            <head>A Phy<U+017F>ical Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e WHEREIN The Rea<U+017F>ons of the Beating of the PULSE, <hi>or</hi> Pul<U+017F>ation <hi>of the</hi> Arteries; <hi>Together with tho<U+017F>e of the</hi> Circulation <hi>of the</hi> Bloud, <hi>are</hi> Mechanically <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd: Which was never done before.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e</hi> being one of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena,</hi> that de<U+017F>erve mans con<U+017F>ideration the be<U+017F>t, it has excited the mo<U+017F>t Learned in all Ages to <U+017F>earch out what might be the cau<U+017F>e of it.</p>
            <p>The be<U+017F>t <hi>Phy<U+017F>itians</hi> and greate<U+017F>t <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophers</hi> of former times, being ignorant of the <hi>Circulation</hi> of the <hi>Bloud,</hi> did a<U+017F>cribe it to their occult qualities, and unknown powers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen,</hi> an Eminent <hi>Phy<U+017F>itian,</hi> <U+017F>earching the natural cau<U+017F>e of the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> thought upon the making of that famous Experiment of his; by which, having put a Quill into an <hi>Artery,</hi> and tied the <hi>Artery</hi> upon it, he found that the <U+017F>aid <hi>Artery</hi> cea<U+017F>ed from beating betwixt the ligature and the extremity, tho it continued <U+017F>till beating betwixt the <U+017F>ame ligature and the heart: And then <U+017F>eeing al<U+017F>o, that the <hi>Artery</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40751:24"/>
being untied from about the Quill, the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e</hi> would immediately pa<U+017F>s beyond the place where the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had been made, and beat all along the <hi>Artery;</hi> altho the capacity of the Quill remained <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame, he concluded, that the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e</hi> was cau<U+017F>ed by a <hi>Pul<U+017F>i<U+017F>ick</hi> faculty re<U+017F>iding in the coats of the <hi>Artery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ga<U+017F><U+017F>endus,</hi> a Modern and mo<U+017F>t Learned Philo<U+017F>opher, attributed the <U+017F>aid effect, to the <hi>Pul<U+017F>ifick</hi> Faculty of the heart; which, in his opinion, communicates it <U+017F>elf to the <hi>Arteries.</hi> Both which opinions (altho propos'd by extraordinary men, yet) are <U+017F>o incon<U+017F>iderable, that they need no refutation.</p>
            <p>The mo<U+017F>t Learned and mo<U+017F>t Profound <hi>Carte<U+017F>ius</hi> was of opinion, that the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e</hi> proceeded from the motion of the <hi>Bloud,</hi> which coming out of the le<U+017F>t <hi>Ventricle</hi> of the Heart into the <hi>Aorta,</hi> in a tumultuous manner, extends it <U+017F>elf forcibly, and thereby drives all the ma<U+017F>s of the <hi>Bloud,</hi> from the heart to the heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, according to the <hi>Circulation</hi> of the Bloud. After which this great Man (who would always give natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and intelligible rea<U+017F>ons for every thing, as he has done for mo<U+017F>t;) coming (at the in<U+017F>tigation of a <hi>Phy<U+017F>itian</hi> of <hi>Louvaine)</hi> to examine <hi>Galen</hi>'s Experiment, he attributed the ce<U+017F><U+017F>ation of the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> that happens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ligature, to the narrowne<U+017F>s of the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age of the <hi>Bloud</hi> through the Quill; which <hi>Bloud,</hi> according to the principles of the Philotopher, coming out of the <U+017F>aid Quill into a wider <U+017F>pace, cannot communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate its action to the <U+017F>ides of the <hi>Artery,</hi> but is di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to imploy the force of its motion forwards, according to the length of the <hi>Artery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40751:24"/>
But the <U+017F>aid <hi>Phy<U+017F>itian</hi> alledging again<U+017F>t this, that if one takes an <hi>Artery</hi> without Quill, or any <hi>Inci<U+017F>ion,</hi> and ties its <U+017F>ides <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e together, that there be left a far <U+017F>maller pa<U+017F><U+017F>age for the Bloud in that place, than in the Quill; the <hi>Artery</hi> will neverthele<U+017F>s continue <U+017F>till to <hi>Beat</hi> on both <U+017F>ides of the ligature, as it did before: (the contrary of which wou'd nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily follow<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> if it were <U+017F>o, that the <U+017F>traitne<U+017F>s of the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age of the Bloud did occa<U+017F>ion the lo<U+017F>s of the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e) Carte<U+017F>ius</hi> was here forced to recede <U+017F>omewhat from his former <hi>Sentiment,</hi> and to confe<U+017F>s, that the motion of the <hi>Arteries</hi> depends partly upon the free continuation of their coats; which totally overthrows his opinion. For, let the power of the <U+017F>aid continuation be what it will; <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing, as the Philo<U+017F>opher did, that its action may be <U+017F>topt by the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the <U+017F>ides of the <hi>Artery:</hi> It is certain, that altho the Quill in the <hi>Artery</hi> were of equal, or, if you will, greater capacity than the <hi>Artery;</hi> yet if the <U+017F>aid <hi>Artery</hi> were tied upon it, the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e</hi> would, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding all that, cea<U+017F>e below the ligature. But <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<U+017F>ius</hi> <U+017F>aid, that <U+017F>uch a Quill as that we were <U+017F>peak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ju<U+017F>t now, being in an <hi>Artery</hi> either tied, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied; wou'd never hinder any part of the <hi>Artery</hi> from <hi>Beating:</hi> And therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Lower</hi> <U+017F>ays, after many Di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions on this Subject, that the knowledge of tho<U+017F>e things was left to God alone.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Willis</hi> a<U+017F>cribes the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e</hi> to the contraction of the <hi>circular Fibres</hi> of the <hi>mu<U+017F>cular</hi> coat of the <hi>Artery:</hi> But it is ab<U+017F>urd to think <U+017F>o; for its impo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40751:25"/>
to imagine that tho<U+017F>e <hi>Fibres</hi> cou'd contract them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves of their own accord; neither does the Doctor give any rea<U+017F>on for what he <U+017F>ays. Be<U+017F>ides, he's incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with him<U+017F>elf, when he a<U+017F>cribes the <U+017F>ame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the circular <hi>Fibres</hi> of the <hi>mu<U+017F>cular</hi> coat of the veins; which are notwith<U+017F>tanding wholly de<U+017F>titute of any <hi>Pul<U+017F>ation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All which con<U+017F>idering, and how the<U+017F>e and other great men had (through the difficulty of the thing, and not out of any in<U+017F>ufficiency in them) fallen into <U+017F>o gro<U+017F>s and <U+017F>o erroneous opinions concerning the Point in Que<U+017F>tion; I concluded, that it was as good as impos<U+017F>ible ever to <U+017F>olve the difficulty. Yet, recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting my <U+017F>elf, and <U+017F>eeing that the <U+017F>aid Effect mu<U+017F>t have a cau<U+017F>e, whatever it be, which probably cannot re<U+017F>ide any where el<U+017F>e, but either in the Heart, Bloud, or coats of the <hi>Artery;</hi> or finally, in them all together; I made a re<U+017F>olution to examine carefully each one of the<U+017F>e things <U+017F>eparately, as pos<U+017F>ibly containing alone the cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ought after; and then all together, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pos<U+017F>ibly Coadjutors in the <hi>production</hi> of the known Effect. And after as exact an Inquiry into the matter as I am capable of, my Rea<U+017F>ons (which wou'd be too tedious to tell you now) per<U+017F>wade me, that all the My<U+017F>tery con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in the three following things.</p>
            <p>The Fir<U+017F>t is, the Structure of the <hi>Artery;</hi> which is made up of four <hi>Coats.</hi> (We <U+017F>hall examine in another place how they are generated at fir<U+017F>t) The fir<U+017F>t of them, which contains the <hi>Bloud</hi> immediately, <U+017F>eems to be <hi>nervous,</hi> and made of <U+017F>trait <hi>Fibres;</hi> which take
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40751:25"/>
their <hi>Origine</hi> from the heart; or rather are a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of tho<U+017F>e that immediately inve<U+017F>t the <hi>cavity</hi> of the heart. As <U+017F>oon as they are arriv'd at the <hi>orifice</hi> of the heart, they rank them<U+017F>elves by one another; form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a certain <hi>Cartilagineous</hi> Ring; from the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of which, they run almo<U+017F>t parallel along the <hi>Artery;</hi> but yet with <U+017F>uch an inclination towards one another, that going from the heart to the extreme parts, they form a kind of <hi>Cone;</hi> (for that we may render our Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e more intelligible; we <U+017F>hall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider here one of the trunks of the great <hi>Artery,</hi> (<U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e the a<U+017F>cending one,) as a continued right <hi>Conical Pipe,</hi> ab<U+017F>tracting from all its divi<U+017F>ions and branches; to every one of which may ea<U+017F>ily be apply'd, what we are going to <U+017F>ay of one of them,) a little below the <hi>Apex</hi> of which, tho<U+017F>e <hi>Fibres</hi> unite them<U+017F>elves together; and do compo<U+017F>e a little <hi>tendinous</hi> ring, called <hi>Ana<U+017F>tomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>is:</hi> to which is affix'd the extremity of the <hi>vena cava:</hi> which vein we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e here to be a <U+017F>ingle <hi>coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> channel, or pipe, di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed, as we have taken the <hi>Artery</hi> to be. Within this <hi>Ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is</hi> there is a little <hi>Valve</hi> <U+017F>o di<U+017F>pos'd, that it permits the bloud to pa<U+017F>s from the <hi>Artery</hi> into the vein, but hinders it from returning back again from the vein into the <hi>Artery.</hi> Between every one of tho<U+017F>e <hi>nervous Fibres,</hi> there is a thin <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane</hi> that joyns them together; (as the skin in a Goo<U+017F>e's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot ties its toes to one another,) which permits the <U+017F>aid <hi>Fibres</hi> to open, and go further from one another, when the <hi>Artery</hi> is dilated: And which do continually increa<U+017F>e in breath, as they go from the <hi>Ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is</hi> to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40751:26"/>
the <hi>ba<U+017F>is</hi> of the <hi>Artery:</hi> <U+017F>o that they become <U+017F>o con<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous near the heart, that Doctor <hi>Willis</hi> took them for <U+017F>ome large fle<U+017F>hy <hi>Fibres;</hi> to which he as<U+017F>ign'd the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <U+017F>hortning the <hi>Artery,</hi> in order to promote the circulation of the Bloud. The <U+017F>econd coat is the <hi>Mu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</hi> and the third the <hi>Glandulous:</hi> but the con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the<U+017F>e middle coats, being not nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>peak of them another time. As to the fourth, or outmo<U+017F>t Coat, it is that which we have mo<U+017F>t need to take notice of here; as being the principal In<U+017F>trument of the <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole</hi> and <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>Artery.</hi> This Coat is made up of two orders, or ranks of <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres;</hi> which proceed from the <hi>oblique Fibres</hi> of the heart; from whence they go twi<U+017F>ting and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them<U+017F>elves about the body of the <hi>Artery,</hi> as <hi>Ivy</hi> does about Trees; <U+017F>ome running upon it from the left to the right, and the others from the right to the left; inter<U+017F>ecting thus one another <hi>obliquely,</hi> as they go from the heart to the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is;</hi> whereby they form a <U+017F>ort of Net, or Sieve-like-woof upon the out<U+017F>ide of the <hi>Artery.</hi> At their coming out of the heart, they are knitted together by a <hi>cartilagineous</hi> <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, that incompa<U+017F><U+017F>es the root of the <hi>Artery</hi> round about, as an iron-ring does the end of a handle: from the circumference of which <hi>cartilagineous</hi> Ring, they run <hi>Helix-wi<U+017F>e</hi> upon the <U+017F>uperficies of the <hi>artery:</hi> at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of which, being arriv'd, they in<U+017F>ert them<U+017F>elves into the <hi>tendinous</hi> <U+017F>mall ring, or <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is.</hi> The<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> are tied <U+017F>o loo<U+017F>ely on the body of the <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> and <U+017F>o <U+017F>lightly between them<U+017F>elves, at the places
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40751:26"/>
where they <hi>inter<U+017F>ect</hi> one another, that they may run very ea<U+017F>ily to and fro upon the <hi>artery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <U+017F>econd thing conducive to the production of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>tated turns of <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole's</hi> and <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole's</hi> of the <hi>artery,</hi> is, that the bloud contains a certain <U+017F>ubtil matter, or vital <U+017F>pirit, which can move it <U+017F>elf, and pa<U+017F>s between its parts very ea<U+017F>ily. And in fine, that the bloud coming out of the heart (where it acquires an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme agitation) into the <hi>arteria magna,</hi> expands it <U+017F>elf with great violence, and <U+017F>trongly dilates that part of the <U+017F>aid <hi>artery</hi> that lies contiguous to the heart, (forcing in the <U+017F>ame time the bloud to advance from the heart towards the extremity,) whereby the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily drawn towards the dilating place, do compre<U+017F>s the <hi>artery</hi> round about all along, &amp; <U+017F>o <U+017F>queeze the <U+017F>ubtil matter, from between the parts of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed bloud, into that which is not; forcing it thus to pa<U+017F>s from the extremity towards the heart, which makes the ebbing or <hi><U+017F>y<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>artery.</hi> And then the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> having been extended violently, and on a <U+017F>udden, upon the <hi>dilatation</hi> of the <hi>artery,</hi> do (by the <hi>Ela<U+017F>tick</hi> faculty of <U+017F>ome of their parts) come back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and re<U+017F>titute them<U+017F>elves into their former <U+017F>itua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and <U+017F>tate; forcing thereby the <U+017F>ubtil matter to fly through the bloud, from the dilated place of the great <hi>Artery,</hi> towards the extremity of the <hi>capillary</hi> ones, &amp;c. which makes the flowing or <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40751:27"/>
               <head>THE EXPLICATION.</head>
               <p>WE have already <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed the <hi>Artery</hi> to be of a right <hi>Conical</hi> figure; let us further, for greater evidence, imagine it to be mentally divided into four parts of equal capacity: <U+017F>o that as much as the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>hall exceed the <U+017F>econd in bredth, the <U+017F>econd will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the fir<U+017F>t in length, &amp;c. Let be<U+017F>ides, the places of the <U+017F>uppos'd divi<U+017F>ions be marked with <U+017F>everal letters, as A, B, C, and let A, denote the fir<U+017F>t divi<U+017F>ion; (proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the heart to the extremity;) B, the <U+017F>econd; and C, the third: let us al<U+017F>o mark the <hi>Ba<U+017F>is</hi> of the <hi>Cylindrical artery,</hi> which is in<U+017F>erted into the <hi>ba<U+017F>is</hi> of the heart, by X; and its <hi>capillary</hi> end in<U+017F>erted into the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of the <hi>annular ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is,</hi> by Y.</p>
               <p>And now, <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e that a certain portion of bloud, as a dram for example, pa<U+017F><U+017F>es out of the heart into the <hi>aorta,</hi> where it <U+017F>wells, and dilates it <U+017F>elf very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderably, (by rea<U+017F>on of a very inten<U+017F>e degree of heat, it acquires in the <hi>ventricles</hi> of the heart; and of its being mixed therein with a certain leaven, or <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative</hi> juice, (it being the re<U+017F>idue of that portion of bloud, that had pa<U+017F>t immediately before through the heart,) which nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily cau<U+017F>es a great commotion and <U+017F>trife among<U+017F>t its parts;) it mu<U+017F>t follow according to true Philo<U+017F>ophy, that the <U+017F>aid portion of bloud coming out of the heart, does in the <U+017F>ame time thru<U+017F>t the bloud already in the <hi>artery,</hi> forwards, and dilates that part of the <hi>artery</hi> that lies contiguous to the heart.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40751:27"/>
It thru<U+017F>ts the bloud, I <U+017F>ay, towards the extremity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e that it mu<U+017F>t occupy a <U+017F>pace in the <hi>artery</hi> equal to its natural bulk, neither greater nor <U+017F>maller; by rea<U+017F>on that a like quantity of the bloud to that, that comes out of the heart into the <hi>artery,</hi> is poured out of the vein into the heart; <U+017F>o that there is only room left in the vein to admit ju<U+017F>t as much bloud, as comes out of the heart at each <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole.</hi> And if we <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e the <U+017F>pace X A, to contain a dram of bloud, (whether more, or le<U+017F>s, makes no matter here) as we have al<U+017F>o <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ed, that the <U+017F>ame quantity comes out of the heart at every <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole,</hi> (or <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole,</hi> as <U+017F>ome would have it) it is an invincible truth, that this bloud coming out of the heart, mu<U+017F>t exactly occupy the <U+017F>pace X A; and that therefore, it thru<U+017F>ts in the <U+017F>ame time, the bloud that occupied it before, into the <U+017F>pace A B; that in A B, into the <U+017F>pace B C; that in the <U+017F>pace B C, into the <U+017F>pace C Y; and that in C Y, into the <hi>capillary</hi> end of the vein, &amp;c. And altho (according to our <hi>Hypothe<U+017F>is)</hi> the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age from the <hi>artery</hi> into the vein be much <U+017F>maller, than that of the heart into the <hi>artery;</hi> yet if the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bloud through the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is,</hi> is to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bloud at the <hi>orifice</hi> of the heart, as the <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of the heart is to the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is;</hi> that is, as X is to Y, (as it may ea<U+017F>ily be <U+017F>o, altho it is naturally otherwi<U+017F>e: the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>es,</hi> from which we have ab<U+017F>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted here, being together at lea<U+017F>t as capacious, as the <hi>orifice</hi> of the heart,) it is plain, that a dram of bloud will as <U+017F>oon pa<U+017F>s from the <hi>artery</hi> into the vein, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <U+017F>hall from the heart into the <hi>artery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40751:28"/>
And as the bloud coming out of the heart into the great <hi>artery,</hi> cannot pos<U+017F>ibly occupy a greater <U+017F>pace, than <U+017F>uch as is adequate to its volume in a conden<U+017F>ed <U+017F>tate; and that neverthele<U+017F>s it dilates it <U+017F>elf, it mu<U+017F>t ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>arily extend and dilate X A, the part of the <hi>artery</hi> that contains it, as much beyond its natural tone, or reach, as the rarefaction of the bloud increa<U+017F>es its vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume; which cannot come to pa<U+017F>s, but the<U+017F>e two things mu<U+017F>t nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily follow. Fir<U+017F>t, that when the bloud dilates it <U+017F>elf, it leaves <U+017F>ome intervals between its parts; which intervals (becau<U+017F>e there is no <hi>vacuum</hi> in nature) mu<U+017F>t in the <U+017F>ame time be filled up with <U+017F>ome other fluid matter: (which ought to be thinner than the bloud; for otherwi<U+017F>e it cou'd not pa<U+017F>s between its parts.) And as this <U+017F>ubtil matter can't come from the heart, becau<U+017F>e that then it's empty; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides its <hi>orifice</hi> is <U+017F>hut clo<U+017F>e by its three <hi>valves;</hi> it can neither come through the coats of the <hi>artery,</hi> by rea<U+017F>on of their thickne<U+017F>s, and clo<U+017F>e texture; neither is there any <U+017F>uch matter about them. It remains then only, that it mu<U+017F>t come from the bloud contained in the <hi>artery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, that the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> mu<U+017F>t be drawn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the dilated place, and the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>artery</hi> made as much narrower than ordinary, as X A, becomes wider than it u<U+017F>es to be. Whereby the <hi>artery</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed round about, the vital <U+017F>pirit is <U+017F>queezed from between the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed parts of the bloud, and forced to advance towards the dilated place; in <U+017F>uch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that as much of the <hi><U+017F>pirit,</hi> as is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to fill
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40751:28"/>
up the <U+017F>paces left between the parts of the dilated bloud, is <U+017F>ent thither from between the parts of that, which is compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed; the remnant of the <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> being equally di<U+017F>tributed through the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>artery;</hi> <U+017F>o that if every one of the four parts, or divi<U+017F>ions of the <hi>artery,</hi> contains a certain quantity of vital <hi><U+017F>pirit,</hi> di<U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>hed into three parts, and that three of tho<U+017F>e parts, do pa<U+017F>s from A B, into X A, two of them will in the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tant pa<U+017F>s from B C, into A B; and one from C Y, into B C; in which action con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts the ebbing, or <hi><U+017F>y<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>artery.</hi> And as a rope, (or more <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly, a gut-<U+017F>tring) which is fixed to any place, being pulled with a jerk, will draw back again him that drew it at fir<U+017F>t; <U+017F>o likewi<U+017F>e the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> being extended vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, and on a <U+017F>udden, upon the <hi>dilatation</hi> of the <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> do come back again <hi>in<U+017F>tantaneou<U+017F>ly,</hi> (by rea<U+017F>on that <U+017F>ome of the parts of each <hi>Fibre,</hi> being <U+017F>trongly thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ted towards its middle, and <U+017F>omewhat bent from its circumference towards its centre, do pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>pring back again, extending them<U+017F>elves according to the bredth of the <hi>Fibre;</hi> whereby the <U+017F>aid <hi>Fibre</hi> is nece<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily as much <U+017F>hortned, as it had been <U+017F>tretch'd before) and re<U+017F>titute them<U+017F>elves into their former <U+017F>ituation &amp; <hi>tone;</hi> (which they are facilitated to do by the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of that extraordinary agitation of the bloud; which it communicates in an in<U+017F>tant to the yielding <U+017F>ides of the <hi>artery)</hi> forcing thereby three parts of the vital <hi><U+017F>pirit,</hi> or <U+017F>ubtil matter, to repa<U+017F>s from X A, to A B; and the two parts, that were already in A B, to pa<U+017F>s into B C; from whence another will pa<U+017F>s into C Y, &amp;c.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40751:29"/>
which makes the flowing, or <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>artery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I fore<U+017F>ee an Objection, that <U+017F>ome may make again<U+017F>t what we have <U+017F>aid, that that portion of the bloud, that comes out of the heart in its <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole,</hi> is dilated, and yet occupies no more of the <hi>artery,</hi> than if it were conden<U+017F>ed; only that part of the <hi>artery</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it, is a little more extended than the re<U+017F>t: for, they will <U+017F>ay, this <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>es, that both the <hi>artery</hi> and the vein are always full of bloud; being certain, that if the bloud, in coming out of the heart into the great <hi>artery,</hi> did find there any empty <U+017F>pace, where it might expand it <U+017F>elf freely, it would <U+017F>tart forwards into it, and then it wou'd not dilate the <hi>artery,</hi> nor by con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence draw the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres;</hi> and therefore there wou'd neither be <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole</hi> nor <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole</hi> in the <hi>artery:</hi> But it is mo<U+017F>t certain, they will continue, that men have <U+017F>ometimes more, and <U+017F>ometimes le<U+017F>s bloud in their bodies: and that if a man has, for example, fifteen oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of bloud drawn, it will follow; that there being a vacuity in the <hi>Sanguiducts,</hi> till the <U+017F>ame quantity of bloud be regenerated a-new, the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e</hi> mu<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o cea<U+017F>e till then; which being contradicted by daily experience, they will conclude, that the motion of the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres,</hi> with whatever el<U+017F>e we have taught concerning the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> is altogether <hi>chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical.</hi> To which I an<U+017F>wer in few words, that for the <hi>Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> and Circulation of the Bloud, it matters not at all, whether or no, the <hi>artery</hi> and vein be quite full of bloud; <U+017F>ince that as the bloud decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es in them, the mu<U+017F>cles of the limbs, and other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40751:29"/>
parts, do proportionably compre<U+017F>s them round about; <U+017F>o that their internal <U+017F>uperficies touches the bloud continually every way; which has the <U+017F>ame effect, as if the <hi>artery</hi> and vein were exactly full of bloud: for the bloud coming out of the heart, and finding as much difficulty in lifting up the adjacent parts, as to drive on the bloud of the <hi>artery</hi> and vein, when they are full on't; it's forced to keep the <U+017F>ame order and method in that ca<U+017F>e, as it does in this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning its dilatation and place in the <hi>artery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, the<U+017F>e being the true and genuine rea<U+017F>ons of the <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole,</hi> and <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole</hi> of the <hi>arteries,</hi> it's very ea<U+017F>y thereby to explain all the <hi>Phenomena</hi> relating to <hi>Galen</hi>'s experiment. For the Quill being put into the <hi>artery,</hi> and left there without being tied, the <hi>artery</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthele<U+017F>s beat <U+017F>till above and below the Quill, as it did before; becau<U+017F>e that the <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> can <U+017F>till play to and fro from one end of the <hi>artery</hi> to the other, without impediment. But if you bind the <U+017F>ides of the <hi>artery</hi> upon the Quill, the motion of the <U+017F>ame <hi><U+017F>piral Fibres</hi> will be intercopted by the <hi>ligature;</hi> <U+017F>o that it mu<U+017F>t nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily follow, (by the foregoing rea<U+017F>ons,) that the <hi>artery</hi> being not alternatively compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, and dilated betwixt the <U+017F>aid <hi>ligature</hi> and the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Pul<U+017F>e</hi> mu<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o cea<U+017F>e in that part of the <U+017F>aid <hi>artery,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Many things may ea<U+017F>ily be explained by this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, tho impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be interpreted any otherwi<U+017F>e; which therefore become as many proofs of its verity: as namely, the difference which is between the <hi>arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40751:30"/>
and venal bloud. For (having demon<U+017F>trated above, that when the bloud advances in the great <hi>artery</hi> from the heart towards the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is,</hi> and from thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vein, the vital <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> goes in the very <U+017F>ame time from the <hi>ana<U+017F>tomo<U+017F>is</hi> towards the heart; whereby the <U+017F>aid <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> is nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily kept within the <hi>artery;)</hi> it is certain, that this di<U+017F>parity proceeds from the want of <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> in the venal to keep its parts in agitation; which abounding in the <hi>arterial,</hi> keeps it in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual effervency, &amp;c. I cou'd add many other things to authorize what we have <U+017F>aid concerning the <hi>Beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Pul<U+017F>e,</hi> and <hi>Circulation</hi> of the Bloud: but I hope this will <U+017F>uffice to rational men, and <U+017F>uch as are of a <hi>Mechanical Genius.</hi> As for tho<U+017F>e that attribute all things to final cau<U+017F>es, and have recour<U+017F>e upon every occa<U+017F>ion, to the de<U+017F>igns and intentions of Nature; (as when they <U+017F>ay, that the Eye-brows are made to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sweat from falling into the eyes, &amp;c.) if, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding all that we can do, they remain <U+017F>till in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>en<U+017F>ible to our rea<U+017F>ons, it matters not much; and, in my opinion, <U+017F>uch per<U+017F>ons had a great deal better <U+017F>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>A<U+017F>trology;</hi> or, if they are big with devotion, go and comment upon <hi>Job,</hi> or Paraphra<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome <hi>P<U+017F>alms,</hi> than meddle with <hi>Phy<U+017F>ical</hi> matters.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40751:30"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section I.</hi> Of the Nature of the Teeth <hi>Page 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. II.</hi> Of the Alteration of the Teeth <hi>p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. III.</hi> Of the Corruption of the Teeth, with their Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies <hi>p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The De<U+017F>cription and <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>e of the Polican <hi>p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. IV.</hi> Of the Re<U+017F>tauration of the Teeth <hi>p. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. V.</hi> Of the Tooth-ake, Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s of the Teeth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Gums, with their Remedies <hi>p. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. VI. <hi>Of Childrens Teeth</hi> p. 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. VII.</hi> Of the Acceleration of the Teeth <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Adverti<U+017F>ement to the Readers <hi>p. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Phy<U+017F>ical Dicour<U+017F>e concerning the Beating of the Pul<U+017F>e, and Circulation of the Bloud <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Explication</hi> p. 52</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>

