<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the causes of some particular rebellious distempers viz. the scurvey, cancers in women's breasts, &amp;c. vapours, and melancholy, &amp;c. weaknesses in women, &amp;c. gout, fistula in ano, dropsy, agues, &amp;c. : together with the vertues and uses of a select number of chymical medicines studiously prepar'd for their cure and adapted to the constitutions and temperaments of all ages and both sexes / by an eminent practitioner in physick, surgery and chymistry ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2006-02">2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11968041</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11968041</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A24961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 46:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the causes of some particular rebellious distempers viz. the scurvey, cancers in women's breasts, &amp;c. vapours, and melancholy, &amp;c. weaknesses in women, &amp;c. gout, fistula in ano, dropsy, agues, &amp;c. : together with the vertues and uses of a select number of chymical medicines studiously prepar'd for their cure and adapted to the constitutions and temperaments of all ages and both sexes / by an eminent practitioner in physick, surgery and chymistry ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51771:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Account of the
CAUSES
Of <U+017F>ome Particular Rebellious
DISTEMPERS,
<hi>VIZ.</hi> 
               <list>
                  <item>The Scurvy,</item>
                  <item>Cancers in Women's
Brea<U+017F>ts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vapours, and
Melancholy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es in Women,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gout,</item>
                  <item>Fi<U+017F>tula <hi>in Ano,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Drop<U+017F>y,</item>
                  <item>Agues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> TOGETHER
With the Vertues and U<U+017F>es of a Select Number of
Chymical Medicines Studiou<U+017F>ly prepar'd for their Cure,
and adapted to the Con<U+017F>titutions and Temperaments
of all Ages, and both Sexes.</p>
            <p>By an Eminent Practitioner in Phy<U+017F>ick, Surgery
and Chymi<U+017F>try.</p>
            <p>THEY BEING
His Choice Secrets, Experienc'd for many Years in
his Practice, to be of wonderful Efficacy, as the
Cures performed by them Manife<U+017F>t; and now, by
the Importunities of many judicious Per<U+017F>ons, <U+017F>et forth
and recommended for the univer<U+017F>al Good and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of all People:</p>
            <p>And are to be had only at <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51771:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51771:2"/>
            <head>THE
PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THERE needs no Apology for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<U+017F>hing
the following Account of
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and the Medicines for
their Cure, the Title Page telling
the World, <hi>'Tis done for the univer<U+017F>al Good
and Benefit of all People,</hi> which indeed was
the Motive; but that the excellent Remedies
recommended for their Cure, may not be branded
with the infamous Appellation of <hi>Quack Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines,</hi>
<U+017F>o dete<U+017F>table to all wi<U+017F>e People (and
indeed not without Rea<U+017F>on, if it be rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider'd
what Riff raff Stuff is <U+017F>et Abroad and
vended under the Specious Name of Medicine)
I <U+017F>hall take leave to <U+017F>ay only thus much in their
behalf, that they have all of them been really
<pb facs="tcp:51771:3"/>
experienc'd for many Years, to be of mo<U+017F>t excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
U<U+017F>es for the Di<U+017F>tempers to which they are
appropriated; and 'tis pre<U+017F>um'd will be found
upon Tryal, more Efficacious than <U+017F>ome may be
willing to believe, upon only the bare hearing of
them, or by reading the following Account given
of their Vertues, which have been lagely known,
or el<U+017F>e had not been recommended: Therefore
'tis hoped, as the intent by publi<U+017F>hing them was
to <hi><U+017F>erve</hi> and not <hi>deceive</hi> the People, as is too
notorio<U+017F>luy known, many of the Quack Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
vended Abroad have done, to the bringing
di<U+017F>repute on the mo<U+017F>t excellent ones, none will
condemn them, till they have tryed them, which
is the true Te<U+017F>t, and by which the Author is
content to Stand or Fall, have Credit or Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</p>
            <p>The Hi<U+017F>tories of Cures perform'd by them,
might have been enumerated, had not de<U+017F>ign'd
Brevity forbid. The few in<U+017F>erted 'tis hop'd will
be <U+017F>ufficient to convince all People till they have
tryed them, that they are Medicines effectual;
and for further Confirmation, <U+017F>hould have
mentioned the Names of the Per<U+017F>ons on whom
the Cures were wrought; but that the Author
is obliged to conceal him<U+017F>elf for the <U+017F>ake of his
con<U+017F>tant Bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s; be<U+017F>ides, the World is now <U+017F>o
<pb facs="tcp:51771:3"/>
Cen<U+017F>orious, that if the be<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>ician recommends
but a Medicine for Publick Good, which he has
experienc'd to be Excellent, he <U+017F>hall pre<U+017F>ently have
the <U+017F>candalous Epithet of Quack put upon him,
tho' its no more than what the greate<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>icians
in all Ages have done, without thinking it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<U+017F><U+017F>ive;
becau<U+017F>e they did it, as the Author here
does his, for the common good of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
but now I <U+017F>ay it cannot be done publickly,
with any tollerable Reputation: For which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
does the Author conceal him<U+017F>elf, and oblig'd
the Seller of them never to let his Name be
known to any, without which <U+017F>olemn Promi<U+017F>e,
they had never been made publick, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently
the People never been benefitted by
them.</p>
            <p>But becau<U+017F>e of this, none need to doubt their
Efficacy, neither will any want proper Directions
how to take and u<U+017F>e them, every thing in that
kind being <U+017F>ufficiently provided for in the Book,
<U+017F>o that none will be at a lo<U+017F>s, or have any need
at any time, upon any pretence, to <U+017F>peak with the
Author concerning 'em; be<U+017F>ides, for their Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy,
the People that <U+017F>ell them can give <U+017F>ome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
being well a<U+017F><U+017F>ur'd both of their Vertues
and the Authors Skill, or el<U+017F>e had not underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
the task of <U+017F>elling them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51771:4"/>
And as they are Medicines effectual, <U+017F>o are
they la<U+017F>ting; for they will retain their Vertues
many Years, and may be carried beyond the Seas:
For that no Climate, Sea<U+017F>on of the Year, or Age
will in the lea<U+017F>t altet or dimini<U+017F>h them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
they be kept from the Air and the
Wet.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_medicines">
            <pb facs="tcp:51771:4"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the Names and
Prices of the Medicines mentioned in this
Book, which are to be had only at the
Place directed in the Title Page, viz. At
the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1. THE <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills for the Scurvy, &amp;c. each
Box Price 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 19. The <hi>Liniment</hi> for Women's Swell'd or Cance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
Brea<U+017F>ts, each Gallipot price 5 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 33. The Suffumigating Powder for Vapours, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condriack
Melancholly and Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Nerves, each
Parcel 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 42. The Ingredients to make the Poultice for the
<hi>Gout,</hi> price 5 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 50. The Bal<U+017F>amick Electuary for Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es in
Women, &amp;c. each Gallypot price 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 55. The Injection for the Cure of <hi>Fi<U+017F>tula's,</hi> each
Bottle price 5 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 61. The Cephalick, or Head Tincture, each Bottle
price 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 67. The Bal<U+017F>amick Re<U+017F>torative Elixir for all Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es
of the Lungs, each Bottle price 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 70. The <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Vegetable and Plai<U+017F>ters for
the Cure of all <U+017F>orts of Agues, both together price
6 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 76. The Hydragogue Tincture for the Drop<U+017F>y, each
Bottle price 3 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:51771:5"/>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 79. The fam'd Eye Powder and Water, both together
price 6 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 81. The Carminative, or Wind expelling Lozenges,
each Box price 2 s. 6 d</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 83. The Bal<U+017F>am to make I<U+017F><U+017F>ues run, &amp;c each Box
price 2 s. 6 d.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51771:5"/>
            <head>Engli<U+017F>h PILLS
FOR THE
SCURVY,
And all other Cutaneous Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, or Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
out of the Body, Sores, &amp;c. from that or
any other Cau<U+017F>es.</head>
            <p>AMONGST all the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es incident to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
Bodies, there is none more predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
(tho' lea<U+017F>t regarded) than the <hi>Scurvy,</hi>
a Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e that <U+017F>eems incident to this Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,
and which <U+017F>pares none of any Age,
Sex or Con<U+017F>titution, being a general Malady <U+017F>carcely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
Notice of, becau<U+017F>e it <U+017F>eldom kills, tho at the <U+017F>ame
time it introduces many direful Di<U+017F>tempers, and proves
the principal and efficient Occa<U+017F>ion thereof.</p>
            <p>The cau<U+017F>e of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> is from an acid corro<U+017F>ive
Humour tainting the Blood and Juices of the Body,
incumbred with Earthy Sulphurs of a Nature rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious
and <U+017F>tubborn, and attended <U+017F>ometimes (e<U+017F>pecially
when inveterate) with a very <U+017F>trong Smell or Stench;
which Volatile Saline Acid, irritates the Nerves and
Membranes, <U+017F>harpens the Lymph, debauches the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Spirits of the Parts, and perverts the equal Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature
of the Blood; this is the immediate cau<U+017F>e of the
<hi>Scurvy:</hi> But the remote Cau<U+017F>es, are the Sea-Air, and
the Specifick Malignity of the Stagnated Waters and
the Earth, affecting, by their corro<U+017F>ive Effluvium's, al<U+017F>o
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51771:6"/>
by infection, an hereditary conveyance from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
and from gro<U+017F>s, faeculent and ob<U+017F>tructive Dyet,
e<U+017F>pecially if over-charged with Salt, or render'd hard
and compact with Smoke, as dry'd Neats Tongues,
Bacon, Sawcages, red Herrings, dry'd Salmon, hung
Beef, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do not only contribute Matter, but obtain
al<U+017F>o a peculiar faculty of impre<U+017F><U+017F>ing a Scorbutick Idea
on it: Of the <U+017F>ame Nature are Melancholick Meats, as
Beef, Pork, Gee<U+017F>e, Ducks, Salt-fi<U+017F>h, and all other Fi<U+017F>h
that are bred in Standing Waters, as Eeles and others;
al<U+017F>o pickled and marinaded Fi<U+017F>h, as pickled Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,
Anchovies, and the like, which bears a great
part in this Morbifick Production; al<U+017F>o a Salin Air
render'd thick and con<U+017F>tipative by Vapours and Damps,
Nitrous Evaporations out of the Earth, filled with pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid
Steams of Sinks, Gutters, Ditches, muddy and
dirty Streets, and Sulphurous Smokes of Chimneys,
<U+017F>tagnating and pent up between narrow Lanes and
Corners, and <U+017F>eldom or but little <U+017F>erenated, or putrify'd,
by the Rays of a clear <U+017F>hining Sun, nor frequently ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilated
with Ea<U+017F>terly Breezes, and <U+017F>uch is the Clime
of <hi>London,</hi> where the Air is experienced clo<U+017F>e, dull,
damp, <U+017F>alin and muddy, over-<U+017F>pread with den<U+017F>e,
dark, <U+017F>alin Clouds (attracted out of the Sea) for two
Thirds, if not three Fourth Parts of the Year, during
which time the Winds <U+017F>eldom blow Ea<U+017F>terly, or is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
with a <U+017F>miling Sun; the two, <hi>viz.</hi> Dyet and
State of the Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are accounted by all, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,
external and internal Agents or Cau<U+017F>es of the
<hi>Scurvy,</hi> agre<U+017F><U+017F>ing the Body both within and without;
the fir<U+017F>t by making its efforts on the Stomach and its
Ferment, thereby a<U+017F><U+017F>aulting the Blood and animal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor;
and the latter, by entring the external Pores by
their <U+017F>ubtle effluvium's, as is mo<U+017F>t certainly and at large
<U+017F>et forth in a late ingenious Tract, entituled, <hi>Scelera
Aquarum;</hi> Wherein the Author tells us,</p>
            <q>
               <p> That <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
is <U+017F>ituated on a wicked Bottom of Earth called
blue Clay; this Bottom is many contiguous, tho'
<U+017F>eparated Bodies, extends it <U+017F>elf round the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
and Lines of Communication <U+017F>ome Miles in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference,
and reacheth likewi<U+017F>e downwards to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51771:6"/>
an enormous Depth towards the Center; for the
boreings that have been frequently made by the
Brewers in que<U+017F>t of the impregnated Water (called
Spring Liquor) hath been mo<U+017F>tly attempted to thirty
and forty Fathom Depth without <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>As all <U+017F>orts of Clay are found by Experience and
Ob<U+017F>ervations of Country Farmers and Brewers, to
abound with a Juice or Salt of an E<U+017F>urine Acid Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and Quality, which vitiates all the Fruits of the
Earth, except it be fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>weetned and <U+017F>heath'd by Chalk
both crude and calcin'd into Lime; <U+017F>o this blue kind
of Glebe more <U+017F>celerous and corro<U+017F>ive than all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
maleficates equally Air and Water, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
all the <U+017F>tagnate Waters of the Neighbourhood
e<U+017F>urine to a very high degree.</p>
               <p>And here it is that the bounty of Nature hath
made it <U+017F>elf remarkable to the Eye, in burying this
bottom of Clay near twenty foot in depth under
Ground; and be<U+017F>ides, covering it over and over
with repeated Strata of diffe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent kinds of Moulds to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the Gravelly Surface of the Earth, left the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>phere
<U+017F>hould be invaded, and the ambient Air
we a<U+017F>pire, <U+017F>hould be thereby exa<U+017F>perated and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
Catarrhous, through the corro<U+017F>ive effluvia <U+017F>ent
up from below; <U+017F>o that till about One Hundred and
Fifty Years ago, when an endle<U+017F>s number of Perfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
began to be made by the common Brewers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Subterranean World, the City of <hi>London</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
its Native State of Health, and was entirely
free from Coughs and Catarrhs, Periodical Fevers,
vulgarly call'd Agues; and in a word, from all the
Symtomatical Branches of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> hitherto enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated.</p>
               <p>And here it may be ob<U+017F>erved by the by, that the
acrid Effluvia <U+017F>ent up from the Clayey Bottom, by
rea<U+017F>on of their volatile Nature, do little harm in
the Summer Sea<U+017F>on; but during that of the Winter,
whil<U+017F>t they are weighed down and reverberated back
towards the Bafis of the Atmo<U+017F>phere by the Fogs and
Fro<U+017F>ts; then I may <U+017F>ay it is, and not till then, that
they begin to Bite even Per<U+017F>ons adult, bur more e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51771:7"/>
the un<U+017F>ea<U+017F>on'd Bodies of Children and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners.</p>
               <p>In <U+017F>hort, the <hi>Scelus Aquoe &amp; Loci,</hi> or corrupted or
corro<U+017F>ive Waters, here in<U+017F>i<U+017F>ted on; <U+017F>lept for a long
Succe<U+017F><U+017F>ion of Ages, out of Harms way in the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
of the Subterranean World; and be<U+017F>ides, the
corro<U+017F>ive Waters were not employed either in Bread
or potable Liquors extracted forth of Malt: And, as
I may add, they were only made u<U+017F>e of for clearing
of the Sight, and for eating away the Kells and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracts
off of dim Eyes.</p>
               <p>But about the Acce<U+017F><U+017F>ion of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to the
Crown (as I am well inform'd) Clay Waters began
to grow into credit with <U+017F>uch as Brewed or Baked for
Sale, as a more powerful-Men<U+017F>truum, for extracting
the Tincture out of Malt: And at that period of Time,
it was that the Waters of <hi>D AT C.</hi> were Carted from
<hi>Hog<U+017F>don</hi> to the <U+017F>everal Brew-hou<U+017F>es in the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,
or City of <hi>London,</hi> at 800 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> Expence;
and at the <U+017F>ame time a world of Wells were made,
and Pumps erected at every corner of the City and
Suburbs.</p>
               <p>In a word, the <hi>Scelus Aquoe &amp; Loci,</hi> now <U+017F>poken
of, that is to <U+017F>ay, the acrid Nature and e<U+017F>urine
Quality of the Stagnate Waters in and about this
City, is <U+017F>ufficiently evinced a <hi>Po<U+017F>teriori</hi> from the ill
natur'd Effects thereof in all Dome<U+017F>tick U<U+017F>es. Fir<U+017F>t,
in chopping and ditching of Hands and Face: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
from coagulating of Alcalous Fluids, both
Soap and Barm: Thirdly, from hardening of Pea<U+017F>e
and redning of Bacon, and all Fle<U+017F>h Meats, if boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
therein; which the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> enumerates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<U+017F>t
ill Signs and Diagno<U+017F>tick of In<U+017F>alubrity or
Unwhol<U+017F>omne<U+017F>s: Fourthly, from the killing of
Flowers and de<U+017F>troying all manner of Garden-<U+017F>tuff,
unle<U+017F>s the acid Salt be r<U+017F>t fievaporated by open Air<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
and In<U+017F>olations on the Surface of the Earth, as
was practi<U+017F>ed by the Ancients, and put in practice
by Gardeners to this Day.</p>
               <p>I had almo<U+017F>t forgot to add here, that the prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
bottom of Clay now <U+017F>poken of, extends it <U+017F>elf
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51771:7"/>
from the Metropolis, or City of <hi>London,</hi> all along the
Banks of the River <hi>Thames,</hi> into the Mar<U+017F>hes or Flats
of <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ex,</hi> which vitiates both Air and Water in the
<hi>Hundreds</hi> to a very high degree, whereby the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
hath been laid of <U+017F>uch Chronical Fevers, and
Scorbutick Agues, as ince<U+017F><U+017F>ently reign in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tricts
of <hi>Dench</hi> and <hi>Rochefort.</hi> In a word, the River
of <hi>Thames</hi> is al<U+017F>o vitiated by Dyers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> <U+017F>o that no
Water is fit for Bread and Brewer's u<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ave the
New River, which is far more Salubrious or Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
than any other Water in or about the City of
<hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>However, the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> whether from immediate or
remote Cau<U+017F>es, is certainly a Corruption and Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
of the Blood and Humours; whence the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction
being hurt, the Stomach (which is the Index of
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es) is depraved, Ob<U+017F>tructions of the Liver and
Spleen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are occa<U+017F>ion'd, bringing, by degrees, a
general Cachexie, or evil Habit of Body; whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
and complicated Di<U+017F>tempers are at length intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,
which affects all Per<U+017F>ons according to their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
and different Tempers and Con<U+017F>titutions.</p>
            <p>Such I <U+017F>ay is the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> that grand Enemy to Health,
and only reigning Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of this Kingdom, which Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons
of all Ranks, Ages and Sexes are more or le<U+017F>s af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
with, it being the original and productive Cau<U+017F>e
of almo<U+017F>t all the Di<U+017F>tempers incident to Humane Bodies;
and from which alone Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e (if not timely removed)
more e<U+017F>pecially proceed Rheumati<U+017F>ms, Gouts, Fevers,
Agues, Jaundice, Green-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, Drop<U+017F>ies, Cholicks,
Stone and Gravel, Phty<U+017F>icks, Con<U+017F>umptions, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions,
Apoplexies, Palfies, Hectick Fevers, Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack
Melancholly, Hy<U+017F>terick Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, Vapours, Fits
of the Mother, Rickets in Children, Kings-evil, Fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Sickne<U+017F>s, and the like, which the<U+017F>e Pills, if taken,
both prevents and Cures; their Reputation having, by
their manifold Vertues, been kept up for many Years,
and accounted the only Sovereign Medicine in the
whole Art of Phy<U+017F>ick, again<U+017F>t all Scorbutick Di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
what<U+017F>oever; they penetrating, in a very <U+017F>hort
<U+017F>pace, the whole Humane Body from Head to Foot;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51771:8"/>
and tho' they never till now were made publick to
the World, yet many Thou<U+017F>ands of Boxes have been
di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed with wonderful Succe<U+017F>s, not only here in
<hi>England,</hi> but al<U+017F>o in <hi>Germany, Holland,</hi> and other
remote Countries, where that devouring Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, the
<hi>Scurvy,</hi> hath likewi<U+017F>e predominated, they being <U+017F>o cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
a Cure for that <U+017F>tubborn and rebellious Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e,
that Thou<U+017F>ands have been cured, when the Di<U+017F>temper
has grown <U+017F>o inveterate and deplorable, as to become a
<U+017F>hame and <U+017F>candal to tho<U+017F>e that have had it, and which
hath been taken by many to be <U+017F>ome bad Di<U+017F>temper;
for the <hi>Scurvy</hi> often cau<U+017F>es great Pains in the Head,
No<U+017F>e, Shoulders, Arms, Hips, Legs, and Bones, with
the Sciatick and other tormenting Pains all over the
whole Body, whereby they <U+017F>leep ill, and tumble
and to<U+017F>s in the Night with great unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s and
trouble, and are attended with a heavine<U+017F>s and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
having reddi<U+017F>h or bluei<U+017F>h Spots or Breakings out
on the Skin, weakne<U+017F>s in the Back, Loyns and Knees,
a bad Stomach, and <U+017F>ometimes lo<U+017F>s of Appetite, <U+017F>trong
or <U+017F>tinking Breath, loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s or forene<U+017F>s of the Teeth
and Gums, Throat and Mouth, with Itchings, Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
Blotches, Boiles, Ulcers, Morphews, Scabs, Scurf,
a general Weakne<U+017F>s and Faintne<U+017F>s over the whole Body;
the Scurvy mo<U+017F>t commonly afflicting People after va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
means, and <U+017F>ometimes with Vomitings, Loo<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es,
and the di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e of almo<U+017F>t innumerable Di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
according to their Con<U+017F>titutions, different Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and Places where they dwell, and <U+017F>o re<U+017F>emble
all manner of Ille<U+017F>s, too tedious here to enumerate, as
that its no wonder their Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are <U+017F>o frequently mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>taken,
and doth, with <U+017F>o much violence and force, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
wander about the Body and affect it, that if
it be neglected, it will at la<U+017F>t get into the Bones, and
infect the very Marrow thereof, yet notwith<U+017F>tanding
(<U+017F>o famous are the<U+017F>e mo<U+017F>t excellent Pills) the Cure then
will be performed, by only a few times more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
taking of them.</p>
            <p>Tho' it is advised, that upon the appearance of any
of tho<U+017F>e Symptoms, you have <U+017F>peedy recour<U+017F>e to the<U+017F>e
Pills, which will prevent their increa<U+017F>e, and carry them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51771:8"/>
off with le<U+017F>s trouble and difficulty; there being <U+017F>carce
one Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e which People are afflicted with here in this
Climate, but the principal and efficient Cau<U+017F>e thereof is
the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> that Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e carrying Thou<U+017F>ands to their
Graves, when it <U+017F>carcely has been known-of what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tempers
they have dy'd, there being very few that
di<U+017F>cerns, or indeed will give, them<U+017F>elves the trouble to
con<U+017F>ider what the original Cau<U+017F>e or occa<U+017F>ion thereof is,
tho' it too manife<U+017F>tly appears (as every judicious Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ician
may di<U+017F>cover, if he will,) that it is the <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
Therefore be well advis'd about your Di<U+017F>temper, and
run not into the Hands of incon<U+017F>iderate Practitioners,
who take not due Thoughts about the original Cau<U+017F>e;
for how many, both Old and Young, are daily carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
off by Fevers, Rheumati<U+017F>ins, Apoplexies, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umptions,
Convul<U+017F>ions, Rickets, King's-evil, and
the like; which, if the original Cau<U+017F>e had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ulted,
and timely recour<U+017F>e had to the<U+017F>e famous Pills,
might in all probability have been alive to this day;
the<U+017F>e Pills being very harmle<U+017F>s and <U+017F>afe, and proves the
only Univer<U+017F>al, Purgative, Pre<U+017F>ervative, Preventative
and Curative Remedy, in the whole Republick of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</p>
            <p>They wonderfully, <U+017F>o far as any Purging Medicine
can<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> prevent and cure the Drop<U+017F>y and Gout <U+017F>peedily
(tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es being the product of the <hi>Scurvy</hi>) taking
away the Water in one, and the Pain in the other, tho'
never <U+017F>o great, and not only gives pre<U+017F>ent Ea<U+017F>e, Relief,
and Comfort in the Gout, and that beyond expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but al<U+017F>o very much le<U+017F><U+017F>ens, if not totally prevents
the Pains returning for the future, they working gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
by Stool and Urine, and <U+017F>ometimes by Vomit, if the
Stomach be very foul, without the lea<U+017F>t Griping or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<U+017F>ick; thereby curing mo<U+017F>t curable Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, by
<U+017F>tirring up and di<U+017F>charging tho<U+017F>e lurking, offending
Humours, <U+017F>weetning the Ma<U+017F>s of Blood and Juices,
and bringing the ill and untoward Habit of Body into
a good, <U+017F>ound and firm Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition: The<U+017F>e Pills having
cured numbers of Per<U+017F>ons both of Drop<U+017F>ies and Gouts,
and that in a very <U+017F>hort time; <U+017F>ome of which have
been given over as incurable, others have gone above
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51771:9"/>
a dozen Years upon Crutches, and never heard to this
Day, that they ever mi<U+017F>t the Cure of one Per<U+017F>on al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
they have been u<U+017F>ed in Practice for above
Twenty Years.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are admirably good again<U+017F>t Con<U+017F>umpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of all <U+017F>orts, that di<U+017F>heartning Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e <U+017F>o daily and
apparently dwindling a Per<U+017F>on to the Grave (and is the
manife<U+017F>t product of the <hi>Scurvy</hi>) not <U+017F>o much from
their adding of Matter, as by taking away the Ob<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
which hinder the Nouri<U+017F>hment from going to
its re<U+017F>pective Parts; in which Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, whether in Old
or Young, they have done Miracles, making the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons
grow plump and full, who but a while before
were reduced to nothing but Skin and Bones; and this
they have generally performed, and <U+017F>carcely been ever
known to fail.</p>
            <p>Al<U+017F>o in that rebellious, trouble<U+017F>ome and oftentimes
loath<U+017F>ome Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, the King's-evil, whether hereditary
or not, which numbers of Per<U+017F>ons of different Ages
and Sexes are infe<U+017F>ted with; they are a wonderful Help
and Cure, whether in the Swellings or running Sores,
di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ing the vitiated and <U+017F>corbutick Blood and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
into <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>tate, that the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is as it were
pulled up by the Roots as never to return again.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e famous Pills are the mo<U+017F>t excellent Head-purge
in Nature, and that for all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es therein, as Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach,
Megrim or Swimming, Vertigo or Giddine<U+017F>s, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy,
Frenzy, Madne<U+017F>s, Melancholy, Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the
Spleen, Dimne<U+017F>s of Sight, Rheums and all other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tempers
in the Eyes, Dea<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, Noi<U+017F>e in the Ears,
Drow<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, Heavine<U+017F>s or Dulne<U+017F>s of the Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
(all the<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>tempers proceeding originally from Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick
habits) and is a Medicine beyond any ever yet
known, being of <U+017F>o Amicable a Property, that none
can pretend to a greater Secret to extirpate the <hi>Scurvy</hi>
and all the effects thereof; there being no Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e <U+017F>o
remote or ab<U+017F>tru<U+017F>e <U+017F>oever in the Body of Man, but the<U+017F>e
Pills will find out, in<U+017F>inuate into, and potently and
univer<U+017F>ally expel or throw out.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are an admirable help for <U+017F>uch Per<U+017F>ons,
who are unhappily afflicted with the <hi>Scurvy</hi> to that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51771:9"/>
degree, as to be exerci<U+017F>ed with Hypochondriack Di<U+017F>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
Hy<U+017F>terick Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, ri<U+017F>ings in the Throat, the
frightful, and as it were dying Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, the Vapours
of all <U+017F>orts, Fits of the Mother, Cloggings, Stuffings,
Gnawings or Illne<U+017F>s at Stomach, whether from Wind,
Humours, or the like; al<U+017F>o for <U+017F>uch as grow too fat,
<U+017F>weat much, and have nau<U+017F>eous <U+017F>pittings in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
Bleeding at No<U+017F>e, Cachexies, have co<U+017F>tive or hot
Bodies, and for all as have lo<U+017F>t their Complexions by
the Green-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, Jaundice or otherwi<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>uch
as are overtaken with lingring Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, growing wor<U+017F>e
and wor<U+017F>e every Year than other, not knowing well
what they ail, having ill Dige<U+017F>tions, Stoppages in the
Head and Brea<U+017F>t, <U+017F>hortne<U+017F>s of Breath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till <U+017F>uch
time as they fall into Drop<U+017F>ies, Hectick Fevers, or deep
Con<U+017F>umptions, pining and wa<U+017F>ting away with dry
Coughs, Whee<U+017F>ings, faint Sweats in the Day or Night,
Weakne<U+017F>s, fainting Fits, and the like. The<U+017F>e admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
Pills carry off all tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es the right way, by
taking them twice or thrice in a Month, or oftner if
you find occa<U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p>They are the be<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>ick in Nature for to take Spring
and Fall, as a Preventative Remedy and to pre<U+017F>erve
Health, as mo<U+017F>t People that have any regard to the
welfare and <U+017F>ecurity thereof, are mindful to take; and
likewi<U+017F>e from any Di<U+017F>order or Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, whether
from Heats or Colds, Surfeits by eating or drinking,
or the like. If taken as <U+017F>oon as your perceive your <U+017F>elf
ill, they mo<U+017F>t a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly prevent any Fever or other
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e from invading you; and there is as much pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
in taking Phy<U+017F>ick Spring and Fall, twice or three
times in each Sea<U+017F>on, to di<U+017F>charge the peccant Humours
which are heap'd up in the Stomach and lodge there
(tho' at the <U+017F>ame time you <U+017F>eem to be very well in
Health) thereby to pre<U+017F>erve from, and prevent Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es
which all Per<U+017F>ons are liable to every Moment, as there
is to take Phy<U+017F>ick for curing tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es when they
have <U+017F>eized you; and no Per<U+017F>on that de<U+017F>ires a happy
and healthy State of Body, will be <U+017F>o imprudent to
neglect that which is <U+017F>o ab<U+017F>olutely and undeniably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary
for for the pre<U+017F>ervation thereof; and I can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51771:10"/>
them, from a very large Experience, that no Phy<U+017F>ick
under the Sun will an<U+017F>wer <U+017F>uch a purpo<U+017F>e beyond
the<U+017F>e famous <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills purge by Stool, Phlegm, Choller and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy,
di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ing all old Ulcers, Fi<U+017F>tula's, running
Sores, Sore Brea<U+017F>ts, Sore Eyes, Scald Head, King's evil,
Swellings or Sores, Wounds, Gangreens, Cankers,
Cancers, Tettars, Ring-worms, Scabs, Salt Humours,
or any other Breakings out, as Pu<U+017F>hes, Boils, Wheals,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> to a <U+017F>peedy healing, by purging away the evil
Humours which feed them; and perfectly removes the
cau<U+017F>e of the Elephantia<U+017F>is or Lepro<U+017F>y.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are of wonderful u<U+017F>e for all Travellers,
Seamen and <U+017F>uch like Per<U+017F>ons who live on bad Dyet,in
ill Airs and moi<U+017F>t Places,and near the Sea Coa<U+017F>t; and for
all <U+017F>uch as have <U+017F>poiled their Bodies, and <U+017F>urfeited their
Heats and Colds, hard and exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive Drinking in their
young Days; and for <U+017F>uch as cannot attend upon a
Cure, but are forced to go about their Bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s: They
may take them to Sea with them, becau<U+017F>e they keep
their Vertues many Years, nor do Sea Voyages <U+017F>poil
them. They will will be found to <U+017F>tand them in great
<U+017F>tead in all Sea-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>es, <U+017F>ickly Climates or Sea<U+017F>ons; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentures,
Fevers, Fluxes, Poy<U+017F>ons, Agues, Surfeits,
and the like Scorbutick Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which <U+017F>o commonly
afflict <U+017F>uch as go to Sea; as that <U+017F>carcely any but are
afflicted in one or more of the<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, <U+017F>o excellent
are the<U+017F>e Pills, that more cannot po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly be done by a
purging Medicine.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are incomparable again<U+017F>t all manner of
Coughs, Colds, Rheums or Di<U+017F>tillations, difficulty of
Breathing, Vomiting, weakne<U+017F>s of the Stomach, want
of Appetite, Pleuri<U+017F>ies, Pains of the <U+017F>ide, <U+017F>pitting of
Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> performing every thing of this kind to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration,
<U+017F>uddenly and <U+017F>trangely ea<U+017F>ing of Pains, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
from Wind, Humours, Colds, Surfeits or any
other Cau<U+017F>e what<U+017F>oever.</p>
            <p>They cure Fevers and Agues of all <U+017F>orts, <U+017F>ometimes
in three Weeks, <U+017F>ometimes in fourteen Days, and
<U+017F>ometimes in le<U+017F>s time, altho' of 2 or 3 Years <U+017F>tanding,
and given over by all Phy<U+017F>icians, and when almo<U+017F>t
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51771:10"/>
every one thought the hopes of Recovery had been
pa<U+017F>t.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills kill all <U+017F>orts of Worms in Old or
Young, altho' the Patient has been almo<U+017F>t de<U+017F>troyed
with them; they bringing away not only the Worms,
dead or alive, but al<U+017F>o Slime, Filthine<U+017F>s, or wormy
Matter, both from the Stomach and Bowels, which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerates
and breeds them; bring down the great Bellies
of Children and others, which Worms occa<U+017F>ions, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
a <U+017F>trong Dige<U+017F>tion and a <U+017F>anative Con<U+017F>titution;
and I cannot forbear repeating them to be, as they
are indeed (and which every one that make tryal
will find) the very be<U+017F>t Remedy in the World again<U+017F>t
the Drop<U+017F>y and the Gout; taking away all Swellings
from the Belly, Thighs and Legs, and all manner of
Pains, tho' fixed in the very Bones; and that in Rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati<U+017F>ms
when the Pains have been <U+017F>o cruel and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
as not to be born without violent Roarings and
Cryings out, they have done wonders, and that when
no other means what<U+017F>oever would any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</p>
            <p>They al<U+017F>o di<U+017F><U+017F>olve the Stone, as much as any Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
in the Univer<U+017F>e is able to do, bringing away,
Slime, Sand and Gravel from the Reins and Bladder,
taking away Stoppage of Urine, and cau<U+017F>ing tho<U+017F>e to
make Water plentifully and ea<U+017F>ily, who could not do
it in <U+017F>ome Days before; this they have done in numbers
of People to admiration.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are a certain Cure for the Falling-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s,
Convul<U+017F>ions (that deplorable and fatal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,
whereby <U+017F>everal Thou<U+017F>ands, and that from a
Scorbutick Cau<U+017F>e, are carried off in a Year) Apoplexies,
Pal<U+017F>ies, Cramps, Lamene<U+017F><U+017F>es, weakne<U+017F>s of Limbs, lo<U+017F>s
of Memory, Sciatica's and all manner of fixed or run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Pains what<U+017F>oever in any part of the Body, all
which does mo<U+017F>t certainly proceed from the <hi>Scurvy,</hi>
that Bane and di<U+017F>troyer of Health and Life; in<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,
that many Bed-rid Per<U+017F>ons, given over in ail ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
as incurable, have, under God, unexpectedly
met with a Cure almo<U+017F>t to a Miracle; <U+017F>o that many
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51771:11"/>
learned Phy<U+017F>icians could not but admire at their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
Vertues.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e <U+017F>amous <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills Cure Barrenne<U+017F>s effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
whether the fault be in the Man or Woman; they
exalting the Generative Faculty, clean<U+017F>ing and <U+017F>trength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the Spermatick Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting all Foulne<U+017F>s and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
in the Act of Generation; bring down the Terms
in Women and Maids, <U+017F>trengthen a weak Back, cure
Ulcers and Stoppages in the Womb, and are wonderful
in all other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es belonging to the Female Sex; they
expel Wind, carry off the Wind Cholick to admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and <U+017F>o <U+017F>peedily Cure the Griping of the Guts, that
many who <U+017F>eemingly were at the point of Death, have
found them a pre<U+017F>ent Remedy, when all other means
have failed.</p>
            <p>They are the mo<U+017F>t powerful Pills in Nature again<U+017F>t
the Rickets in Children, the pale and wan Countenance,
whether from the Green-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s or otherwi<U+017F>e in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,
all manner of Stoppages and Pains in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
Head and Brain, Liver, Spleen, Reins, Womb
and Bowels; they purify, clean<U+017F>e and <U+017F>weeten the
whole Ma<U+017F>s of Blood, rectify all the Di<U+017F>tempers of the
Head, quicken the Sen<U+017F>es, add a good Colour to the
Face, <U+017F>trengthen the Sight, and <U+017F>o wonderfully recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
the Natural, Vital and Animal Spirits, as that the
Body thereby is made perfectly able to with<U+017F>tand and
re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t all its Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>They clean<U+017F>e the Body of Wind, Water and ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
without the lea<U+017F>t Griping or making Sick, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s,
as was <U+017F>aid before, the Stomach be very foul) or
any way weakning the Body; which done, they cea<U+017F>e
working; for they will work no longer than there is
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>y Matter to work upon, but contrarywi<U+017F>e will
help all inward wa<U+017F>tings or decays of Nature, cau<U+017F>ed
through Pains, Wrenches, Brui<U+017F>es or over-<U+017F>trainings;
they <U+017F>topping all Weepings, Moi<U+017F>tures, Whites, Fluxes,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> by carrying off the Humours another way, thereby
<U+017F>trengthning the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, fortifying Nature, and re<U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the decay'd Parts even to a wonder.</p>
            <p>In fine, the<U+017F>e Pills are the chief and real Medicine
now u<U+017F>ed for the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> and the afore<U+017F>aid Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51771:11"/>
which are produc'd there-from, and found to be <U+017F>uch
from long Experience, not only here in <hi>England,</hi> but
in many Foreign Countries and Kingdoms; they being
cryed up and prized above all Remedies what<U+017F>oever;
in<U+017F>omuch, that in <U+017F>ome Thou<U+017F>ands of Families, on mo<U+017F>t
occa<U+017F>ions, they are their only Phy<U+017F>ick; and indeed no
Per<U+017F>on living, from the highe<U+017F>t to the lowe<U+017F>t, can have
a better Purging Medicine in the World, let the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
condition be from what cau<U+017F>e or occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>oever,
they being known to be <U+017F>afe in Operation, and certain
in the end propo<U+017F>ed; for no Per<U+017F>on curable, troubled
with the afore<U+017F>aid Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es ever failed of a Cure, e<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
if they continued them (without delay of time,
or taking of other Phy<U+017F>ick) according to the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
and all Per<U+017F>ons that have been known to take
the<U+017F>e Pills, have found good at the fir<U+017F>t taking, and <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Hundreds, yea Thou<U+017F>ands of People who have
taken them, have given them as great Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
as it was ever po<U+017F><U+017F>ible any Medicine could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve.</p>
            <p>Their <U+017F>afety, and the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s that has followed upon
the u<U+017F>e of them, has brought them into the great e<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
they have have acquired in many parts of the
World; for as much as they that take the<U+017F>e Pills need
not go under long, dangerous and chargeable Cour<U+017F>es
of Phy<U+017F>ick, nor <U+017F>uffer by bad Medicines, or be driven
time after time from one Phy<U+017F>ician to another, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
hundreds daily are, not knowing where to apply
them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>afe, when only a Box or two of the<U+017F>e Pills
will do more notable Cures than twenty times that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
expended upon Doctors.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are the only Antidote in Nature again<U+017F>t
all infectious Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, contagious Airs, and pre<U+017F>erves
from the mi<U+017F>chief of Fogs, and unwhole<U+017F>ome and <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focated
Vapours in Mar<U+017F>hy or Fenny Countries, which
ari<U+017F>e from the Earth or Water; they making old Age
comely, and the Countenance of all that take them to
be chearful and Sanguine; they mundify and clean<U+017F>e
the Skin of all its Impurities, re<U+017F>tores and increa<U+017F>e
Beauty; and abound with more Vertues than any one
Medicine be<U+017F>ides; for altho' many Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es have been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51771:12"/>
mentioned, the labour might have been <U+017F>aved; for as
they are Pills of an univer<U+017F>al Tendency, and I verily
believe the only Purging Medicine in the World, it
might only have been <U+017F>aid they are good for every Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e;
and not only for the Di<U+017F>tempers herein in<U+017F>erted,
but al<U+017F>o for many others, known or unknown, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
name or number, even when they are <U+017F>o unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
afflicted, as not knowing what they ail. The<U+017F>e
Pills being endowed with <U+017F>uch excellent Properties, and
are <U+017F>o full and effectual a healer, that they de<U+017F>ervedly
merit the Title of the only univer<U+017F>al Pills in the
World.</p>
            <p>And although they are of <U+017F>uch admirable Vertues,
yet I mu<U+017F>t inform you, that when the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is of
long continuance and <U+017F>tubborn, a perfect Cure cannot
be expected in a few times taking them, in tho<U+017F>e Ca<U+017F>es
you may take them in the large<U+017F>t Do<U+017F>e, and that at
lea<U+017F>t for ten or fifteen times or more, as need requires,
omitting them a day or two, as you <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee cau<U+017F>e;
but if any <U+017F>hall pre<U+017F>ume, upon the commendation of
the<U+017F>e Pills, that any Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, in what<U+017F>oever condition
the Patient is in, mu<U+017F>t be infallibly cured, he is mi<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;
for I <U+017F>peak here only of <U+017F>uch Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es as by God's
Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing, and the very be<U+017F>t of Means (as the<U+017F>e Pills un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
are) they may receive cure for; for in <U+017F>ome
Ca<U+017F>es no Medicine in the World can prevail, for <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
the Lungs them<U+017F>elves, or the Liver or the Reins
are ulcerated and putrefy'd, and <U+017F>ometimes other inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Parts are con<U+017F>umed; and what Medicine in Nature
can repair <U+017F>uch Ruins, or make new Vi<U+017F>cera when the
old are peri<U+017F>hed?</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills operate extreamly plea<U+017F>ant, <U+017F>afe and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
and is Phy<U+017F>ick fit to be taken by Per<U+017F>ons of the
greate<U+017F>t Rank and Dignity, and that by all Ages and
Sexes from Two Years old to Four<U+017F>core and upwards
at any Sea<U+017F>on of the Year; and it is ob<U+017F>ervable that
the<U+017F>e Pills after four or five times taking, keep the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
open for a Month together, and leave not the Body
co<U+017F>tive and bound, as is the Property of all other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ick,
by which good Property, Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>eem to melt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51771:12"/>
The<U+017F>e Pills are of an admirable and friendly quality,
performing all its Operations as-Nature-her <U+017F>elf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires,
and is di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to the Action, tho' chiefly by
Stool and Urine, <U+017F>o that they are bound to that way of
Operation as be<U+017F>t <U+017F>erves Nature's end in re<U+017F>toring
Health: Hence it is, that they cure Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with <U+017F>o
great <U+017F>afety, <U+017F>peed and ea<U+017F>e, and that without almo<U+017F>t
any other Medicine, they being (as was <U+017F>aid before) fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
for all Ages, Sexes and Con<U+017F>titutions what<U+017F>oever;
and that if there but little Corruption in the Body,
they bring forth but little, if much, they bring forth
much, and in Per<U+017F>ons perfectly well, they will <U+017F>carcely
work at all, becau<U+017F>e in <U+017F>uch they have no Enemy to
meet or contend withal.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e Pills are not only the <U+017F>ure<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t certain
Medicine, as well as cheape<U+017F>t, for the <hi>Scurvy</hi> and all the
a<U+017F>ore<U+017F>aid Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which are the con<U+017F>equents or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions
thereof, of any ever yet publi<U+017F>hed or admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tred,
but doth a thou<U+017F>and times more excel the be<U+017F>t
prepared and mo<U+017F>t celebrated <U+017F>orts of Spirit of Scurvy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra<U+017F>s,
<U+017F>o highly applauded for the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> they affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
what is herein propo<U+017F>ed <U+017F>o <U+017F>tupendiou<U+017F>ly and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
the power of any other Remedy, whether ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
or extraordinary, as that they never can be vallued
or e<U+017F>teemed enough; for what Reachings, Strainings,
Vomitings, Gripings, illne<U+017F>s at the Stomach, <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s
at Heart, Faintings and other very unplea<U+017F>ing Effects,
many Medicines occa<U+017F>ion, which are here avoided;
this <U+017F>ingle Medicine gently clean<U+017F>ing the Stomach and
Bowels of their dro<U+017F><U+017F>y, mucilaginous Dregs, <U+017F>aluting
the Vital Powers like an Angel of Peace, and piercing
the whole Body like Lightning, doth, as it were by its
Character and benign Beams, <U+017F>ubdue the Malignant
Powers of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and throughly overcome the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<U+017F>ick
Matter thereof, and that without the lea<U+017F>t per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbution
of Humours, alteration of Body, change of
Countenance, impair of Health, or any ill attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
they gently removing Ob<U+017F>tructions of all kinds,
exciting an Appetite, and rendering the Body vigorous,
active and <U+017F>prightly to the admiration of all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51771:13"/>
And this they do not only by fighting or contending
with the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e after a rugged and robu<U+017F>t manner, but
in a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ive way, by glancing, as it were, and piercing
of it with the <U+017F>ubtilty of their Effluviums, and as it
were by charming of it, undoes it in its very Root and
E<U+017F><U+017F>ence, whereby the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>y Matter being melted and
changed in its Nature, Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and the very Seeds of
of them in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly vani<U+017F>h away, thereby curing tho<U+017F>e
Di<U+017F>tempers which are almo<U+017F>t incredible to relate.</p>
            <p>But no more need to be <U+017F>aid of their Vertues, only
give me leave to add, that the<U+017F>e Pills are cheap, ea<U+017F>y
approved helps, free from the lea<U+017F>t danger upon any
account what<U+017F>oever; are <U+017F>afe and benign in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ition,
rational in their Preparation, amicable and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted
to all Con<U+017F>titutions, mo<U+017F>t powerful again<U+017F>t
tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es to which they are appropriated; able to
<U+017F>tand the te<U+017F>t of all Tryals, and have an uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<hi>Probatum e<U+017F>t</hi> continually attending them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
made of nothing that neither nau<U+017F>eates the Stomach,
or tortures the Patient, but operates <hi>Cito, Tuto &amp; Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunde,</hi>
even when many other Medicines of far greater
Names, have wofully failed: Their gratefulne<U+017F>s to the
Sen<U+017F>es and Animal Spirits are <U+017F>uch, as will invite as
well as a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t all the Powers of Nature to with<U+017F>tand
the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and by the <U+017F>ubtilty of their Temper, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrate
into tho<U+017F>e clo<U+017F>e Rece<U+017F><U+017F>es where the Roots of
Di<U+017F>tempers u<U+017F>ually lodge, and into which the common,
dull and earthy Preparations, <U+017F>o frequently u<U+017F>ed in
practice can never po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly enter or reach into; but as
Experience is the be<U+017F>t Schoolma<U+017F>ter, I leave every one
to make Tryal and judge as they find, and accordingly
to commend or di<U+017F>prai<U+017F>e them to their Neighbours and
Friends, not doubting but they will perform what is
herein a<U+017F><U+017F>erted, without hazard of Body, Pur<U+017F>e or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,
as <U+017F>ome Thou<U+017F>ands in this Kingdom can,
upon their own Knowledge, te<U+017F>tify, what is <U+017F>aid of
them, being no Rhodomontade Story to rai<U+017F>e a Penny,
nor guilded Bu<U+017F>h to <U+017F>et off bad Wine, but Matter of
Fact, back'd with <U+017F>uch number of Experiences, as not
to leave the lea<U+017F>t umbrage or <U+017F>hadow of Fal<U+017F>ity or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51771:13"/>
For the<U+017F>e Pills are no fallacious, emperical Medicine,
repugnant to Art or incon<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with Rea<U+017F>on, but a
regularly prepared <hi>Arcanum,</hi> much in vogue for their
Vertues, being homogene to Nature, and <U+017F>o peculiarly
adapted again<U+017F>t the <hi>Scurvy</hi> and its Con<U+017F>equents, as that
no Medicine in the Univer<U+017F>e can po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly tran<U+017F>cend
them, they being a Medicine, tho' very difficult, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen<U+017F>ive
and tedious in preparing, yet are of <U+017F>uch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties,
as to retain their Vertues for numbers of Years,
and that to work all good effects, as well after a length
of time as at their fir<U+017F>t preparing. I <U+017F>hall now clo<U+017F>e
all with Advice that you take your Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e in time, and
not render it incurable by delay, an Error daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
tho' contrary to the whole<U+017F>ome Dictates of the
Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Principiis ob<U+017F>ta <U+017F>ero Medicina paratur,</l>
               <l>Cum mala per long as invaluere moras.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Delay not any known Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e too long,</l>
               <l>Le<U+017F>t thou grow weaker, and it grow more <U+017F>trong.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The way and manner of taking the<U+017F>e Pills are as
follows, <hi>viz.</hi> From Two Years old to Three or Four
Years, you may give one Pill; from Four Years old to
Ten Years, you may give two or three Pills; from Ten
Years old to Sixteen Years, you may give three or four
Pills; and from Sixteen Years old to Three<U+017F>core and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
you may <U+017F>afely give five or <U+017F>ix Pills. You may
begin with a little Do<U+017F>e fir<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>o encrea<U+017F>e it as you
find the Body is in <U+017F>trength. They may be either <U+017F>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd
down alone, or taken in a Spoonful of Ale, Beer,
Po<U+017F><U+017F>et-drink or Water-gruel, of wrapp'd up in a Wafer,
the Pap of an Apple, or Honey, or in a <U+017F>tew'd Prune,
or in a little Syrup; and <U+017F>uch as cannot <U+017F>wallow Pills,
may brui<U+017F>e them and take them mixed with a little
Beer, Ale, Wine or Broth, as every one likes be<U+017F>t,
and <U+017F>o take them early in the Morning, or late at
Night going to Bed, drinking in the Morning Po<U+017F><U+017F>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drink
or Water-gruel, as they operate, or you may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51771:14"/>
drinking any thing if you had rather, and that
without ob<U+017F>ervation of any other order what<U+017F>oever, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
taking heed that you get no Cold.</p>
            <p>The price of a Box of the<U+017F>e famous <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills
(each containing <U+017F>ix Do<U+017F>es) is Three Shillings and Six
Pence, and are <U+017F>old only at the Places aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
and which for prevention of Counterfeits,
are to be had at no other Place in the Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides,
whatever may be pretended by any to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51771:14"/>
            <head>A
LINIMENT
FOR
Sore, Swell'd or Cancerated
BREASTS
IN
WOMEN,
WITH THEIR
Nature, Cau<U+017F>e, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is not my de<U+017F>ign to write any thing here concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Cancers in any part of the Body, <U+017F>ave only
tho<U+017F>e that happen in the Brea<U+017F>ts of Women,
wherein I <U+017F>hall to the meane<U+017F>t Capacity, <U+017F>hew the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
between tho<U+017F>e that really are, and tho<U+017F>e that
are only imagined, or reputed to be Cancerous; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the Mi<U+017F>takes too common, may be prevented, and
Ruine to the Patient <U+017F>aved; when the Name is now <U+017F>o
frequent, and the fear of it <U+017F>o dreadful, that not one
<U+017F>well'd or pained Brea<U+017F>t in Twenty, but is pre<U+017F>ently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51771:15"/>
thought <U+017F>o, and every Goody Nur<U+017F>e, Doctre<U+017F>s or Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife,
will pronounce <U+017F>o right or wrong, and con<U+017F>equent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
has a never failing Remedy for Cure, which upon
applying, produces a Cancer, where no <U+017F>uch thing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
had been.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Cancer</hi> is as much as to a Crab, and is a hard pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Tumour, either Whole or Ulcerous, and is <U+017F>aid to
have its ri<U+017F>e from many Cau<U+017F>es; <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay from ill Diet,
Meats of ill Juice, of a hot quality, and thick and
glutinous <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and that Onions, Leeks, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,
Veni<U+017F>on and hot Spic'd Meats, eat too plentifully,
and hot fiery Liquors, that burn and make adu<U+017F>t the
Blood and Humours, <U+017F>uch as Brandy, <U+017F>trong Wines,
&amp;c. immoderately drank, breed them. Others, that
the Air, perturbations of the Mind, Melancholly, ill
Habits of Body, hot, <U+017F>harp Humours, where there is
a di<U+017F>cra<U+017F><U+017F>ys of the Blood and Lympha, being fill'd with
an Acrimonious Salt, and a malign Sulphur is their
occa<U+017F>ion. Others, that they <U+017F>eldom proceed but from
Blows, Strokes, Punches, or <U+017F>uch external Violence,
ill handling, Tumours from curdled Milk upon Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
in, Impo<U+017F>thumes, &amp;c. by which means there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
an acid Ferment in the Blood, or it may be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructions
of the Terms, or <U+017F>ome other illne<U+017F>s, which
oftentimes cau<U+017F>es Humours to flow thither, where co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulating,
is capable to produce a Cancerous Germen,
e<U+017F>pecially upon ill management, <U+017F>o as in time it increa<U+017F>es
and arrives to to that degree of inveteracy, which we
<U+017F>ometimes find them to be.</p>
            <p>Having now accounted for the cau<U+017F>e of Cancers in
the Brea<U+017F>ts, we come to their Definitions, and are preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
Tumours of a hard, lumpy, round or unequal
Sub<U+017F>tance; of a livid or black Colour, having great
Veins every way round it, which the Blood extends and
makes turgid and vi<U+017F>ible, re<U+017F>embling the Feet of a
Crab, from whence it took its Name, and is full of
Pain, and very hot, and of a cruel and horrid A<U+017F>pect;
and <U+017F>ometimes ri<U+017F>es to <U+017F>uch a hight of Malignity, that
the Matter it contains when it is broke, is as <U+017F>harp and
as corro<U+017F>ive as <hi>Aqua Fortis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51771:15"/>
They are, as <U+017F>aid at fir<U+017F>t, Whole or Ulcerous; in the
beginning, growing or increa<U+017F>ing, they are generally
whole, but when come to ripene<U+017F>s, they break, run or
gleet, and are then called <hi>Cancer Ulceratus,</hi> or <hi>Ulcus
Canceratum.</hi> This Humour being fixt upon <U+017F>ome
one or more of the Glands of the Brea<U+017F>t, from ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the Cau<U+017F>es mentioned, and being <U+017F>harp and
corro<U+017F>ive, is apt to convert whatever comes to it of
Blood, into the <U+017F>ame Acrimony with it <U+017F>elf, and <U+017F>o in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>es
apace, while the Skin is whole; but much more
when upon the breaking of the Skin, for then the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ion
of the Airs adds to the vigour of the Ferment,
when it grows fierce or enraged, and <U+017F>o <U+017F>hoots forth
it <U+017F>elf in the nature of a Fungus, or Excre<U+017F>cences, or
Tubercles, &amp;c. This part being deprav'd, and a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
Ferment therein, the Humours that flow thither,
are <U+017F>till farther changed, till at length they partake of
a malign and poi<U+017F>onous Nature, vehemently delete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of a <U+017F>tinking Ar<U+017F>enical Sulphur, and
a Catheretick, or highly corro<U+017F>ive Salt, extreamly <U+017F>ubtle
and penetrating.</p>
            <p>This malign Humour, when <U+017F>o from whatever
Cau<U+017F>es, chiefly take up its <U+017F>eat in parts that are
Glandulous, beginning in the Glandule of a Part, and
mo<U+017F>t often affects Womens Brea<U+017F>ts, by rea<U+017F>on of their
loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s, great Humidities, and <U+017F>trong Ferment they
contain, and at fir<U+017F>t is very difficult to be known; for
it at fir<U+017F>t exceeds not the bigne<U+017F>s of a Pea or a Bean,
which in time increa<U+017F>es <U+017F>lowly to the bigne<U+017F>s of an Egg
or a Melon, or as <U+017F>ometimes it has been known as big
as a Pompion, tho again in <U+017F>ome, according as is the
Cau<U+017F>e, it grows big of a <U+017F>udden, and di<U+017F>covers its evil
Nature by the grievous Symptoms that appear, and a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it
increa<U+017F>es in bigne<U+017F>s, it increa<U+017F>es in malignity.</p>
            <p>In the Cure of Cancers, various Succe<U+017F><U+017F>es have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd,
which have divided the Opinions of Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
concerning the Cau<U+017F>es of them. The Ancients ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erv'd,
that Women were mo<U+017F>t troubled with Cancers,
upon the <U+017F>topping of their Monthly Vi<U+017F>its, and that
when at any time they had <U+017F>wellings in their Brea<U+017F>ts,
upon the provocation of that Evacuation, the <U+017F>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51771:16"/>
either <U+017F>unk or left thin, from whence they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,
that the <U+017F>topping of that Cour<U+017F>e in Women,
was the only Cau<U+017F>e thereof; and this they endeavour'd
to explain, by <U+017F>aying that the Blood, by <U+017F>uch <U+017F>toppages
being not purify'd from the Atribilious Humour or
Acids, which <U+017F>eparate them<U+017F>elves from it, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
flowing of the Cour<U+017F>es, di<U+017F>charge them<U+017F>elves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<U+017F>ome one of the Glandulous Parts, and tho<U+017F>e of the
Brea<U+017F>t, more generally, from the Communication there
is between them and the Womb, which Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
Experience confirms, becau<U+017F>e we <U+017F>ee that ju<U+017F>t upon,
or a little before the coming down of the Cour<U+017F>es, the
Brea<U+017F>ts of Women are tender; that is, the Glandules or
Kernels of them, <U+017F>o as not to be handled or pre<U+017F>s'd with
ea<U+017F>e, which upon the flowing of the Cour<U+017F>es, that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne<U+017F>s
leaves them, and they may be felt and handled
without any manner of unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, <U+017F>o that it is plain,
that upon the <U+017F>toppage of the Cour<U+017F>es in Women, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
are oftentimes occa<U+017F>ion'd, e<U+017F>pecially where the
Blood abounds with Atrabilious Humours or Acids. I
<U+017F>ay <U+017F>ometimes it is <U+017F>o, for it mu<U+017F>t not be <U+017F>aid to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<U+017F>o, becau<U+017F>e we have in<U+017F>tances without number,
of Women that have had them by Blows, Brui<U+017F>es,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before we have made mention of; and as was
the ca<U+017F>e of a Gentlewoman, who<U+017F>e Husband after a
Drunken Bout was thrown into a Fever, and being
delirious, upon her giving him <U+017F>omething to drink, he
hit her Left Brea<U+017F>t with his Hand, which caus'd it to
Cancerate, of which <U+017F>he <U+017F>oon after dy'd. We are a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ur'd
by many ob<U+017F>ervations, that Cancers <U+017F>ometimes
have proceeded from the <U+017F>topping of the Monthly Vi<U+017F>its,
by Frights, violent Grief, and by letting of Blood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ea<U+017F>onably
at the times of the Cour<U+017F>es actually running,
which are dangerous <U+017F>topping them, and care <U+017F>hould
be forthwith taken to bring them to flow again, or el<U+017F>e
the Brea<U+017F>ts may be affected, e<U+017F>pecially if the Blood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds
with Atrabilious Humours or Acids as before-mentioned.</p>
            <p>The hardne<U+017F>s of Cancers is from the thickne<U+017F>s of the
Humour; the pain of them is from the conjoyn'd Cau<U+017F>e,
it being <U+017F>harp and corro<U+017F>ive; the Heat of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51771:16"/>
from the extremity of Pain; the livid or black<U+017F>h
colour is from the Malignity and Poi<U+017F>on, which even
di<U+017F>colours the pure<U+017F>t Metals, if touch'd with it; the
roundne<U+017F>s of the Cancers is from the thickne<U+017F>s of the
Matter, which cannot <U+017F>pread it <U+017F>elf abroad as Humours
do that are more fluid; the inequality of <U+017F>hape of the
Cancerous Tumour, as <U+017F>ometimes 3 or 4 <U+017F>quare, or
longi<U+017F>h proceeds from the Ferment of the Humour, and
becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ometimes it is contain'd in <U+017F>everal little Glands;
and its turgid Veins, like to Crab's Claws, is cau<U+017F>ed
from the Recrements of the Blood filling tho<U+017F>e Parts,
which by rea<U+017F>on of Matter ob<U+017F>tructing or pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing upon
them, hinders its getting forth.</p>
            <p>Cancers are known in part by the Places they fix on,
which are the Glands, tho' they may breed in almo<U+017F>t
all parts of the Body; and this <hi>Aegineta</hi> confirms, who
<U+017F>ays, a Cancer may happen to <U+017F>undry Places, as the
Lips, Tongue, Cheeks, Womb, and other loo<U+017F>e Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous
Parts; but were One has a Cancer in any part
be<U+017F>ides, Twenty have them in their Brea<U+017F>ts; and <U+017F>o
<U+017F>ays <hi>Galen,</hi> That Cancerous Tumours are chiefly in
Women's Brea<U+017F>ts, which have not their Purgations
according to Nature, and the rea<U+017F>on <U+017F>eems to be from
the con<U+017F>ent of the Parts, as before ob<U+017F>erved; for that
the <hi>Mammariae</hi> Veins, or Veins of the Brea<U+017F>ts, meet
with the <hi>Uterinae,</hi> or Veins of the Womb under the
<hi>Mu<U+017F>culi recti</hi> of the Belly, by which means there is a
tran<U+017F>lation of the Matter from the Womb to the
Brea<U+017F>ts.</p>
            <p>Where Cancers in the Brea<U+017F>ts are painful, there is
al<U+017F>o attending a Pul<U+017F>ation, or beating like a Pul<U+017F>e,
together with a Heat more than ordinary; and where
the Pains are very <U+017F>harp, <U+017F>o as if the Part was <U+017F>truck
with a Dart, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> the Matter is very corro<U+017F>ive, and
will certainly in a little time break forth in a Gleeting
or <U+017F>ome dangerous <U+017F>tinking Ulcer; and when they are
Ulcerated, as frequently they are, from the breaking of
<U+017F>ome of the Tubercls lying under the Skin, whether
the Matter that runs be much or little, the Ulcer is
painful and very <U+017F>tinking, and not only di<U+017F>charge a
<U+017F>tinking Gleety Humour, but al<U+017F>o there thru<U+017F>ts forth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51771:17"/>
hard and painful Lips, which in time, if not rightly
managed, fixes to the Ribs (that is, if the Cancer be
in the Brea<U+017F>t or <U+017F>ide of it) becoming, by the quick
progre<U+017F>s it makes, of a horrible and frightful appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>Such Cancers <U+017F>ometimes bleed, either through the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
of <U+017F>ome Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, or from the <U+017F>harp corro<U+017F>ive
Nature of the Humour, which gnaws the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els a<U+017F>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
tho' I have known them to bleed while they have
been whole, the Blood i<U+017F><U+017F>uing through the Nipple, or
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall Pin-hole. Some Cancers again, that are
Ulcerated, <U+017F>end forth a Fungus or fle<U+017F>hy Excre<U+017F>cencies;
other con<U+017F>ume and eat away all the Fle<U+017F>h about them,
after a wonderful, and indeed dreadful manner; and
both the<U+017F>e often bleed, and that in great quanties <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time,
becau<U+017F>e the Capillary Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els are by the corroding
quality of a Cancer, eaten a<U+017F>under, whence the flux
of Blood is <U+017F>o great, that the <U+017F>trength of the Patient is
quickly <U+017F>pent, and the Spirits being exhau<U+017F>ted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umed,
they <U+017F>oon dye; as a poor Woman did that I
knew, after labouring under a Cancerated Brea<U+017F>t very
painful, for near two Years, and could all that while
have no Remedy; for indeed <U+017F>uch are very rarely to be
cur'd, and if at all, it is by Surgery; that is, by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
off the Brea<U+017F>t in time, which the Woman I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
was by many Surgeons advis'd to, but would not
<U+017F>ubmit to the Operation.</p>
            <p>Tho<U+017F>e inveterate and dangerous Cancers but <U+017F>eldom
happen, and is frequently more from want of timely
and proper Applications than the Nature of them; for
they are oftentimes aggravated and enraged, and the
Humour, by wrong Applications inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,
made corro<U+017F>ive and <U+017F>harp, as we frequently
find it to be; and the Humour is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> corro<U+017F>ive, it is
as <U+017F>ubtle, quick and penetrating as Poi<U+017F>on it <U+017F>elf, as
will appear from the following Relation, which a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon
tells us happened upon him<U+017F>elf, who was by
Name Mr. <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> one of the Surgeons of
St <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Ho<U+017F>pital in <hi>Southwark,</hi> who at the cutting
off of a large Cancerated Brea<U+017F>t, had (after the Brea<U+017F>t
was off) a Curio<U+017F>ity to ta<U+017F>te the Juice, or Matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51771:17"/>
in one of the little Cy<U+017F>tis's or Glands of the <U+017F>ame,
which he did by touching it with one of his Fingers,
and then ta<U+017F>ting it from the <U+017F>ame with his Tongue, the
Ta<U+017F>te of which he prote<U+017F>ted did immediately like a
Ga<U+017F>s, pierce through the whole <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of his Tongue,
and pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed down his Throat not le<U+017F>s <U+017F>harp or biting
than Oyl of Vitriol, Spirit of Nitre, or <hi>Aquae Fortis,</hi> or
<U+017F>ome vehement Catheretick, or Cau<U+017F>tick Salt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho'
he pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>pit out, and wa<U+017F>h'd his Mouth with
Water, and that oftentimes, and al<U+017F>o with Wine, and
drank pre<U+017F>ently very freely of Wine after it, yet could
not get rid of the Ta<U+017F>te thereof, but it continued with
him, and brought him (who was a very <U+017F>trong Man)
into a Con<U+017F>umption, or wa<U+017F>ting pining Condition,
attended with <U+017F>everal other ill Symptoms, which in a
few Months after killed him, the Ta<U+017F>te thereof never
going off from his Tongue to his dying Hour; and that
the Ta<U+017F>te of the Juice, or Matter of that Cancerated
Brea<U+017F>t, he declared upon his Death-bed, and near the
la<U+017F>t Moments of his Life, to be the true and only Cau<U+017F>e
of his langui<U+017F>hing Condition and Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen</hi> tells us, and the <U+017F>ame is confirmed by daily
Experience, that Cancers in the outward Parts, as in
the Brea<U+017F>t, may in the beginning be cur'd, but when
they are come to a con<U+017F>iderable bigne<U+017F>s, oftentimes will
yield to no Remedy but extirpation; indeed a palliative
Cure may be pre<U+017F>crib'd, which, if the Cancer be not
Ulcerated, may make the Patient ea<U+017F>y, and prolong
Life, <U+017F>o as not to dye the <U+017F>ooner, becau<U+017F>e of that Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer;
but when it is Ulcerated, it can never be cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri<U+017F>ed,
but as long as it <U+017F>o remains, the Patient will
live in continual Pain and Filthine<U+017F>s, and at la<U+017F>t dye
mi<U+017F>erably, unle<U+017F>s it is cur'd by U<U+017F>tion, Cautry, or
Extirpation, and then may prove but a doubtful
Cure.</p>
            <p>If a Cancer in the Brea<U+017F>t proceeds from malignant
Humours or corro<U+017F>ive Salts in the Blood, it is generally
incurable, by rea<U+017F>on of its malignant and poy<U+017F>onous
Ferment, which <U+017F>eldom yields to any internal and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
Remedies, whether Vomiting, Purging, Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
Sweating, Dyet-drink; nay Salivations, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51771:18"/>
of Annodines, Suppuratives, or any other
kind of Medicine; or if in <U+017F>ome it <U+017F>hould <U+017F>eem to yield,
or indeed <U+017F>eem to be cur'd, while it proceeds from tho<U+017F>e
corro<U+017F>ive Humours, they many times breed again, and
break forth afre<U+017F>h, either in the <U+017F>ame place, or in <U+017F>ome
other parts of the Body.</p>
            <p>But if a Cancer proceeds from external Cau<U+017F>es, as
Brui<U+017F>es, Blows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and be taken in time, and the
hurt lies not very deep, a Cure, with good Succe<U+017F>s,
may be undertaken, yea oftentimes tho' they lie deep;
but then mu<U+017F>t be with proper Applications; for wrong
Medicines apply'd, tho' the Injury be but <U+017F>mall, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd
to what, of it <U+017F>elf it might never have came to,
therefore is a caution worthy to be taken notice of;
many Women, by undue tampering, and ill advice
and Medicines, having been ruin'd, and lo<U+017F>t their Lives,
which otherwi<U+017F>e, in all likelihood, might have been
pre<U+017F>erv'd: Therefore before external Applications be
made to a Cancerated Brea<U+017F>t, or <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed Cancerated
Brea<U+017F>ts, it ought to be con<U+017F>ider'd whether it be recent
and <U+017F>mall, or inveterate and great; if the fir<U+017F>t, it will
by proper Applications, admit of Cure, (I <U+017F>ay proper
Applications, becau<U+017F>e by and by I <U+017F>hall come to relate
what is the mo<U+017F>t proper to apply to a true Cancer, or
an imagin'd Cancer of the Brea<U+017F>t) if the <U+017F>econd, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
will admit of Cure without cutting. A pallative
Cure may be had, if it be not ulcerated, as <U+017F>aid before,
where, by proper Remedies, Ea<U+017F>e may be had and Life
prolong'd, and that done by divers Medicines, at lea<U+017F>t
every Nur<U+017F>e, or good Woman has a Medicine, and that
if you will believe them, they <U+017F>ay will cure; but tho<U+017F>e
hap-hazzard Remedies I have known fatal, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
advi<U+017F>e none to give Ear to them. But I would
not have it under<U+017F>tood, that I de<U+017F>ign here to direct to
the Cure of Cancerated Brea<U+017F>ts of all <U+017F>orts, I mean
tho<U+017F>e that are running and ulcerate, which require a
skilful Surgeon's attendance and care; but only tho<U+017F>e
that are Swell'd and Tumefy'd, as well <U+017F>uch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,
or only intermittingly painful, and whether
proceeding from Blows, Falls, Strokes, ill Habits of
Body, Tumours from Milk, hardne<U+017F><U+017F>es of the Brea<U+017F>ts,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51771:18"/>
by Impo<U+017F>thumes after Lyings-in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which oftentimes
by ill management, and pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing and handling, turn to
Cancers; I <U+017F>ay from what ever cau<U+017F>e they proceed from,
<U+017F>o they be whole and taken in time, may be cur'd by
proper Applications; and if they be broken or ulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
to prevent its increa<U+017F>e, and remove the hardne<U+017F>s
and <U+017F>welling about it; a Medicine or two may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,
that will (if any thing will) not fail of proving
<U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful: But as I <U+017F>aid before, every <U+017F>well'd Brea<U+017F>t
being not always Cancerous, it may be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in two
or three Words more to explain which hard or painful
Brea<U+017F>ts can ju<U+017F>tly be <U+017F>aid to be Cancerous, and which
not <U+017F>o.</p>
            <p>A Cancer in the Brea<U+017F>t at its fir<U+017F>t appearance looks
like a <U+017F>mall round <U+017F>welling, more or le<U+017F>s deep in the
Glandulous Sub<U+017F>tance of the Part, with little or no
Pain; and when the hardne<U+017F>s increa<U+017F>es, the Pain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<U+017F>harp, and its ob<U+017F>erv'd to be uneven, and as the
<U+017F>welling increa<U+017F>es, it becomes of a livid, or bluei<U+017F>h, or
blacki<U+017F>h Colour, the Nipples at the <U+017F>ame time often
<U+017F>inking in, round about which al<U+017F>o there ari<U+017F>es hard,
uneven, heavy Protuberances, or little Swellings,
which, as they grow big, do at la<U+017F>t pierce the Skin,
and di<U+017F>cover the Cancerous Ma<U+017F>s, from whence an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceration
proceeds in its Sub<U+017F>tance; the running Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
of which is reddi<U+017F>h, the edges of the Sore broken
or ragged, the tops <U+017F>pungy, and when it comes to a
cadaverous Smell or Stench, it <U+017F>hews the utmo<U+017F>t <U+017F>tate
of a Cancer in the Brea<U+017F>t, which will not yield for Cure
to the be<U+017F>t Remedies in Practice.</p>
            <p>Now in order to compa<U+017F>s the Cure of a Cancer, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
a good Under<U+017F>tanding in the nature of them,
without which nothing can rightly be done; and
if every hard, <U+017F>wel'd, tumify'd or painful Brea<U+017F>t
were known at fir<U+017F>t whether Cancerous or not, many
<U+017F>ucceeding mi<U+017F>chiefs might be prevented; but it is <U+017F>o
common a thing for almo<U+017F>t every Practitioner, and every
tatling Go<U+017F><U+017F>ip, pre<U+017F>ently to declare upon <U+017F>ight of a hard
or <U+017F>well'd Brea<U+017F>t, that it is Cancerous, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
make Applications to it as <U+017F>uch, that <U+017F>carce one
Brea<U+017F>t in twenty they look upon or manage, but is made
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51771:19"/>
Cancerous, tho' it had at fir<U+017F>t no manner of relation to
it: Therefore that none may be deceiv'd that reads this
in time, and fall a Sacrifice to the Ignorance, or Avarice
of <U+017F>uch and many others abroad, that undertake what
they know nothing of; and to <U+017F>et People in a clear
light, as to the Matter of a Concern <U+017F>o dangerous in
it <U+017F>elf, as is a Cancer, was the occa<U+017F>ion of this Tract,
recommending to them a Medicine for outward U<U+017F>e,
and another for inward, that will <U+017F>oon di<U+017F>cover whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
Swelling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be Cancerous or not; for if not
Cancerous, by the u<U+017F>e of this it will <U+017F>oon di<U+017F>appear,
and the Patient be well; and if it be truly Cancerous,
the continuing them, if not too far gone, will effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
cure; almo<U+017F>t wonders having been done by them,
by others as well as by my <U+017F>elf, in my Practice in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
with only u<U+017F>ing them as directed, and as by and
by <U+017F>hall be related, and as the following in<U+017F>tances of
Cures perform'd make appear.</p>
            <p>A young La<U+017F>s of about Fifteen Years old, by a Blow
which <U+017F>he receiv'd upon one of her Brea<U+017F>ts, had a great
hardne<U+017F>s and Pain, which was cur'd by the Liniment
I <U+017F>hall by and by mention, altho' the hardne<U+017F>s and
Pain was <U+017F>o great, that <U+017F>he was in the utmo<U+017F>t danger
of a Cancer, tho' it was not a Cancer, as <U+017F>he was told
by others that <U+017F>he apply'd to before <U+017F>he came to me,
it was. I order'd her to bathe her Brea<U+017F>t warm with the
Liniment every Night and Morning, applying a piece
of Flannel over it; by which means, and before <U+017F>he
u<U+017F>ed all of what I gave her, <U+017F>he was perfectly cur'd,
which might be in Three Weeks time, and never
then, or after did any thing el<U+017F>e to it.</p>
            <p>A poor Working-Woman, by a Blow upon her
Right Brea<U+017F>t with the Key of a Door, which <U+017F>he run
again<U+017F>t, had a great Pain in it that <U+017F>he could not Re<U+017F>t
Night not Day; the Brui<U+017F>e inflam'd and Swell'd, <U+017F>he
ran from one to another for help, till at length <U+017F>he was
told it was a Cancer, and mu<U+017F>t be cut off, <U+017F>he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd
by one that had us'd the Liniment in a Swell'd
Brea<U+017F>t, to come to me, which <U+017F>he did. The Symptoms
were <U+017F>o bad, that I very much que<U+017F>tion'd her Cure,
yet I undertook her, and order'd her to anoint with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51771:19"/>
the Liniment, which <U+017F>he had not us'd above a Week,
but the Pain much abated, and Swelling began to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,
and <U+017F>he continued it con<U+017F>tantly Night and Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and in about Two Months time, was at well as
ever <U+017F>he was in her Life.</p>
            <p>A Gentlewoman, a particular Friend of mine, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
a Lying-in had a <U+017F>ore Brea<U+017F>t, which, altho' broke,
continued hard and <U+017F>ometimes painful, at length is
turn'd to a Gleety Humour, running out at a place
near the Nipple like a Fi<U+017F>tula, the Humour that run
being <U+017F>ometimes yellow, and <U+017F>ometimes of other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours;
and <U+017F>ometimes thick, at other times thin, <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
it did not run at all, at other times bur<U+017F>t our
again, <U+017F>till continuing hard, tender and <U+017F>omething
painful, which put her in fear of a Cancer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
did <U+017F>omething re<U+017F>emble a Fi<U+017F>tulous Cancer; but
notwith<U+017F>tanding, upon bathing all the Swelling with
the Liniment before <U+017F>poken of, <U+017F>he in about Sixteen
Weeks got cur'd of it, and is now perfectly well,
tho' it be Four Years <U+017F>ince it was perform'd, only
at times <U+017F>ome of the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills before-mentioned,
were given her inwardly to purge a little, which are
mo<U+017F>t proper, when Humours abound, and the Body
be gro<U+017F>s, or foul, to purge now and then, in order
to the quicker and more certain amendment.</p>
            <p>A Gentlewoman by a punch upon her Brea<U+017F>t by a
Man's ru<U+017F>hing by her in the Street, had <U+017F>uch a Pain,
throbbing, and at length Inflamation and Swelling,
that <U+017F>he was told it was a Cancer, and had divers
things of divers Per<U+017F>ons for Cure, but all to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e,
rather aggravating than abating the Symptoms.
She took inwardly Wood-lice, for a Month together
us'd Bleeding, Purging, and to the Brea<U+017F>t Poultices,
Ointments, Oyls, Suphs, and even every thing <U+017F>he
had heard commended: At length <U+017F>ome Body told
her of my Liniment, <U+017F>he came to my Hou<U+017F>e and had
it, by the u<U+017F>e of which, and now and then purging
with the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills afore<U+017F>aid, <U+017F>he became, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
well in about Nine Weeks time, tho' I was at
fir<U+017F>t jealous, whether ever it would be cured or
not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51771:20"/>
I could give many other in<U+017F>tances, were it not
needle<U+017F>s; the<U+017F>e two or three I think <U+017F>ufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,
if not, more will not do it; which however,
the u<U+017F>e of the Liniment will, that it is really the
only Medicine I believe upon the Earth, for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of Swellings on the Brea<U+017F>ts of Women, whether
Cancerous or not, and whether broken or whole, to
anoint the hardne<U+017F>s or Swelling; but to the Sores it
mu<U+017F>t not be apply'd, but mu<U+017F>t be manag'd by <U+017F>ome
Surgeon; either do I believe any Medicine what<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
will do like it; for it di<U+017F>per<U+017F>es all the hard and
tumify'd Kernels, takes off all Pain, Brui<U+017F>es and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammations;
for if inflam'd, it pre<U+017F>ently abates it, if
the Brea<U+017F>t be cold, as <U+017F>ome have ob<U+017F>erv'd it to be, it
warms and comforts it; and in fine, does every thing
Nature in that Matter requires to be done, curing
all Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions of the Brea<U+017F>ts curable. Therefore
for the <U+017F>akes of tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>tand in need, I wi<U+017F>h they
were as <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of its Effects as I am, and then none
under that Calamity but would u<U+017F>e it, and where
now there are Twenty Cancerated Brea<U+017F>ts, there
would not be Three, as I am verily per<U+017F>waded; <U+017F>uch
is the great force, power and vertue of this Liniment,
which is <U+017F>o innocent that it may be eat, and yet
of <U+017F>uch wonderful Effects, that if any <U+017F>ore Brea<U+017F>t be
to be cur'd, 'twill infallibly do it, and if incurable,
will no more injure it than applying upon it only a
piece of Flannel or Cloth.</p>
            <p>By this time the Reader may be in expectation, or
at lea<U+017F>t wi<U+017F>e de<U+017F>irous of knowing what this Liniment
is compounded of, which I mu<U+017F>t beg pardon for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing;
and <U+017F>hall proceed to direct the way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of u<U+017F>ing it, which is thus; Anoint the Swell'd
or Pain'd Brea<U+017F>t with a little of it, with a warm
Hand every Night and Morning, for almo<U+017F>t a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of an Hour together, applying a Piece of Flannel
over; and this mu<U+017F>t be done daily for a con<U+017F>iderable
time; for it is frequently ob<U+017F>erv'd, that the Glands
in the Brea<U+017F>ts are very hard, and it cannot be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
they <U+017F>hould <U+017F>often pre<U+017F>ently; but this every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51771:20"/>
may depend upon, that if they continue u<U+017F>ing it,
without once omitting it, it will infallibly cure; <U+017F>ome
People are cur'd <U+017F>ooner by it, in others it is longer fir<U+017F>t,
according to the Condition of the Brea<U+017F>t and Con<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
of the Patient; but the Rule mu<U+017F>t be this, to
per<U+017F>i<U+017F>t in the u<U+017F>e of it, till the Pain, Swelling, Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> are all gone, which infallibly will be,
<U+017F>ometimes in a Month (as have been done in very bad
Brea<U+017F>ts) have been cured by it, and <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ooner;
others again have taken up two or three Months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they have been well; but then they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tantly
found an Amendment, which I affirm by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
under God, every one, that keeps <U+017F>trictly to
its u<U+017F>e, without wavering, or being weary, and I
think none <U+017F>hould be tired on <U+017F>uch an account; for
what would one give to be cur'd of an incurable
Cancer? Let every one but con<U+017F>ider that, and they
will not be a weary of doing that which will re<U+017F>tore
them to their Health, and pre<U+017F>erve their Lives, which,
I <U+017F>ay, under God, this Liniment will do, if u<U+017F>ed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
as is directed.</p>
            <p>But, as <U+017F>aid before, it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in <U+017F>ome Con<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions
to u<U+017F>e a little Purging al<U+017F>o, during the u<U+017F>e
of the Liniment, e<U+017F>pecially in Bodies that are gro<U+017F>s
or <U+017F>oul, and where the Humours flow to the Brea<U+017F>t
to cau<U+017F>e Inflammation, Pain or more Swelling, or if
the Habit of the Body be but indifferent; in <U+017F>uch
Ca<U+017F>es, and indeed mo<U+017F>t ca<U+017F>es of <U+017F>ore Brea<U+017F>ts, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
to Purge, to do which, nothing can be more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent
or more adapted to correct or carry off tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ort
of Humours, whether Cancerous or otherwi<U+017F>e, than
the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Scorbutick Pill, <U+017F>o largely before <U+017F>poken of,
the taking of two, three, four, five or <U+017F>ix of which,
according as is the <U+017F>trength of the Patient, every third
or fourth Morning, oftner or <U+017F>eldomer, as there may be
occa<U+017F>ion, keeping warm tho<U+017F>e days, and drinking Po<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>et-drink,
Broth or Gruel warm as they operate, and
as is directed in the account given, will be of excellent
u<U+017F>e, and contribute greatly to the benefit of the Patient;
<U+017F>o that the Pills inwardly and the Liniment outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51771:21"/>
will do more I verily believe in Cancerated, Swell'd,
Sore or hard Brea<U+017F>ts, than any <U+017F>ort of Medicines or
Methods, that can by all the Phy<U+017F>icians in the World
be pre<U+017F>crib'd or advis'd to; for I <U+017F>peak it from large Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
and where it not <U+017F>o, I <U+017F>hould not be <U+017F>o po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>itive
in the Matter as I am; therefore all People may
depend upon it, which when they have tryed, will
e<U+017F>teem it, as many others do, to be the only Remedies
in that ca<U+017F>e in the whole World.</p>
            <p>The Price of this Liniment is Five Shillings the
Gallipot. To be had only at the Place aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51771:21"/>
            <head>THE
Suffumigating Powder For Vapours or Hy<U+017F>terick Fits in Women,
and Hypochondriack Melancholly or Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
in Men, and all other Fits and Di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
of the Nerves in general.</head>
            <p>HAD I not more than ordinary Rea<U+017F>on and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
for many Years of being acquainted
with tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and con<U+017F>equently of their
Cure, I <U+017F>hould not take upon me to be <U+017F>o ab<U+017F>olute as
you will find me to be in the Matter; but they being
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es which do very frequently deceive numbers of
Per<U+017F>ons that are afflicted therewith, <U+017F>o as that they
know not what they aile; I <U+017F>hall for their <U+017F>akes and
benefits, before I come to treat of the above<U+017F>aid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine
for the Cure, de<U+017F>cribe the Symptoms and
Cau<U+017F>es thereof, and begin fir<U+017F>t with the Vapours.</p>
            <p>Fir<U+017F>t then, the Vapours, otherwi<U+017F>e called Hy<U+017F>terick
Fits, or Fits of the Mother, is a Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e which more
generally afflicts Humane Kind than any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>oever,
and <hi>Proteus</hi> like, transforms it <U+017F>elf into the
Shape and Repre<U+017F>entation of almo<U+017F>t all Di<U+017F>tempers, tho<U+017F>e
who are troubled therewith, generally perceiving them
approach in the following manner: Fir<U+017F>t, they feel a
heavine<U+017F>s upon their Brea<U+017F>t, a grumbling in their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
they belch up, and <U+017F>ometimes Vomit <U+017F>owr, <U+017F>harp,
in<U+017F>ipid, or bitter Humour; they have a difficulty in
breathing, and think they feel <U+017F>omething come up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
their Throat, which is ready to choak them, they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51771:22"/>
<U+017F>truggle, cry out, make odd and inarticulate Sounds
or Mutterings, they perceive a Swimming in their
Heads, a Dimne<U+017F>s come over their Eyes, they turn
Pale, are <U+017F>carce able to <U+017F>tand, their Pul<U+017F>e is weak, they
<U+017F>hut their Eyes, cry, <U+017F>hriek out, groan, foam at the
Mouth, and remain Sen<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s for <U+017F>ome time, afterwards
by little and little their Pul<U+017F>e returns, their Face re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains
its natural colour, their Body grows hot, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
they open their Eyes, and by degrees come to
them<U+017F>elves.</p>
            <p>Some moreover, have their Bellies <U+017F>well'd and
<U+017F>tretched like a Drum, their Hypochondria's di<U+017F>tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and they fancy they feel <U+017F>omewhat within them
rowl from place to place, which the Ancients ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd
to be the Womb changing from place to place,
whereas the Ligaments which tye it down render
that impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible; be<U+017F>ides that, Men are al<U+017F>o afflicted
with this Symptom as well as Women; their Pul<U+017F>e
is almo<U+017F>t imperceptible, they feel a violent Cold
run up their Backs, which afterwards <U+017F>trikes through
their whole Body, their Head-achs, and <U+017F>ometimes
there en<U+017F>ues a Palpitation of the Heart and a faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
away; there are many, who when the<U+017F>e acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
are over, come quietly to them<U+017F>elves by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
and in others when the violent cold is ended a
no le<U+017F>s violent Heat <U+017F>ucceeds, which ca<U+017F>ts them again
into many of the former accidents, as Palpitation of
the Heart, Head-achs, Giddine<U+017F>s, difficulty in Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
and into <U+017F>ome new ones, as Flu<U+017F>hings of the Face,
Raving, Convul<U+017F>ions, foaming at the Mouth, violent
beating of the Mu<U+017F>cles and Arteries, and a tingling Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ation
in the Thighs, which are Paralitick, during the
cold Fit; nay, <U+017F>ometimes the Pal<U+017F>ie will continue in
the hot Fit too, <U+017F>ometimes the cold with which the Fit
begins is hardly perceptible, and then the Patient has
no remarkable accidents whil<U+017F>t the cold la<U+017F>ts; but when
the hot Fit comes on, it is accompanied with <U+017F>everal of
the above-numbred accidents, but the Pul<U+017F>e beats high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and quicker than in the foregoing <U+017F>tate, and if no
coldne<U+017F>s was to be perceived at all before the hot Fit,
then many of the <U+017F>ame accidents will happen, but only
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51771:22"/>
in a more violent degree, and <U+017F>till more frequent and
beats higher.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the Patients in this Di<U+017F>temper fall into
<U+017F>uch violent Fits of Struggling, that they can hardly
be held; they mutter odd and inarticulate Sounds,
grate their Teeth, foam at their Mouths, and <U+017F>trike
their Brea<U+017F>ts; others <U+017F>uffer much violent, and long
continued Contractions of the Diaphragm and Int<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<U+017F>tal
Mu<U+017F>cles, that their Brea<U+017F>t and lower Belly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
elevated for a long time together, <U+017F>o that they
cannot draw their Breath all that while; nay, <U+017F>ome
have lain for three whole days without the lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>ign
of breathing perceivable by tho<U+017F>e that were about
them.</p>
            <p>One complains of a violent Pain on the top of
her Head, which is frequently accompanied with Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting.</p>
            <p>Another is troubled with a Pain under her Heart,
and a reaching to Vomit, or Vomits a mixture of
Porraceous and Cholerick Humours, and it ends in a
Jaundice.</p>
            <p>A third lyes with her Jaws pre<U+017F>s'd together with all
the violence imaginable, and her No<U+017F>trils drawn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e that <U+017F>he is in danger of being <U+017F>uffocated,
and <U+017F>ometimes remains for a con<U+017F>iderable while as if <U+017F>he
were dead.</p>
            <p>A fourth upon the <U+017F>mell of Civit, Musk, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergrea<U+017F>e,
or any <U+017F>uch <U+017F>weet Scent, <U+017F>hall fall into
Fits.</p>
            <p>A fifth <U+017F>hall be mole<U+017F>ted with them upon any
Anger, Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion or Di<U+017F>turbance of Mind, which is
immediately followed with great quantity of pale
Urine.</p>
            <p>A <U+017F>ixth is very thoughtful, blu<U+017F>hes or grows pale
on a <U+017F>udden, has a deprav'd Appetite, <U+017F>ometimes to
craving, at other times to loathing all <U+017F>orts of u<U+017F>ual
Meats, and is plea<U+017F>ed only with the eating of ab<U+017F>urd
things, as Chalk, Charcole, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <U+017F>eventh will on a <U+017F>udden fall into extravagant Fits
of Crying or Laughing, without being provok'd by any
external Cau<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51771:23"/>
Be<U+017F>ides all the<U+017F>e, <U+017F>everal other accidents happen to
People troubled with this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, as a Pain in the
Bladder and Kidneys, like that of the Stone and Gravel,
violent Cholicks, Swellings in the Jaws, Shoulders,
Legs, Hands or Thighs, which yield not to the Finger
that pre<U+017F><U+017F>es, nor retain any Mark; Pain in the Back,
which all feel more or le<U+017F>s, as al<U+017F>o in <U+017F>everal Parts of
the Body <U+017F>o violent, that the Place affected cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
touching for a long while afterwards; they breath
<U+017F>hort and with Pain, yawn and <U+017F>tretch, their Sleep is
di<U+017F>turb'd, and their Dreams are frightful, their Eyes
are fixt and <U+017F>taring, <U+017F>ometimes they remember what
happen'd in their Fit, <U+017F>ometimes they do not, they
cough without intermi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, <U+017F>pit in va<U+017F>t quantities for
<U+017F>everal Weeks, as if they were in a Salivation, with
many other accidents too tedious to enumerate.</p>
            <p>La<U+017F>tly, we ob<U+017F>erve that tho<U+017F>e who have labour'd
long under this Di<U+017F>tempe are oppre<U+017F>s'd with a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Angui<U+017F>h of Mind, and a deep Melancholly, always
reflecting on what can perplex, terrifie and di<U+017F>order
them mo<U+017F>t, <U+017F>o that at lea<U+017F>t they think their Recovery
impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, and are very angry with tho<U+017F>e that pretend
there is any hopes of it; the lea<U+017F>t contradiction to their
will, ca<U+017F>t them into violent Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions; they are fickle,
wavering and uncon<U+017F>tant, now re<U+017F>olving on one thing,
and immediately changing to <U+017F>omething el<U+017F>e, which
they as pre<U+017F>ently quit, and by indulging their Di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
decline all <U+017F>orts of Diver<U+017F>ions.</p>
            <p>But Note, that all the<U+017F>e accidents do not happen to
every one that has Vapours, or Hy<U+017F>terick Fits, but <U+017F>ome
to one <U+017F>ome to another: This Per<U+017F>on <U+017F>hall be mole<U+017F>ted
with a great many, that with but a few of tho<U+017F>e Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms,
and it <U+017F>uffices, that any two or three of them
return by intervals, to have them term'd Vapours.</p>
            <p>It is al<U+017F>o ob<U+017F>erv'd, that this Di<U+017F>temper comes by Fits,
and has its intervals like an Ague, tho' the return be
not exactly Periodical like it, and that in every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxi<U+017F>m
the <U+017F>ame accidents happen as did in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
provided the Patient committed no exce<U+017F>s in
the interval.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51771:23"/>
Thus much for the Symptoms, the next thing to
be con<U+017F>ider'd, is the Cau<U+017F>e of this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which is
nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to be taken notice of, the better to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
as much as is po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, and which <U+017F>ome a<U+017F><U+017F>ign to this,
others to that, and others different to both, which,
tho' all plau<U+017F>ible Notions, fall <U+017F>hort of the real cau<U+017F>e,
wanting Rea<U+017F>on back'd by Experience and Matter of
Fact to <U+017F>upport them; but forbearing to enumerate
their <U+017F>everal imaginary Notions, I <U+017F>hall in <U+017F>hort, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
my <U+017F>elf to <U+017F>hew the true and only Cau<U+017F>es thereof,
which are Crudities and Indige<U+017F>tions of the Stomach,
nothing el<U+017F>e being to be found within the Stomach and
the Guts capable of producing tho<U+017F>e Symptoms, unle<U+017F>s it
be the Aliments we take, but the<U+017F>e we know when well
concocted and dige<U+017F>ted, are <U+017F>o far from producing any
ill effects upon Humane Bodies, that they alone <U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tain
and pre<U+017F>erve them in a capacity of exerci<U+017F>ing their
Natural and Animal Functions: However, if they by
any vitious Concoction turn into Crudities and Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<U+017F>tions,
then their laudable Qualities are chang'd into
quite oppo<U+017F>ite ones, and they produce the many Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
and Symptoms of this Di<U+017F>temper; for when by
the vitious qualification of the Ferment of the Stomach,
the Aliments are not well dige<U+017F>ted, they turn into
Crudities, the<U+017F>e Crudities by little and little gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
in the wrinkles and <U+017F>olds of the Stomach and
Guts, where they lye for <U+017F>ome time without much <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible
motion or fermentation within them<U+017F>elves, till at
la<U+017F>t by the Circumjacent Parts, their gro<U+017F><U+017F>er Salts are
divided and put into motion, which Fermentation is
augmented by the various Juices that flow into the Guts,
from the many Glands which are placed in the lower
Belly, and by this means they are di<U+017F><U+017F>olv'd and liqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd
as to enter by the Milky Veins into the Blood,
where they produce all the accidents of this Di<U+017F>temper,
which the only way to prevent in all Per<U+017F>ons, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pecially
in <U+017F>uch where the Vapours are fear'd, is to
clean<U+017F>e the Stomach and Bowels of the Saburra which
lies in them; and that frequently, <hi>viz.</hi> once in a
Month, oftner or <U+017F>eldomer, as there may be occa<U+017F>ion,
with <U+017F>ome proper, gentle, ab<U+017F>ter<U+017F>ive Vomit or Purge,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51771:24"/>
than which nothing can exceed the famous <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi>
Pills aforegoing, taking them as you <U+017F>ee occa<U+017F>ion; thus
much for the Symptoms, Cau<U+017F>es, and Prevention of
the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>But perfectly to cure the Vapours or Hy<U+017F>terick Fits,
or Fits of the Mother, in <U+017F>uch that are <U+017F>o unhappily
afflicted, the Cau<U+017F>e mu<U+017F>t be eradicated, and the Blood
re<U+017F>tored to its Natural Con<U+017F>titution, without which the
effect can never cea<U+017F>e, and that the common Medicines
in Practice are not capable of performing it, is daily <U+017F>een
by the few (if any) that are cured therewith, they only
being <U+017F>ufficient, and <U+017F>ometimes not that, to appea<U+017F>e the
Symptom<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and palliate the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e; but <U+017F>uch is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency
of the afore<U+017F>aid <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills and this <hi>Suffumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi>
that they immediately <U+017F>trike at the Root of the
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and never leave (if reiterated) till the whole Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy
of the Body is chang'd, which will <U+017F>oon be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap>, or not return of the u<U+017F>ual
Symptoms, or Paroxi<U+017F>ms, the manner of taking which
Pills, with ob<U+017F>ervations to be heeded as to Diet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
is at large before <U+017F>et forth, with which and this <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumigation</hi>
(they ob<U+017F>erving Rules as to Diet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of Hy<U+017F>terick Per<U+017F>ons have been cured, when they
have lain <U+017F>ome Months in violent Ravings, and other
Symptoms, almo<U+017F>t <U+017F>uppos'd irretrievable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of Hypochondriack Melancholly, or Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
in Men, which is a <U+017F>ort of Cachexie that frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
reigns in our Northern Climates, who<U+017F>e Symptoms
appearing mo<U+017F>tly in the Hypochondria, is term'd the
Hypochondriack Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and when its Symptoms are
very fierce and exalted, 'tis entitule the Scurvy, a
Name given it by the <hi>Saxons</hi> in Nor<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Germany,</hi> who
are mo<U+017F>t liable to it; the better part of Authors upon
this Subject being amus'd with its Symptoms and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,
have vainly fancy'd to e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>h its Original Seat
in <U+017F>everal Bowels that are only accidentally concern'd;
but if they trac'd it to its <U+017F>tate of Infancy and fir<U+017F>t begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
they mu<U+017F>t have pitch'd upon the Stomach for
the Place of its Nativity, and upon the Acid vi<U+017F>cous
Cruditie, that a faulty dige<U+017F>tion occa<U+017F>ion for its Cau<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51771:24"/>
For our further <U+017F>atisfaction in this matter, we <U+017F>hall
briefly run over its Symptoms, and if we find that they
owe their Being to an Acid Crudity in the Stomach,
<U+017F>hall reckon that we have made our point good. In the
fir<U+017F>t place then, the Appetite is over-keen in Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack
Per<U+017F>ons, their Dige<U+017F>tion being weak, and follow'd
by Convul<U+017F>ive or weighty Pains in the Stomach, belching
Wind and Noi<U+017F>e, e<U+017F>pecially in the left <U+017F>ide of the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
where the Gut-Colon is <U+017F>traitned; they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
Co<U+017F>tive, and Laxatives operate better in them
than Purgatives; if an Artificial or Natural Vomiting
happen, they throw up Acid Matter, which <U+017F>tupfiies,
or <U+017F>ets the Teeth on edge, and which will corrode a
Copper Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el <U+017F>o as to render it ru<U+017F>ty. After Eating,
they are oft-times <U+017F>eiz'd with a gnawing Pain in the
Stomach, reaching along the Back from the lower part
to the Neck of the Gullet (which <U+017F>ome mi<U+017F>cal Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phritick
Pains) as al<U+017F>o with <U+017F>udden flu<U+017F>hings in the
Face, wringing Pains in the Guts, palpitation of the
Heart, perturbation of Mind, and a difficulty of breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
occa<U+017F>ion'd either by vi<U+017F>cous Crudities di<U+017F>tending
the Stomach or Convul<U+017F>ions of the Midriff, and Mu<U+017F>cles
of the Brea<U+017F>t, or Wind in the Abdomen, hindring the
de<U+017F>cent of the Midriff; while their Stomach is empty,
they are apt to be giddy and dull, they are liable to
periodical Exa<U+017F>perations; frequently they are <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible
(as it were) of Fumes ri<U+017F>ing up from the Belly, and the
Paroxi<U+017F>m re<U+017F>embles an Hy<U+017F>terical Fit, in the Paroxi<U+017F>m
the colour and con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of their Urine is incon<U+017F>tant,
but when 'tis over, returns to a Natural order. The<U+017F>e
are the Symptoms of Hypochondriack Per<U+017F>on, but
all of them are rarely to be <U+017F>een in one Per<U+017F>on, the mo<U+017F>t
certain Symptoms that always attend, are Gripings and
Wind in the Guts, a weak Stomach, Co<U+017F>tivene<U+017F>s, and
Perturbation of the Head.</p>
            <p>The Symptoms being thus premis'd, we come now
to enquire after<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the Cau<U+017F>e of this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, the fir<U+017F>t and
original of which is a vicious Acid in the Stomach en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging
the Appetite, but unfit for Dige<U+017F>tion, hence
en<U+017F>ues an Acid Crudity in the fir<U+017F>t Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praves
the cra<U+017F>is of the Blood, prevents the due <U+017F>epara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51771:25"/>
of volatil Spirits, upon which the Lymph becomes
Acid, and the Bile inactive.</p>
            <p>The<U+017F>e are the Sources of all the preceding Symptoms,
<U+017F>ince Wind, Noi<U+017F>e, Griping of the Guts and Co<U+017F>tive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
are the natural re<U+017F>ult of a vicious Acid in the fir<U+017F>t
Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, as flu<U+017F>hings in the Face ari<U+017F>e from its effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<U+017F>cence
with the Bile, the Convul<U+017F>ions of the nervous
Membranes in <U+017F>everal Parts of the Body are the effect
of its Iritation; its Crudity impairs the due Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Blood, and cau<U+017F>es a palpitation of the
Heart, and difficulty of Breathing; it depraves the
Nutritious Juice of the Bowels which <U+017F>ettles into hard
Swellings, and occa<U+017F>ions a degeneracy and au<U+017F>terity in
the Spirits; hence Fear, Melancholly, irregular Thoughts
and uncouth emotions en<U+017F>ue.</p>
            <p>The remote Cau<U+017F>es that promote Crudities are Acid
Liquors or Salt Victuals, or <U+017F>uch as are dried in the
Smoak, <U+017F>ince both partake of the Acid Spirit of Salt or
Soot; al<U+017F>o want of motion to promote dige<U+017F>tion, and
the <U+017F>peedy a<U+017F><U+017F>imilation of the Chyle; likewi<U+017F>e Noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Study and over thoughtfulne<U+017F>s and care, exhau<U+017F>t
the Spirits, impoveri<U+017F>h the Blood, and render the Lymph
acid; Thus much for the Symptoms and Cau<U+017F>e of this
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Cure, its con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in correcting and
evacuating the Crudities of the fir<U+017F>t Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
the Stomach, retrieving the due cra<U+017F>is of the
Blood, and re<U+017F>toring all wonted Evacuations to their
former cour<U+017F>e, in order to compa<U+017F>s which ends, let the
following Rules be heedfully minded.</p>
            <p>1<U+017F>t, That a Do<U+017F>e of the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills aforemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
be taken <U+017F>o often as you find occa<U+017F>ion, with a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
regular Diet, and u<U+017F>ing a moderate quantity of true
natural red Wine mix'd with Water in<U+017F>tead of Malt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinks,
which, with the u<U+017F>e of the Suffumigating
Powder I <U+017F>hall by and by give directions about, never
fails <U+017F>etting them to rights, as numbers in very deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
conditions have happily experienced.</p>
            <p>2dly, Their way of living both in the Vapours and
Hypochondriack Melancholly, as to Dyet, ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>t
chiefly of cooling refre<U+017F>hing Nouri<U+017F>hments, Food of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51771:25"/>
good Juyce, eating Water-gruel, Barley and Rice-Broths,
Rice-milk, boil'd and roa<U+017F>t Veal and Mutton,
Veal or Chicken-Broths not made <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong as u<U+017F>ually,
eating no Salt or <U+017F>piced Meats.</p>
            <p>3dly, They mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>leep not too much, neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge
Melancholly or thoughtfulne<U+017F>s, but be cheerful
and u<U+017F>e diver<U+017F>ions, keeping in company that is mirthful
and talkative, ride and take the fre<U+017F>h Air; which, with
the variety of different Company and Objects which they
<U+017F>ee, concur to plea<U+017F>ure the Mind and remove all anxious
Thoughts, and thereby contribute much towards the
Cure.</p>
            <p>And for all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Nerves, Fits of all <U+017F>orts,
whether Convul<U+017F>ions, Falling Sickne<U+017F>s, Apoplexies,
Lethargies, Pal<U+017F>ies or other Di<U+017F>orders of the Animal
Spirits and Brain, Spa<U+017F>ms, Tremblings, Contractions,
Relaxations of the Limbs, Numbne<U+017F>s, Coldne<U+017F>s, or
the like, a Do<U+017F>e now and then of the afore<U+017F>aid <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi>
Pills, and u<U+017F>ing the Suffumigating Powder, as I <U+017F>hall
pre<U+017F>ently direct, nothing will be found more efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
e<U+017F>pecially if the contracted or relaxed Limbs be
anointed every Night with Oil of Amber, and the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
Diet-drink be made and drank con<U+017F>tantly of,
which is al<U+017F>o excellent in Vapours and Melancholly.</p>
            <p>Take Mu<U+017F>tard Seeds, 4 Ounces bui<U+017F>ed, Hor<U+017F>e-radi<U+017F>h
Roots two Ounces, Scurvy-gra<U+017F>s two Handfuls, Aaron
Roots half an Ounce, Bryony Roots two Ounces, boil
all in a Gallon of Spring Water till a Quart be boil'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
then <U+017F>train it, and drink half a Pint three times
a day.</p>
            <p>U<U+017F>e the Suffumigating Powder thus, put a Paper of
it upon <U+017F>ome live Coals in a Cha<U+017F>ing-di<U+017F>h or <U+017F>ome <U+017F>uch
a thing, and put in under a Chair with a Hole in it,
clapping a Funnel upon the Coals, <U+017F>o that the Smoak
will go through the Funnel, and the Patient <U+017F>it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
upon the Chair bare, will receive it up the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
which mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>o done every Night going to Bed,
or once in 2 or 3 Nights, according as there is occa<U+017F>ion,
whereby in Fits, Vapours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there is in<U+017F>tant Relief.
The Price of this Powder is 3 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi> the four Papers.
To be had at the Place aforementioned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:51771:26"/>
            <head>THE
CATAPLASM:
OR,
POULTICE
FOR THE
GOUT.</head>
            <p>THO' I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething concerning the Gout,
before I <U+017F>peak <U+017F>o particularly of the Poultice
for its ea<U+017F>e; yet the Reader is not to expect any
learned account of it, that being <U+017F>ufficiently Done by
divers Authors, but only ju<U+017F>t <U+017F>o much as to inform tho<U+017F>e
that are afflicted with that Di<U+017F>temper, how far they
may pre<U+017F>erve them<U+017F>elves from its fury by a regular
mode of living, and how thereby tho<U+017F>e that ever had
any touch of it, may certainly nip it in its Bud, <U+017F>o as
never after to be afflicted with it:</p>
            <p>But the Publi<U+017F>hing a Medicine (tho' the mo<U+017F>t cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated
one) and crying up its virtues without giving a
<hi>Rationale</hi> of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, looks <U+017F>o rank Quacki<U+017F>h, that
every Man of Sen<U+017F>e will (and with very good rea<U+017F>on)
account it all bomba<U+017F>t and <U+017F>plutter, and for that very
rea<U+017F>on decry it, as coming from <U+017F>ome illeterate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51771:26"/>
for the <U+017F>ake only of getting a little Money;
for which rea<U+017F>on, to convince the World, that the
Author of this Medicine is not altogether unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Nature and Cau<U+017F>e of the Gout <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap>
as the way to Remedy its excruciating Pains, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap>
not recommend this Medicine but from a well g<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Experience, he here offers to every ones con<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, a <U+017F>hort hint of the Blood, its changes A
nalitically prov'd, and the <hi>Rationale</hi> of the Gout,
its Nature and Cau<U+017F>es from thence explicately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</p>
            <p>The Blood of Man is made up of a mixture of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
Principles, to wit, a Bitter, a Sweet, a Salt, an
Acid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the mixture and temperaments of which,
while mutual, pre<U+017F>erves the Body in a <U+017F>tate of Health,
and con<U+017F>equently creates no trouble or unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s: But
when any one of the<U+017F>e Principles is divided or <U+017F>epera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
from the re<U+017F>t, and exi<U+017F>ts by it <U+017F>elf, then the effects
plainly <U+017F>hew what great Trouble, Perplexity, and Pain
it creates in the Body.</p>
            <p>Now nothing more conduces to the <U+017F>eparation of
tho<U+017F>e Homogene Principles of of the Blood, than a fault
in either <U+017F>ome, or all of the <U+017F>ix Non-naturals, as Air;
Meat and Drink; Sleep and want of Sleep; the Motion
and Re<U+017F>t of the Body; the retaining and di<U+017F>charging of
the Excrements; and the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions of the Mind; but
the chief error is in Meat and Drink, in pampering
the Body with more plenty than is needful; by which
means the Particles of the Blood are not <U+017F>o exactly mix'd
with the re<U+017F>t of the Ma<U+017F>s, but are blended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
<U+017F>o as to become Heterogeneous (the Principles
jarring one with another) occa<U+017F>ioning <U+017F>uch a perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and preternatural Fermentation, as evidently <U+017F>hew
Sanguification to be vitiated, and the who<U+017F>e Ma<U+017F>s cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted,
thereby forcing the Sharp and Foreign Juices,
together with part of the Serum, by what way it finds;
as for in<U+017F>tance, if they get into the Guts, they are eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated
by a watery Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s; if into the Kidneys, by
plenty of Urine; if into the habit of the Body, by the
Pores of the Skin; but if they fall upon the Joynts,
they pierce into the innermost rece<U+017F>les and inter<U+017F>tices of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51771:27"/>
the Nervous Parts, and cau<U+017F>e the Gout; and as the Salt
in the Serum is the thicker or thinner, it much alters its
Nature; <U+017F>o that when the Extremities of the Mu<U+017F>cles,
Tendons, Ligaments, Fibres, and other Nervous parts
of the Joynts are twitched by them, more or le<U+017F>s Pain,
Heat and Violence are occa<U+017F>ion'd, and it proves to be a
Fit of a longer or <U+017F>horter duration.</p>
            <p>This Serum, tho' it be thin and <U+017F>harp, is at fir<U+017F>t but
very <U+017F>mall, occa<U+017F>ioning but little Pain; but that little
Pain, if the Cau<U+017F>e of it be timely remov'd, grows great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
at every Fit, and the more violent the Pain is,
greater <U+017F>tore of Serum abounds, and very often a flood
of other Humours is carried along with it; which
cau<U+017F>es that Swelling, Heat, Throbbing and Unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s
every one afflicted with it feels, which leaves not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
till the Humour is <U+017F>pent, at which time that Fit of
the Gout is at end.</p>
            <p>I <U+017F>aid before that a fault in <U+017F>ome of the <U+017F>ix Non-Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals
nam'd, was the cau<U+017F>e of the Gout, and that pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering
the Body with plenty, was the Chief, I mean
thereby Gluttony and Drunkenne<U+017F>s, e<U+017F>pecially upon
eating <U+017F>uch Meats as are <U+017F>tor'd with <U+017F>harp Matter, not
to be <U+017F>ufficiently <U+017F>eparated or di<U+017F>charg'd, or that can be
ea<U+017F>ily mix'd or temper'd with the other Juices of our
Bodies; as al<U+017F>o drinking too plentifully of Wines
which have much Tartar in them: For not only that
Tartar, but the Spiritous part breeds the Gout; which
Spirit con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts of an Oil, an Acid and a Volatile Salt,
in which the <U+017F>trength of Wine con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts. Yet as Exce<U+017F>s
therein hurts, <U+017F>o Temperance pre<U+017F>erves the Health:
For tho<U+017F>e Wines which mo<U+017F>t abound with Tartar, are
much more homogene to our Bodies, than other Wines
that have little Tartar in them, and <U+017F>hould be made
choice of; and are the be<U+017F>t with Moderation for all
Con<U+017F>titutions and Temperaments, and the Red of all
<U+017F>orts, is far more preferrable than the White.</p>
            <p>And not only is it manife<U+017F>t that the Gout is bred by
Gluttony and Drunkenne<U+017F>s, but al<U+017F>o other innumerable
inconveniencies are caus'd thereby, for by that means
the Appetite is de<U+017F>troy'd, the Dige<U+017F>tions vitiated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
the con<U+017F>equences of which every one may ea<U+017F>ily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51771:27"/>
and time, (if not prevented) will mo<U+017F>t certainly
and fatally determine: For a good Appetite and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
Dige<U+017F>tions, are <U+017F>o indi<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ably nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to the
<U+017F>upport and pre<U+017F>ervation of Humane Life, that we can
no more <hi>well</hi> <U+017F>ub<U+017F>i<U+017F>t without the one, than we can <hi>long</hi>
without the other; the one indicates Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es pre<U+017F>ent,
the other threatens Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es to come, and frequently
brings the whole Humane Oeconomy into di<U+017F>order and
confu<U+017F>ion: For when there is a depravitty of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae
Viae,</hi> the Chyle into which the Food is converted in
the Stomach, is deprav'd al<U+017F>o; and according as is the
Chyle, <U+017F>o mu<U+017F>t the Blood of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity be, whether it be
good or whether it be bad, and according to which the
Body <U+017F>uffers more or le<U+017F>s.</p>
            <p>And as <U+017F>ome forts of Meats and Drinks, and Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance
therein are hurtful, <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o the Eating of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
are more than ordinary pernicious, for they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
the functions of the Body, and injure the mind;
and then at tho<U+017F>e Sea<U+017F>ons to eat too plentifully, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes
much more to the <U+017F>poiling of the Blood, as
every one that has for any time followed the Practice
has ob<U+017F>erv'd; few things being more detrimental and
ruinous to the Health, as all Phy<U+017F>icians allow; and
as in <hi>Schola Salerni</hi> it is well noted, where it is
<U+017F>aid,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ex magna Coena Stomacho fit maxima Paena,</l>
               <l>Ut <U+017F>is nocte levis, <U+017F>it tibi Coena brevis.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Great Suppers put the Stomach to great pain,</l>
               <l>Sup lightly, if good Re<U+017F>t you mean to gain.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Al<U+017F>o over hard Study, e<U+017F>pecially in the Night time,
which in this Ca<U+017F>e is the wor<U+017F>t, and afflicting Cares,
hinders Sanguification and breed the Gout; <U+017F>o that the
<U+017F>harp part in the Aliment receiv'd, is either not well
mix'd, or not well <U+017F>eparated, and therefore cannot be
well di<U+017F>charged. Likewi<U+017F>e Anger and Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion very
much injure: For,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:51771:28"/>
               <l>Exhiler at Tri<U+017F>tres, iratos, placat, amantes,</l>
               <l>Ne fuit amentes, mens laeta, requires, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>'Tis Mirth that Nur<U+017F>eth Life and Blood,</l>
               <l>Far more than Wine, or Re<U+017F>t or Food.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Al<U+017F>o immoderate and un<U+017F>ea<U+017F>onable Venery conduces
not a little; for it weakens the Strength, hurts the
Brain, extingui<U+017F>hes Radical Moi<U+017F>ture, and ha<U+017F>tens old
Age and Death; the Sperm, or Seed of Generation,
being the only Comfort of Nature, which willfully
<U+017F>hed or lo<U+017F>t, injures a Man more than the lo<U+017F>s of forty
times that quanty of Blood; wherefore <hi>Virgil</hi> well
<U+017F>ays,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nulla Magis animi vires Indu<U+017F>tria firmat,</l>
               <l>Quam Venerem &amp; caeci <U+017F>timulos avertere amoris.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Much Venery cau<U+017F>e great Ills to Mind and Blood,</l>
               <l>Exhau<U+017F>ts the Stock, unfits Man for's Wife's good,</l>
               <l>When moderately us'd, holds long, and helps as Food.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Levinus Lemnius</hi> likewi<U+017F>e <U+017F>ays, if a Man intends
to Live Long and happy during the Life he leads, he
<U+017F>hould,
<q>Ve<U+017F>ci citra <U+017F>aturitatem, non refugere laborem, vitale <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
con<U+017F>ervare.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That is, make light Meals, u<U+017F>e Exerci<U+017F>e, and pre<U+017F>erve
his Seed, which is the vital and principal Part of Life,
and certainly nothing more a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly breeds the Gout
than immmoderate Venery.</p>
            <p>Thus the Cau<U+017F>es of the Gout being <U+017F>ufficiently expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,
I <U+017F>hall next give a definition of it, its Nature
and Remedy.</p>
            <p>The Gout then is a mo<U+017F>t inten<U+017F>e, <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Pain of the
Tendonous Membranous Parts about the Joints, cau<U+017F>ed
by a Serous, Pungent and exceeding <U+017F>harp Humour,
forced <U+017F>uddenly out of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els from an inward di<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ition,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51771:28"/>
and led thither by the inter<U+017F>tices of the Nervous
Parts.</p>
            <p>The <U+017F>ign of its coming, or being pre<U+017F>ent, are <U+017F>ometimes
wandring Pains, e<U+017F>pecially in the Joynts of the Feet or
Hands: That it is at hand, is <U+017F>hewn by a <U+017F>tretching,
yawning, painful wearine<U+017F>s; Catarrhs, Pains in the
Limbs and Joints, and <U+017F>ometimes a heavine<U+017F>s in the
Head, a kind of Feveri<U+017F>h heat, a pricking Pain in the
Joints, cau<U+017F>ing <U+017F>tarting, with inability to move; and
after that comes a Swelling, u<U+017F>ually red, attended with
Watching, lo<U+017F>s of Strength, <U+017F>tiffne<U+017F>s of the Parts, and
<U+017F>everal other complaints, not alike to all at all
times, yet is what Gouty People well know, and
are more acquainted with than is con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with their
Ea<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>The way to remedy this untoward Evil, is fir<U+017F>t to
remove the Cau<U+017F>e, that is, that which aggravates the
Paroxi<U+017F>m; and <U+017F>econdly to pre<U+017F>erve the Patient from
the return of a Fit, or at lea<U+017F>twi<U+017F>e to render it when it
comes, more ea<U+017F>y, and not <U+017F>o intollerable as we fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
find it to be; for when it has once feiz'd a Man,
it will (if not prevented by proper Medicines) return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
at certain <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons and di<U+017F>tances of Time, as the
Gouty Matter in the Blood is a fre<U+017F>h increas'd, gather'd
and led down to the Joints, which di<U+017F>tances are longer
or <U+017F>horter, and the Paroxi<U+017F>ms greater or le<U+017F><U+017F>er, according
as the Patient live Regular or Irregular, and according
as is the <U+017F>trength or weakne<U+017F>s of his Con<U+017F>titution; for
if it be weak or broke, or the Patient in <hi>Mala Stamina
Vitae,</hi> it occa<U+017F>ions its coming oftener, pains him wor<U+017F>er,
and holds him longer than if the <U+017F>ame Con<U+017F>titution
was <U+017F>tronger, and the Patient in <hi>Bona Stamina Vitae;</hi> and
al<U+017F>o acccording as he takes proper Medicines to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
that Humour, by leading it away by the proper
Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages.</p>
            <p>I know <U+017F>ome Phy<U+017F>ician's Doctrine is to let Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
take her free Cour<U+017F>e, advi<U+017F>ing their Patients to
bear under the burden of that intolerable Mi<U+017F>ery
as well as they can. Indeed, in the Knotted Gout the
Advice may hold good, for there, no Cure can be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51771:29"/>
expected, according to that known ancient, but true
<hi>Axiom,</hi>
               <q>Solvere nodo<U+017F>am ne<U+017F>cit Medicina Podagram.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Again<U+017F>t the knotted Gout no Medicine can prevail.</p>
            <p>But even there a Cure, as to the Fit, may be obtain'd, as
well as in other Fits of the Gout; for the longer a Patient
lies under its <U+017F>everity the more the Humours of the Body
flow down, which keeps the Part more lax and weaker,
and the Patient longer confin'd, which may be prevented;
and when a Remedy to Ea<U+017F>e, by carrying tho<U+017F>e Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
away by Urine and Per<U+017F>piration, which would
crowd down upon tho<U+017F>e weakned Joints, may <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be had; for a Patient to reject it, and not to hearken
to <U+017F>uch a Remedy, <U+017F>hews his willingne<U+017F>s to retain his
Mi<U+017F>ery, and is like <U+017F>uffering an Ague to <U+017F>hake him for
a Year, or <U+017F>ome certain time, before he'll prevail'd with
to take Medicines to cure it.</p>
            <p>But the common <U+017F>aying among all being, That there's
no Cure for the Gout, makes every one's Propo<U+017F>als look
Prepo<U+017F>terous, even where there is but the bare menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning
of doing it: But if any thing I <U+017F>ay be found out
that manife<U+017F>tly carries off the Gouty Cau<U+017F>e by Urine
and Per<U+017F>piration, which would otherwi<U+017F>e flow down
to the Joints, <U+017F>o that the Patient is <U+017F>av'd from the Pain,
I fee not why any <U+017F>hould be offended, or that a Gouty
Patient would rather bear his Pain than be <U+017F>o incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous,
as not to make experiment of it, when the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the Medicine is <U+017F>uch, and the Operation <U+017F>o <U+017F>afe,
that every one that has any knowledge of things, mu<U+017F>t
allow that it cannot po<U+017F><U+017F>ible be hurtful, for that no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation
is more to advantage than by Urine and
Peripiration, and that with <U+017F>uch a Medicine as makes a
regular <U+017F>eparation by the <U+017F>trainers, by fir<U+017F>t carrying
them away <U+017F>moothly and freely throughly the Uteters,
which always of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity would have been thrown
upon the Joints and con<U+017F>equently cau<U+017F>e a Fit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Dieureticks being what all Phy<U+017F>icians allow to be
the mo<U+017F>t effectual Evacuations to dive<U+017F>t the Blood of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51771:29"/>
tho<U+017F>e peccant Salts, which, if not remov'd, would
prove injurious to the Patient.</p>
            <p>And to do this, nothing is more prevalent than the
<hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills aforemention'd, who<U+017F>e admirable Virtues
are <U+017F>uch, that tho<U+017F>e who never try'd them, will <U+017F>carce
believe; who yet after taking them, will to every one
of their Friends recommend them. Therefore to <U+017F>ay
more would be needle<U+017F>s; nothing being <U+017F>o like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
a Man of their Efficacy, as making tryal, which
is the tru<U+017F>t Te<U+017F>t; and by who<U+017F>e Succe<U+017F>s the Reputation
both of the Medicine and the Author de<U+017F>ires to depend,
and by which he is content either to <U+017F>tand or to
fall.</p>
            <p>The Pills are taken as directed in the Account be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
given of them, and that oftener or <U+017F>eldomer, as
there may be occa<U+017F>ion. And to give pre<U+017F>ent Ea<U+017F>e and
remove wholly the Pain, the Catapla<U+017F>m is to be apply'd
warm to the Part every Night and Morning, till the
Pain is quite gone, which will <U+017F>oon be.</p>
            <p>The Price of the Ingredients is Five Shillings the
Gallipot, which are to be boiled with fix Ounces of
Crumbs of White Bread and a Pint of Milk, to the
con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of a Catapla<U+017F>m, or Poultice, which is to
be <U+017F>pread upon Linnen Cloath, as thick as two
Crown Pieces put together, and applyed I <U+017F>ay as warm
as can well be borne to the Gouty Part, renewing it
very Night and Morning. The Pot of Ingredients are
to be had only at the Place aforementioned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:51771:30"/>
            <head>Electuarium Bal<U+017F>amicum:
OR,
True Bal<U+017F>amick Electuary
FOR
All manner of Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es in Women, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THIS is <U+017F>uch a wonderful Medicine that I think
it cannot be equal'd, its Vertues being <U+017F>uch
in the Di<U+017F>tempers to which it is appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,
as every one that <U+017F>hall take it mu<U+017F>t own are
not ordinary, it being a far different thing than what
by its appearance may be taken for by mo<U+017F>t, or the
Medicine makers now adays, would have it to be;
being an Electuary which has done, and (by the Ble<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
of God) will do much more benefit in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
particular Ca<U+017F>es, than any other Medicine of what
kind <U+017F>oever, numbers of both Sexes having with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
ob<U+017F>erv'd its Effects, and been cured by it, who for
many Months together have been under Cour<U+017F>es of
Phy<U+017F>ick, by Advice of Eminent Practitioners to no
purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>It infallibly and expeditiou<U+017F>ly cures Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es of
the Back in both Sexes, and all Pains of the Back
what<U+017F>oever, whether occa<U+017F>ioned from Brui<U+017F>es, Falls,
Wrenches, Strains by lifting, carrying, or by Sickne<U+017F>s
and Weakne<U+017F>s, or from Womens Mi<U+017F>carriages, Lyings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
Frights, Grief, or the like. And for Bearings down,
or falling down of the Womb, by weakne<U+017F>s or relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51771:30"/>
of the Lagaments, caus'd by hard Travel, or by
violent occa<U+017F>ions, as Blows, Falls, lifting or carrying
heavy Burdens, Over-walking, Running, or the like;
'tis a pre<U+017F>ent Remedy, by comforting, ea<U+017F>ing, healing
and <U+017F>trengthning the Parts.</p>
            <p>It effectually prevents Mi<U+017F>carriages, tho' you have
mi<U+017F>carried never <U+017F>o many times; and this it does by
<U+017F>trengthening and nouri<U+017F>hing the Womb and weak
Foetus therein; for it corrects the Blood and Humours
that affords Nouri<U+017F>hment, and if the Symptoms or
danger at any time of Mi<U+017F>carrying appears, the taking
immediately of this Electuary, certainly <U+017F>ecures you,
if not too far let alone before you begin.</p>
            <p>It wonderfully corrects and alters the heat, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
and <U+017F>harpne<U+017F>s of the Blood, which occa<U+017F>ions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate
or over-flowing of the Cour<U+017F>es of Nature, by
which many are reduc'd to a very low and dangerous
condition, and that more e<U+017F>pecially in Elderly Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
upon whom, they ought naturally to <U+017F>top, which
if neglected, and not timely remedied, will occa<U+017F>ion
Bearings down, bring the Whites, and other weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es
and <U+017F>oulne<U+017F>s of the Womb, introducing in time
Ulcers, Cancers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for prevention of which, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuary
is a mo<U+017F>t admirable Remedy, only the better
to correct and thoroughly to evacuate the vitious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
'twill be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary that you Purge twice or
thrice in the time of taking it with our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills
aforegoing</p>
            <p>And al<U+017F>o for the Whites, a Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e very trouble<U+017F>ome
and <U+017F>pending, and which mo<U+017F>t Women are incident
to, both Old and Young, but more e<U+017F>pecially Elderly
Women, after their Cour<U+017F>es have left them, or are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
to leave them, and that generally more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
for want of taking proper Medicines to <U+017F>ettle
their Bodies at the time of their Termes leaving them<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
'tis an excellent Remedy, perfecting the Cure, tho'
of never <U+017F>o many Years <U+017F>tanding, and the Patient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
by the length of time and greatne<U+017F>s of the Flux,
to <U+017F>o weak a condition as <U+017F>carcely able to go about, only
twice or thrice, in the time of taking the Electuary,
you mu<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o Purge with our Pills afore<U+017F>aid; but
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51771:31"/>
if the Whites be neglected or not timely cured, they will
bring great pain and weakne<U+017F>s in the Back and whole
Body, and occa<U+017F>ion many other dangerous Maladies,
as Cachexies, Drop<U+017F>ies, Con<U+017F>umptions, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> which may
prove fatal.</p>
            <p>Such Women therefore that have regard to their own
welfare, will have recour<U+017F>e to this Electuary at <U+017F>uch time
as the Cour<U+017F>es of Nature are about to leave them, and
not as many do, take little or no care concerning it,
notwith<U+017F>tanding Nature is always <U+017F>o kind to let them
know, that <U+017F>he wants the help of Art at that Juncture,
by their Cour<U+017F>es dodging them, and their flowing but
poorly, and <U+017F>ometimes not at all, ebbing and flowing
untimely and irregular, <U+017F>ometimes paler and thinner,
at other times in <U+017F>maller quantity and foul, which is
warning <U+017F>ufficient, that <U+017F>he <U+017F>tands in need of help, and
that they ought at that time to be <U+017F>ettled and di<U+017F>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed
after a particular manner, and not be neglected as
many Women to their Sorrow have done, who for
want of <U+017F>uch care, are now complaining of either Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour,
Flu<U+017F>hings all over the Body, the Whites in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance,
pur<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s at Stomach, lo<U+017F>s of Appetite, Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,
Faintings, or other the like Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions,
which if not timely remedied, brings
Ulcers or Cancers in the Womb, Drop<U+017F>ies, Con<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
or other fatal Di<U+017F>tempers; but Women that are
wife will in time prevent tho<U+017F>e inconveniencies, by
making u<U+017F>e of this Electuary, which will be of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>peakable
advantage; who in the time of taking it
(if Plethorick or full of Blood and not much reduc'd)
mu<U+017F>t once be let Blood, and purge with our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi>
Pills aforegoing, once, ju<U+017F>t before you begin with the
Electuary, and twice or thrice more in the time that
your are taking it, by which means they will a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly
be pre<U+017F>erved and <U+017F>ecured from tho<U+017F>e Dangers.</p>
            <p>Al<U+017F>o for <U+017F>uch Women that are afflicted with a Flux
of their Cour<U+017F>es and the Whites together, as numbers
of them are, and reduc'd extreamly low with the <U+017F>ame,
this Electuary is a Remedy that cannot be equall'd;
only for correction of Humours and the better to clean<U+017F>e
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51771:31"/>
the Womb, 'tis convenient to Purge al<U+017F>o once or twice
with our Pills aforegoing.</p>
            <p>And likewi<U+017F>e for all Loo<U+017F>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es, Bloody-fluxes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Bleedings, Bleedings at No<U+017F>e, Spitting or Vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of Blood, bloody Urine, and the like, whether
from the <U+017F>harpne<U+017F>s of the Blood, a Vein broke, Falls,
Brui<U+017F>es, or any manner of cau<U+017F>e or occa<U+017F>ion, there is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the like pre<U+017F>ent Remedy in the whole Republick of
Medicine, it retrieving in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>es, many times when
all hopes of Life have been di<U+017F>pair'd of, and di<U+017F><U+017F>olves
congeal'd or coagulated Blood remaining in any part of
the Body; tho' indeed in all tho<U+017F>e ca<U+017F>es (if <U+017F>trength
will permit) 'twill al<U+017F>o be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to Purge now and
then with our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills afore<U+017F>aid.</p>
            <p>And as this Electuary has cured many in the aforego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Di<U+017F>tempers, <U+017F>o likewi<U+017F>e has it perfectly cured <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Children and others of riper Years of incontinency
of Urine, Pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing in Bed, and the Diabetes, and that
after the continuance of the Di<U+017F>temper for <U+017F>everal Years,
and when multitudes of Medicines have been u<U+017F>ed to
no purpo<U+017F>e; and has al<U+017F>o cured <U+017F>everal Children and
others of the falling down of the Fundament and
Ruptures where the Rim or <hi>Peritonaeum</hi> has not been
broken, it being a Medicine which <U+017F>o admirably and
potently <U+017F>trengthens the inward Parts, as never to fail,
tho' <U+017F>ometimes I have been oblig'd for the better facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating
and making la<U+017F>ting the Cure, <U+017F>o as that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temper
may never return again) to exhibit our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi>
Pills (<U+017F>o often mentioned) for correcting of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
admini<U+017F>tring them in proportion to the Age and
Strength of the Patient.</p>
            <p>In fine, 'tis <U+017F>o excellent a Medicine, that it corrects
and amends all ill Vices, Weakne<U+017F><U+017F>es, Foulne<U+017F><U+017F>es and
di<U+017F>orders of the Womb, Bowels and Reins, that tend
to corrupt and de<U+017F>troy them, whether it be from any
preternatural Fluxes, or abounding of virious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and which happening upon the Womb, is
mo<U+017F>t times the cau<U+017F>e or occa<U+017F>ion of Barenne<U+017F>s, and will
(and that more e<U+017F>pecially with the u<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o of our afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aid
Pills) pre<U+017F>erve the Womb truly clean and fine, and
make it apt for Conception (as by many has been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd)
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51771:32"/>
and prevent the many Inconveniencies and
Mi<U+017F>chiefs which Women are daily complaining of;
and therefore do recommend it as one of the mo<U+017F>t
u<U+017F>eful and nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary Medicines hitherto di<U+017F>cover'd,
for the <U+017F>everal particulars occa<U+017F>ions before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Directions.</head>
               <p>TAke the quantity of a Small-Nut of it from off a
Knife's Point every Morning fa<U+017F>ting, and the <U+017F>ame
at going to Bed, drinking a Gla<U+017F>s of Tent, <hi>Alicant,</hi>
raw or burnt Claret, or Ale after it; and if your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
be very bad, then take the like quantity at
Noon, eating nothing for an Hour before or after it,
and this repeat every day till you find your <U+017F>elf cured:
And Children mu<U+017F>t take it after the <U+017F>ame manner,
only the Do<U+017F>e is to be proportion'd according to their
Age, and in every of the Ca<U+017F>es mentioned, the Pills
mu<U+017F>t occa<U+017F>ionally be exhibited as afore<U+017F>aid.</p>
               <p>It is a Cordial corroborating, and <U+017F>trengthning Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,
makes not the Stomach <U+017F>ick or unea<U+017F>ie, unle<U+017F>s
it be very weak or <U+017F>oul, nor cau<U+017F>es the lea<U+017F>t di<U+017F>order
what<U+017F>oever, but is <U+017F>o very <U+017F>afe and harmle<U+017F>s, that you
may go abroad in the taking, (if able) and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any other care or ob<U+017F>ervation than what is u<U+017F>ual;
only let your Motion and Exerci<U+017F>e be gentle, the quieter
and <U+017F>tiller you keep, the better.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:51771:32"/>
            <head>OF THE
CAUSES
OF THE
FISTULA in Ano:
OR,
The Fundament,
With its certain Cure by an Injection, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Cutting or Burning, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Cau<U+017F>es of Fi<U+017F>tula's proceed chiefly from
Plegmons and Hemorrhoids, or Piles, broken or
ill cur'd, or that are not cur'd in a long time;
as al<U+017F>o from the application of Hor<U+017F>e-leeches to the Pile<U+017F>,
which are commonly done, and not well cur'd, they
leaving <U+017F>ome Venemous Matter behind them, which in
time creates a malignant or corro<U+017F>ive Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, that
in time makes a Sinus, or Hollowne<U+017F>s, becoming, if neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,
Callous; al<U+017F>o Brui<U+017F>es or Hurts on tho<U+017F>e Parts
cau<U+017F>e Swellings and Fi<U+017F>tula's. I <U+017F>ay often tho<U+017F>e are the
cau<U+017F>es of Fi<U+017F>tula's in the Fundament; but there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Cau<U+017F>e not much taken notice of, or at lea<U+017F>t wi<U+017F>e is
what few People care to own, and that is, proceeding
from, an ill cur'd Clap, which is more frequently the
cau<U+017F>e of Fi<U+017F>tula's than any other, I having ob<U+017F>erv'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51771:33"/>
that where one Fi<U+017F>tula is occa<U+017F>ion'd by any other means,
ten proceeds from that, tho' it may be <U+017F>o many Years
after, as to give rea<U+017F>ons to the contrary, yet is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<U+017F>o; e<U+017F>pecially if the Patient had been for Cure of
that Clap in the Hands of <U+017F>ome Pretender, or was too
ha<U+017F>tily cur'd, which is what now adays, tho' very
wrongful to the Patient, mo<U+017F>t endeavour to be valu'd
upon, when a true Cure is <hi>gradatium,</hi> and ought to be
no more hudled up, than it <U+017F>hould be prolong'd, as
all true Arti<U+017F>ts in <U+017F>uch Cures well know.</p>
            <p>The Fi<U+017F>tula generally comes on gradually, its Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing at fir<U+017F>t between the Tunicles of the <hi>Inte<U+017F>tinum
Rectum,</hi> and is of a thin gleety Nature, which makes
its way out near the verge of the Fundament, through
as it were at fir<U+017F>t of a <U+017F>mall Pin-hole, and is perceiv'd
by its <U+017F>taining the Shirt or Shift of the Patient without
any Pain, and is thought (tho' mi<U+017F>takenly) to be rather
a kind of Sweating Moi<U+017F>ture than a real Fi<U+017F>tulous
Matter.</p>
            <p>But in time, if not remedied, this Humour occa<U+017F>ions
an itching, and <U+017F>ubjects the Patient to excoriation or
galling of the Part by it continual moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>harp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
of the Humour, which al<U+017F>o in longer time cau<U+017F>es
<U+017F>everal kinds of <U+017F>mall Pimples or Pu<U+017F>tles to break out;
and <U+017F>ometimes Rhagades, Fi<U+017F><U+017F>urae or Chops, which at
length cau<U+017F>es the Sinus to <U+017F>pread outwards, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity
of the Orifice to grow hard, callous and <U+017F>o
contracted, as not to admit the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing in of a <U+017F>mall
Probe.</p>
            <p>Sometimes tho<U+017F>e Fi<U+017F>tula's pa<U+017F>s deep among the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<U+017F>titia
of the Mu<U+017F>cles, according to the <U+017F>harp Matter
can make its way; <U+017F>ometimes they penetrate through
the <hi>Inte<U+017F>tinum Rectum</hi> to the very neck of the Bladder,
may, <U+017F>ometimes into the <hi>Pelvis,</hi> or among<U+017F>t the <hi>Mu<U+017F>culi
Glut<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i</hi> and other Parts, being then very painful, and
<U+017F>ends forth a purulent <U+017F>anious Matter, <U+017F>harp, ugly and
<U+017F>tinking, and that in greater or le<U+017F>s quantity, as the
hollowne<U+017F>s reaches, which in time grows very Callcus,
and makes its twi<U+017F>ting and twining like a Coney Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow,
which are the very wor<U+017F>t <U+017F>ort of Fi<U+017F>tula's.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:51771:33"/>
There are two <U+017F>orts of Fi<U+017F>tula's <hi>in Ano,</hi> one pierces
through the <hi>Inte<U+017F>tinum Rectum,</hi> or Gut, into the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament,
and the other not, and both of them are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<U+017F>hallow or deep, which you may ea<U+017F>ily come to
find out. If it pa<U+017F><U+017F>es into the Fundament, you will,
upon breaking Wind, find part of it make its way
through the Sinus of the Fi<U+017F>tula; al<U+017F>o if the Excrements
appear mingled with the Quittour of the Fi<U+017F>tula, or if
the Quittour that comes from the outer Orifice of the
Fi<U+017F>tula <U+017F>mells like the Excrements, it is a certain <U+017F>ign
it pa<U+017F><U+017F>es into the Fundament. If by injecting any Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
at the outer Orifice of the Fi<U+017F>tula, part of it pa<U+017F><U+017F>es
through into the Fundament, or if by pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing a pliable
Probe into the outer Orifice of the Fi<U+017F>tula, you can
feel the end of the Probe bare to your Finger put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Fundament, they are infallible <U+017F>igns the Fi<U+017F>tula
goes into the Fundament.</p>
            <p>As for the Pre<U+017F>ages or Progno<U+017F>ticks of Fi<U+017F>tula's,
it is allow'd by all that they are not ea<U+017F>y of Cure; for
the Parts being depending, and as it were the Sink of
the Body, <U+017F>o great plenty of Humours and Impurities,
and much <U+017F>uperfluous Moi<U+017F>ture <U+017F>lows naturally down,
and always hinders the Cure.</p>
            <p>The Curative part of Fi<U+017F>tula's, Authors tell us, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
on five means, <hi>viz.</hi> Diet, internal Medicaments,
Inci<U+017F>ion, Deligation, and Topical Applications. As
for Diet and internal Medicaments, they are what is
ab<U+017F>olutely nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, as al<U+017F>o <U+017F>ome Topical means; but
for Inci<U+017F>ion or Cutting, or applying Cau<U+017F>ticks or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<U+017F>ives,
<U+017F>o frequently now adays advis'd, and almo<U+017F>t as
frequently perform'd (but with what Succe<U+017F>s the Patients
them<U+017F>elves are be<U+017F>t able to relate) I by no means agree
to, unle<U+017F>s in <U+017F>ome particular Ca<U+017F>es, where the Patients
Life is in danger, and where no other means what<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
will avail. Such I <U+017F>ay, for to <U+017F>ave Life, cutting or
applying Cau<U+017F>ticks <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are and ought to be us'd, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o
in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>uperficial Fi<U+017F>tula's that run upwards by the
<hi>Inte<U+017F>tinum Rectum;</hi> but to make Inci<U+017F>ien in all promi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuou<U+017F>ly,
has been the ruine of many, and the one cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
which the Patient was told would be <U+017F>ufficient
for Cure, has occa<U+017F>ioned more Sinus's by the Inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51771:34"/>
and Pain, and the f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uxion of Humours thereby upon
tho<U+017F>e depending Parts, <U+017F>o that cutting again and again
has been done, to the utter <U+017F>poiling of the Patient, cau<U+017F>ing
the Fi<U+017F>tula to be inveterate, to run much, to the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating
the Body, decaying the Strength, whence lo<U+017F>s or
debilitation of Stomach en<U+017F>ues, and at length Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
cold Sweats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which brings the Fi<U+017F>tula and
whole Body into <U+017F>uch a State, as that all hopes of Cure
are pa<U+017F>t, e<U+017F>pecially if the Fi<U+017F>tula was deep, or penetrated
beyond the <hi>Mu<U+017F>culi Ani,</hi> for by cutting <U+017F>uch, if they
are cur'd, the Patients will <U+017F>carcely ever retain their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements
but with great difficulty, if no wor<U+017F>e accidents
happen; and if they reach beyond the Sphincter, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
of the excrements will be impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, <U+017F>o that
great care ought to be taken, and a Skilful Surgeon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd
with, before the Patient <U+017F>ubmits to be cut at
all.</p>
            <p>It is allow'd by all, that Fi<U+017F>tula's that are very Sinous,
and have been of long <U+017F>tanding, are dangerous and of
difficult Cure, e<U+017F>pecially if they di<U+017F>charge a large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
of Pus, and lie <U+017F>o far di<U+017F>tant, as that there is no
coming at the bottom, but the nearer they are to the
<hi>Anus,</hi> the more ea<U+017F>ie they are of Cure.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anus,</hi> or Fundament, is more <U+017F>ubject to Fi<U+017F>tula's
than any other part in the whole Body, becau<U+017F>e the
great quantity of Fat, with which the <hi>Inte<U+017F>tinum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum</hi>
is loaded, and the Evacuation of the Excrements
(this being the common Sink where all the filth of the
Body is brought down to be carried off) from its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
Humidity and numerous Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, as Branches of
the Hypoga<U+017F>trick Arteries and Veins; a Branch of the
Aorta; another of the Inferior or Me<U+017F>enterick Artery;
the Hemoirrhoidal Veins; the va<U+017F>t number of Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;
the Glands al<U+017F>o <U+017F>eperating a white Glairy Vi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous
Liquor; I <U+017F>ay tho<U+017F>e meeting there and Humours
from internal Cau<U+017F>es, whether Ob<U+017F>tructions, Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,
A<U+017F>ce<U+017F><U+017F>es, Ulcers, Piles; or external, as Blows,
Contu<U+017F>ions, impure Embraces, Falls, Leeches ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> which happening more or le<U+017F>s to meet there,
as being a Part more di<U+017F>pos'd, it is no wonder to find
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51771:34"/>
Fi<U+017F>tula's <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon form'd and <U+017F>o frequent as we ob<U+017F>erve
them to be.</p>
            <p>There are <U+017F>ome Fi<U+017F>tula's that are not noi<U+017F>ome nor ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
trouble<U+017F>ome or painful, and that <U+017F>ometimes are open
and run, at other times clo<U+017F>e, and the Patient is dry,
and thus they do for many Years without any great
inconveniency, and is what is found expedient for the
Health of the Patient; for thereby the Body is di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd
of <U+017F>uperfluous Humours, which otherwi<U+017F>e
might breed great di<U+017F>orders, and endanger the Patient's
Life. I have known many People have <U+017F>uch Fi<U+017F>tula's
which have contributed greatly to their Health, and
continued on them to the end of their Lives.</p>
            <p>But enough has been <U+017F>aid as to the Nature, Cau<U+017F>e
and Con<U+017F>equence of this trouble<U+017F>ome and oftentimes
dangerous Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition. I <U+017F>hall now come to <U+017F>peakof
its Cure, which is what was chiefly at fir<U+017F>t aim'd at,
and what I pre<U+017F>ume is by the Patient expected.</p>
            <p>I have <U+017F>aid already that cutting is not nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in all,
and <U+017F>hew'd wherein it is, and is not for the Patients
<U+017F>afety, and where it is not I <U+017F>hall recommend a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,
which if follow'd according to directions, will
be found more beneficial than many Phy<U+017F>icians and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons
will be ready or willing to believe.</p>
            <p>In the fir<U+017F>t place, the Patient is gently to purge with
the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills herein recommended, and to repeat
them oncein a Week, oftner or <U+017F>eldomer as the Body
is gro<U+017F>s, or Humours abound, but not to take too large
a Do<U+017F>e; for gentle Purging is be<U+017F>t; and he is al<U+017F>o at the
<U+017F>ame time to make the following Dyet-drink, which he
is con<U+017F>tantly to drink of till he is perfectly well; and is
this.</p>
            <p>Take Burdock Roots 8 Ounces; Elecampane Roots
3 Ounces; Tormentil and Bi<U+017F>tort Roots, of each an
Ounce; Sanicle 2 handfuls; Germander, Ground-Ivy
and Agrimony, of each 2 handfuls; Sar<U+017F>aparilla 6
Ounces; China Roots 3 Ounces; Sa<U+017F><U+017F>aphras 3 Ounces;
Guaiacum 4 Ounces; Rai<U+017F>ons of the Sun and Figs, of
each 4 Ounces, Liquori<U+017F>h 3 Ounces; boil all in 12
Pints of Lime Water, till 2 Pints are boil'd away, then
<U+017F>train it and drink half a Pint every Morning, and 4 or 5
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51771:35"/>
in the Evening, and at Night going to Bed, a little
warm'd.</p>
            <p>Upon the u<U+017F>e of this Dyet-drink, and now and then,
(but not too often) purging with the afore<U+017F>aid Pills, and
u<U+017F>ing at the <U+017F>ame time the Injection into the Fi<U+017F>tula, the
Patient will find the Cure will come on; for the Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
gently carries off the Humonrs, the Dyet-drink dries
up the <U+017F>uperfluous Moi<U+017F>ture, and nouri<U+017F>hes and <U+017F>trength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens
the Body, and the Injection, which I am now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to mention, will clean<U+017F>e and cicatrize the Fi<U+017F>tula,
that the Patient, if he continues the Cour<U+017F>e long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
which he mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>ure to do, if he expects to
be well (for tho<U+017F>e things will take up time, in <U+017F>ome
more in <U+017F>ome le<U+017F>s, according as is the Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition)
will find it to an<U+017F>wer his expectation, without the pain
and danger of cutting, which has ruin'd many.</p>
            <p>The Injection for this purpo<U+017F>e is neither corro<U+017F>ive or
will cau<U+017F>e pain; it is to be injected into the Fi<U+017F>tula eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Night and Morning warm with a Syringe, two Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes
full each time, which upon ca<U+017F>ting in, he will
find (if the Fi<U+017F>tula goes into the Fundament) to come
<U+017F>ome of it out at the Fundament; but he is not to put
the point of the Syringe into the Fi<U+017F>tula too far, but
ju<U+017F>t <U+017F>o much in, as that the Liquor will be forc'd into
the Orifice;</p>
            <p>By this means I have cur'd <U+017F>everal, and mo<U+017F>t, if
not all that u<U+017F>e the method, will have the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s;
for the Injection takes away all Callo<U+017F>ity; and
yet I <U+017F>ay, without pain, clean<U+017F>es, a<U+017F>tringes, dries up
and cicatrizes the Part, that by degrees the Fi<U+017F>tula will
clo<U+017F>e and heal up from end to end to the great plea<U+017F>ure
and <U+017F>atisfaction of the before terrify'd Patient, who
cou'd hear nothing from his Surgeon but Cutting, Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
which News is receiv'd by <U+017F>ome as unwelcome as
an <hi>Old-Baily</hi> Sentence to a Criminal.</p>
            <p>The Price of the Injection is 5s. the Bottle. To be
had only at the Place before-mentioned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:51771:35"/>
            <head>Tinctura Cephalica:
OR,
HEAD-TINCTURE.</head>
            <p>THE mo<U+017F>t incomparable and appropriated Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
that can po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly be made u<U+017F>e of for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting
and curing all Di<U+017F>tempers of the Head
and Brain, as Head-achs, Megrim, Vertigo, Epilep<U+017F>ies,
Pal<U+017F>ies, Apoplexies, Lethargies, Convul<U+017F>ions, Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ies,
Carus, Coma, trembling of the Nerves, Numb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
lo<U+017F>s of Memory, dulne<U+017F>s and heavine<U+017F>s of the Sen<U+017F>es,
Drow<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, ta<U+017F>ting and <U+017F>melling hurt, weakne<U+017F>s, glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering
or dulne<U+017F>s of the Sight, thickne<U+017F>s of Hearing,
noi<U+017F>es in the Head, beating or <U+017F>hooting Pains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
which numbers of Per<U+017F>ons are <U+017F>orely afflicted with,
and which very often <U+017F>eizes <U+017F>uch as are over thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
and <U+017F>tudious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es (among<U+017F>t the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
that afflict Mankind) being generally the mo<U+017F>t un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable,
la<U+017F>ting and dangerous.</p>
            <p>It truly and mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>tupendou<U+017F>ly repairs weak Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories,
bad Eye-<U+017F>ight and Hearing, being inwardly
taken, and outwardly made u<U+017F>e of, and <U+017F>trengthens
and pre<U+017F>erves the <U+017F>ame, removing dulne<U+017F>s, drow<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s
and heavine<U+017F>s from the Spirits and Sen<U+017F>es, rendring the
Intellectuals lively, quick and apprehen<U+017F>ive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being
peculiarly adapted to remove all Head-di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, even to
help <U+017F>uch that are craz'd, who<U+017F>e Sen<U+017F>es are almo<U+017F>t gone,
occa<U+017F>ioned from over-whelming Perplexities; for
which, and all Di<U+017F>contents, vain Fears, fooli<U+017F>h Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es
and Imaginations, which di<U+017F>compo<U+017F>e and en<U+017F>lave
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51771:36"/>
the Mind, hurry and di<U+017F>order the Spirits, thereby hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Brain, impairing the Memory, Sight, Hearing,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> it has been experienc'd, to do more than many other
Medicines of greater repute.</p>
            <p>It comforts and <U+017F>trengthens the Brain and Nerves
powerfully, refre<U+017F>hes the Sen<U+017F>itive Faculties, relieves the
Animal Spirits, being excellent al<U+017F>o in <U+017F>everal other
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Head, whether recent or inveterate;
as Stuffings of the Head, Colds, Catarrhs or defluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Rheum, whether upon, the Eyes, No<U+017F>e, Teeth,
Palate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cures the Pal<U+017F>ie of the Tongue, running
Sores or Impo<U+017F>thumes in the Ears, being admirable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t
Deafne<U+017F>s or thickne<U+017F>s of Hearing, noi<U+017F>e and pains
in the Ears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> <U+017F>wellings of the Throat, Jaws, and
the like, from a defluxion of Humours.</p>
            <p>It is a certain Remedy in the Apoplexy both for
Prevention and Cure (that Di<U+017F>temper of late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
very frequent and fatal) and will do more in
that ca<U+017F>e than any Per<U+017F>on is aware, if it be inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
taken, and outwardly us'd in the beginning of the
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and reiterated in the Intervals of time,
as nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity requires; it di<U+017F>cu<U+017F><U+017F>ing Flatulencies, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>orbing
the Acid Humour, which are many times
the original Cau<U+017F>es of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, attracting or draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
away the Morbifick Matter from the Parts affected,
de<U+017F>troying and carrying it off the right way, that the
the like can <U+017F>carcely be done by any other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <p>In the Megrim, Vertigo, Giddine<U+017F>s or Swimming in
the Head, and in the mo<U+017F>t cruel, vehement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate
Head-achs, they do wonders, taking away the
Pain in many Per<U+017F>ons in 3 or 4 minutes time, and
that with the u<U+017F>e of it inwardly taken, and a little
<U+017F>nuft up the No<U+017F>trils, and the Head, Temples,
Forehead and behind the Ears being bathed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
and that <U+017F>o perfectly, as never to return more
from that pre<U+017F>ent Cau<U+017F>e: This I can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure you upon
my own Experience; for they radically cure after all
other things have been found ineffectual, and when
the hope of Cure has been pa<U+017F>t, by removing the cau<U+017F>e
or occa<U+017F>ion thereof; without doubt in the ca<U+017F>es of an
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51771:36"/>
old and vehement Head-ach, Giddine<U+017F>s, Swimming
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> whether continual, or coming by Fits, it has no
equal in the whole World. This Tincture, and the
<hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills before mentioned, cured a Woman that
had the Head-ach from her Minority, <U+017F>o violently
<U+017F>ometimes, that it was thought <U+017F>he would be di<U+017F>tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and at all times <U+017F>o extream, as to make Life very
uncomfortable and unfit for the doing of any Bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s,
and, this was done with only two Boxes of Pills and
two Bottles of the Tincture, tho' <U+017F>he had gone through
Cour<U+017F>es of Phy<U+017F>ick, with Bli<U+017F>tering, Cupping, Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> for near 20 Years together to little or no
purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>In the Pal<U+017F>ie and Dead-Pal<U+017F>ie, as <U+017F>ome call it, it is
the greate<U+017F>t and noble<U+017F>t Medicament known; for being
taken inwardly, and al<U+017F>o u<U+017F>ed outwardly, it takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
the benumedne<U+017F>s of the Parts, and re<U+017F>tores its
Sen<U+017F>e and feeling; curing the <U+017F>haking or trembling of
the Head and Members, ari<U+017F>ing from weakne<U+017F>s and
relaxation of the Nerves, cau<U+017F>ed either by old Age or
a coldne<U+017F>s of Humours, and <U+017F>o <U+017F>trengthens tho<U+017F>e Parts
affected, that they <U+017F>eem to put new life into them
again.</p>
            <p>Nor do know, or believe there can be, any equal
to it for the Cure of the Epilep<U+017F>ie, or Falling Sickne<U+017F>s,
and that not only in Children (proceeding from Faults
of the Stomach, Wind, corrupted Food, Worms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)
but al<U+017F>o in elder Per<U+017F>ons, it having cured in both Sexes
of 20, 30 and 40 Years of Age, having done <U+017F>o great
Cures of that kind, which <U+017F>hould they be related, they
would not ea<U+017F>ily be believed, except by tho<U+017F>e who were
Eye-witne<U+017F><U+017F>es of the <U+017F>ame; and likewi<U+017F>e it cures Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion
Fits almo<U+017F>t to a Miracle; for it dige<U+017F>ts that pitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
Humour which <U+017F>o much abounds in <U+017F>uch Per<U+017F>ons,
by exciting their inward heat and <U+017F>trengthening the
Brain, which is in many Per<U+017F>ons the cau<U+017F>e of this Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e,
it <U+017F>eparating, and con<U+017F>uming in the Stomach and
Bowels tho<U+017F>e Acrid and Malign Vapours which a<U+017F>cend
to the Brain, and which by pricking with their <U+017F>harp
Points the Membranes and Nervous Filaments, excite
and induce this terrible Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:51771:37"/>
This Medicine by its <U+017F>ubtle and penetrative Particles
enter into the very <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Nerves, opens their
Pores, removes their Ob<U+017F>tructions, refre<U+017F>hes and cau<U+017F>es
a free cour<U+017F>e and circulation of the Animal Spirits, it
acuates or <U+017F>harpens all the Sen<U+017F>es, both internal and
external, facilitates and expedites the motions of the
Members thro' the whole Body.</p>
            <p>And by taking this Tincture inwardly, and u<U+017F>ing it
at the <U+017F>ame time outwardly, warms, comforts and
<U+017F>trengthens the Brain and Nerves after a very wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
manner, thereby helping the weakne<U+017F>s of the Sight,
<U+017F>trengthning the Eyes, fortifying the vi<U+017F>ive Faculties
and Nerves, and multiplies and clears the Animal and
Vi<U+017F>ive Spirits, taking away Darkne<U+017F>s, Clouds, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> which obfu<U+017F>cates the Sight, or ob<U+017F>tructs the
Optick Nerves.</p>
            <p>But during taking the Tincture in all the <U+017F>everal ca<U+017F>es
before <U+017F>poken of, it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary now and then to purge
gently with the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills aforemention'd; which,
together with the Tincture, performs after a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
manner, and proves thereby the mo<U+017F>t ab<U+017F>olute and
exqui<U+017F>ite Method that the World can afford.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Directions.</head>
               <p>TAKE of the Tincture 60, 80, or 100 Drops, more
or le<U+017F>s, as your Di<U+017F>temper requires, and that in
extremities twice, thrice or four times a Day, well
mix'd in a Gla<U+017F>s of Sack or other Wine, taking it the
fir<U+017F>t thing in the Morning, and the la<U+017F>t thing at Night,
and once or twice in the Day time at convenient
di<U+017F>tances; but if the ca<U+017F>e be not extream,6o or 80 Drops
Night and Morning will be <U+017F>ufficient, and this do
daily as well tho<U+017F>e days you take the Pills as not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any ob<U+017F>ervation as to Diet or Confinement, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
not Purging, but cures by a Specifick Property;
and <U+017F>uch as care not to take it in Wine may take
it in Ale or Beer, or in Sage or Ro<U+017F>emary Tea, but
then they mu<U+017F>t drink it off immediately, well <U+017F>tirring
it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:51771:37"/>
Al<U+017F>o in Pains of the Head, Megrim, Apoplexies,
Pal<U+017F>ies, and all other the Di<U+017F>tempers of the Brain and
Nerves for outward u<U+017F>e, pour a little of it into the
Palm of your Hand and <U+017F>nuff it up your No<U+017F>trils, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<U+017F>o twice or thrice in a day, and in extremities oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
bathing al<U+017F>o <U+017F>ome of it in with your Hand all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the Head, Neck, Forehead, Temples, upon the
Eye-brows, behind the Ears, rubbing it in without the
u<U+017F>e of any Fire; it will <U+017F>ink in almo<U+017F>t as fa<U+017F>t as you
lay it on, and will admirably comfort the Head and
Brain; <U+017F>trengthen the Sight, and perform wonderful
Cures, and that more e<U+017F>ecially, if you Purge now and
then with the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills.</p>
               <p>In the Tooth ach or Defluxions upon the Jaws, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> by holding a little in the Mouth, and <U+017F>nuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing
<U+017F>ome up the No<U+017F>trils as afore<U+017F>aid, 'tis a pre<U+017F>ent
help, and by dropping a few Drops into the Ears
twice in a Day, putting in a little Cotton or Wool
dipt in the <U+017F>ame a little warm'd, 'twill be an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
Remedy in Pains of the Ears, Deafne<U+017F>s,
Noi<U+017F>e, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Virtues of the <U+017F>aid <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Pills and Tincture in
one other particular Di<U+017F>temper, I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of, their Effects being <U+017F>o very remarkable; and that
is, in the mo<U+017F>t violent and extream Collicks or racking
griping Pains of the Bowels and Stomach, even when
the Patient hath been at the point of Death, rolling,
tumbling about and roaring out with Pain, as if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tracted;
four of the Pills being taken, and 100 or 150
Drops, or more, of the Tincture mix'd in a Gla<U+017F>s of
Sack or White Wine hot or mull'd, drank immediately
after them, gives in<U+017F>tant Ea<U+017F>e, even upon the <U+017F>pot,
when Gly<U+017F>ters and all other Medicines have been ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual,
and comforts and heals the Bowels <U+017F>o, that the
Patient in half an Hours time after, is as if nothing
had ailed him; they being of great power to <U+017F>uppre<U+017F>s
Wind and Humours that fly upwards, by which may
be <U+017F>een their Excellency in defending the Head from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious
Fumes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which <U+017F>o frequently indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>e
it; and al<U+017F>o 50 or 60 Drops of the Tincture taken
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51771:38"/>
twice a Day in a little White Wine, gives immediate
Ea<U+017F>e in After-pains to Lying-in Women, it bing a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicince
of clean<U+017F>ing, <U+017F>afe and <U+017F>trengthening Properties.</p>
               <p>A few Drops <U+017F>nufft up the No<U+017F>e, ea<U+017F>es the
mo<U+017F>t violent Pains thereof in a Moment, and that
without <U+017F>neezing or endangering Cold; and for that
very u<U+017F>e, it is <U+017F>carcely to be expre<U+017F>s'd the wonderful
and in<U+017F>tant Ea<U+017F>e it gives; for no <U+017F>ooner is it <U+017F>nufft
up the No<U+017F>e, but the Pain is gone, tho' before it was
never <U+017F>o intollerable, and by continuing, prevents its
return, having cur'd old inveterate Head-achs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Years <U+017F>tanding, in an in<U+017F>tant, which long cour<U+017F>es
of Phy<U+017F>ick were not able to do.</p>
               <p>The Price of this Tincture is Three Shillings and
Six Pence the Bottle, to be had only at the Place
before-mentioned.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:51771:38"/>
            <head>THE
Bal<U+017F>amick Re<U+017F>torative
ELIXIR
FOR
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Lungs, whether Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umptions,
A<U+017F>tma's, Phty<U+017F>icks, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>BEING a wonderful rich and plea<U+017F>ant Medicine
of <U+017F>tupendious Effects, it admirably <U+017F>trengthens
the Lungs, being the very Life or Bal<U+017F>am thereof,
clean<U+017F>ing the Pipes of tough foul Spittings, thickned
by a preternatural Heat, helps <U+017F>hortne<U+017F>s of Breath,
ea<U+017F>es and remedies Coughs, tho' never <U+017F>o violent and
perplexing, all A<U+017F>thmatick Stoppages of the Lungs,
Hoar<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s, Di<U+017F>tillations or Defluxious of Rheum, all
Whee<U+017F>ings, <U+017F>traitne<U+017F>s of the Che<U+017F>t, not to be reach by
Syrups, Oils, Licks, Slops, or Lozenges, which oftend
the Stomach and feed the unnatural Fire; it comforts
Nature, nouri<U+017F>hes and enriches the Blood, chears the
Heart, recreats and revives the Spirits and Vitals,
tho' never <U+017F>o low and drooping, being an exceeding ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
Cordial; it takes off your <U+017F>pending, faint, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu<U+017F>e
Night-<U+017F>weats, <U+017F>trikes at the root or cau<U+017F>e of all
Con<U+017F>umptions, and <U+017F>o re<U+017F>tores and renews the whole
habit of Body and Blood, as that in the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>pending
and langui<U+017F>hing Ca<U+017F>es, even when the Patient is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
to a pining emaciated Condition, contributes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51771:39"/>
more towards the Cure, than it is po<U+017F><U+017F>ible for any other
<U+017F>ingle Medicine to do; and is a Specifick Cure for
Hooping and Chin-coughs in Children.</p>
            <p>And for weakly and Con<U+017F>umptive People, who<U+017F>e
Lungs are Ulcerated, <U+017F>pitting up foul, purulent, bloody
Matter, with tedious hollow Coughs, Hectick Fever,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis an admirable thing, it <U+017F>upporting the Body
wonderfully; and will be found much more prevalent
and re<U+017F>toring in all Cafes of the Lungs, if it be taken
4 or 5 times in a Day, 2 or 3 Di<U+017F>hes at a time, in Tea
made of Ground-Ivy and Liquori<U+017F>h, two handfuls of
the former and two Ounces of the latter to a Quart of
boiling Water, <U+017F>weetned with Sugar-Candy: And if
at any time the Body be pur<U+017F>y or <U+017F>topt up, or the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach
be foul, and Dige<U+017F>tion bad, or are hot and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tive
Bodied, it may be al<U+017F>o convenient (if Strength
will permit) to take now and then a Do<U+017F>e of our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gli<U+017F>h</hi>
Pills aforementioned, of who<U+017F>e Vertues in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umptive
Habits you may read in its place.</p>
            <p>A certain Woman, among others, was cured with
this Elixir of an inveterate pineing and wa<U+017F>ting, <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
to be an incurable Con<U+017F>umption, and that after
two Years de<U+017F>pair, when <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o weak <U+017F>he could
not <U+017F>tand without two to hold her, looking like (as it
were) the Picture of Death, and given over as pa<U+017F>t all
hopes by <U+017F>everal very able and learned Men, the alone
taking of this Medicine in Sack or Milk, and <U+017F>ometimes in
Ale <U+017F>weetned, but mo<U+017F>t commonly in Milk, Morning,
Noon and Night, and in Extremities of Faintings, &amp;c.
oftner, continuing the <U+017F>ame for about 5 or 6 Weeks time,
re<U+017F>tored her through the Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing of God, to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of all that knew her, and in all probability will
perform the <U+017F>ame in others, when greater Remedies and
Methods may be ineffectual.</p>
            <p>You will find it <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly rai<U+017F>e your Spirits, and give
Relief after a little while taking it, and will correct
and de<U+017F>troy every irregular Humour in the Body, and
prevent Con<U+017F>umptious beyond any thing known;
twill a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t Nature in all her declinings and decays, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
when the radical Moi<U+017F>ture is con<U+017F>uming, and the
Vital flame almo<U+017F>t <U+017F>pent or worn out, provided the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51771:39"/>
Lungs them<U+017F>elves, Liver, &amp;c. be not putrify'd, for
then no Medicine can repair tho<U+017F>e Ruines, or make
new Vi<U+017F>cera when the old are peri<U+017F>h'd, tho' it has
performed marvellous Cures in Ca<U+017F>es that have
been <U+017F>o reported, which are too tedious here to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions.</head>
               <p>TAKE 30 Drops of it every Morning; the <U+017F>ame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o
an hour after Dinner, and at Night going to
Bed, mixt in a <U+017F>mall Gla<U+017F>s of good Canary, old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laga,
the Tea aforemention'd, Milk, or any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Liquor: And Children may take half that quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
or in proportion to their Age, and thus continue it
for one, two, or three Months together, as you <U+017F>ee oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ion,
without any other ob<U+017F>ervation.</p>
               <p>The Price is Three Shillings and Six Pence a Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
to be had only at the Place aformentioned.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:51771:40"/>
            <head>AN
Engli<U+017F>h Vegetable
For all Sorts of
AGUES.</head>
            <p>THERE are divers <U+017F>orts of Agues, which are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h'd
according to the difference there is
in their intermi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, &amp;c. Some are Quotidian
Agues, or Simple Quotidian, that come daily, and
that not with vehemen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cold at the fir<U+017F>t, but cold and
colder by degrees, nor is the hot Fit very exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive: The
Thir<U+017F>t in <U+017F>uch is but <U+017F>mall, the Urine white or thin,
and watery, or thick and troubled; and the hot Fit
generally la<U+017F>ts eighteen Hours, and <U+017F>ometimes with
Vomiting of Phlegm. The<U+017F>e Fits oftentimes <U+017F>eize the
Patient in the Night-time, and is frequently dangerous,
becau<U+017F>e its continuance being long, is more <U+017F>ubject to
degenerate into a Cachexie, Drop<U+017F>y or Lethargy.
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> <U+017F>ays, That it is more dangerous if it comes
in the Day-time, than if it comes in the Night. It is
the Stomach that is for the mo<U+017F>t part afflicted in the<U+017F>e
Agues, becau<U+017F>e, as <U+017F>aid before, the Patient in the Fit
is <U+017F>ometimes inclin'd to Vomit, which when done,
gives relief.</p>
            <p>Others are double Quotidian Agues, or eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Day Agues, returning twice in Twenty-four
Hours, with Coldne<U+017F>s of the extream Parts; but there
is went to be no <U+017F>hivering Fit, or but very little; the
Symptoms are otherwi<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ame as in the Simple
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51771:40"/>
Quotidian afore <U+017F>poken of, and caus'd al<U+017F>o chiefly from
the Stomach, but reduplicate and <U+017F>tronger, holding
commonly longer and more tedious, unle<U+017F>s <U+017F>ome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
Critical Evacuation intervene; and as the Cau<U+017F>es
are reduplicate, <U+017F>o do they <U+017F>hew more danger than the
Simple Quotidian; and if it continues long, does rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
fail degenerating into <U+017F>ome other chronick and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and more particularly into a Drop<U+017F>y.</p>
            <p>Others are Tertian Agues, or Agues of the third Day,
and comes with vehement cold or rigorous <U+017F>haking Fit,
as tho' the Patient were pricked, follow'd with a hot
Fit and other Symptoms; the Pul<U+017F>e is equal, and anon
a violent heat increa<U+017F>eth, with great Thir<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
vomiting of Choler, with reddi<U+017F>h Urine; giving
the Patient very great unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, dreading every Fit,
which oftetimes is more than other, <U+017F>hifting as to times,
keeping no periodical Paroxi<U+017F>ms, but comes <U+017F>o uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
that the Patient knows not in that Day what
time to expect it. The <U+017F>haking coldne<U+017F>s at fir<U+017F>t com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
is vehement and <U+017F>harp, the heat and burning in
the hot Fit is al<U+017F>o violent and <U+017F>trong, <U+017F>preading it <U+017F>elf
over the whole Body in the heigtht of the Fit; and
towards the end of the hot Fit, the whole Body is in
a gentle Sweat. The<U+017F>e <U+017F>ort of Agues holding not above
the fourth Fit, other times not above the <U+017F>eventh, each
Fit holding not above Twelve Hours, and is without
much danger, unle<U+017F>s Malignity be joyn'd with it;
and if breakings out on the Lips, Scabs or a Loo<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s
happens, it is very healthful, becau<U+017F>e they are critical,
tho' the<U+017F>e are Malign and Pe<U+017F>tilential Tertians, which,
tho' they have evident Intermi<U+017F><U+017F>ions as the others, yet
do often kill the Patient; be<U+017F>ides, many accidents may
fall in upon a Tertian Ague, <U+017F>uch as a Surfeit, violent
Cold, &amp;c. which may breed danger, tho' the Ague
may have none of it <U+017F>elf.</p>
            <p>Other Agues there are called Semi-tertian, which
whether they be exqui<U+017F>ite, that is, where Choler and
Phlegm equally abound, vexing the Patient continually,
but the third Day with a <U+017F>haking Fit, or Spurious,
wherein either Choler or Phlegm mo<U+017F>t abounds; if the
fir<U+017F>t, repre<U+017F>ent chiefly a Tertian, if the latter, a Quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51771:41"/>
of which we have <U+017F>poken before; yet the<U+017F>e cau<U+017F>e
no great Thir<U+017F>t or Burning, but <U+017F>ometimes is attended
with an inflamation of <U+017F>ome Vi<U+017F>cera, or Bowels, as
Stomach, Liver, Spleen, or Parts adjacent, which is
caus'd when the Feveri<U+017F>h Matter is carried thither with
the Blood. The Semiter-tian Ague, both exqui<U+017F>ite and
<U+017F>purious (for they differ chiefly in degree) are both
dangerous, becau<U+017F>e thereby the Stomach and Nervous
Parts are very much affected, and is attended with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t
a continuil burning Fever; but e<U+017F>pecially the
exqui<U+017F>ite, being there is a dryne<U+017F>s of the Tongue, Thir<U+017F>t,
Swooning, Watching, and <U+017F>ometimes raving and dead
Sleep, and is what <hi>Hippocrates</hi> account among<U+017F>t acute
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and continues long; <hi>Avicen</hi> <U+017F>ays <U+017F>even
Months, and at la<U+017F>t ends frequently in a Hectick.</p>
            <p>There is al<U+017F>o the double Tertian Ague, which comes
once or twice a Day, two Days together, leaving the
Patient free one Day between. Some Authors menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
a triple Tertian, where there are three Fits in two
Days, and one Day clear between; but is reckon'd to be
<U+017F>eldom <U+017F>een, and le<U+017F>s ea<U+017F>ie to be di<U+017F>cover'd by a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ician,
tho' he had <hi>Argus</hi>'s Eyes. The<U+017F>e Agues are
chiefly of Humours gather'd together in the Liver, Gall,
Stomach, Me<U+017F>entery, Pancreas, or in the Veins of tho<U+017F>e
Parts. In this Ague it is a hard Matter to get a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
time for the giving Medicine to Cure, becau<U+017F>e
oftentimes there is no long; <U+017F>pace beetween the two Fits;
for <U+017F>ometimes the Fits hold <U+017F>o long, that the one begins
before the other is ended, being thereby much more
dangerous than a Semi-tertian, becau<U+017F>e it comes from a
reduplication of the Cau<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>The next is the Quarian Ague, or Ague that comes
every fourth Day, and is accompanied with vehement
Cold<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> as if it would nip and break the Bones; the Pulle
is flow in the beginning of the Fit, and afterwards the
Melancholly Humour by little and little is inflam'd,
whence comes a burning or hot Fit; the Urine is white,
thin and watery, with two Days intermi<U+017F><U+017F>ion each Fit;
and when the Fit is coming, it cau<U+017F>es reachings and
yawning, with a <U+017F>haking Fit: at fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>mall, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
extream, yet not <U+017F>o much pricking, as rendring the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51771:41"/>
Patient as if he were beat or brui<U+017F>el; the Cau<U+017F>e is
from Melancholly and adult Humours, known by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying
the Appetite, cau<U+017F>ing great Chir<U+017F>ts, and Head
and Back ach. The<U+017F>e <U+017F>ort of Agues are of all of them,
of longe<U+017F>t continuance, handling a Patient <U+017F>ometimes
half a Year or a Year, or if it happen in the fall of the
Leaf, two Years or longer; and is <U+017F>ometimes dangerous,
e<U+017F>pecially if it degenerates into a continual Quartan,
or happens to afflict People of Sixty Years of Age or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</p>
            <p>There is al<U+017F>o the Compound Quartan Ague, which
is either double or triple: in the double, the Fit leaves
the Patient two Days free, and comes the next two
Days; in the triple, the Paroxi<U+017F>m returns three Days
together, leaving two Days free after them, as in a
Quotidian and double Tertian; the<U+017F>e come of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly.
Putrifying in divers parts of the Body, and are
dangerous, if not in time cured, being el<U+017F>e apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
into chronick, inveterate and incurable Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es,
and that becau<U+017F>e the Fit <U+017F>o often returns; it ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates
and wa<U+017F>tes the Body exceedingly, con<U+017F>uming the
radical Moi<U+017F>ture, depre<U+017F><U+017F>ing the Spirits, ob<U+017F>tructing the
Natural, Vital and Animal Functions, and at la<U+017F>t
brings the Body into an incurable Hectick, Con<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
or Drop<U+017F>y: But if the Ague be taken in time,
and it happens to a young <U+017F>trong Per<U+017F>on, and proper
Medicines be exhibited, there may be no great doubt of
a Cure; but if it happens to an old Per<U+017F>on, who is
weak of Nature, and that in the Winter al<U+017F>o, it is de<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate,
and if cannot <U+017F>oon be got off, but contiues
long, will prove Mortal.</p>
            <p>Thus have I run through the Nature and Cau<U+017F>es of
the di<U+017F>tinct <U+017F>orts of Agues, and which, as all Authors
ob<U+017F>erve, are generally to be cured by the <U+017F>ame Cla<U+017F>s of
Medicines, only regarding the Strength and Con<U+017F>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Patient.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Vegetable and Plai<U+017F>ters, at fir<U+017F>t menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,
<U+017F>eldom or never fail, if us'd together, to cure
the mo<U+017F>t inveterate and chronick <U+017F>ort, provided they
both be made u<U+017F>e of in time, before Nature is too
much depre<U+017F>s'd by the <U+017F>everity of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and yet
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51771:42"/>
even in People that were Young, and not Old,
they have effected the Cure, which before had baffled
Je<U+017F>uits Powder, the Bitters, Alteratives, &amp;c. And
in tho<U+017F>e Agues of late <U+017F>tanding, the Vegetable alone
has cured without the Plai<U+017F>ter, and in <U+017F>ome the Plai<U+017F>ter
without the Vegetable; but where the Ca<U+017F>e is <U+017F>evere,
to expedite the Cure, I generally u<U+017F>e both; but <U+017F>ome,
(e<U+017F>pecially Children) cannot be gotten to take any
inward Medicine at all, and there the applying the
Plai<U+017F>ters mo<U+017F>t commonly does, only mu<U+017F>t be renewed
more times than there would be occa<U+017F>ion, if the Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
was taken al<U+017F>o at the <U+017F>ame time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions for taking the Vegetable Powder,
and applying the Plai<U+017F>ters.</head>
               <p>A Man or Woman may take a whole Paper at a
time, which mu<U+017F>t always be taken in a Gla<U+017F>s of
hot Wine, an Hour or two before the Fit, and be
cover'd up warm; whereupon it will cau<U+017F>e in <U+017F>ome
gentle Vomiting and Sweat, in others only Sweat, in
others will only work by Urine, but which way <U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
it operates, it never falls <U+017F>hort of expectation, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
almo<U+017F>t all Agues without u<U+017F>ing any thing el<U+017F>e;
but where the Ca<U+017F>e is inveterate, and has been of long
<U+017F>tanding, we are forc'd to apply the Plai<U+017F>ters al<U+017F>o,
which I <U+017F>hall by and by give Directions about.</p>
               <p>One of 12 or 15 Years of Age, may take two thirds
of a Paper: tho<U+017F>e of younger Years in proportion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
giving it in Wine as before directed; and is to
be repeated to every one for 5 or 6 times, more or le<U+017F>s,
as the Ague is <U+017F>evere, or has been of longer or <U+017F>horter
continuance, tho' not one Ague in twenty requires its
being taken above three times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> There is no occa<U+017F>ion to drink any thing with
it, more than the few Spoonfuls of Wine, ju<U+017F>t to mix
it and make it drinkable, which may be White Wine
or any other Wine, proportioning the quantity, as the
Patient is either a grown Per<U+017F>on or Child. A grown
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51771:42"/>
Per<U+017F>on taking it in 6 or 8 Spoonfuls, and always as hot
as it can be well drank.</p>
               <p>The Plai<U+017F>ters to the Wri<U+017F>ts, mu<U+017F>t be prepared and
applyed thus: To all the Powder in the Box and the
whole Yolk of a new laid Egg, which mix and beat
up well together in a Mortar or Porringer <gap reason="illegible" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
rating them well together, adding <U+017F>o much <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc><…></desc>
                  </gap>
and <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t Vineger as will be <U+017F>ufficient to make it
into <U+017F>uch a con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tency as <hi>Venice</hi> Treacle is; then <U+017F>pread
it pretty thick upon a Linnen Cloth of 2 or 3 Inches
broad for a grown Per<U+017F>on, but narrower for Children,
which apply upon the Pul<U+017F>es of both Wri<U+017F>ts, tying them
on, <U+017F>o as not to come off, where they mu<U+017F>t remain
without changing them, for nine Days, becau<U+017F>e this
Remedy exerts its vertues but by degrees. And it
ought to be applyed an Hour or half an Hour before
the Fit comes, and if the Ague be not cur'd in nine
Days, to be laid on afre<U+017F>h.</p>
               <p>The Price of the Vegetable Powder is <hi>2s. 6d.</hi> a
Paper, and the Box of Powder for Plai<U+017F>ters is 3 <hi>s. 6d.</hi>
both to be had at the Place afore-mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The<U+017F>e Plai<U+017F>ters to the Wri<U+017F>ts frequently, I may <U+017F>ay
generally, Cure all forts of Agues (unle<U+017F>s they be of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
long <U+017F>tanding indeed, and attended with other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions)
without any inward Medicine at all, but
where there is a complication of Infirmities, be<U+017F>ides the
Ague, that the Stomach is foul and Blood injur'd, there
is a nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity for an inward Medicine, than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can exceed the Vegetable Powder before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,
and will do a hundred times more Service, and
is a thou<U+017F>and times more <U+017F>afer than Je<U+017F>uits Bark, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other Medicine what<U+017F>oever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:51771:43"/>
            <head>Hydragogue Tincture:
OR,
DROPS,
Purging away Water, thereby curing
Drop<U+017F>ies of all <U+017F>orts.</head>
            <p>BEFORE I <U+017F>peak of the excellent Vertues of the<U+017F>e
Drops, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething of the <U+017F>everal <U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
of Drop<U+017F>ies, which, as they affect diver<U+017F>ly,
so go under divers appellations, as the <hi>A<U+017F>cites, Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panites</hi>
and <hi>Ana<U+017F>arca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>A<U+017F>cites,</hi> or <hi>Hydrops Abdominis,</hi> is in <hi>Engli<U+017F>h,</hi> the
Watery Drop<U+017F>y in the Belly, and is always attended
with a <U+017F>tretching of the Belly, by rea<U+017F>on of the <U+017F>uper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding
of ferous, watery and <U+017F>alt Humours, ca<U+017F>t
forth into the capacity of the Abdomen, through fault
of the Liver, Spleen and Reins, cau<U+017F>ing al<U+017F>o the Feet,
Thigh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and in Men <U+017F>ometimes the Cods to <U+017F>well, and
is known by the <U+017F>welling of the Belly, a difficulty of
Breathing, and the hoar<U+017F>e <U+017F>ound of the Belly if <U+017F>truck,
like as if a Bladder half full was <U+017F>truck upon; al<U+017F>o up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
compre<U+017F><U+017F>ing the Belly with the Fingers, it pits and
leaves the print of them thereon; and if the Patient
turns from <U+017F>ide to <U+017F>ide, a Noi<U+017F>e like the murmuring or
waving of Water is heard, and the Water by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance
there, will in time putrify and corrupt the
Bowele, cau<U+017F>e a Fever and Thir<U+017F>t, and wa<U+017F>te the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51771:43"/>
Strength and Spirits: Therefore all imaginable
care ought to be taken to evacuate the Water in time,
both by Stool and Urine, or el<U+017F>e the Patient will
dye; and if let alone <U+017F>o long as that the Patient's
Strength be <U+017F>pent, not being able to bear Purging
Medicines; then Tapping mu<U+017F>t be u<U+017F>ed, as the only
pre<U+017F>ent way to <U+017F>ecure the Patient, if that Method will
do it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tympanites,</hi> or Windy Drop<U+017F>y, <U+017F>hews it <U+017F>elf
al<U+017F>o by a di<U+017F>tention or <U+017F>tretching of the Belly; but as
the other contains Water within the capacity of the
Abdomen, this contains only Wind, which <U+017F>o di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tends
the Belly, that it being <U+017F>truck upon with the
Hand, <U+017F>ounds like a Drum, and is rather more <U+017F>well'd
than the watery Drop<U+017F>ies, and the Navel hangs out,
but will not leave any impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion upon pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing it
with the Fingers; the Patient is mo<U+017F>t afflicted with
Pain about the Navel and Loins in Windy Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ies
like a Cholick, when there is no <U+017F>uch Pain in a
watery one, and is ea<U+017F>ier to be cured, and of le<U+017F>s
danger.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ana<U+017F>arca,</hi> or <hi>Leucophlegmatia,</hi> is a Drop<U+017F>y of
the whole Habit of the Body, the Water being di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<U+017F>ed,
<U+017F>o that all the Fle<U+017F>h appears moi<U+017F>t, <U+017F>woln and
wet, wherein not only the Hands, Arms; Brea<U+017F>t, Face,
Thighs, Legs and Feet <U+017F>well, but the whole Body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o,
whereby, if you make a pre<U+017F><U+017F>ure with your Finger
into the Fle<U+017F>h in any part, it will pit and leave an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p>The cau<U+017F>e of this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is chiefly Cold, or by very
plentifully drinking cold Water, or Small Beer, or
el<U+017F>e proceeds from a defect of the Liver, or defect of
Natural Heat, Ob<U+017F>tructions and imbicility of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
from whence a collection of pituitous and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
Humours is produced, and univer<U+017F>al Cachexy.</p>
            <p>If this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e be recent, and in a young Per<U+017F>on,
it is not difficult to cure: In Per<U+017F>ons aged, it is very
doubtful, if not de<U+017F>perate<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and indeed <U+017F>uch as are
much in Years <U+017F>eldom find a Cure for it: But yet the
Vertues of the Hydragogue Tincture are <U+017F>uch, as that
it has cured <U+017F>everal Elderly People by being follow'd for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51771:44"/>
<U+017F>ome continuance, which they mu<U+017F>t, tho' it is what
<U+017F>ome will not be prevail'd upon to do, being <U+017F>oon wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of the be<U+017F>t of Medicines, if <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey find not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
Relief, when the continuance of the Medicine
would to all appearance have cured them: Therefore
it is advi<U+017F>ed, that all People that have the Drop<U+017F>y, or
are Drop<U+017F>ically inclin'd, take the Drops con<U+017F>tantly as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,
and then a Cure may be expected.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions for the taking of the Hydragogue
Tincture.</head>
               <p>THE Patient is to take from 15 to 20, 30, 40, 50
or 60 Drops, more or le<U+017F>s, as they operate by
Urine or Stool, taking them always in White Wine,
wherein Mu<U+017F>tard Seed or Hor<U+017F>e-radi<U+017F>h Roots have been
<U+017F>teeped; but if they purge much, a le<U+017F>s Do<U+017F>e mu<U+017F>t be
taken; if they do not purge at all, a greater Do<U+017F>e;
and will al<U+017F>o work by Urine plentifully, tho' at the
fir<U+017F>t taking them they may <U+017F>eem to give frequent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions
to Urine, and but little come; but after a little
waiting the Urine will come plentifully, and the Patient
be reliev'd. They are to be taken every Night and
Morning, and al<U+017F>o in the middle of the Day, if there
be occa<U+017F>ion.</p>
               <p>The Price is 3 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi> the Bottle. To be had only at
the Place before mentioned.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:51771:44"/>
            <head>The mo<U+017F>t Famous
Eye-Powder &amp; Water
IN THE
WORLD.</head>
            <p>THE Eye is a tender part, and is <U+017F>oon injur'd by
extraneous Bodies, as al<U+017F>o by Humours flowing
upon them from within the Body; and as tho<U+017F>e
injure them one way, <U+017F>o oftentimes does wrong Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
the other, nay, make the Ca<U+017F>e more de<U+017F>perate, <U+017F>o
that the Remedy proves wor<U+017F>e than the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, whence
comes Cataracts and Blindne<U+017F>s; for many People
grow dim-<U+017F>ighted and dark by Humours upon the Eyes,
which at length breed Spots, Films, Skins, Clouds,
Webs, and the like, which grow over the Sight, the
fore-runners of which are Atoms, Flys, Gnats, H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irs,
Threads, &amp;c. flying or <U+017F>wimming before them, and
which if not remedied in time, increa<U+017F>e to Cataracts,
the couching of which <U+017F>ometimes cures, but oftner <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot
nay, frequently ruins the Sight for ever, as many can
too truly Witne<U+017F>s; now the<U+017F>e Spots, Films, Skins, etc.
tho' <U+017F>aid by Oculi<U+017F>ts to be incurable but by Couching;
they telling their Patients they mu<U+017F>t wait till they come
to ripe Cataracts to be couch'd, are to be cur'd without,
even tho' grown to ripe Cataracts, and that by blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a little of a <U+017F>afe Powder, and u<U+017F>ing a Water into
the Eyes, the continual u<U+017F>ing of which will <U+017F>often and
wear a way gradually that Skinny or filmy Sub<U+017F>tance,
which is a Humour congeal'd; and di<U+017F><U+017F>olves and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forbs
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51771:45"/>
the gro<U+017F>s vi<U+017F>cid Humours that <U+017F>upplies and gives
ri<U+017F>e to tho<U+017F>e Films, &amp;c. to the perfect re<U+017F>toration of the
Sight, whereby not one in a hundred that u<U+017F>es it, would
ever <U+017F>tand in need of being couch'd, or would ever have
their Sight impair'd or injur'd by Humours, Spots, Skins,
Films, or the like; but to the contrary, keep off Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
clears and <U+017F>trengthens the Sight, that all that once
u<U+017F>e them, will recommend to all they know; for they
are <U+017F>uch innocent Medicines, as that they may be taken
inwardly, and have done <U+017F>uch notable Cures, as are to
be wonder'd at, even in all <U+017F>orts of Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions of the
Eyes, whether they before, running, hot or inflam'd,
and that when Purgings, Bleedings, Bli<U+017F>terings, Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings,
I<U+017F><U+017F>ues and Seatons have been us'd to no purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions for u<U+017F>ing the Eye Powder and
Water.</head>
               <p>IF the Eyes be very <U+017F>ore, tender, <U+017F>well'd, hot or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd,
the Water alone will be <U+017F>ufficient, without
the Powder, wa<U+017F>hing with it 2, 3 or 4 times a Day or
oftener, as there may be occa<U+017F>ion, but if there be no
Humour, but Spots, Films, Skins or the like, there the
Powder mu<U+017F>t be u<U+017F>ed al<U+017F>o, a little of it being to be blown
into the Eyes 3 or 4 times a Day, daily, till well, and
the Eyes to be wa<U+017F>h'd an Hour after it with the Water;
but if the Powder or Water <U+017F>hould occa<U+017F>ion any <U+017F>mart,
as in weak tender Eyes they may (tho' without the lea<U+017F>t
injury) then it is to be u<U+017F>ed <U+017F>eldomer, and then they
will be bearable. It is admirable to find how they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
clear and <U+017F>trengthen the Sight, and remove all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
Spots, Films, &amp;c. that darken, or obfu<U+017F>cate the
Sight; and if People that have weak tender Eyes, and
are fearful of Cataracts or Blindne<U+017F>s, the u<U+017F>e of it in
time will prevent any <U+017F>uch bad Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, or dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
or weakne<U+017F>s of Sight.</p>
               <p>The Price of the Powder is <hi>2s. 6d.</hi> the Paper, the
Water <hi>3s. 6d.</hi> both to be had at the Place before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
and no where el<U+017F>e.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:51771:45"/>
            <head>THE
CARMINATIVE:
OR,
Wind Expelling
LOZENGES.</head>
            <p>THE mo<U+017F>t famous Medicine for the expelling of
Wind, ever known, they keep the Wind out
of the Stomach, if one of them be held in the
Mouth in a Morning or any other time in the Day,
and are more ready and much more whole<U+017F>ome, as well
as beneficial, than Cordial Drams; for the<U+017F>e break a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
the Wind pent up in the Stomach and Bowels,
and <U+017F>trengthen them, creating an Appetite, and not
de<U+017F>troying it as Drams do; be<U+017F>ides, they keep the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<U+017F>o <U+017F>olutive, as tho<U+017F>e that take them will never be
co<U+017F>tive; but always open. In the Cholick, Gripes,
Stitches in the Sides, Windy Vapours that oppre<U+017F>s the
Head, <U+017F>owr Belchings, Hiccups, &amp;c. they are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;
if taken after Eating, they cau<U+017F>e good Dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tion,
and rectify all Indige<U+017F>tions and Di<U+017F>orders of the
Stomach; purifying the Blood, curing Heart-burn,
making the Breath <U+017F>weet, and do render the whole
Body and Mind, chearful, light<U+017F>ome and ea<U+017F>y; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
really a pretty nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary Companion, in ca<U+017F>e of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51771:46"/>
ill Scents, bad Air, &amp;c. and <U+017F>o delightful and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ant
to the Ta<U+017F>te, as well well as helpful to the
health, that none that once try them, will ever be
without them.</p>
            <p>It is only putting one of them into the Mouth at
a time, and <U+017F>wallowing it as it di<U+017F><U+017F>olves, and <U+017F>o do
as often in a Day as you plea<U+017F>e. The Price is Two
Shillings and Six Pence a Box, which will la<U+017F>t a
long time, and are only to be had at the Place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:51771:46"/>
            <head>A
BALSAM
To Make
ISSUES Run;
Which is al<U+017F>o good to clean<U+017F>e old
Sores, Ulcers, Wounds, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THIS Medicine is fit and nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for all
Families, on the acccout of Hurts, Sores,
Wounds, Ulcers, &amp;c. as for the making I<U+017F><U+017F>ues
run; for if a little of it be <U+017F>pread upon Linit or Tow,
and applied to the Sore Place, it wonderfully clean<U+017F>es
it, that a little Diachylon Plai<U+017F>ter afterwards will be
<U+017F>ufficient to heal it. But for to make I<U+017F><U+017F>ues run, it is
not to be parallell'd, removing all Inflamations about
them, taking away proud Fle<U+017F>h, and cau<U+017F>ing the Pea to
keep in, and this only by <U+017F>mearing <U+017F>ome of it all round
the Orifice, and moi<U+017F>tning the Pea with it, putting it
in, and doing it <U+017F>o every time the I<U+017F><U+017F>ue is dre<U+017F>t, which
is once a Day, that being <U+017F>ufficient, and applying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
it Oil Cloth or Plai<U+017F>ter, as u<U+017F>ual. But if there be
much proud Fle<U+017F>h, you may anoint that with it twice
a Day, but if not much, once a Day will be <U+017F>ufficient.
It is indeed an excellent thing to keep I<U+017F><U+017F>ues ea<U+017F>y, <U+017F>weet <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc><1… pages missing></desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

