<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Experiments and considerations about the porosity of bodies in two essays / by the honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12547275</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12547275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A28974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 955:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Experiments and considerations about the porosity of bodies in two essays / by the honourable Robert Boyle ...</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 145 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chemistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Porosity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physiology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXPERIMENTS AND Con<U+017F>iderations ABOUT THE Poro<U+017F>ity of Bodies, IN TWO ESSAYS.</p>
            <p>By the Honourable ROBERT BOYLE, Fellow of the Royal Society.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is to be adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis'd, not to expect in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing E<U+017F><U+017F>ay a Regular, or <U+017F>o much as a Coherent, Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. For it was intended only as a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of loo<U+017F>e Experiments and Ob<U+017F>ervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the Poro<U+017F>ity of the parts of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies belonging as Chymi<U+017F>ts <U+017F>peak) to the Animal Kingdom, and laid (not to <U+017F>ay thrown (together, in order to what I had thoughts of offering, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Intelligible account of Occult Qualities. I am not ignorant, that even one of the mo<U+017F>t ancient and famous of Phy<U+017F>icians hath <U+017F>aid, that a mans body is
<pb facs="tcp:63097:3"/>
(almo<U+017F>t) every where per<U+017F>pirable. But I judg'd that a Doctrine of <U+017F>uch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and which diver<U+017F>e things in the Theory and Practice of after Phy<U+017F>icians may make one think they either disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved or di<U+017F>regarded, did not de<U+017F>erve to be <U+017F>lightly deliver'd, and in general terms, but to be more narrowly con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and likewi<U+017F>e made out by Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar In<U+017F>tances, who<U+017F>e applyablene<U+017F>s and u<U+017F>efulne<U+017F>s to explain divers ob<U+017F>cure <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> may hereafter appear much greater, then perchance at the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight they will be thought.</p>
            <p>And the foregoing adverti<U+017F>ement, with a light change, which 'tis pre<U+017F>um'd the Reader may ea<U+017F>ily make of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf, is to be extended to the E<U+017F><U+017F>ay tacked to this <hi>about the Pores of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Bodies,</hi> and <U+017F>o may excu<U+017F>e the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence of a di<U+017F>tinct Preface to it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63097:3"/>
            <head>An E<U+017F><U+017F>ay of the POROUSNESS OF ANIMAL BODIES.</head>
            <p>AS the mo<U+017F>t numerous part of the Pores of Bodies is too minute to be <U+017F>een, <U+017F>o the Contemplation of them has been thought too incon<U+017F>iderable to be regarded. But when I con<U+017F>ider, how much mo<U+017F>t of the Qualities of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and con<U+017F>equently their operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons depend upon the <U+017F>tructure of their minute, and <U+017F>ingly invi<U+017F>ible, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and that to this latent contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g> bigne<U+017F>s the figure and the collocation of the Intervals and Pores
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63097:4"/>
do nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily concur with the Size, Shape and Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition or contrivance of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantial parts I cannot but think the Doctrine of the <U+017F>mall Pores of Bodies, of no <U+017F>mall importance to Natural Philo<U+017F>ophy. And I <U+017F>carce doubt, but if <U+017F>uch little things had not e<U+017F>caped the <U+017F>ight of our Illu<U+017F>trious <hi>Verulam,</hi> he would have afforded a good Porology (if I may <U+017F>o call it) a place, (and perhaps not the lowe<U+017F>t nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) among his <hi>De<U+017F>iderata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>though</hi> other imployments and avocations hinder me from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to treat of this <U+017F>ubject as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and particularly as it de<U+017F>erveth, or even as I had de<U+017F>ign'd in a Scheme drawn diver<U+017F>e years <U+017F>ince, and <U+017F>een by <U+017F>ome <hi>Virtuo<U+017F>i; Yet,</hi> not to leave apart of Phy<U+017F>icks, that <U+017F>eems to me <U+017F>o curious and important, altogether as unculti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated as I found it; I <U+017F>hall pre<U+017F>ent you as many of the Notes I had drawn together about this <U+017F>ubject, as I can conveniently (for I do not pretend to do it methodically) reduced to three heads: Whereof the fir<U+017F>t, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63097:4"/>
will challenge to it <U+017F>elf this pre<U+017F>ent e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ay, is the <hi>poro<U+017F>ity of Animal Bodies,</hi> about which I <U+017F>hall not be <U+017F>olicitous to mar<U+017F>hal my ob<U+017F>ervations, <U+017F>ince they all con<U+017F>pire to <U+017F>hew but this one thing; That the parts of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, e<U+017F>pecially while<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, are furni<U+017F>hed with numerous Pores.</p>
            <p>Tho<U+017F>e parts of the Bodies of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, wherein their poro<U+017F>ity may be be<U+017F>t <U+017F>hewn <U+017F>eem to be their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes or Skins, the Bones, the Fle<U+017F>h, and Coagmentations of Membranes, Fle<U+017F>h and Juices. And therefore it would be proper enough to treat of the<U+017F>e Heads di<U+017F>tinctly, and give In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances of each of them in particular. But yet I think it will be more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to <U+017F>et down in order the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Fountains, whence the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances belonging to the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Kingdom (as the Chymi<U+017F>ts <U+017F>peak) may be derived, and to annex to each of the<U+017F>e the Experiments and ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, upon which I argue from it, and which it will be ea<U+017F>y to refer, if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63097:5"/>
that be thought fit, to this or that of the parts above mentioned (namely the Membranes, Bones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) whereto they <U+017F>hall (re<U+017F>pectively) appear the mo<U+017F>t properly to belong.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THe fir<U+017F>t thing from which I will deduce the Poro<U+017F>ity we have been <U+017F>peaking of, is, the Frame or Con<U+017F>titution of the <U+017F>table Parts of the Bodies of Animals. For the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of an Animal being not a rude and indige<U+017F>ted lump of matter, but a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous engine, admirably framed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived for the exerci<U+017F>e of <U+017F>everal Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as Nutrition, Generation, Sen<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many differing local Motions, it was nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary that it <U+017F>hould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>hed with variety of Di<U+017F><U+017F>imilar and Organical parts not only very Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but very differingly, contrived congruous to the <U+017F>everal u<U+017F>es for which they were de<U+017F>igned, or if you plea<U+017F>e, to the <U+017F>everal Functions they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63097:5"/>
were to perform. And, becau<U+017F>e 'twill be ea<U+017F>ily granted, that the Corpu<U+017F>cles, that are skilfully brought together for <U+017F>uch purpo<U+017F>es, mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>o contexed as not to touch one another exactly every where, it will readily follow that they mu<U+017F>t leave little Intervals or Pores between them, and that, con<U+017F>idering the multitude of particles that mu<U+017F>t go to the making up the Body of the Animal, and the great difference and variety in point of bigne<U+017F>s and figure of the Corpu<U+017F>cles that are requi<U+017F>ite to contex <U+017F>uch differing parts, as Membranes, Fibres Bones, Grizles, Ligaments, Veins, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terys, Nerves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Both the number and the variety of the Pores cannot but be very great. This argument will be much confirmed, by what there will be occa<U+017F>ion to <U+017F>ay further to the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e, in the E<U+017F><U+017F>ay touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poro<U+017F>ity of even Solid Bodies. Wherefore I <U+017F>hall now proceed to the Second thing, whence we may derive that of Animal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63097:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THis is afforded us by con<U+017F>ider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nutrition of Animals. For there being continually a great wa<U+017F>te made of their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, partly by the exclu<U+017F>ion of vi<U+017F>ible excrements, and partly by the avolation of invi<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <U+017F>team, this great lo<U+017F>s mu<U+017F>t ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>arily from time to time be repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by the <U+017F>upplies afforded by Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of which the be<U+017F>t, if not the only Intelligible, way of giving an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is, to conceive that the alimental Juice, prepared chiefly in the Stomach is impelled or attracted (for to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e it matters not which) to the parts of the Body that are to be nouri<U+017F>hed by it, and the Corpu<U+017F>cles of the juice in<U+017F>inuate them<U+017F>elves at tho<U+017F>e Pores they find commen<U+017F>urate to their Bigne<U+017F>s, and Shape; and tho<U+017F>e that are mu<U+017F>t congruous, being a<U+017F><U+017F>imilated, add to the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the part wherein
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63097:6"/>
they <U+017F>ettle, and <U+017F>o make amends for the Con<U+017F>umption of tho<U+017F>e that were lo<U+017F>t by that part before. This may be illu<U+017F>trated by what happens in Plants, and e<U+017F>pecially Trees, in which, of the various Corpu<U+017F>cles that are to be found in the liquors, that moi<U+017F>ten the Earth, and are agitated by the heat of the Sun and the Air, tho<U+017F>e that happen to be commen<U+017F>urate to the Pores of the Root, are by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention impelled into it, or imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by it, and thence conveyed to the other parts of the Tree in the form of Sap which pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing through new <U+017F>trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, (whereby its Corpu<U+017F>cles are <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, and prepared or fitted to be detained in <U+017F>everal parts) receives the alterations requi<U+017F>ite to the being turned into Wood, Bark, Leaves, Blo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>oms, Fruit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to return to Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, our argument from their Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be much confirmed, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>idering, that in Children and in other young Animals, that have not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their due Stature and Bulk, the Nutrition is <U+017F>o copious as to amount
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63097:7"/>
to a continu'd Augmentation. For, as 'tis evident that Animals grow in all their parts, and each part according to all its Dimen<U+017F>ions, in <U+017F>o much that even the cavities of Bones increa<U+017F>e; <U+017F>o we cannot well conceive how this can be done, unle<U+017F>s the Nutritive liquor be di<U+017F>tributed through the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the part that is to be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<U+017F>hed and augmented. And to this di<U+017F>tribution 'tis requi<U+017F>ite that the Body abound with Pores into which the congruous particles of the Juice may be intimatly admitted, &amp; penetrating even into the innermo<U+017F>t rece<U+017F><U+017F>es, may place or lodge them<U+017F>elves in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that is mo<U+017F>t convenient for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Increa<U+017F>e of the part. But the more particular Declaration of this Proce<U+017F>s I leave to Anatomi<U+017F>ts and Phy<U+017F>icians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving premis'd once for all, that in this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay, I often u<U+017F>e the word Skin in the lax and popular <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63097:7"/>
without nicely di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>hing the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermis</hi> or <hi>Cuticula,</hi> called in Engli<U+017F>h the <hi>Scarf-skin,</hi> from the <hi>Cutis</hi> it inve<U+017F>ts and <U+017F>ticks clo<U+017F>ely to; I <U+017F>hall proceed to another Topic, whence the Porou<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of Animals may be argued, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the great plenty of matter that is daily carried off by Sweat, and in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Tran<U+017F>piration. For, 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t that Sweat is di<U+017F>charged at the Pores of the skin; and <U+017F>ince there is no penetration of Dimen<U+017F>ions, we may <U+017F>afely conclude, that the matter that is not wa<U+017F>ted by Sweat, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible way of evacuation, mu<U+017F>t have <U+017F>mall Pores or out-lets in the Skin, at which it may i<U+017F><U+017F>ue in the form of <U+017F>teams; though nothing hinders but that invi<U+017F>ible <hi>Effluvia</hi> al<U+017F>o may evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate at the <U+017F>ame Pores with the Sweat, though for want of plenty or gro<U+017F><U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, or a fit di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition in the ambient, tho<U+017F>e Effluvia be not at the Orifices of tho<U+017F>e Pores brought into little Drops, <U+017F>uch as tho<U+017F>e of <U+017F>weat.</p>
               <p>That therefore the Skins of a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Animals, though they <U+017F>eem
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63097:8"/>
clo<U+017F>e to the eye, may be porous, may (as we have been <U+017F>aying) be argued in many of them from their <U+017F>weating. But becau<U+017F>e all of them have not been ob<U+017F>erved to <U+017F>weat, as is wont to be particularly affirmed of Dogs, we <U+017F>hall add <U+017F>ome other In<U+017F>tances to make it probable.</p>
               <p>We may <U+017F>ometimes, in the <U+017F>mooth skin of a living man, di<U+017F>cern Pores with good Micro<U+017F>copes, and, with one that is none of the be<U+017F>t, we may ea<U+017F>ily on the in<U+017F>ide of gloves, which are made but of skins dre<U+017F>t, di<U+017F>cern good <U+017F>tore of the<U+017F>e little out-lets: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times orderly enough ranged to make the <U+017F>ight not unplea<U+017F>ant. And though <U+017F>ome of them may, I think, be <U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pected to have been made by the Hairs that grew on the skin before 'twas dre<U+017F>t, yet that greater numbers of them, than can be <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed to come from thence, are perforations that pa<U+017F>s quite through the Leather, may, not improbably, be <U+017F>hewn by the u<U+017F>ual Practice of Chymi<U+017F>ts, to purify Quick-<U+017F>ilver by tying it up <U+017F>trictly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63097:8"/>
in a piece of kids or <U+017F>heeps Leather, and then wringing it hard to force it out; by which means the lower <U+017F>urface of the Leather will be covered with a Mercurial Dew or Sweat which will fall down and fly out, as the Pores happen to open this or that way, in a thick <U+017F>hower of globules, leaving the dro<U+017F>s behind in the Leather. And tho when a mans skin is tanned it is of a greater thickne<U+017F>s then one would expect, and that which I employed <U+017F>eem'd almo<U+017F>t as thick as a Buck-skin Glove yet having had the curio<U+017F>ity to try the <U+017F>ame Experiment with the skin of a mans Arm, I found the Quick-Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would be <U+017F>queez'd out at the Pores of that al<U+017F>o. 'Tis not nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary that I <U+017F>hould here inquire, whether the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle holes, unperceiv'd by the naked Eye, at which the Sweat is di<U+017F>charged, and perhaps the matter that the Body loo<U+017F>es by in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible tran<U+017F>piration gets out, be not, at lea<U+017F>t mo<U+017F>t of them, the Orifices of <U+017F>mall excretory ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, belonging to tho<U+017F>e very numerous glandules which the excellent Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>ts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63097:9"/>
                  <hi>Steno and Malpighi</hi> are <U+017F>aid to have di<U+017F>covered beneath the <hi>Cuticula,</hi> and which for their <U+017F>malne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>hape have been called <hi>Glandulae miliares.</hi> I need not, I <U+017F>ay, engage in this inquiry, <U+017F>ince according to this ingenious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion al<U+017F>o, the Skin mu<U+017F>t be allow'd a multitude of <U+017F>mall Perforations or Pores, and that is <U+017F>ufficient for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, from whence<U+017F>oever this Poro<U+017F>ity proceeds in a mans Skin. For the next ob<U+017F>ervation will <U+017F>hew that <U+017F>ome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of Animals may give pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to tran<U+017F>pir'd matter without being perfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the excretou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules.</p>
               <p>The Membranes or Skins under the <U+017F>hells of Hens Eggs, though they be very thin, are of a Contexture very fine and clo<U+017F>e as may be confirmed by their re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting the <U+017F>harp Corpu<U+017F>cles of Vinegar; and yet, that not only the<U+017F>e Skins, but the <U+017F>hells that cover them, are porous, may be inferred from the Experiments I made, of keeping them <U+017F>u<U+017F>pended for a good while, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully counterpoi<U+017F>ed in good <U+017F>cales;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63097:9"/>
for by the<U+017F>e it appeared, that the Eggs did from time to time manife<U+017F>tly lo<U+017F>e in weight; which could not rea<U+017F>onably be imputed but to an invi<U+017F>ible Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>piration, the rather, becau<U+017F>e u<U+017F>ually in eggs that have been kept long, there will be at one end a cavity which is wont to increa<U+017F>e with their age, and is made by the <U+017F>hrinking of the Membrane from the Shell, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate it <U+017F>elf to the dimini<U+017F>hed quantity of matter, that remains to be involved by it.</p>
               <p>When I con<U+017F>ider the plenty of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is wont to be di<U+017F>charged dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Per<U+017F>piration, e<U+017F>pecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Healthful men that exerci<U+017F>e them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves moderately, I cannot but think it probable, that the minute Pores, that <U+017F>uffice for the carrying off <U+017F>o much matter, are very numerous, and are much more <U+017F>o than even by the multitude of drops of <U+017F>weat, that <U+017F>erve to wet the skin, men are wont to imagine. For <hi>Sanctorius</hi> in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent little Tract <hi>de Medicina <U+017F>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> affirms, that what is barely car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63097:10"/>
off by in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible tran<U+017F>piration does ordinarily amount to more, that is, dimini<U+017F>hes more the weight of a mans Body, than all the vi<U+017F>ible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements (whether gro<U+017F>s or liquid) put together. <hi>Aph. vi.</hi> He adds, If the meat and Drink, taken in one day, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the weight of eight pound, the in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Tran<U+017F>piration ordinarily amounts to five pounds or thereabouts. And el<U+017F>ewhere <U+017F>ays, that <U+017F>ometimes in the <U+017F>pace of 24 hours, in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time, a healthy Body may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale fifty ounces or more. And <U+017F>ome Tryals, that I have carefully made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my <U+017F>elf, added to <U+017F>ome others of a very curious as well as great Prince, that made u<U+017F>e of a like in<U+017F>trument, &amp; did me the honour to acquaint me with the events, gave me no cau<U+017F>e to reject <hi>Sanctorius</hi> ob<U+017F>ervations, con<U+017F>idering the difference in point of heat, between the climate of <hi>Italy,</hi> where he writ, and that of <hi>England,</hi> where ours were made; only I fear, there has been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted an over<U+017F>ight by tho<U+017F>e many that a<U+017F>cribe all the decrement of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63097:10"/>
weight, that is not referrable to the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er Excrements, to what tran<U+017F>pires at the Pores of the vi<U+017F>ible parts of the skin, without taking notice of that great plenty of <U+017F>teams that is in expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations di<U+017F>charged through the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe by the Lungs, and appear manife<U+017F>t to the Eye it <U+017F>elf in fro<U+017F>ty weather; though they may be pre<U+017F>umed to be then le<U+017F>s copious than tho<U+017F>e Invi<U+017F>ible ones that are emitted in Summer, when the ambient Air is much war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But <hi>though</hi> I look upon the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe as the great Chimney of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in compari<U+017F>on of tho<U+017F>e little Chimneys (if I may <U+017F>o call them) in the Skin, at which the matter that is wa<U+017F>ted by per<U+017F>piration is emitted, <hi>yet</hi> the number of the<U+017F>e little vents is <U+017F>o very great, that the fuliginous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations that <U+017F>teal out at them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be very con<U+017F>iderable. Be<U+017F>ides that, tho<U+017F>e that are di<U+017F>charged at the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria,</hi> do probably, at lea<U+017F>t for the mo<U+017F>t part, i<U+017F><U+017F>ue out at the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Pores of the Membranes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<U+017F>t the Lungs; which membranes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63097:11"/>
may be lookt upon as external parts of the Body, in reference to the air, tho not in reference to our <U+017F>ight. But, to return to our Eggs, we may <U+017F>afely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a very great evacuation to be made at the Pores of the skin in man, who is a <U+017F>anguineous and hot Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, <U+017F>ince we <U+017F>ee that even Eggs, that are <U+017F>till actually cold, tran<U+017F>pire. And I el<U+017F>ewhere mention the copious tran<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration even of Frogs, that are always cold to the touch; and the Decrement in weight of <U+017F>ome Animals, <U+017F>oon after they are <U+017F>trangled or <U+017F>uffocated, when, their vital Heat being extinct, no more fumes are emitted by expirations at the wind-Pipe: To which <U+017F>igns may be added the trivial experiment of holding in warm weather the palp of ones Finger, as near as one can without contact, to <U+017F>ome cold &amp; <U+017F>olid <U+017F>mooth body, as to a piece of poli<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Steel or Silver; for you will often times <U+017F>ee this Body pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>ullyed or overca<U+017F>t, with the invi<U+017F>ible <U+017F>teams that i<U+017F><U+017F>ue out of the Pores of the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and are by the cold and <U+017F>mooth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63097:11"/>
<U+017F>urface of the Body conden<U+017F>ed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vi<U+017F>ible <U+017F>teams, that do as 'twere cloud that <U+017F>urface, but upon the Removal of the Finger, quickly fly off, and leave it bright again.</p>
               <p>The Perviou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the skin out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards may not improbably be argued from the quickne<U+017F>s wherewith <U+017F>ome Medicines take away <U+017F>ome black and blew Di<U+017F>colorations of the skin, that happen upon <U+017F>ome lighter <U+017F>troke, or other contu<U+017F>ions. For, <U+017F>ince the<U+017F>e pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural and un<U+017F>ightly colours are wont by Phy<U+017F>icians to be imputed to <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall portions of blood, that upon the contu<U+017F>ion is forced out of the capillary ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that lye beneath the <U+017F>urface of it, &amp; being extrava<U+017F>ated are obliged to <U+017F>tagnate there; it <U+017F>eems very likely, that if a powerful Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine do quickly remove the di<U+017F>colora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that work is performed by attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, and di<U+017F><U+017F>olving, and agitating the matter, and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ing it to tran<U+017F>pire through the cutaneous Pores, though perhaps, when 'tis thus changed, <U+017F>ome part of it may be imbibed again by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63097:12"/>
the Capillary Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and <U+017F>o by the circulation carryed into the ma<U+017F>s of Blood. Now, that there are Medicines that will <U+017F>peedily work upon <U+017F>uch black and blew marks, the Books and Practice of Phy<U+017F>icians and Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will oblige us to admit. <hi>Helmont</hi> talks much of the great vertue of white Briony root in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>es. And a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Experiment made a while ago by a Learned acquaintance of mine in an odd ca<U+017F>e, did not give <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> the Lye. And I know an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Per<U+017F>on, who having <U+017F>ome while <U+017F>ince received a <U+017F>troke, by a kick of an Hor<U+017F>e, on his Leg, a very threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning contu<U+017F>ion, which made the part look black and frightful, he was in a few hours cured of the pain of the hurt, and freed from the black part of the Di<U+017F>coloration by the bare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the chopt leaves of Hi<U+017F><U+017F>op mixt with fre<U+017F>h Butter into the form of a Pulte<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>Nor is it only the Skin that covers the vi<U+017F>ible parts of the Body that we judg to be thus porous, but in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63097:12"/>
that inve<U+017F>t the internal parts, we may rea<U+017F>onably <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e both nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and very various Pores, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the exigency of their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and different Functions or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For, the two fir<U+017F>t cau<U+017F>es of Poro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity mention'd in this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay, are as well applicable to the Membranes that cover the internal parts, as the Liver, the Spleen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Skin, or Membrane that covers the Limbs; and in <U+017F>ome re<U+017F>pects the tran<U+017F>piration through <U+017F>uch Pores <U+017F>eems more advantaged, than that through the Pores of the <U+017F>urface of the Body; <U+017F>ince the parts that environ the Spleen, Liver, Kidneys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in man, are hot in compari<U+017F>on of the ambient Air, and being al<U+017F>o wet, which the Air is not, the laxity of the Pores of the internal parts is doubly befriended. And perhaps it may be allowable to conceive, both the Skin that covers the Limbs, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes that inve<U+017F>t the internal parts of the Body, to be like wor<U+017F>ted <U+017F>tock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Wa<U+017F>t-Coats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which in their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63097:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63097:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63097:14"/>
ordinary <U+017F>tate have a kind of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, but upon occa<U+017F>ion can have their Pores every way enlarged and <U+017F>tretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in this or that manner, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents that work on them determine them to be. This may be confirmed, by what we manife<U+017F>tly <U+017F>ee in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <U+017F>ort of leather, as that of Kid or Lamb, and by the latent Pores that may be opened in Sheeps-Leather, and mans Leather, by the pre<U+017F><U+017F>ure of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Quick-Silver.</p>
               <p>This Poro<U+017F>ity of a living mans Skin and other Membranes, though inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ones, will the more ea<U+017F>ily be a<U+017F><U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to if it appear that <U+017F>uch thick and gro<U+017F>s Membranes, as the urinary blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of dead Animals, are Porous and Penetrable even by Water. This we tryed, by putting <U+017F>ome <U+017F>alt of Tartar in a clean well dryed bladder (which ought to be afterwards tyed up clo<U+017F>e in the neck, le<U+017F>t the effect <U+017F>hould be a<U+017F>cribed to the moi<U+017F>t Air) and leaving the lower part of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as far as the Salt, reached immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed in common Water, who<U+017F>e parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63097:14"/>
by degrees in<U+017F>inuated them<U+017F>elves into the Pores of the bladder, in plenty enough to re<U+017F>olve the Salt of Tartar into a liquor. And, that it may not be <U+017F>aid that the Acrimony of the Salt, by fretting the bladder, made way for the Corpu<U+017F>cles of the Water, I <U+017F>hall add that the Experiment <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, but much more <U+017F>lowly, when we tryed it with Sugar in<U+017F>tead of Salt of Tartar. And there are <U+017F>ome, who pretend that certain Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups made this <U+017F>lovenly way, which they would have pa<U+017F>s for a <U+017F>ecret, are very much preferable to tho<U+017F>e made of common Water.</p>
               <p>That the films that line the <U+017F>hells of Eggs are of a very clo<U+017F>e Contexture <U+017F>eems probable, as by other things, <U+017F>o by their re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting <U+017F>ome liquors, <U+017F>harp enough to corrode the <U+017F>hell, and yet that <U+017F>uch Membranes are pervious to Liquors that are none of the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile of all, we found by the en<U+017F>uing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. This was made by taking an ordinary Hens Egg, and keeping it for two or three days in di<U+017F>till'd Vinegar,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63097:15"/>
or in <U+017F>trong crude Vinegar. For then taking it out of the Liquor and wiping it well, it was vi<U+017F>ibly, and not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderably, <U+017F>well'd, which I concluded to be from the ingre<U+017F>s of <U+017F>ome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the liquors, at the Pores of the Skins that inve<U+017F>t the White of the Egg. For we found nothing broken, though we made the Tryal more than once. And to be <U+017F>atisfied that the manife<U+017F>t expan<U+017F>ion proceeded from <U+017F>ome other cau<U+017F>e, than the meer dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the White, or Yolk, or both, we compared the weight of the Egg, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was taken out and well wiped, with that which had been taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas put into the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> and found the Egg, notwith<U+017F>tanding the lo<U+017F>s of the Shell, to be con<U+017F>iderably heavier than 'twas before its immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion.</p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hall add on this occa<U+017F>ion that by a more unlikely way than that newly recited, both the Egg, Shell and Lining of an Egg, may be penetrated. For, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding the fine and clo<U+017F>e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of the Membranes that inve<U+017F>t
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63097:15"/>
the Eggs, the <hi>Chine<U+017F>es</hi> have a way of Salting them in the <U+017F>hell, as I have been a<U+017F><U+017F>ured both by Engli<U+017F>h and Dutch Merchants trading to the Ea<U+017F>t <hi>Indies.</hi> And in one of the Dutch Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals <U+017F>ent by the Council of <hi>Batavia</hi> to their Principals in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted by an Engli<U+017F>h man of War, I met with divers accounts of great numbers of <U+017F>alted Eggs, that were <U+017F>uch or <U+017F>uch a day of <U+017F>uch a Month brought in by Sea to <hi>Batavia</hi> or other Ports. Long after which time, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an ingenious Phy<U+017F>ician, that liv'd in <hi>Batavia,</hi> I learned by enquiry from him, that 'tis very true that <U+017F>uch Eggs are frequently met with in tho<U+017F>e parts; he having divers times eaten of them there: <U+017F>ome that he judged to have been either boyled or roa<U+017F>ted, before they were <U+017F>alted; and others that were raw, when they came to be dre<U+017F><U+017F>ed for him, but yet retained a Briny ta<U+017F>t. And, though the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants I enquired of could not tell me what way the <hi>Chine<U+017F>es</hi> employed to Salt their Eggs, without making them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63097:16"/>
unfit for common u<U+017F>e, yet by a tryal made with clay and Brine, in which I kept the Eggs for a competent time, I was per<U+017F>waded that 'twas po<U+017F><U+017F>ible the <hi>Chine<U+017F>es</hi> <U+017F>hould have the Art a<U+017F>cribed to them. For upon the breaking of an Egg coated with clay, after it had lain for a competent time in Brine, I found its Ta<U+017F>t con<U+017F>iderably Salt, but was, by I know not what accident, hindered from pro<U+017F>ecuting the Experiment, and endeavouring to make it more practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and u<U+017F>eful.</p>
               <p>I knew a Phy<U+017F>itian of more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning than vertue, who, being tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a violent and ob<U+017F>tinate Colic of a peculiar kind, was wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him<U+017F>elf by Cli<U+017F>ters of Sack; thô he u<U+017F>ually found that not long after he had taken any of them, they would make him giddy, and fuddle him, as he him<U+017F>elf confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed to me. But upon this In<U+017F>tance I lay not much weight, and le<U+017F>s upon what was an<U+017F>wered me by a great Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, who having practi<U+017F>ed his Art in the <hi>We<U+017F>t-Indies,</hi> and being asked
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63097:16"/>
by me whether he had not dre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Wounds and Ulcers with the recent juice of Tobacco (a plant I u<U+017F>e to keep growing in my Garden for its excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues in cuts, burns, and tumors;) and whether, if he employed it, he did not find it emetick, he told me among other things, that having Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times dre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with this Juice a <U+017F>mall Ulcer in a Womans leg, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <U+017F>oon after the application would grow <U+017F>ick, and have her <U+017F>tomack tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or actually vomit. But, as I was <U+017F>aying, on this in<U+017F>tance I lay no <U+017F>tre<U+017F>s, becau<U+017F>e the Corpu<U+017F>cles of the Tobacco might probably enough get in at the <U+017F>mall Orifices of <U+017F>ome corroded Ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els, and <U+017F>o be conveyed inwards, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the help of the Circulation of the blood, than on the account of the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the Parts. And therefore I <U+017F>hall rather mention what has been related to me, by an eminent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ician of the famous Colledge of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> namely, that he had divers times given him<U+017F>elf a vomit, by a certain application of decocted Tobacco to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63097:17"/>
his wri<U+017F>ts, and <U+017F>ome other external parts; which brings into my mind, what is affirmed to have been ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <U+017F>ome Children that have <U+017F>cabb'd Heads, who have been made Drunk, by the application of Clothes or <U+017F>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wetted in Infu<U+017F>ion of Tobacco, or of <U+017F>trong Liquors, and applied to the part affected. Though in this ca<U+017F>e the inebriating Particles may be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected to have got in, not at the meer Pores, but rather at the Orifices of the Capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, that were made acce<U+017F><U+017F>ible by <U+017F>uch little <U+017F>olutions of Continui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as are <U+017F>eldom wanting in <U+017F>cabbed Heads.</p>
               <p>That Children may be purged by outward applications is a<U+017F><U+017F>erted by <U+017F>ome Phy<U+017F>icians; and an experienced Per<U+017F>on of that number has affirmed to me, that he can almo<U+017F>t con<U+017F>tantly do it by a Plai<U+017F>ter. But 'tis more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable what was related to me by an eminent <hi>Virtuo<U+017F>o,</hi> who being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to believe <U+017F>uch things a while before he told me the <U+017F>tory, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ired by a curious Per<U+017F>on to <U+017F>hew him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63097:17"/>
his Hand which the Relator having done the other took it in his hand, which was moi<U+017F>tened (as was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed) with a kind of <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Chymical Oil, but <U+017F>o <U+017F>lightly, that the Relator <U+017F>carce minded it, till <U+017F>ome time after when he found him<U+017F>elf pre<U+017F>t with a motion, like that which a purge would have given him; for the other thereupon <U+017F>miling, my acquaintance began to <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect what the matter might be, and was in a <U+017F>hort time purged four times, without griping, or other pain or di<U+017F>compo<U+017F>ure. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Membranes, it may <U+017F>erve to make way for your admitting it, to ob<U+017F>erve, that <hi>though</hi> Lute-<U+017F>trings be but Ropes of Fibres (which are at lea<U+017F>t the chief parts that Membranes con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t of) dead, cold and <U+017F>tiff, <hi>yet</hi> when the lute is in tune they will <U+017F>ometimes in wet weather <U+017F>well <U+017F>o forcibly as with noi<U+017F>e and violence to break, which proceeds from the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ingre<U+017F>s of moi<U+017F>t vapors into their Pores, whereby they are not only <U+017F>hortened, but as I have tryed in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63097:18"/>
nice <U+017F>cales, made manife<U+017F>tly heavier.</p>
               <p>The Poro<U+017F>ity of the internal parts of Animals by both the foremention'd ways (<hi>viz.</hi> of emi<U+017F><U+017F>ion and reception of Corpu<U+017F>cles,) may be confirmed by the things that happen in <U+017F>ome of the <hi>Meta<U+017F>ta<U+017F>es</hi> or Tran<U+017F>lations (as the Phy<U+017F>itians call them) of the morbifick matter in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed Bodies. 'Tis known to them that are any thing conver<U+017F>ant with Ho<U+017F>pitals, or the ob<U+017F>ervations of Phy<U+017F>icians, that there do not <U+017F>eldom occur in Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>udden Removes of the matter that cau<U+017F>ed them, from one part to another according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and functions of which, there may emerge a new Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, more or le<U+017F>s dangerous than the former, as the invaded part is more or le<U+017F>s noble. Thus oftentimes the matter, which in the <U+017F>anguiferous Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els produced a Feaver, being di<U+017F>charged upon <U+017F>ome internal parts of the Head, produces a <hi>Delirium</hi> or <hi>Phrenitis</hi>; in the latter of which I have <U+017F>omewhat wondered, to <U+017F>ee the Patients Water <U+017F>o like that of a Per<U+017F>on without a Feaver; the <U+017F>ame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63097:18"/>
Febrile matter either by a deviation of Nature, or medicines improper or unskillfully given, is di<U+017F>charged <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the <hi>Pleura,</hi> or Membrane that lines the <U+017F>ides of the Che<U+017F>t; <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the throat; <U+017F>ometimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Guts; and cau<U+017F>es in the fir<U+017F>t ca<U+017F>e a Pleuri<U+017F>ie, in the 2d a Squinancy, and in the third a Flux, for the mo<U+017F>t part dy<U+017F>enterical. But, becau<U+017F>e I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, that many, if not mo<U+017F>t, of the<U+017F>e tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of peccant humors, are made by the help of the circulation of the Blood, I forbore at the beginning of this Section to <U+017F>peak in <hi>general terms,</hi> when I mentioned them in reference to the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the internal parts of the Body, and contented my <U+017F>elf to intimate, that <hi><U+017F>ome</hi> of them may <U+017F>erve to confirm that Poro<U+017F>ity.</p>
               <p>This will not perhaps <U+017F>eem impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if we con<U+017F>ider that 'tis in effect already proved, by the <U+017F>ame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which we have <U+017F>hewn, that both the Skin and the internal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes are furni<U+017F>hed with Pores, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meable by Particles who<U+017F>e Shape and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63097:19"/>
Size are corre<U+017F>pondent to them. For we may thence probably deduce, that when a morbifick matter, whether in the form of Liquor, or of exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, chances to have Corpu<U+017F>cles <U+017F>uited to the Pores of this or that part of the Body, it may, by a concour<U+017F>e of Circum<U+017F>tances, be determined to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade it, and <U+017F>o di<U+017F>lodge from its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer receptacle, and excite Di<U+017F>orders in the part it removes to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>ANother thing whence the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<U+017F>ity of Animals may be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> is, their taking in of <hi>Effluvia</hi> from without. For the<U+017F>e cannot get into the internal parts of the Body, to perform their operations there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out penetrating the Skin, and con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently entring the Pores of it.</p>
               <p>Now, That things, outwardly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Body, may without wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Skin, be convey'd to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, there are many things that argue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63097:19"/>And fir<U+017F>t, it has been ob<U+017F>erved in <U+017F>ome Per<U+017F>ons, (for all are not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to admit the action of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Poy<U+017F>ons) that <hi>Cantharides,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing externally apply'd by Chyrurgions or Phy<U+017F>icians, may <U+017F>oon, and before they break the Skin, produce great di<U+017F>orders in the Urinary Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, and <U+017F>ometimes cau<U+017F>e bloody Water. And I remember, that having once had a bli<U+017F>tering Plai<U+017F>ter, applyed by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chyrurgion between my <U+017F>houlders, though I knew not that there were any <hi>Cantharides</hi> at all mixt with the other Ingredients, yet it gave me about the neck of my Bladder one of the <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible<U+017F>t pains I had ever felt, and forced me to <U+017F>end for help at a very un<U+017F>ea<U+017F>onable time of night.</p>
               <p>The Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the Skin may be al<U+017F>o argued from divers of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects even of Milder Plai<U+017F>ters. For, though <U+017F>ome Plai<U+017F>ters may operate as they clo<U+017F>ely <U+017F>tick to the Skin, and hinder Per<U+017F>piration from within, and fence the part from the external cold; yet, twill <U+017F>carce be denied, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63097:20"/>
many of them have notable effects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other accounts, whereof none is <U+017F>o likely and con<U+017F>iderable as the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ingre<U+017F>s of the Corpu<U+017F>cles of the Plai<U+017F>ter, that enter at the Pores of the Skin, and being once got in, act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their re<U+017F>pective Natures &amp; Vertues. The like may be <U+017F>aid of Ointments, who<U+017F>e operations, e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on Children (who<U+017F>e Skin is ordinarily more <U+017F>oft and lax) are <U+017F>ometimes very notable. And I have known con<U+017F>iderable things performed by them, in an internal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of grown men, where I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>carce have expected a Vegetable Ointment <U+017F>hould perform <U+017F>o much: I <U+017F>ay, a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable Ointment, for 'tis vulgarly known that by Mercurial Ointments Salivation may be excited; and <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, again<U+017F>t the Phy<U+017F>itians will, the Corpu<U+017F>cles of the Quick Silver get <U+017F>o far into the Body, that he is not able to get them out again.</p>
               <p>What we lately <U+017F>aid of Plai<U+017F>ters, may be applyed to tho<U+017F>e that Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians call <hi>Pericarpia,</hi> or Wri<U+017F>t-bands:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63097:20"/>
The better <U+017F>ort of which, though <U+017F>ometimes ineffectual, are oftentimes <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful in <U+017F>topping Fits of Agues, as I have frequently found in a mixture, el<U+017F>ewhere mention'd, of Currans, Hops, Bay<U+017F>alt well beaten together, by which, by Gods ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing, many, and I among others, have been freed from <U+017F>imple Tertians, and either double Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians or Quotidians.</p>
               <p>The Argument of the Poro<U+017F>ity of Animals, drawn from tho<U+017F>e things that get in through their skins, without breaking or wounding them, may be much <U+017F>trengthned, if it can be made appear, that tho<U+017F>e Phy<U+017F>itians do not deceive us, who a<U+017F>cribe <U+017F>en<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Operations and Vertues, to things externally applyed, in <U+017F>o loo<U+017F>e a way, that they do not <U+017F>o much as <U+017F>tick to the Skin, or perhaps immediately touch it; <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>ome call <hi>Periapta</hi> and <hi>Appen<U+017F>a</hi>; divers of which are be<U+017F>t known among us, by the name of Amulets; <U+017F>uch as are the Quills con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Quick-<U+017F>ilver or Ar<U+017F>enick, that <U+017F>ome hang about their necks, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63097:21"/>
wear under their Shirts, again<U+017F>t the Plague and other Contagious Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es; and the Blood<U+017F>tones that others wear again<U+017F>t Haemorrhages; and the <U+017F>tone which the Women u<U+017F>e in the <hi>Ea<U+017F>t-Indies,</hi> for a quite contrary effect, in <hi>Ob<U+017F>tructione Men<U+017F>ium.</hi> That many of the<U+017F>e external Medicines, an<U+017F>wer not the promi<U+017F>es of tho<U+017F>e that extol them, having <U+017F>ome of them no <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible operation at all, and others no con<U+017F>iderable one, experience has a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ured judicious ob<U+017F>ervers; but that <U+017F>ome of them, e<U+017F>pecially on <U+017F>ome Patients, may have con<U+017F>iderable, not to <U+017F>ay admirable, operations, I confe<U+017F>s my <U+017F>elf by other motives, as well as Authority, to be per<U+017F>waded. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been one <U+017F>ummer frequently <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to bleed at the No<U+017F>e, and reduced to imploy <U+017F>everal remedies to check that di<U+017F>temper; that which I found the mo<U+017F>t effectual to <U+017F>tanch the blood, was <U+017F>ome mo<U+017F>s of a dead mans Scull (<U+017F>ent for a pre<U+017F>ent out of <hi>Ireland</hi> where 'tis far le<U+017F>s rare than in mo<U+017F>t other Countrys) though it did but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63097:21"/>
touch my skin till the herb was a little warm'd by it. And though I remember not that I have known any great matter done to <U+017F>top Haemorrha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies by the bare outward application of other Blood-<U+017F>tones; yet of one that look'd almo<U+017F>t like an Agate, I admired the effects, e<U+017F>pecially upon a young and extraordinarily Sanguin per<U+017F>on. To which I <U+017F>hall add a memorable thing,<note rend="inter">If one would <U+017F>ee this pa<U+017F><U+017F>age at large he may find it at the end of the E<U+017F><U+017F>ay.</note> communicated to the experienced <hi>Zwelfer</hi> by the chief Phy<U+017F>itian of the States of <hi>Moravia.</hi> For this learned man whom he extols for a great Phy<U+017F>ician and Philo<U+017F>opher; a<U+017F><U+017F>ures him, that having prepared <U+017F>ome Trochi<U+017F>chs of Toads according to <hi>Helmonts</hi> way, (which I remember I al<U+017F>o was <U+017F>olici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to prepare, but had not occa<U+017F>ion to make tryal of their vertue,) he not only found, that being worn as Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets they pre<U+017F>erved him and all his Dome<U+017F>ticks, and Friends, from the Plague (though he daily vi<U+017F>ited the infected) but that having cau<U+017F>ed the<U+017F>e
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63097:22"/>
Trochi<U+017F>chs to be put upon the Plague <U+017F>ores of <U+017F>everal per<U+017F>ons, none of them died, but the venom of the pe<U+017F>tilential Carbuncles was thereby <U+017F>o weakened that the ulcers were afterward ea<U+017F>ily cured by vulgar remedies.</p>
               <p>And now, as to the difficulty, which I acknowledge not to be <U+017F>mall, to conceive how Bodies actually cold can emit <hi>Effluvia,</hi> capable of pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating (without moi<U+017F>tening it) a Membrane of <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e a Contexture as a mans Skin; I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e it will be much le<U+017F><U+017F>ened in the objectors opinion, by what he will meet with hereafter about the Pores of Bodies, and the Figures of Corpu<U+017F>cles. For <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing the<U+017F>e to be congruous, it will not <U+017F>eem incredible, that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets <U+017F>hould in tract of time get pa<U+017F><U+017F>age through the Pores of the Skin of a Living Body. And to make this the more probable, I will give an In<U+017F>tance in the Skin of a dead <hi>Animal.</hi> And, becau<U+017F>e this requires a Liquor I much employ in the<U+017F>e trials about Porology, though I have many years <U+017F>ince in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63097:22"/>
another Tract taught how to make it for another purpo<U+017F>e; yet I <U+017F>hall here repeat, that 'tis made by exactly ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Flower of Brim<U+017F>tone, powdered <hi>Sal Armoniac</hi> and good Quicklime in equal quantities, <U+017F>ave that, if the Quicklime be not very dry and good, a fourth or fifth part mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>uper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added, for the<U+017F>e being nimbly mixed, and di<U+017F>tilled by degrees of Fire in a Retort, till the Sand be at length brought to be almo<U+017F>t red hot, there will come over a <U+017F>moaking Spirit, which mu<U+017F>t be kept very carefully <U+017F>topt, and which for di<U+017F>tinctions <U+017F>ake, I al<U+017F>o u<U+017F>e to call, The <hi>Permeating Men<U+017F>truum or Liquor,</hi> and its expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the Penetrant, or Permeating Fumes.</p>
               <p>And now you will ea<U+017F>ily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tand the experiment I was about to mention, which was this; We took a very clean piece of poli<U+017F>h'd Copper, in want of which one of <U+017F>ilver will <U+017F>erve the turn, and having lapt it up in a piece of either Lambs or <U+017F>heeps Leather, <U+017F>o that it was every way
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63097:23"/>
inclo<U+017F>ed, we then held it over the Orifice of the Vial that contained the Spirit, at a pretty di<U+017F>tance from the Liquor, who<U+017F>e fumes neverthele<U+017F>s did quickly, (perhaps in a minute of an hour or le<U+017F>s) pervade the Pores of the Leather, and operate upon the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded metal as appeared by the deep and la<U+017F>ting tincture it had given to the lower <U+017F>urface of it, though the interpo<U+017F>ed Leather it <U+017F>elf was not deprived of its whitene<U+017F>s, nor at all <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ibly di<U+017F>coloured; however it <U+017F>melt of the Sulplureous <U+017F>teams that had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded it. And, if I mi<U+017F>remember not, the <U+017F>ame Experiment <U+017F>ucceeded, though <U+017F>omewhat more <U+017F>lowly, when a double Leather was interpo<U+017F>ed between the fumes and a new piece of Copper coin. This will be thought the le<U+017F>s <U+017F>trange, when I <U+017F>hall come to <U+017F>ome other In<U+017F>tances of the Penetrancy of the<U+017F>e Spirits. In the mean while I leave it to be con<U+017F>idered, whether this may not <U+017F>ugge<U+017F>t <U+017F>ome conjecture at that <U+017F>trange <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> which is recorded by Authors of good repute,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63097:23"/>
That <U+017F>ometimes in great Thunders the Lightening, among other opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, has been found to have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>tly di<U+017F>coloured mens money, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out burning the Pur<U+017F>es or Pockets wherein it lay. For in our experiment, the <U+017F>teams that in a trice pervaded the Leather, the mo<U+017F>t u<U+017F>ual matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Pur<U+017F>es are made, were <U+017F>ulphureous, as the <U+017F>mell argues, that tho<U+017F>e which accompany the <hi>Fulmen</hi> are wont to be; and whereas the<U+017F>e, when they invade Bodies, are u<U+017F>ually very hot, ours operated when the Liquor that emitted them was actually cold. And if it be <U+017F>aid, that <U+017F>ometimes their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney has been found di<U+017F>colored in their Pockets, who were not <U+017F>truck, by the <hi>Fulmen,</hi> but had it only pa<U+017F>s near them, it may be objected, that tho the intire Body, whether fluid or <U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, if there be any of this latter kind that is in Latine called <hi>Fulmen</hi> (for our Engli<U+017F>h word, <hi>Thunderbolt</hi> <U+017F>eems not <U+017F>o applicable to a fluid) did not touch them, yet it might <U+017F>catter <U+017F>teams enough round about it, to cau<U+017F>e
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63097:24"/>
the <hi>Phoenomenon.</hi> For confirmation of which I <U+017F>hall take notice, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable Per<U+017F>on of my acquaintance, having had the Curio<U+017F>ity to a<U+017F>cend a burning mountain in <hi>America,</hi> till the <U+017F>ulphureous <U+017F>teams grew too offen<U+017F>ive to him, he told me that, among other operations he ob<U+017F>erved them to have upon him, one was, that he found the money he had about him turned of a black and dirty colour, <U+017F>uch as I have ob<U+017F>erved our <U+017F>ulphureous <U+017F>teams of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten give both to Copper, and to Silver Coins. But whether or no our Spirits will ju<U+017F>tify the conjecture, they invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to mention, at lea<U+017F>t their <U+017F>o ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ily pervading the Skin of a dead Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal may make it probable, that the Skin of a Living man may be ea<U+017F>ily pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated by external <U+017F>teams who<U+017F>e ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Eye does not perceive, and who<U+017F>e operations, though not incon<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, may therefore be un<U+017F>u<U+017F>pected. I leave to Phy<U+017F>itians to con<U+017F>ider, what u<U+017F>e may be made of this ob<U+017F>ervation, in reference to the propagation of contagious Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, by the contact of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63097:24"/>
infected Air, di<U+017F>tinct from the Re<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it, and by the penetration of the <U+017F>teams, that i<U+017F><U+017F>uing from divers Bodies invade the Skin, and may perhaps be capable of operations, either hurtful or friendly, that are not u<U+017F>ually <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected to proceed from <U+017F>uch cau<U+017F>es, and are therefore mi<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribed to others. And on this occa<U+017F>ion it will not be impertinent to add, that by hanging up <U+017F>heeps Leather or Lambs Leather in the free Air, the vapors of it would <U+017F>o in<U+017F>inuate them<U+017F>elves into the Pores in wet weather, that a moderate degree of moi<U+017F>ture in the Air would add to it a not incon<U+017F>iderable weight, of which dry weather, whether hot or cold, would deprive it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>I Mu<U+017F>t not in this place omit <U+017F>ome In<U+017F>tances, very proper to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t the Penetrablene<U+017F>s of Membranes to Fumes them<U+017F>elves, if they be <U+017F>ubtile
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63097:25"/>
enough for their Pores, or corre<U+017F>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough to them.</p>
               <p>Among the ob<U+017F>ervations publi<U+017F>hed by Phy<U+017F>icians I have met with <U+017F>ome by which it appears that <hi>Cantharides</hi> may have great Effects upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Parts of the Body, though they do not <U+017F>o much as touch the Skin, but are placed at <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance from it,<note rend="inter">Schenkii Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervationum Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Ob<U+017F>. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> <U+017F>o that their <hi>Effluvia</hi> mu<U+017F>t be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>mitted through other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies before they can pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate that. The learned <hi>Michael Pa<U+017F>chalius</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a Chyrurgion, who was twice brought to void much Blood with his Urine, by <U+017F>ome Spani<U+017F>h Flies that he carryed about in a Pur<U+017F>e or Bag. And another Doctor of note relates of another per<U+017F>on that came to complain to him, that he pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed Blood, having carryed about with him <hi>Cantharides,</hi> though in his Pocket, and adds, that a like Ca<U+017F>e was recounted to him by <hi>Helidaeus,</hi> whom he calls an eminent <hi>Bolognian</hi> Phy<U+017F>ician.</p>
               <p>We <U+017F>ee, that in Linnen Cloth, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63097:25"/>
finer and more <U+017F>lender the threads are the clo<U+017F>er and le<U+017F>s Porous, <hi>coeteris paribus,</hi> the Linnen is: By analogy to which one may e<U+017F>teem the thin film that lines the <U+017F>hell of an Egg, to be of an exceeding clo<U+017F>e Contexture; and yet that even this film is not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to <U+017F>ome Fumes, I have found by the following Tryal.</p>
               <p>To make this, we <U+017F>lowly and warily pick'd off a <U+017F>ufficient part of the Shell of a Hens Egg, from the Skin that lay ju<U+017F>t beneath it, and is wont to <U+017F>tick <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e to it, that their <U+017F>eparation, without injuring the Membrane, is not ea<U+017F>y. In this Skin, being wip'd, we wrapt up a flat piece of Copper, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>urface was made bright, that the change of Colour might be the better <U+017F>een; and having kept this covered bit of Plate, over the Fumes of our <U+017F>moaking Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor lately mentioned for a minute or two by our ghe<U+017F>s we unfolded the Skin, and found, as we expected, that the lower <U+017F>urface of the Copper which was it that had been held over the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63097:26"/>
Fumes, was turned of a very dark co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which manife<U+017F>ted that even <U+017F>o fine and clo<U+017F>ely contexed a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane was not only, as we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <U+017F>hewn, penetrable by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, but readily pervious to our <U+017F>ulphureous exhalations, tho the<U+017F>e were probably but faintly emitted, <U+017F>ince the Liquor they came from was then actually cold. But in making the Tryal it is fit to hold (as we did in that newly recited) the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane again<U+017F>t the light, to <U+017F>ee if it be intire, and have e<U+017F>caped all tho<U+017F>e little lacerations that are hardly avoidable in <U+017F>evering it from the Shell it <U+017F>ticks <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e to. If this caution be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, 'tis ea<U+017F>y to be impo<U+017F>ed on, by overlooking <U+017F>ome little holes, that are not ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>cerned when one looks down upon the Skin, and yet may be <U+017F>ufficient to make the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment deceitful. But, thô when 'tis well made, it is a notable confirmation of the Doctrine endeavoured to be e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>hed in this Paper, yet I <U+017F>hall now <U+017F>ubjoyn a more con<U+017F>iderable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63097:26"/>
In<U+017F>tance to the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>The Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the Internal Membranes of the Body, will be more ea<U+017F>ily granted, if it be con<U+017F>idered that either the Liquors, or the moi<U+017F>t Exhalations, who<U+017F>e Action is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the Natural Heat of the Parts, keeps them con<U+017F>tantly wet or moi<U+017F>t, and thereby renders them more lax, and more penetrable by <U+017F>ubtle Spirits or other Corpu<U+017F>cles. In favour of this Reflection I made the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Experiment. We took a piece of a dryed Urinary Bladder, which was judged to have been a Calfs; and having lapt it about a new piece of Silver Coin, <U+017F>o that the Bladder was <U+017F>ingle where it covered the lower <U+017F>ide of the Piece, we kept it for divers Minutes, by gue<U+017F>s, over the Spirituous Fumes of our often mentioned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meating Liquor, but could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Coin was thereby at all affected or terni<U+017F>hed. Whence we concluded that the Pores of the dry Bladder were too clo<U+017F>e and narrow<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> to give pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to the Expirations of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63097:27"/>
the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum.</hi> But pre<U+017F>uming that moi<U+017F>ture would <U+017F>ome what relax them with another piece of the <U+017F>ame Bladder, made limber by being a little wetted in common Water, we lapt up another like peace of new Coin, as we had done the former, and kept it at the <U+017F>ame di<U+017F>tance as before, from the Liquor, but not for <U+017F>o long a time. For after about two Minutes, by gue<U+017F>s, we remov'd and took out the Piece, and, as we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, found much of its lower <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face (that regarded the Liquor) deeply di<U+017F>coloured. Which Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not only ju<U+017F>tify what I lately <U+017F>aid, of the greater Laxity of moi<U+017F>t than of dry Membranes, but will be thought no mean confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what is in this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay delivered about the Poro<U+017F>ity of Membranes, <U+017F>ince the Urinary Bladder does, as Anatomi<U+017F>ts well know, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t of more than one Membrane, though they <U+017F>tick <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e together, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear but one to the Eye. And this Bladder was <U+017F>peedily penetrated by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63097:27"/>
the Fumes that our Liquor emitted in exceeding Cold and Fro<U+017F>ty weather, though the Bladder it <U+017F>elf was not in the warm Body of the live Animal, but had been <U+017F>o long kept dryed and cold, that probably the Moi<U+017F>ture it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced in <U+017F>carce one minute of an Hour, could not re<U+017F>tore it to the Laxity it had, whil<U+017F>t it was a part of the living Calf.</p>
               <p>One of the notable<U+017F>t In<U+017F>tances I ever met with, of the Poro<U+017F>ity of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Membranes of the Humane Body, was afforded me by that <hi>Briti<U+017F>h</hi> Nobleman, of whom our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Harvey</hi> tells a memorable, not to <U+017F>ay matchle<U+017F>s, <U+017F>tory. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, having in his youth, by an accident which that Doctor relates, had a great and la<U+017F>ting Perforation made in his <hi>Thorax,</hi> at which the motion of his Heart could be directly perceiv'd did not only out live the accident, but grew a <U+017F>trong, and <U+017F>omewhat corpulent man; and <U+017F>o robu<U+017F>t, as well as Gallant, that he afterwards was a Souldier, and had
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63097:28"/>
the honour to command a Body of an Army for the King. This Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander</hi> (for that was his la<U+017F>t Title having mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed one of my neare<U+017F>t kin<U+017F>women, and having been told that I was very de<U+017F>irous to <U+017F>ee, what I had heard <U+017F>uch <U+017F>trange things of, very obliging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came, at a fit time, to give me that <U+017F>atisfaction. In order to which he removed that which covered the wide Orifice of his Hurt, and gave me the opportunity of looking into his <hi>Thorax,</hi> and of di<U+017F>cerning there the motions of the Cone, as they call it, or <hi>Mucro</hi> of the Heart. But the<U+017F>e things I mention but upon the by, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>trangene<U+017F>s of the fact; the thing I principally intended relates to my pre<U+017F>ent argument. Having then made <U+017F>everal inquiries fit for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, his Lord<U+017F>hip told me, that when he did, as he was wont to do from time to time, (though not every day) inject with a Syringe <U+017F>ome actually warm medicated Liquor into his <hi>Thorax,</hi> to clean<U+017F>e and cheri<U+017F>h the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63097:28"/>
Parts, he <U+017F>hould quickly and plainly find in his Mouth the ta<U+017F>t and <U+017F>mell of the Drugs, wherewith the Liquor had been impregnated. And I further learned, that, whereas he con<U+017F>tantly wore upon the unclo<U+017F>ed part of his Che<U+017F>t, a Silken Quilt, <U+017F>tuffed with Aromatick and odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Powders, to defend the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Parts and keep them warm; when he came, as he u<U+017F>ed to do after <U+017F>ome weeks, to imploy a new Quilt, the fragrant <hi>Effluvia</hi> of it would min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with his breath in ex<U+017F>piration, and very <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly perfume it, not, as I declared I <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected, upon the <U+017F>core of the plea<U+017F>ing Exhalations that might get up between his Clothes and his Body, but that got into the Organs of Re<U+017F>piration, and came out with his Breath at his Mouth, as was confirmed to me by a grave &amp; judicious State<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that happened to be then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent, and knew this General very well. Other circum<U+017F>tances I might add, but that I dare not tru<U+017F>t my memory for them, and unhappily lo<U+017F>t the Paper,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63097:29"/>
wherein the oddne<U+017F>s of the things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited me to <U+017F>et them down, for fear of forgetting them.</p>
               <p>That part of this Narrative which relates to Injections may be much confirm'd by what is delivered by <hi>Galen</hi> him<U+017F>elf, who <U+017F>ays that <hi>Mul<U+017F>um</hi> or <hi>Honeyed Water,</hi> being injected at the Orifice of Wounds penetrating into the cavity of the <hi>Thorax,</hi> has been ob<U+017F>erved to be in part received into the Lungs, and di<U+017F>charged out of the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria</hi> by coughing. And this he mentions as a known thing, imploying it as a <hi>Medium</hi> whereby to prove another.</p>
               <p>The mention that has been made of the Poro<U+017F>ity of Membranes, brings into my mind what I once ob<U+017F>erved at the Di<U+017F><U+017F>ection, made by <U+017F>ome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icians, and Anatomi<U+017F>ts, of a lu<U+017F>ty Souldier, that was hanged for I know not what crime. This man, though otherwi<U+017F>e young and <U+017F>ound, was ob<U+017F>erved to have been long mole<U+017F>ted with what they call a <hi><U+017F>hort, dry Cough,</hi> which made us expect to find <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63097:29"/>
much ami<U+017F>s in his Lungs. But meeting with nothing there, we were at a lo<U+017F>s for the cau<U+017F>e of this Cough, till coming to con<U+017F>ider the internal part of the Che<U+017F>t, we perceived <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on one of the <U+017F>ides, by tracing of which we di<U+017F>covered, that between the <hi>Pleura</hi> and the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the interco<U+017F>tal mu<U+017F>cles, there was lodged a certain matter, of the breadth of a Silver Crown piece, or thereabouts, of a roundi<U+017F>h figure, and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>tence and almo<U+017F>t colour of new, <U+017F>oft Chee<U+017F>e, which odd <U+017F>tuff was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to have been the remains of <U+017F>ome ill cured Pleuri<U+017F>y, and to have tran<U+017F>mitted through the Pores of the <hi>Pleura,</hi> though that be a very clo<U+017F>e Membrane, <U+017F>ome noxious <hi>Effluvia,</hi> which ever and anon irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lungs into an irregular and trouble<U+017F>om motion, and <U+017F>o produced the Cough the Malefactor had been mole<U+017F>ted with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63097:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Am well aware that 'tis far le<U+017F>s difficult, to prove the permeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of <U+017F>ingle Membranes, than that of <U+017F>uch a Part of the Body, as <U+017F>eems to be an aggregate of <U+017F>everal parts, which in regard of their clo<U+017F>e adhe<U+017F>ion, are looked upon but as one part, to which, on that account, men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give a di<U+017F>tinct name. But yet there are <U+017F>ome <hi>Phaenomena</hi> that <U+017F>eem to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, that even <U+017F>uch compounded or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ulting parts if I may <U+017F>o call them, are not de<U+017F>titute of Pores, which whether they be not <U+017F>ome of them the Orifices of exceeding <U+017F>lender and therefore unob<U+017F>erved Capillary Ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els, I mu<U+017F>t not now <U+017F>tay to enquire.</p>
               <p>When the cavity of the <hi>Abdomen</hi> in tho<U+017F>e Hydropical Per<U+017F>ons that are troubled with an <hi>A<U+017F>cites,</hi> is filled with Water, or rather with a Liquor that I have found to be much more vi<U+017F>cous, it ju<U+017F>tly appears <U+017F>trange, that by an
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63097:30"/>
Hydragogue, or <U+017F>ome appropriated purging medicine, great quantities of this gro<U+017F>s Liquor <U+017F>hould in a <U+017F>hort time be carryed off by Siege, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps al<U+017F>o by Urine, though to get into the cavity of the Guts, or that of either of the Kidneys, it <U+017F>eems nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ary that it Permeate the Tunicles, and other component parts, of the <hi>Vi<U+017F>cera</hi> it gets into.</p>
               <p>I know not whether I may on this occa<U+017F>ion take notice of what Phy<U+017F>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ob<U+017F>erve to occur now and then in <hi>Empyema's</hi> that follow ill condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Pleuri<U+017F>ies.</hi> For it has <U+017F>everal times been ob<U+017F>erved, that upon the bur<U+017F>ting of <U+017F>uch impo<U+017F>thumes into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t, the Purulent matter hath been voided by Siege and Urine. I he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>itate, as I was <U+017F>aying, whether I <U+017F>hould alledge this <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> as a proof of what I now contend for, till it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined whether this <hi>Meta<U+017F>ta<U+017F>is</hi> be made by <hi>tran<U+017F>udation</hi> properly <U+017F>o called, or by the ingre<U+017F>s of the <hi>Pus</hi> into the imperfectly clo<U+017F>ed Orifices of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the Lungs;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63097:31"/>
where being once admitted and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the Blood they may with this circulating Liquor arrive at the Kidneys, or any other Parts fitted to make a <U+017F>ecretion of this Heterogeneous matter.</p>
               <p>But whatever be the Rea<U+017F>on or manner of it, we find that the Lungs do <U+017F>ometimes odly convey things to di<U+017F>tant parts of the Body. And if I may here mention a thing, <hi>cui honos praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis e<U+017F>t,</hi> I <U+017F>hall add that I have <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times ob<U+017F>erv'd in my <U+017F>elf, that when I had been an actor or an a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tant in the Di<U+017F><U+017F>ection of a living Dog, e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if his Blood or Body were rankly Scented, I <U+017F>hould divers hours after plainly find that odour in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements I voided by Siege.</p>
               <p>A famous Chirurgeon and Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>t relates, that one who was very ill of a drop<U+017F>y, judged to ari<U+017F>e from a <hi>Scirrhus</hi> of the Spleen, coming to ask his coun<U+017F>el and a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, though he judged the patients ca<U+017F>e de<U+017F>perate, yet to content him, he ordered him to dip a very large Sponge in good Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime-Water,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63097:31"/>
and having <U+017F>queezed out the <U+017F>uperfluous Liquor, to bind it upon the region of the Spleen, only <U+017F>hifting it from time to time. He adds, that after <U+017F>ome months he was much <U+017F>urprized to receive a vi<U+017F>it from this Patient, with <U+017F>olemn thanks for his recovery; the outward Medicine having, it <U+017F>eems, re<U+017F>olved the <hi>Scirrhus</hi> and concurred with nature to evacuate the hydropical humour. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olution of which hard tumour it <U+017F>eems nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, that the <U+017F>anative Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<U+017F>cles of the external remedy <U+017F>hould at length penetrate, not only the <hi>Epidermis,</hi> and the true <hi>Cutis,</hi> but the Mu<U+017F>cles them<U+017F>elves of the <hi>Abdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and <U+017F>ome other interpo<U+017F>ed parts.</p>
               <p>The<U+017F>e in<U+017F>tances may be <U+017F>trengthen'd by an eminent ob<U+017F>ervation of <hi>Galen,</hi> who takes notice that Bones being <U+017F>ometimes broken, without piercing the Skin that covers the part they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to, when the <hi>Callus</hi> is making, and the broken parts of the Bone begin to be conglutinated together, a Portion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63097:32"/>
of that Blood which had flowed to the part affected is carryed to the Skin and permeats that, <U+017F>o as to wet and foul the Dre<U+017F><U+017F>ings or Bandages that are kept upon the limb affected by the Fracture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOnes, Horns,</hi> and parts of the like Sub<U+017F>tance, being tho<U+017F>e that are granted to be the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>olid of the Bodies of Animals, I come in the la<U+017F>t place to <U+017F>hew by particular Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o have their <hi>Pores.</hi> I <U+017F>ay, by particular Experiments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e in a general way, their <hi>Poro<U+017F>ity</hi> has been already proved, by the <U+017F>ame Arguments, from their original Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nutrition, Augmentation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That have been employed to manife<U+017F>t the <hi>Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Animal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances in general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Nails of men, as well as their <hi>Skins,</hi> are Porous, may be gathered from their being ea<U+017F>ily and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63097:32"/>
permanently tinged with divers me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline <U+017F>olutions, and particularly with tho<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ilver in <hi>Aquafortis,</hi> and Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia</hi>; the former of which <U+017F>olutions though cold, will but too ea<U+017F>ily tinge the Skin and Nails it chances to touch, and makes <U+017F>ome little <U+017F>tay upon, with a dark and blacki<U+017F>h colour; which I found not that I could wa<U+017F>h out with water, or, even with a far more penetrating and ab<U+017F>ter<U+017F>ive liquor. The like durablene<U+017F>s I found in the Purple <U+017F>pots, that I <U+017F>ometimes purpo<U+017F>ely made on my Nails, by letting <U+017F>ome little drops of the <U+017F>olution of Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia</hi> dry upon them, which I now and then did, to ob<U+017F>erve the way of the Nails growth. For if the <U+017F>tain were made near the root of the nail, it would be <U+017F>till, though very <U+017F>lowly, thru<U+017F>t on by the new matter, till after <U+017F>ome weeks it arrived to the further end of the Nail, and was fit to be pared off with it. But this only upon the by. 'Tis more to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e to take notice, that, though the <hi>Men<U+017F>truums</hi> imployed in the recited
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63097:33"/>
Experiments be of them<U+017F>elves very acid and corro<U+017F>ive, yet they are <U+017F>o changed by the metals they have di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved, that they are Acid no more, the <U+017F>olution of Silver being rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly bitter, and that of Gold of a kind of <hi>Stiptic</hi> ta<U+017F>t, almo<U+017F>t like that which <U+017F>loes, growing in the hedges, are wont to be of.</p>
               <p>Ivory is a thing too well known to need to be de<U+017F>cribed. And, <U+017F>ince 'tis generally lookt upon (for I have had no opportunity to compare it with the Bones) as the <U+017F>olide<U+017F>t part of the va<U+017F>te<U+017F>t of Tere<U+017F>trial Animals, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments proving its poro<U+017F>ity, will be <U+017F>trong pre<U+017F>umptions for that of the harde<U+017F>t parts of other Animals. And the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Ivory may be argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <U+017F>everal ways of dying it with permanent colours. For in the<U+017F>e colorations the Tinctures that make them, mu<U+017F>t penetrate into, and be lodged in the Sub<U+017F>tance of the Ivory, e<U+017F>pecially when the Sub<U+017F>tance remains <U+017F>mooth and gla<U+017F><U+017F>y, as I have divers times made it do, when I employed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63097:33"/>
fit <hi>Men<U+017F>truums</hi> and Metalline Pigments. The <U+017F>olution I formerly mentioned of Silver in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> being laid upon Ivory, will <U+017F>oon give it a dark and blacki<U+017F>h <U+017F>tain, which is not, that I have found, to be wa<U+017F>hed off. I remember al<U+017F>o that I many years <U+017F>ince taught <U+017F>ome ingenious artificers, to adorn Ivory with a fine purple colour, by moi<U+017F>tening it with, and <U+017F>uffering lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urely to dry on it, a <U+017F>olution of Gold made in <hi>Aqua Regia.</hi> And if occa<U+017F>ion required, allayed with water, nor needs either of the<U+017F>e <U+017F>olutions be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed hot, any more than the Ivory needs to be heated. Both which cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<U+017F>tances favour the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>olid Body.</p>
               <p>Copper di<U+017F><U+017F>olved in <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> <U+017F>tains Ivory with a blewi<U+017F>h colour, as I have <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>een in the hafts of knifes, about who<U+017F>e coloration never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thele<U+017F>s another way is al<U+017F>o employed. But I remember that without making u<U+017F>e of any Acid or Corro<U+017F>ive <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truum,</hi> I have even in the cold <U+017F>tained Ivory, with a fine and permanent
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63097:34"/>
blew, like a Turquois, by <U+017F>uffering to dry upon it as deep a <U+017F>olution as I could make of Crude Copper, in an urinous Spirit, as that of <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to return to Bones, their growth in all their dimen<U+017F>ions, does, as I lately noted, argue their Poro<U+017F>ity and the marrow that is found in the great hollow Bones, whether it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<U+017F>h them or no, mu<U+017F>t it <U+017F>elf be <U+017F>upply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <U+017F>ome alimental juice, that <U+017F>oaks or otherways penetrates, into the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities that contain it.</p>
               <p>Nor does it <U+017F>eem at all improbable, that Blood it <U+017F>elf may through <U+017F>mall Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els be conveyed into the very <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance of the Bone, <U+017F>o as that the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els reach at lea<U+017F>t a little way in it, though perhaps the Liquor they carry may afterwards by Imbibition be brought to the more internal parts of the Bone. For not to urge that we manife<U+017F>tly <U+017F>ee, that on each <U+017F>ide of the lower Jaw, Nature has been careful to perforate the Bones and make a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel in the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of it; which Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63097:34"/>
receives not only a larger Nerve but a Vein, &amp; Artery to bring in &amp; carry back Blood for the nouri<U+017F>hment of the Teeth, by di<U+017F>tinct Sprigs <U+017F>ent from the great branch to the particular Teeth. Not to urge this, I <U+017F>ay, (which I mention but to <U+017F>hew that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion lately propo<U+017F>ed is agreeable to a known practice of Nature) I have been a<U+017F><U+017F>ured by eminent Anatomi<U+017F>ts, whom I purpo<U+017F>ely con<U+017F>ulted, that they have ob<U+017F>erved Blood-ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to enter a great way into the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the larger Bones. And one of them affirmed, that he had traced a Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el even to the great Cavity of the Bone. Which I the le<U+017F>s <U+017F>crupled to admit, becau<U+017F>e it has been ob<U+017F>erved, that in younger Animals the Cavity is in great part furni<U+017F>hed with Blood<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> as well as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and in tho<U+017F>e larger Pores, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many are found in the more Spongy Sub<U+017F>tance of divers Bones, Blood has been ob<U+017F>erved to have been lodged, as al<U+017F>o in the <U+017F>pongy part of the Skull, that lies between the two Tables, as I have been a<U+017F><U+017F>ured by Skilful Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witne<U+017F><U+017F>es.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63097:35"/>The blackne<U+017F>s al<U+017F>o, that Bones ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire when put into a competent heat, and a peculiar kind of fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s which they may by heat be made to afford, <U+017F>hew that they harbour, even in their internal parts, <U+017F>tore of Unctuous Particles, <U+017F>eparable from the <U+017F>olid <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, (which <U+017F>till retains its <U+017F>hape and continues <U+017F>olid) in who<U+017F>e Pores they may thereby be argued to have been lodged. The Lightne<U+017F>s of Bones, even when their Cavity is acce<U+017F><U+017F>ible to (Air and) Water, is al<U+017F>o a great <U+017F>ign of their Poro<U+017F>ity. And <U+017F>o is their being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roded by tinging liquors, if they be penetrative and well applyed. I know not whether I <U+017F>hould add on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ion, that having taken calcined and pulverized Bones, <U+017F>uch as we u<U+017F>e to make our Cupels of, and, after having given them a good heat, kept them for <U+017F>ome time in the Air, but in a well covered place; I found the imbibed moi<U+017F>ture of the Air to have manife<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increa<U+017F>ed their weight; and that I al<U+017F>o ob<U+017F>erved in a curious <hi>Skeleton,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63097:35"/>
where the Bones were kept together by wires, in<U+017F>tead of other Ligaments, that though I kept it in a well cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed place, not far from a Kitchin Fire, yet in very moi<U+017F>t weather the Bones <U+017F>eemed to <U+017F>well, <U+017F>ince tho<U+017F>e joynts that were ea<U+017F>y to be bent, in dry weather, and that after <U+017F>everal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, would grow <U+017F>tiff and refractory, and indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to be put into <U+017F>uch motions, when the weather was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderably wet. The<U+017F>e particulars (as I was <U+017F>aying) I am <U+017F>omewhat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whether I <U+017F>hould here in<U+017F>ert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e one may <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect the <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> may proceed rather from <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what el<U+017F>e, than the imbibed moi<U+017F>ture of the Air; and yet I would not omitt to mention the<U+017F>e ob<U+017F>ervations, becau<U+017F>e I do not yet <U+017F>ee any cau<U+017F>e to which they may more probably (or indeed <U+017F>o probably) be a<U+017F><U+017F>igned.</p>
               <p>And on this occa<U+017F>ion I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ubjoyn <U+017F>ome ob<U+017F>ervations made on large and <U+017F>olid Ox Bones, which in one of my Note Books I find thus regi<U+017F>tred. <hi>Nov.</hi> 15. We weighed two [entire or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken]
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63097:36"/>
Marrow Bones, and found the one to weigh <U+2125>xxix + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g><U+017F>s, and the other <U+2125>xxiv + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>iv + 30 gr. <hi>Nov.</hi> 24. The former weighed <U+2125>xxix + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>vi, and the latter <U+2125>xxv + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>i + 30 gr. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28. the former weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <U+2125>xxix + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>iij. 55 gr. and the latter <U+2125>xxiv + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>vii. + 39 gr. <hi>June</hi> 7th of the following year, the former weigh'd <U+2125>xxix + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>ii. And the latter <U+2125>xxiv + <g ref="char:dram"><U+0292></g>vii. By which ob<U+017F>ervations purpo<U+017F>ely made at differing times of the year, and in very good <U+017F>cales, it <U+017F>eems that Bones do plentifully enough imbibe the Exhalations of the Air, and emit them again, together with <U+017F>ome of their own, according as the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent happens to be di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed. And the<U+017F>e alterations argue the Bones to abound with Pores, <U+017F>ince the external <U+017F>teams mu<U+017F>t have Pores to receive them, and the <hi>Effluvia</hi> mu<U+017F>t upon their rece<U+017F>s leave Pores behind them.</p>
               <p>I confe<U+017F>s that to think (as with <U+017F>ome Anatomi<U+017F>ts I lately <U+017F>eemed to do) that Bones them<U+017F>elves admit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els capable of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63097:36"/>
conveying a nutritive Liquor, we mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e tho<U+017F>e Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els extreamly <U+017F>lender. But that 'tis not only po<U+017F><U+017F>ible but <U+017F>omewhat credible, there may be <U+017F>uch, I am induced to think, by what is known to happen in that di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which from the Country it mo<U+017F>t infe<U+017F>ts is called the <hi>Plica Polonica.</hi> For, tho one would think that the hairs of men are much too <U+017F>lender, to have cavities in them capable of vi<U+017F>ible Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors; and though I have found it very difficult, even with a good Micro<U+017F>cope, to perceive any cavities in the hair of a man tran<U+017F>ver<U+017F>ly cut; yet not only <U+017F>ome other writers of good note, but the Judicious <hi>Sennertus</hi> him<U+017F>elf deliver, that in this di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e (of which he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly treats) it has been ob<U+017F>erved, that if the Patients cau<U+017F>e their intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled hair to be cut, as they <U+017F>ometimes do, by rea<U+017F>on of its na<U+017F>tine<U+017F>s or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ightline<U+017F>s, they are not only thereby endangered, but <U+017F>ometimes the <U+017F>ingle hairs will actually bleed, where the ends have been cut off; <U+017F>o that <U+017F>o thick a Liquor as Blood may be conveyed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63097:37"/>
through Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, that can at mo<U+017F>t be but in a proper <U+017F>en<U+017F>e <hi>Capillary</hi> and mu<U+017F>t be far le<U+017F>s than hairs, if their Perfora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be like tho<U+017F>e by which many Plants have their nouri<U+017F>hment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to them, or <U+017F>uch as are obvious in divers Canes, which being cut quite through transver<U+017F>ly, di<U+017F>cover a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of di<U+017F>tinct Pores, that by <U+017F>ome Experiments one may be induced to gue<U+017F>s, reach all along, and make the Cane like a Cylindrical Bundle of Minute Pipes; or rather a multitude of <U+017F>mall cavities, that perforate from end to end the <hi>Parenchyma,</hi> or Sub<U+017F>tance analogous to it, that gives them <U+017F>tabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. And for the pre<U+017F>ent this <U+017F>ort of Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els <U+017F>eem to me, the more likely to be tho<U+017F>e that convey the Blood to the extream Parts of the Hair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e even in Hor<U+017F>e hairs, which yet are nouri<U+017F>hed and grow, I am not yet <U+017F>ure, that I have di<U+017F>covered with my Micro<U+017F>copes any cavity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect there may be divers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptible ones, for the Hair is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<U+017F>hed and grows, which it is not like
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63097:37"/>
it <U+017F>hould do if the Body were <U+017F>olid; and if there were but a <U+017F>ingle cavity in it, as in the lower part of a Quill, 'tis like the Micro<U+017F>cope I u<U+017F>ed would have di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it, <U+017F>ince with one much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour I could ea<U+017F>ily <U+017F>ee, that <U+017F>everal little <U+017F>hort Hairs, that grow upon the Animal that yields Musk, had each of them a cavity in it like that of the lower part of a Quill.</p>
               <p>To the things that have already been <U+017F>aid about the Poro<U+017F>ity of Bones, I <U+017F>hall now add an ob<U+017F>ervation of a very learned Phy<U+017F>ician, that is very remarkable to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e it argues, that even Bodies not <U+017F>aline, nor actually moi<U+017F>t, may from without get into the Pores and Cavities of Humane Bones. Divers Phy<U+017F>icians have complain'd of the mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs done to the Bones by Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, employ'd to <U+017F>alivate in Venereal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. Whereof I remember I have read a very notable In<U+017F>tance, in a learned Book (which I have not now by me) of an eminent Roman Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F><U+017F>or of Phy<U+017F>ick, who had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63097:38"/>
of making <U+017F>everal curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervations in the famous Ho<U+017F>pital of the <hi>Incurabili</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi>; and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more to be credited; where he relates, that in the Cavity of at lea<U+017F>t one Pocky-mans Bones, there was found real Quick-Silver that had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated thither. And this brings into my mind a memorable ob<U+017F>ervation of an ancient and experienced Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, who being famous for the cure of Venereal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, was asked by me, what In<U+017F>tances he had found of the Penetration of Quick-Silver, either outwardly or inwardly admini<U+017F>tred, into the Bones of men? To this he an<U+017F>wered, that he could not <U+017F>ay he had him<U+017F>elf taken notice of any Quick-Silver, in the Cavities of greater Bones, but that <U+017F>ome other Practition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had told him, that they had met with <U+017F>uch In<U+017F>tances, as I enquired after. But for him<U+017F>elf, he only remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that a Patient, who had been ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly fluxed with mercurial Inunctions, coming afterwards to have one of the Grinders of his lower Jaw pulled out,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63097:38"/>
becau<U+017F>e of the raging pain it had long put him to; my Relater had the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<U+017F>ity to view narrowly this great Tooth, and found, to his wonder, a little drop of true Mercury in that <U+017F>lender Cavity of the Root, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the <U+017F>mall Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els which convey nouri<U+017F>hment and <U+017F>en<U+017F>e to the Tooth, in more than one of who<U+017F>e three Roots he affirmed to me that he found true, though but exceeding little, Quick-Silver. But a full Te<U+017F>timony to my pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e is afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me by the experienced Phy<U+017F>ician <hi>Eu<U+017F>tachius Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> who relates,<note rend="inter">Eu<U+017F>tach. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius (apud Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertum) lib. <hi>5.</hi> de morbis acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> that he <U+017F>aw him<U+017F>elf, and that others al<U+017F>o ob<U+017F>erved, <U+017F>ome Bodies di<U+017F><U+017F>ected, of tho<U+017F>e that had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed for the Venereal Pox, in the Cavities of who<U+017F>e Bones no <U+017F>mall quantity of Quick Silver was got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, (which yet (to add that upon the by) he <U+017F>ays, did not hinder <U+017F>ome of them from living many years, <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving tho<U+017F>e Inunctions.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:63097:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>I Am not ignorant that, among the Particulars laid together in the foregoing E<U+017F><U+017F>ay, there are <U+017F>ome that are not ab<U+017F>olutely nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, to prove the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of the Bodies of Animals. But I thought it not impertinent to mention them, becau<U+017F>e I hoped that they, in conjunction with the re<U+017F>t, may be of <U+017F>ome u<U+017F>e to Naturali<U+017F>ts, in giving an account of <U+017F>everal things that pa<U+017F>s in a Humane Body, whether <U+017F>ound or <U+017F>ick, e<U+017F>pecially if it be of a Topical di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, and may remove, or much le<U+017F><U+017F>en that great Prejudice, that makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (and <U+017F>ome of them otherwi<U+017F>e learned) Phy<U+017F>icians de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e the u<U+017F>e of all <hi>Amulets, Pericarpia,</hi> and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Medicines in Di<U+017F>tempers of the Inward parts, upon a confident, but not well grounded <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ition, that the<U+017F>e Remedies immediately touching but the out<U+017F>ide of the Skin, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exerci<U+017F>e any con<U+017F>iderable opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63097:39"/>
upon the internal parts of the Body.</p>
               <p>But though I have thus acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged <U+017F>ome Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of the foregoing E<U+017F><U+017F>ay to be <U+017F>upernumerary, yet I mu<U+017F>t not di<U+017F>mi<U+017F>s it without intimating that I might from one Topick more have fetched a probable, though not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<U+017F>trative argument, in favour of the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Animals. For this may be very probably argued from hence, that even Inanimate, Solid and Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Bodies, that in all likelyhood mu<U+017F>t be of a far clo<U+017F>er Texture than the living Bodies of Animals (who<U+017F>e various Functions require a greater number and diver<U+017F>ity of Pores in their differing Organs) are not devoid of Pores, and have <U+017F>ome of them very numerous ones, as will be <U+017F>ufficiently made out in the following E<U+017F><U+017F>ay, to which I <U+017F>hall therefore ha<U+017F>ten.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:63097:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>N. B.</hi> The following Paper is that which is refer'd to in the 35th Page of this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note rend="inter">Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoeiae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae cla<U+017F><U+017F>is xiii. <hi>pa.</hi> 614.615.</note>Hujus rei veritatem comprobat Docti<U+017F><U+017F>imus ac celeberrimus Medicus &amp; Philo<U+017F>ophus D. <hi>Johannes Chry<U+017F>o<U+017F>tomus</hi> Irmbler, Statuum Moraviae Marchionatûs Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomedicus, his verbis ad me <U+017F>cribens: Et revera paravi ego, Anno M. <hi>DCLV,</hi> quo tempore inter Infectos ver<U+017F>abar quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie, Trochi<U+017F>cos Bufonios, eó<U+017F>que ut caetera Helmontii, indefe<U+017F><U+017F>i veritatis indagandae, &amp; ex puteo Opinionum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum no<U+017F>tram credulitatem excaecanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eruendae, nati Philo<U+017F>ophi, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta <U+017F>uas laudes <U+017F>u<U+017F>tinere comperi: Inter, viginti autem Bufones vix unum quidem, jucundo <U+017F>ane <U+017F>pectaculo, vidi ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculos, per nares &amp; oculos egre<U+017F><U+017F>uros, manu repellere quamdiu poterat, doxec elanguerit Bufo: <U+017F>ed Trochi<U+017F>cos ex vermiculis unà cum pulvere emo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui bufonis, &amp; materiâ per anum (non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63097:40"/>
vidi per vomitum;) <U+017F>cilicet alis, pedibus, capitibus, ventribus Scara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeorum viridibus, aurati<U+017F>ve &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris, quos bufo cum terra in e<U+017F>cam vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ejectâ, cerea patinâ exceptis, cum Tragacantho ro<U+017F>ato formatos, pluribus per<U+017F>onis <U+017F>uper anthraces opponi feci, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nullum eorum mortuum e<U+017F><U+017F>e dicere po<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>um, <U+017F>ed &amp; meorum dome<U+017F>ticorum, ut &amp; aliorum, quibus dedi, amicorum nullus, quod <U+017F>cio, infectus e<U+017F>t. Sic comperi non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm hi<U+017F>ce Trochi<U+017F>cis enervari virus pe<U+017F>tilens in Carbunculo jam admi<U+017F><U+017F>um, ut dein vulgaribus chirurgicis remediis ulcus facili negotio fuerit curatum, <U+017F>ed etiam ad <U+017F>ini<U+017F>tram mammam liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, mihi meísque accur<U+017F>ui &amp; occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ui infectorum expo<U+017F>itis, animo<U+017F>itatem quandam indicibilem conferre, atque ita mia<U+017F>mata &amp; effluvia pe<U+017F>tilentialia abarcere. Hucusque Excel. Medicus Moraviae.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:63097:41"/>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63097:41"/>
            <head>An E<U+017F><U+017F>ay of the POROUSNESS OF SOLID BODIES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I</head>
               <p>AS 'twill with far le<U+017F>s difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be allowed, that Animals and Vegetables, and <U+017F>uch Bodies, as have belonged to either, abound with Pores, than that Inanimate, Solid, and even Ponderous Bodies are not de<U+017F>titute of them: So 'tis far le<U+017F>s difficult to make out the former than the latter of the<U+017F>e Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>itions.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63097:42"/>
And therefore, <hi>Pyrophilus,</hi> I hope you will not expect that I <U+017F>hould give you as many proofs of the one, as I have of the other; however I de<U+017F>pair not, that tho<U+017F>e I <U+017F>hall pre<U+017F>ent you, will appear <U+017F>ufficient for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, though they be not numerous enough to make me careful to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hal them in any exact order.</p>
               <p>Of the rea<U+017F>ons that induce me to think that even Solid Bodies are not de<U+017F>titute of Pores, there are <hi><U+017F>ome</hi> that have a greater Affinity with tho<U+017F>e ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that the Schools are wont to call <hi>à priori,</hi> becau<U+017F>e they require more unobvious Ratiocinations upon Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ical Principles, and <hi>others</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>emble, and indeed are, <U+017F>uch proofs as are u<U+017F>ually named <hi>à po<U+017F>teriori,</hi> being <U+017F>ugge<U+017F>ted by the <hi>Phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> afforded us by experience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of any difficult Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
               <p>Of the Fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ort of Rea<U+017F>ons I <U+017F>hall propo<U+017F>e to you three; and begin with that, which may be drawn from the Origine and Formation of divers hard
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63097:42"/>
Bodies.<note rend="inter">See the Tract of the Origine and Vertues of Gems, and the Notes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical production of Hardne<U+017F>s.</note> For I have el<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where endeavour<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and I hope not un<U+017F>u<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>sfully, to <U+017F>hew, both that divers <U+017F>tones, and even Gems them<U+017F>elves, and that <U+017F>everal Metalline and other Mineral Bodies, were once either vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible Liquors or at lea<U+017F>t very <U+017F>oft <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances. And I have el<U+017F>ewhere proved, that both the<U+017F>e kinds of Bodies do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>t of, (which is the ca<U+017F>e of Liquors) or abound in (which is the ca<U+017F>e of <U+017F>oft and moi<U+017F>t Bodies) minute particles of determinate Sizes and Shapes; from whence I think one may very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conclude, that <U+017F>uch Gems and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mineral Bodies, notwith<U+017F>tanding any hardne<U+017F>s they afterwards come to acquire, are not de<U+017F>titute of Pores, <U+017F>ince 'tis no way likely, that Corpu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of various and very irregular Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, <U+017F>uch as tho<U+017F>e of mo<U+017F>t Liquors of the terre<U+017F>trial Globe are wont to be, can be <U+017F>o brought together, e<U+017F>pecially by chance, cold, or any other <U+017F>uch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, as not to intercept little Intervals or Pores between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:63097:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>ANother thing which makes me think the Poro<U+017F>ity of the mo<U+017F>t part even of Solid Bodies to be great, is the con<U+017F>ideration of the great di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity, that may be found in the <U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Gravities of <U+017F>uch Bodies, as the Eye does not perceive to be Porous. For, <hi>though</hi> Water be a Body of that kind, and though its parts be <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e packt together, that the attempts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious men, to make a manife<U+017F>t com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of that Liquor by outward violence, have not hitherto proved <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful, <hi>yet</hi> we find, that <U+017F>tones, Clays, metals, and even <U+017F>ome Woods and a multitude of other kinds of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, will readily <U+017F>ink in Water, and by con<U+017F>equence are <U+017F>pecifically heavyer than it; which greater gravity <U+017F>eems not any way explicable, without <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ing, or at lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>o well as by <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ing, that the Corpu<U+017F>cles whereof
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63097:43"/>
<U+017F>uch <U+017F>inking Bodies con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t, do either lye clo<U+017F>er together, or are <U+017F>eparately more <U+017F>olid, than tho<U+017F>e of Water; which Liquor mu<U+017F>t con<U+017F>equently be Porous, though neither the Eye, nor the great force that has been <U+017F>everal ways em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to compre<U+017F>s it, can di<U+017F>cover any Pores in it. Upon the <U+017F>ame ground I further conclude, that <U+017F>olid Stones them<U+017F>elves, as Marble, Flints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are not free from Poro<U+017F>ity. For whereas, as far as <U+017F>everal Tryals purpo<U+017F>ely made can inform me, I have found, that <U+017F>uch of the<U+017F>e as have nothing metalline in them do <U+017F>eldom or never reach to treble the weight of an equal bulk of Water, they will, upon the former grounds, appear to be con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably Porous; <U+017F>ince the lighte<U+017F>t me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, which are Tin and Iron, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twice heavier <hi>in <U+017F>pecie,</hi> that is, the bulks being equal, than Marble, Flints, Chry<U+017F>tal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by the <U+017F>ame rea<U+017F>on I al<U+017F>o infer the great Poro<U+017F>ity, even of the Solid Body of Iron, which is as well heavier, as very much harder, than Tinn. For though
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63097:44"/>
Copper be a good deal more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than Iron, or Steel, yet I have divers times found fine Gold, to be more than twice as heavy <hi>in <U+017F>pecie</hi> as Copper, <U+017F>ince, whereas this Metal, whether it be <hi>European,</hi> or brought from <hi>Japan</hi> (for of that al<U+017F>o I made Tryal) is about nine times as heavy as <U+017F>o much Water; I found refined Gold to be about nineteen times as heavy as Water equal to it in bulk. By which it <U+017F>eems highly probable, that <U+017F>o <U+017F>olid and heavy a Body, as Iron or Steel it <U+017F>elf, may be <U+017F>o porous, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline matter equal to it in weight may naturally be contained in much le<U+017F>s than half the Dimen<U+017F>ions that Metal po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es. And that Gold it <U+017F>elf, which is the mo<U+017F>t comPact and <U+017F>olid Body we know of, is not de<U+017F>titute of Pores, may appear by the Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of it in Quick-Silver, of which I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>peak a little below. And if any <U+017F>hould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that hardne<U+017F>s may be a greater argument of the Compactne<U+017F>s of a Body, and its immunity from Pores, than its <U+017F>pecifick weight can be; I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63097:44"/>
<U+017F>hall add, that though I have found that <hi>Emery,</hi> which is the Body em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to cut <U+017F>teel and Load-<U+017F>tones and Cry<U+017F>tal, and the mo<U+017F>t of Gems, being indeed much harder than Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Flints, be far heavier than thrice its bulk of Water; <hi>yet</hi> that ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s proceeds, as I el<U+017F>e where inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, from the mixture of a metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Sub<U+017F>tance, which I have <U+017F>eparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it. And Diamonds, though much harder Bodies than <hi>Emery,</hi> and indeed the harde<U+017F>t we know of in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are <U+017F>o far from being, as <U+017F>ome of late have written, the mo<U+017F>t ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Bodies, that having examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them hydro<U+017F>tatically, by a way el<U+017F>ewhere mentioned, I found them not much heavier than either Cry<U+017F>tal, or fine Gla<U+017F>s, and not half <U+017F>o heavy as the lighte<U+017F>t Metals.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:63097:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe next thing, from which the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Solid Bodies, and even tho<U+017F>e that belong to the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdom (as the Chymi<U+017F>ts <U+017F>peak) may be deduced, is the <U+017F>ame with the fir<U+017F>t of tho<U+017F>e from which we former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argued the Poro<U+017F>ity of Sub<U+017F>tances belonging to the Animal Kingdom, namely, the very frame &amp; con<U+017F>titution of <U+017F>uch Bodies. For the <U+017F>olide<U+017F>t Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies them<U+017F>elves, re<U+017F>ulting from the Convention or Coalition of a great number of Particles of <U+017F>everal big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es and <U+017F>hapes, we cannot rea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, (e<U+017F>pecially in tho<U+017F>e concretes wherein they are not ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a <U+017F>eminal Principle) that they <U+017F>hould be contexed <U+017F>o, as to touch one another exactly every where and therefore they mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity leave <U+017F>ome little Intervals and Pores be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63097:45"/>This rea<U+017F>on will, I hope, appear clear enough of it <U+017F>elf, to him that <U+017F>hall attentively con<U+017F>ider it, e<U+017F>pecially if he know, that it has been Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically demon<U+017F>trated, that there are but very few figures that will, (as they <U+017F>peak) <hi>implere <U+017F>patium,</hi> that is, which being adju<U+017F>ted to one another will <U+017F>o exactly touch, that there is not the lea<U+017F>t unfilled <U+017F>pace within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference or circuit, if the figures be plain, or within the ambient <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies,</hi> if they be <U+017F>olid; <U+017F>o that, con<U+017F>ider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the va<U+017F>t variety of other Figures, which made <hi>Epicurus</hi> and other <hi>Ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>ts</hi> pronounce it <hi>incomprehen<U+017F>ible,</hi> 'tis very obvious to conceive, that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<U+017F>cles of <U+017F>uch differing <U+017F>hapes being put together, will leave multitudes of little Pores intercepted, between tho<U+017F>e parts that do not every where touch one another. And even the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Figures lately <U+017F>poken of, may be <U+017F>aid to fill <U+017F>pace rather in a <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical</hi> than a <hi>Phy<U+017F>ical</hi> <U+017F>en<U+017F>e. For, if <U+017F>uch Portions of matter as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to con<U+017F>titute, for in<U+017F>tance, a Cube,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63097:46"/>
were actually put together, they would not exactly fill the <U+017F>pace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended within the ambient <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Body they compo<U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e the component Bodies, being Phy<U+017F>ical, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t of Corpu<U+017F>cles of their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <U+017F>hapes, which we never find Mathematically exqui<U+017F>ite. As if, for example, the Cube were of Marble, no Art could poli<U+017F>h the <U+017F>ides of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent Body <U+017F>o, as that they <U+017F>hould be perfectly <U+017F>moothed <U+017F>ince (as, if I mi<U+017F>take not, the learned <hi>Ga<U+017F><U+017F>endus</hi> well ob<U+017F>erves) Emery, Pumice-<U+017F>tone, and even Puttee, or other Powders that are employed to poli<U+017F>h them, do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t of little hard angular Corpu<U+017F>cles, that leave <U+017F>mall <U+017F>cratches, like <U+017F>o many little furrows, on their <U+017F>urfaces, which mu<U+017F>t needs hinder the perfect contact of the whole <U+017F>urfaces of two contiguous Bodies, and con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently leave here and there Intervals or Pores, between tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>urfaces; to which I <U+017F>hall add that Marble it <U+017F>elf as 'tis Marble, abounds with internal Pores, as will ere long appear by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63097:46"/>
Experience, and as may be rationally conjectured from the Specifick Levity of it, in compari<U+017F>on of Gold and Lead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>HAving di<U+017F>patched the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>à priori,</hi> that may be imployed to <U+017F>hew the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Solid Bodies, 'twill be now <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to propo<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome Experiments and ob<U+017F>ervations, that may (as 'twere) <hi>à po<U+017F>teriori</hi> either evince or confirm the <U+017F>ame Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Of the<U+017F>e In<U+017F>tances <U+017F>ome relate to Solid Bodies that are of le<U+017F>s <U+017F>pecifick gravity <U+017F>ome to Fo<U+017F><U+017F>iles pre<U+017F>umed to be devoid of Metalline parts, <U+017F>ome to Minerals that are thought to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of a Metalline nature, <U+017F>ome to Metals them<U+017F>elves, and <U+017F>ome to Gla<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>To begin with the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ort of the<U+017F>e In<U+017F>tances; That Wood is Porous, there are many things that argue; <U+017F>ome of which are el<U+017F>ewhere mentioned. But few would <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect, that Quick-Silver which is <U+017F>o unapt to enter the Pores
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63097:47"/>
of Bodies much le<U+017F>s compact, <U+017F>hould permeate peices of Wood of a con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thickne<U+017F>s; and yet, that we have made it do by the following Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We took a wooden Trunk, <U+017F>uch as is employed to <U+017F>hoot pellets at Birds, with <U+017F>trength enough to kill them, and having clo<U+017F>ely <U+017F>topt one end of it, we poured in Quick Silver at the other, till it reached to a good height in the cylindrical Cavity of the In<U+017F>trument, and then the lower parts of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline Liquor, being a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ted by the weight of the Incumbent ones, (not to mention that of the Air) to pre<U+017F>s into the Pores of the Wood, they i<U+017F><U+017F>ued out at them on all <U+017F>ides, in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of minute drops, much after the manner of Quick-Silver <U+017F>trained through Leather, out of amalgams; which was a <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> not unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ant to behold. But till I have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to repeat this Experiment with differing circum<U+017F>tances, I <U+017F>hall not think it fit to lay much <U+017F>tre<U+017F>s upon it, for want of knowing, what intere<U+017F>t the great weight of the Quick Silver may have had in the event.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:63097:47"/>And this caution may perchance be applicable to the following Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, namely, that having, by the help of my Pneumatical Engine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn the Air from one <U+017F>ide of a round peice of board, the Air on the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ite <U+017F>ide, not having its pre<U+017F><U+017F>ure any longer re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ted by that which it u<U+017F>ed to meet with from the withdrawn Air, pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed <U+017F>o <U+017F>trongly again<U+017F>t the <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Wood expo<U+017F>ed to it, as to make it <U+017F>elf way through the Pores of it, and get copiou<U+017F>ly enough into the Cavity whence the other Air had been pumpt out; (the weight of the incumbent Atmo<U+017F>phere doing on this occa<U+017F>ion, what the weight of the Quick-Silver did on that la<U+017F>t recited:) Which was a <U+017F>urprizing <U+017F>pectacle to the by-<U+017F>tanders becau<U+017F>e the board that was thus permeated, was of <U+017F>trong Wood, and of con<U+017F>iderable thickne<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hould here <U+017F>ubjoin <U+017F>everal other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Wood, if I could di<U+017F>play them without more words, than I am willing to allow them;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63097:48"/>
and I pre<U+017F>ume it may here <U+017F>uffice, if I let you <U+017F>ee by <U+017F>ome <U+017F>urprizing Effects that when Wood is reduced to that thinne<U+017F>s, that its clo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s or Poro<U+017F>ity may conveniently be examined, it will ea<U+017F>ily enough give pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, even unto vi<U+017F>ible, odorable, and tinging Corpu<U+017F>cles though they invade it not in the form of a Liquor, but of dry Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations, <U+017F>o they be not incommen<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to its Pores. This I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, you will not <U+017F>cruple to infer from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Tryals, as they were long <U+017F>ince <U+017F>et down in one of my Note-Books.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Fumes of our <U+017F>moaking Liquor [de<U+017F>cribed in the foregoing E<U+017F><U+017F>ay] tinged a Copper half penny, through a broad thin <U+017F>having of Dale, that did not, when held again<U+017F>t the window, di<U+017F>cover any perforation; tinged it, I <U+017F>ay, very deeply in about a quarter of a minute and <U+017F>omewhat le<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <U+017F>ame Fumes tinged mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>tly, but not <U+017F>o notably, the <U+017F>ame half penny fir<U+017F>t clean<U+017F>ed through two <U+017F>uch <U+017F>havings of Dale, laid one upon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63097:48"/>
another in <U+017F>omwhat le<U+017F>s than one minute.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And in about one minute the <U+017F>ame Fumes tinged the clean<U+017F>ed half penny, through three <U+017F>uch <U+017F>havings of Dale very vi<U+017F>ibly, but not <U+017F>o con<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuou<U+017F>ly, as through the two foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. The<U+017F>e Tryals were made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of heat to promote the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the Fumes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>FRom the con<U+017F>ideration of Woods let us now proceed to give <U+017F>ome In<U+017F>tances of the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies made of clo<U+017F>e and compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and perhaps well baked Clays or other Earths.</p>
               <p>That Earthen Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, thô <U+017F>trong and well bak'd, are many of them porous enough may be argued not only from what has been lately reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but from hence, that <U+017F>ome of them will <U+017F>uffer them<U+017F>elves to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63097:49"/>
<U+017F>oakt through by Oyl. Others by <U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Nitre, and <U+017F>ome other Salts. And there are very few of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excepting <hi>Ha<U+017F><U+017F>ian</hi> Crucibles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves, that will long keep Salt of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and <U+017F>uch like fixt Alcalies, in fu<U+017F>ion without being penetrated by them. I have heard Di<U+017F>tillers complain, that when they have di<U+017F>tilled corro<U+017F>ive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials, as Vitriol and Salt-Petre, with <U+017F>trong fires, in tho<U+017F>e Earthen Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that are commonly made u<U+017F>e of in <hi>London</hi> (e<U+017F>pecially by refiners) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tead of Retorts though their necks be <U+017F>trait and long (upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they are called long-necks) a con<U+017F>iderable quantity of the fine<U+017F>t Spirits make their e<U+017F>cape quite tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el; <U+017F>o that in the Retort and Receiver many ounces are found want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of the fir<U+017F>t weight of the matter to be di<U+017F>tilled. And this <U+017F>ometimes, when the Vitriol has been previou<U+017F>ly calcin'd, and a rea<U+017F>onable allowance has been made, for what may have e<U+017F>caped thorow the Lute, that joined together the long Neck and Receiver.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63097:49"/>
And <hi>though</hi> I have ob<U+017F>erved of our Bottles, made of the <U+017F>ame Earth with Juggs, that they are hard enough to <U+017F>trike Fire with a good Steel, <hi>yet</hi> a good Experimenter upon <U+017F>uch Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of whom I made enquiry, has a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me that the<U+017F>e, as compact as they are, may, even without external heat, have their Pores pervaded by the finer parts of Spirituous Liquors.</p>
               <p>To this purpo<U+017F>e I remember that meeting once with a <hi>Virtuo<U+017F>o,</hi> that was curious about the ways of making Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as brisk and <U+017F>pirituous a Liquor as he could; I enquired of him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was able to keep in the <U+017F>ubtil Spirit of this Skilfully fermented Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, in tho<U+017F>e earthen Bottles, that, by rea<U+017F>on of the <U+017F>olidity they acquire by the vehement coction of the Fire, are commonly called <hi><U+017F>tone Bottles</hi>; to which he replyed. that he often found to his trouble, that the Liquor would permeate the compact Sub<U+017F>tance of the Bottles: And when I objected that the Spirits might either e<U+017F>cape out at the Cork, which I have made <U+017F>everal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:63097:50"/>
of divers kinds that would readily permeate; he replyed, that what he had <U+017F>aid appeared by the out<U+017F>ide of the Bottles: To which when I further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that the <U+017F>ight of dew on the <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Bottles, would not convince me, without ta<U+017F>ting whether it were vinous, becau<U+017F>e I had divers times ob<U+017F>erved, that brisk Liquors would produce a dew, on the out<U+017F>ide of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that contained them, not by any tran<U+017F>udation (for I have made Tryal of it in Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es) but by conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing the aqueous vapors, di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed through the neighbouring part of the Ambient Air: He replyed that, be<U+017F>ides what his ta<U+017F>t had informed him of the quality of this dew, he found that the included Liquor, though exactly <U+017F>topt, wa<U+017F>ted in not very many Months <U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderably, as <U+017F>ometimes to lo<U+017F>e a <U+017F>ixth, or even a fifth part; &amp; this e<U+017F>cape or percolation of the Liquor through the Sub<U+017F>tance of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, he affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him<U+017F>elf to have ob<U+017F>erved, not only in one or two Bottles, but in very many and the like ob<U+017F>ervation for the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63097:50"/>
main was confirmed to me, upon his own experience, by an eminent Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, who, being a great Lover of brisk Sider, u<U+017F>ed to bottle it up early and carefully.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though</hi> good <hi>Ha<U+017F><U+017F>ian</hi> Crucibles be very clo<U+017F>ely compacted, as well as throughly baked Bodies, and upon that account are able to keep Silver and divers other Metals long in fu<U+017F>ion, without letting them at all run out; <hi>yet</hi> having di<U+017F><U+017F>olved Silver in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> I ob<U+017F>erved that, <hi>though</hi> the Salts were by this operation <U+017F>o chang'd that this horn-like Silver did di<U+017F><U+017F>olve nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> nor in the <hi>Aqua Regia</hi> that I put it into; <hi>yet</hi> when I kept it a while in fu<U+017F>ion, (which 'tis ea<U+017F>ily brought to be) among quick Coals, it would without cracking or perforating the Crucible, <U+017F>oak into it, and permeate the Pores of it, in I know not how many places, as I convinced <U+017F>ome curious per<U+017F>ons, by <U+017F>hewing them on the out<U+017F>ide of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, a multitude of minute globules of pure Silver, like <U+017F>o many little drops, that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63097:51"/>
were got thither, as it were, by tran<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>FRom baked Earths, that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igned in point of hardne<U+017F>s to emulate <U+017F>tones, we will proceed to give <U+017F>ome in<U+017F>tances of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Natural Stones them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves.</p>
               <p>There goes a tradition, that in <U+017F>ome part of the <hi>We<U+017F>t-Indies</hi> they have a Stone, of which they make large Ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els, wherein they put Water to perco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, as it were, through a <U+017F>trainer. Of the<U+017F>e Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els I had one <U+017F>ent me for a pre<U+017F>ent, whereof being hereafter to give <U+017F>ome account in a more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune place, I <U+017F>hall now only take notice that I found that Water would (thô <U+017F>lowly) <U+017F>oak through the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, thô it were con<U+017F>iderably thick.</p>
               <p>If, as many of the Ancients, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63097:51"/>
mo<U+017F>t of the modern Corpu<U+017F>cular Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<U+017F>ophers have conceived, the Tran<U+017F>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and Opacity of Bodies proceeds from a Rectitude or Crookedne<U+017F>s of Pores, which makes them fit or unfit to transmit the Light, that tends to pervade them in Phy<U+017F>ically <U+017F>traight Lines: If this <hi>Hypothe<U+017F>is,</hi> I <U+017F>ay, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, we may draw a very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument, that Stones may be Porous, from the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of that odd Gem, that is be<U+017F>t known by the name of <hi>Oculus Mundi.</hi> For this <U+017F>mall <U+017F>tone (at lea<U+017F>t that which I made my Ob<U+017F>ervations of) when 'tis dry, and is kept in the Air, is opacous, almo<U+017F>t like a poli<U+017F>hed piece of white Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and <U+017F>o it continues, as long as 'tis kept dry. But if you put it into fair water, it will in no long time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by degrees quite Tran<U+017F>parent, and that which I made Tryal of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then not unlike a piece of clear yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Amber which by degrees does in the free Air lo<U+017F>e its Tran<U+017F>parency and turn to be opacous as before. Now according to the above mentioned
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63097:52"/>
Corpu<U+017F>cular <hi>Hypothe<U+017F>is,</hi> the Pellucidne<U+017F>s which the Stone acquires in Water, may be accounted for, by <U+017F>aying, that the Liquor getting in at the crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pores of the Stone, does for the time rectify them, and make them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the <U+017F>traight Beams of Light; as we <U+017F>ee that White Paper, being wetted with Water, or, which does far better, being made <U+017F>o imbide Oyl, has its Pores <U+017F>o changed and rectified, that the Water much le<U+017F><U+017F>ens its Opacity, and makes it almo<U+017F>t Semidiaphanous and the Oyl, if it be fine and well <U+017F>oaked up, makes it Tran<U+017F>parent. But upon the rece<U+017F>s or evaporation of the imbibed Particles of Water, the Pores of the little Stone becoming crooked again reflect the Rays of light they <U+017F>hould tran<U+017F>mit. Which explication will be the better allowed of, if my memory do not mi<U+017F>inform me, when it tells me, that a learned Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Royal Society found the <hi>Oculus Mundi</hi> to weigh more in a nice ballance, when it was taken out of the Water and well wiped, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63097:52"/>
it was put in. This Stone, which very few of the writers about Gems take notice of, is <U+017F>o rare and difficult to be got, that I had not opportunity to make upon it all the Tryals I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ired; and therefore, though the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be curious, I may, I hope, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<U+017F>ed, if I ha<U+017F>ten from it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>There is <U+017F>o much difference in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Qualities betwixt Stones and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, that 'tis very probable, that when the Corpu<U+017F>cles of both come to be brought together into one Ma<U+017F>s, they will not touch one another <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e, as not to leave <U+017F>tore of little Intervals or Pores between them. And upon this ground I have been apt to think that divers very hard Stones, Diapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and Opacous, are not devoid of Poro<U+017F>ity. For I have el<U+017F>ewhere deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a way by which I have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good <U+017F>tore of Metalline parts, both from American <hi>Granats,</hi> and from <hi>Emery</hi>; though this la<U+017F>t be <U+017F>o exceeding hard a Stone, that 'tis u<U+017F>ually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by artificers to work upon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63097:53"/>
Iron and Steel, and to cut not only <hi>Rock Cry<U+017F>tal,</hi> but divers Gems that are harder than either that or Steel.</p>
               <p>Upon the <U+017F>ame ground one may probably infer the Poro<U+017F>ity of many Artificial Gems made by Fu<U+017F>ion; for to give the<U+017F>e the colour of Sapphirs, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pazes, Amethy<U+017F>ts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are wont to add to the vitrifiable matter, either <U+017F>ome prepared metal, as calcined Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>calx</hi> of Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or el<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome Mineral as <hi>Zaffora</hi> and <hi>Manganeze</hi> (as the Gla<U+017F>s-men call <hi>Magne<U+017F>ia</hi>) that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in Metalline parts. Nay I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I have <U+017F>ometimes given the colour to the vitrified <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, by imploying natural Gems, as Granats; though to <U+017F>hew that the coloration which the ma<U+017F>s received from the<U+017F>e, proceeded from the Metalline Corpu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that lay hid in the tinging matter, the Colour produced was not that which was con<U+017F>picuous in the Gem it <U+017F>elf, but one very different from it, and <U+017F>uch as the metal, which upon other accounts I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed the Gem to partake of, ought, according to the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63097:53"/>
Grounds I proceeded upon, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in the vitrifiable matter. And this very Experiment makes it al<U+017F>o highly probable, that even natural tran<U+017F>parent Gems, (divers of which are much harder than Marble, Iron &amp; even Steel) are them<U+017F>elves Porous; <U+017F>ince, notwith<U+017F>tanding their Tran<U+017F>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and <U+017F>eeming Homogeneity. They are made up of Ingredients of <U+017F>uch differing natures as are Stony and Metalline Corpu<U+017F>cles.</p>
               <p>From the <U+017F>ame Ground we may likewi<U+017F>e deduce the Poro<U+017F>ity of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ites; many of which I have ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be, not only hard enough, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to <U+017F>trike fire by colli<U+017F>ion with Steel, but more ponderous than even divers Oars, that were rich enough in Metal, to be wrought with good profit. And yet the<U+017F>e hard and heavy (Mineral) Stones are very far from being homogeneous; <U+017F>ince I have met with few Inanimate Bodies, produced by Nature her <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>o com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as <U+017F>everal Marca<U+017F>ites that I have <U+017F>een. For the<U+017F>e are wont to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63097:54"/>
more or le<U+017F>s Copper, and Iron too: and they abound in Combu<U+017F>tible Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, a Corro<U+017F>ive Salt, and a certain Fixt Sub<U+017F>tance, which I found to differ from true Earth, but of who<U+017F>e Nature the Tryals I have hitherto made on it, have but little <U+017F>atisfied me.</p>
               <p>I might here deduce the Poro<U+017F>ity of the Load-<U+017F>tone, as hard and <U+017F>olid a Body as it is, partly from the <hi>Effluvia</hi> it emits and admits, and partly from the Heterogeneity I have by Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tryals found to be in it. But the<U+017F>e things belong more properly to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per about Magnetical Bodies, for which I the more willingly re<U+017F>erve them, becau<U+017F>e other Experiments will keep them from being needful to be here in<U+017F>i<U+017F>ted on.</p>
               <p>The Poro<U+017F>ity of Marble, and divers other Stones of like Contexture, may with probability be deduc'd from this, that they are liable to be di<U+017F><U+017F>olved by divers of the corro<U+017F>ive <hi>Men<U+017F>truums</hi> of the Chymi<U+017F>ts, <U+017F>uch as <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> <U+017F>p. of Salt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <U+017F>ome of them even by Vegetable Liquors, of Natures own
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63097:54"/>
preparing, as the juice of Limons, and that of Barberries. But a more noble and <U+017F>atisfactory in<U+017F>tance may be afforded, by the invention of <U+017F>taining or colouring white Marble, without imploying any fretting Liquor, or <U+017F>poiling the Texture of it. This way being ca<U+017F>ually lighted on by an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stone-cutter in <hi>Oxford,</hi> who gained by it both credit and money, he long <U+017F>ince thought fit to acquaint me with it, upon condition of <U+017F>ecre<U+017F>y (which I have to this day inviolably kept) and of my a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ting him to improve his Invention by making it practicable with other Colours than Red. The<U+017F>e circum<U+017F>tances I mention, to <U+017F>ignify that I write not by gue<U+017F>s, of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, having both <U+017F>een the Experiment tried, and made it my <U+017F>elf. But though I found it far le<U+017F>s improvable to other u<U+017F>es, then one would expect, yet, as to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, it is very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ite. For by this way an excellent red Colour, may be made to <U+017F>oak into a piece of White Marble, almo<U+017F>t as Oyl will do into Leather, without
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63097:55"/>
impairing, that I ob<U+017F>erved, the <U+017F>oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the <U+017F>tone, which, after being dyed, will be capable of a fine glo<U+017F>s as before. Some other Colours (yet but few fair ones) would by this way be brought to <U+017F>oak into Marble, on which one may with them <U+017F>o define, and limit the Colorations, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Artificer, when I brought him to ki<U+017F>s the Kings hand, pre<U+017F>ented His Maje<U+017F>ty with an <hi>Andromeda,</hi> who<U+017F>e Colours were <U+017F>o vivid, that this skilful Judge of curious things, was plea<U+017F>ed to honour it with a place among his Rarities. And, to <U+017F>atisfy his Maje<U+017F>ty that the fine Red was not, as <U+017F>ome <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected, a mere varni<U+017F>h, I purpo<U+017F>ely broke a plate of Marble, in who<U+017F>e fragments he <U+017F>aw, that the Pigment had <U+017F>unk to a con<U+017F>iderable depth, into the very Sub<U+017F>tance of the Stone. And I doubt not but it might have been made ea<U+017F>ily enough to <U+017F>ink much deeper, if it had been thought nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary. A fine Plate of <U+017F>uch White Marble, with the penetrating Pictures of Coloured Flowers drawn upon it I
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63097:55"/>
yet keep by me to <U+017F>atisfy the curious. And <U+017F>ome Uten<U+017F>ils, as Hafts of Knives, Salt-Sellers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have known to have la<U+017F>ted <U+017F>everal years.</p>
               <p>There is an Experiment that <U+017F>eems much <U+017F>tronger for the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Solid Bodies, than that it <U+017F>elf (which was lately recited) of <U+017F>taining Marble. For in <hi>Italy</hi> <U+017F>ome Gold<U+017F>miths have a way of imbuing Fragments of Rock-Cry<U+017F>tal, which is a Body much harder than Marble, with divers Colours; which do <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>o imbelli<U+017F>h them, that having ground off tho<U+017F>e parts that would not receive the <U+017F>ame Tincture, they <U+017F>et <U+017F>ome of them in Gold Rings, and <U+017F>ell them with profit. When I was inform'd of this, I thought of a Compo<U+017F>ition, that I hop'd might perform the <U+017F>ame thing, and perhaps better than that which was employ'd by them, who either knew not, or for ought I could perceive, us'd not, <U+017F>ome Minerals that I thought fit for the purpo<U+017F>e. Upon this Pre<U+017F>umption we carefully cemented <U+017F>ome clear Fragments of Native Cry<U+017F>tal with a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63097:56"/>
Compo<U+017F>ition of <U+017F>ome Volatile Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, together with a Salt or two, and having <U+017F>uffered the Crucibles to cool lei<U+017F>urely, we had divers of the Fragments <U+017F>tain'd here and there, <U+017F>ome with one Colour and <U+017F>ome with another, as differing Fumes happen'd to invade them. And of the<U+017F>e Colours <U+017F>ome were dark or dull, and <U+017F>ome vivid enough. But having con<U+017F>ider'd the <U+017F>tain'd pieces, and the progre<U+017F>s of the Operation, more attentively, I began to doubt, whether the<U+017F>e Adventitious Colours were really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the bare penetrating of the Mineral Fumes into the Pores of the Cry<U+017F>tal it <U+017F>elf. For I thought it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, and not very unprobable, that the great Heat of the Fire, and the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Mixture, might cleave or flaw in many places <U+017F>ome of the Cry<U+017F>talline Fragments; and that the finer parts of the Minerals being vehemently agitated, might in<U+017F>inuate them<U+017F>elves into the<U+017F>e thin Flaws, which upon the <U+017F>low refrigeration of the Stones, <U+017F>hutting them<U+017F>elves clo<U+017F>e again, might
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63097:56"/>
lock up the tinging Particles, without appearing di<U+017F>continued, e<U+017F>pecially to the Eyes of Per<U+017F>ons that were not made u<U+017F>e of with a more than ordinary at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, excited by di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>t. This <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion was not removed by the apparent entirene<U+017F>s of each little piece of Cry<U+017F>tal. For having taken more than once a Lump of that <U+017F>tone, and <U+017F>lowly brought it to be red hot in the Fire, I found that if I warily quenched it in Water, though it would thereby acquire a multitude of little cracks or Flaws, which de<U+017F>troyed its former tran<U+017F>parency, and made it look whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>h, yet it continued <U+017F>till an entire Body, notwith<U+017F>tanding the di<U+017F>advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous ha<U+017F>te, wherewith the operation had been performed. And having after this <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion, inquired of an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lapidary, that belonged to a great Prince whether in poli<U+017F>hing of Gems upon the Wheel, he had taken notice that the Heat would flaw them, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wered me, that now and then he had ob<U+017F>erved that <U+017F>ome Stones, e<U+017F>pecially<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> if I mi<U+017F>remember not, Rubies, when
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63097:57"/>
they were very much heated by the <U+017F>wift motion of the Engine he employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to poli<U+017F>h them, did cleave as it <U+017F>eemed to him, and gape, <U+017F>o as at fir<U+017F>t to make him fear the Stones were <U+017F>poiled; and yet afterwards they clo<U+017F>ed <U+017F>o perfectly, that no Flaw at all could be perceived in them. I have mentioned the foregoing Experiment of tinging Cry<U+017F>tal, to comply with the dictates of Philo<U+017F>ophical candor, which forbids me to lay much <U+017F>tre<U+017F>s upon a Proof, who<U+017F>e validity I my <U+017F>elf di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>t. But perhaps my <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion may by further Tryal, which I have not now conveniency to make, appear not to have been well grounded, and in that ca<U+017F>e the tinging of Cry<U+017F>tal, as well inwardly as outwardly, by Fumes will be a noble Argument for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<U+017F>ity of Solid Bodies, Rock-Cry<U+017F>tal being harder, and probably clo<U+017F>er, not only than Marble, but even than Gla<U+017F>s.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:63097:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THat Metals, though the heavie<U+017F>t of Bodies, are not de<U+017F>titute of Pores, may be with probability proved in a general way by this; That they are all di<U+017F><U+017F>oluble in their appropriate <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> as Gold in <hi>Aqua Regia,</hi> and all the re<U+017F>t in <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> except Tin, which yet it <U+017F>elf will be corroded by that <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> though not well kept up in a fluid form, as it may be by another <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> which I el<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where teach; and <U+017F>ometimes the <U+017F>ame Metal may be di<U+017F><U+017F>olved by very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> as Lead by <hi>Aqua for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and Spirit of Vinegar; and Copper by <hi>Aqua fortis, Aqua Regia,</hi> Spirit of Vinegar, Spirit of Salt, and <U+017F>ome other Solvents, that upon Trial I have found <U+017F>ufficient for that purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>But 'twill, I pre<U+017F>ume, be thought more con<U+017F>iderable to my pre<U+017F>ent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if it be <U+017F>hewn, that Bodies that appear Gro<U+017F>s, and which in their Natural <U+017F>tate are not fluid, and are
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63097:58"/>
confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed to be of a compounded na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will penetrate Metals quite through, even without melting them.</p>
               <p>This we have divers times effected by a Cementation of Copper Plates, With common <f0><U+009F><U+009C><U+008D> (much a kin to a way pre<U+017F>cribed by <U+017F>ome Alchymi<U+017F>ts to make <hi>Vitriolum Veneris</hi>) which we warily performed much after this manner. We took good Copper lami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to the thickne<U+017F>s of a Shilling or thereabouts, and having cut it into <U+017F>mall pieces, that they might the more ea<U+017F>ily be put into a Crucible or Cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pot, we <U+017F>trewed at the bottom of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el <U+017F>ome beaten <f0><U+009F><U+009C><U+008D>, and then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it pretty well with <U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e Plates, which were laid on flat-wi<U+017F>e. Upon the<U+017F>e we <U+017F>trewed another Bed of powdered Brim<U+017F>tone, and cover'd that al<U+017F>o with Plates, upon which we put more Sulphur, &amp; <U+017F>o continu'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one lair of Brim<U+017F>tone, &amp; another of Metal, till we had employed all our Plates, or filled the Crucible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing careful that the uppermo<U+017F>t Bed, as well as the lowe<U+017F>t, <U+017F>hould be of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63097:58"/>
This done, we luted on an earthen Cover to the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, to keep the <f0><U+009F><U+009C><U+008D> from taking Fire, and afterwards having placed the Pot among<U+017F>t Coals kindled at a good di<U+017F>tance from it, that it might be heated by degrees, we kept it for <U+017F>ome few hours (perhaps Two or Three) in <U+017F>uch a degree of Fire as was <U+017F>ufficient to keep the Sulphur melted (which is ea<U+017F>ily enough done) without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Metal to fu<U+017F>ion; the Pot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold, we took off the cover, and found the Plates quite altered in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Texture, <U+017F>ome of them hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dark and dirty Colour, whil<U+017F>t others looked of a fine Violet or Blew; they were generally <U+017F>o brittle, that 'twas very ea<U+017F>y to break them with ones finger, and reduce them to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And (now to add <U+017F>uch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances as a Chymi<U+017F>t would not take notice of) many of the Plates, when they were broken, appeared to have been (by the contiguous Beds of Sulphur above and below) horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally divided each of them into two
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63097:59"/>
Plates, divers of which in <U+017F>ome places had a manife<U+017F>t di<U+017F>tance or Cavity between them. And 'twas ob<U+017F>ervable, that when I con<U+017F>idered one or other of the<U+017F>e Plates attentively in the parts that had been contiguous before I broke it, I could plainly di<U+017F>cern a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude as 'twere of Fibres, reaching from one of the flat <U+017F>ides of the Plate to the other, &amp; running many of them, as to <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, parallel to one another. The<U+017F>e Circum<U+017F>tances may <U+017F>ufficiently argue, that the Plates were pierced quite through by the Brim<U+017F>tone; but for confirmation of this, and to <U+017F>hew too that the Sulphur does as it were <U+017F>oak into the Body of the Metal, and in a Gro<U+017F>s manner lodge it <U+017F>elf there; I <U+017F>hall add, that not only to the Eye the Plates appeared much <U+017F>welled, or thicker then when they were put in, but having weighed them before the operation was begun, and after it was quite ended, the Copper, though it needed not to be freed from externally adhering Sulphur, was found to have a con<U+017F>iderable increa<U+017F>e of weight by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63097:59"/>
the acce<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the Sulphur, which (to add that circum<U+017F>tance) though it appeared not to the Eye, yet if a Plate were laid upon quick Coles, and blown, would often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times di<U+017F>cover it <U+017F>elf by a Blew flame.</p>
               <p>By making the like Experiment for the main, we found that refined Silver, though a more heavy and compact Body, than Copper, and not di<U+017F><U+017F>oluble by mo<U+017F>t of the <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> that work on this Metal, is penetrable by the Body of Sulphur, which will al<U+017F>o cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine Tin and Lead and (e<U+017F>pecially) Iron.</p>
               <p>Nor is Sulphur the only con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent Body that has this ingre<U+017F>s into Metals; for we have found them penetrable by prepared Ar<U+017F>enick. But becau<U+017F>e the<U+017F>e operations are not <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>y, and the Subject is not ea<U+017F>ily handled without danger, I forbear the mention of them in this place, where, after what has been recited, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary.</p>
               <p>Another Experiment there is,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63097:60"/>
which does more advantageou<U+017F>ly than that made with Brim<U+017F>tone, di<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Poro<U+017F>ity of Copper. For there is a way by which, without the help of Salts, Sulphur or Ar<U+017F>enick, one may make a <U+017F>olid and heavy Body <U+017F>oak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pores of that Metal, and give it a durable Colour. I <U+017F>hall not mention the way, becau<U+017F>e of the bad u<U+017F>e that may be made of it. But having had the curio<U+017F>ity more than once to try it upon a new Copper Farthing, the event was, that one part of it, which I purpo<U+017F>ely forbore to tinge, remained common Copper <U+017F>till, but the other part acquired a yellow, that differed very little, if at all, from a Golden Colour, the former <U+017F>tamp that was impre<U+017F><U+017F>ed upon the coin continuing vi<U+017F>ible. And to convince the <U+017F>crupulous, that the Pigment did really <U+017F>ink, and as it were <U+017F>oak into the Body of the Metal, and did not meerly colour the <hi>Superficies,</hi> I made them take notice, that the Farthing was not melted, and yet by filing off a wide gap from the Edge of the Coin, inwards, it plainly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:63097:60"/>
appeared, that the Yellow or Golden Colour had penetrated a pretty way beneath the <U+017F>urface of the Farthing; <U+017F>o that it looked there as if two thin Plates, the one Yellow, and the other Reddi<U+017F>h, did, without any Interval be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, lye upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>If Bodies be not to be pervaded, or deeply pierced into, by Corpu<U+017F>cles, but only to have their more <U+017F>uperficial Pores, if I may <U+017F>o call them, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby, 'tis po<U+017F><U+017F>ible that Bodies, which are either much harder, or much clo<U+017F>er, than Marble, Alaba<U+017F>ter or the like Bodies, may have their Pores po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed even by odorous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<U+017F>cles; I <U+017F>ay, <hi>even by <U+017F>uch,</hi> becau<U+017F>e they are mo<U+017F>t of them gro<U+017F>s enough to be kept from exhaling, by Bodies much le<U+017F>s compact then Earthen Bottles; and are far from being of the fine<U+017F>t particles that Nature affords. But that <U+017F>uch odorous Corpu<U+017F>cles may lodge them<U+017F>elves in the exterior Pores of very clo<U+017F>e Bodies, I have been inclined to think, <hi>not only,</hi> by the ob<U+017F>tinately
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63097:61"/>
adhering Odour, which I found by Tryal, that <U+017F>ome <U+017F>uttle and Spirituous parts, <U+017F>uch as the Chymi<U+017F>ts would perhaps call in their Aggregates, the E<U+017F><U+017F>ence of Musk, Amber, Amber-greece, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> notwith<U+017F>tanding the wa<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, that had long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <U+017F>uch Liquors; but by what has been a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me by a Phy<U+017F>ician of great Experience, who travelled and lived much in the Ea<U+017F>t. For having told him, that I had been informed, that in <U+017F>ome places le<U+017F>s famous then <hi>Dama<U+017F>cus,</hi> for curio<U+017F>ity in making fine Sword blades, there was a way found and practi<U+017F>ed of making them richly <U+017F>cented, without injury to their Glo<U+017F>s; I de<U+017F>ired to know of him, if at <hi>Dama<U+017F>cus,</hi> or el<U+017F>ewhere, he had <U+017F>een any of them; to which he replied, that he did not remember he had, but yet made no doubt the Information might be true. For he him<U+017F>elf had in <hi>Europe,</hi> and kept for divers years, a Watch, who<U+017F>e Metalline Ca<U+017F>e, was richly perfumed; and when I askt him, whether there were not <U+017F>ome
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63097:61"/>
thin varni<U+017F>h, or <U+017F>ome outward Ca<U+017F>e of perfumed Leather, or Chagran, or <U+017F>omewhat el<U+017F>e, from whence the odour proceeded, he a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me, that his ob<U+017F>ervations had prevented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved that and divers other Scruples, and that the ca<U+017F>e being clean and Glo<U+017F><U+017F>y, he could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Odour proceeded from any thing el<U+017F>e, than <U+017F>ome odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous thing, or other that was invi<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lodged in the Pores, or Porous Sub<U+017F>tance of the metal it <U+017F>elf. And indeed, <U+017F>ince both Ar<U+017F>enick, and even common Sulphur, may by Art be as it were incorporated with <U+017F>ome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, and even with Silver, I <U+017F>ee not why it <U+017F>hould be impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, that <U+017F>ome plea<U+017F>ingly <U+017F>cented Sub<U+017F>tances <U+017F>hould be admitted into the Pores of Metalline Bodies, and be volatile enough to have their <U+017F>ubtiler parts fly off in odorous Exhalations, e<U+017F>pecially if they be a little excited, as the Watch Ca<U+017F>e lately mentioned was, by a gentle heat, <U+017F>uch as was that of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63097:62"/>
wearers pocket. And on this occa<U+017F>ion I remember to have made a certain Metalline compo<U+017F>ition, which looked like Gold, and of which I cau<U+017F>ed a Ring to be ca<U+017F>t, and yet this Metal retained <U+017F>o many unperceived Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Corpu<U+017F>cles in it, that an Ingenious Per<U+017F>on to whom I di<U+017F>covered the compo<U+017F>ition of it, found after Tryal, as he a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me, that being worn as a Ring, it had in <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tempers, particularly of the Eyes, manife<U+017F>t ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that evidently enough <U+017F>eemed to flow, at lea<U+017F>t in great part, from its participation of the Mercury we employed in preparing the Factitious Metal.</p>
               <p>Since the writing of the former part of this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay, having met with an inqui<U+017F>itive Nobleman, who had lived in <U+017F>everal parts of <hi>Africk,</hi> and was Governour of the be<U+017F>t Town the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropeans</hi> have on that Continent, I di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>ed with him, among other things, about the Skill that <U+017F>ome a<U+017F>cribe to the <hi>African Moors,</hi> of making excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent weapons, whereof I knew his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:63097:62"/>
was very curious. Upon which occa<U+017F>ion he told me, that <U+017F>ome of the Off-Spring of the <hi>Granadine Moors</hi> were indeed the be<U+017F>t at making Arms that ever he met with; and that he had <U+017F>een <U+017F>ome weapons of their forging and tempering, that he preferred even to tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Dama<U+017F>co.</hi> And when I asked him whether any of them had the art of perfuming their Weapons, he an<U+017F>wered me, that <U+017F>ome of them did it admirably well, and in<U+017F>tanced in a Blade which he kept for <U+017F>ome years, &amp; found it <U+017F>till to retain the perfumed <U+017F>cent, which he <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed to be as it were incorporated with the Steel whereof the Blade was made. When I told him, I <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected that the <U+017F>cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard might have been well perfumed, and communicate its odour to the contained Blade, he allowed the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to be plau<U+017F>ible, but replyed<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> that it was not concluding, <U+017F>ince mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking the Scabbard, as not hand<U+017F>om &amp; fa<U+017F>hionable enough, he cau<U+017F>ed a new one to be made, wherein he afterwards kept it. And the <U+017F>ame Lord further
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63097:63"/>
told me, that he had al<U+017F>o a Fowling Piece, who<U+017F>e Barrel was perfumed. And when I objected that perhaps the odoriferous <U+017F>cent proceeded from the <U+017F>tock, and not from the Metal, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wered that the Gun not being, when it came into his po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion, skilfully and hand<U+017F>omely mounted, he cau<U+017F>ed the Barrel to be fitted with a new <U+017F>tock, notwith<U+017F>tanding which, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to <U+017F>mell fragrantly. And when I further asked, whether he ever cau<U+017F>ed the Gun to be wa<U+017F>hed or <U+017F>coured after it was grown foul by having been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <U+017F>hot in, he an<U+017F>wered me, that he had, and, as far as I can remember, <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, that after it was made clean it did (notwith<U+017F>tanding the ill <U+017F>cent that the <U+017F>oot of the Powder had given it) retain a plea<U+017F>ing <U+017F>mell, but fainter than before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:63097:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>SInce the Subject of this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay is the <hi>Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Solid Bodies,</hi> and <U+017F>ince there is no Body that is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally reputed <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>e and compact as Gla<U+017F>s, it will be pertinent to this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, and probably will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that I <U+017F>hould here <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething about the Que<U+017F>tion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gla<U+017F>s be, or be not, devoid of Pores.</p>
               <p>But before I acquaint you with my Tryals, or my thoughts, about this Problem, I think it requi<U+017F>ite to clear the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, in which I mean to handle it, that I may not, as <U+017F>ome others have done, for want of di<U+017F>tinctly <U+017F>tating the Que<U+017F>tion, <U+017F>peak confu<U+017F>edly and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neou<U+017F>ly of it.</p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hall then here ob<U+017F>erve, to prevent mi<U+017F>takes, that the Poro<U+017F>ity of Gla<U+017F>s may admit of two Acceptions. For it may be <U+017F>aid to be quite pervious to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63097:64"/>
Fluids, as a Boot is to Water, or only to be capable of having its <U+017F>uperficial parts further and further di<U+017F><U+017F>olved or corroded thereby, as a Silver Cup is Porous in reference to <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> which cannot <U+017F>weat through it, as Water does through a Boot, but eat its way through it, by di<U+017F><U+017F>olving the Texture of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el.</p>
               <p>Another thing requi<U+017F>ite to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>ed, to prevent Ambiguity, is, that Gla<U+017F>s it <U+017F>elf is not all of one <U+017F>ort, as men unacquainted with Chymi<U+017F>try are wont to pre<U+017F>ume, for Gla<U+017F>s of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, for in<U+017F>tance, and that of Lead, both of them made <hi>per <U+017F>e,</hi> do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>tly differ, u<U+017F>ually in colour, and con<U+017F>tantly in weight, and al<U+017F>o in their operations upon Humane Bodies; and both the<U+017F>e <U+017F>orts of Gla<U+017F>s do in <U+017F>everal points differ from <hi>common Gla<U+017F>s,</hi> under which name, for brevities <U+017F>ake, I comprehend both White or Cry<U+017F>talline Gla<U+017F>s, as 'tis called in the Shops, and that cour<U+017F>er <U+017F>ort, which they u<U+017F>ually call Green Gla<U+017F>s; both which <U+017F>orts I here con<U+017F>ider under one Notion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:63097:64"/>
both are made of fixt Alcalies, and other fit Ingredients, as Sand, Earth, A<U+017F>hes, Pebbles, or Flints, Colliquated by a <U+017F>trong &amp; la<U+017F>ting ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Fire: and 'tis of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Gla<U+017F>s, in the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e now declared, that I <U+017F>hall con<U+017F>ider the Poro<U+017F>ity in the remaining part of this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay. In which to proceed with <U+017F>ome Method, I <U+017F>hall dige<U+017F>t what I have to <U+017F>ay into the en<U+017F>uing Propo<U+017F>itions, and the ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations annext to them.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Prop 1.</hi> 'Tis very probable, that Gla<U+017F>s may be pierced into to <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance, even by vi<U+017F>ible and tangible Bodies.</q>
               <p>I know that this will <U+017F>eem a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox to many, and repugnant to common Experience, which <U+017F>hews that Gla<U+017F>s Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els will contain very <U+017F>ubtile and even highly corro<U+017F>ive Liquors, as the Spirit of Hart<U+017F>horn, of Urine, and that of Nitre; as al<U+017F>o tho<U+017F>e potent <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> as <hi>Aqua fortis, Aqua Regis,</hi> and Oil of Vitriol,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63097:65"/>
which not only are not ob<U+017F>erved to pierce into it, but are unable to make any <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible alteration, <U+017F>o much as on the <U+017F>uperficial parts, even in tho<U+017F>e Vials wherein they have been long kept.</p>
               <p>But, notwith<U+017F>tanding all this, I pre<U+017F>ume you will not condemn the lately propo<U+017F>ed Paradox, when you have con<U+017F>idered what may be <U+017F>aid to ju<U+017F>tifie it. For, be<U+017F>ides that it may be made probable <hi>à Priori,</hi> by the Arguments whence we have formerly proved the Porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Solid Bodies in general; there are two <U+017F>orts of Experiments, from whence one may argue, that Gla<U+017F>s in particular is not devoid of Pores in the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e wherein we are now <U+017F>peak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
               <p>And fir<U+017F>t, I remember, that, having kept for a good while in a vial, a quantity of a certain Spirit of Salt, that I had re<U+017F>erved in a cool place; I found, when I came to u<U+017F>e it, that the Gla<U+017F>s was crackt, and mo<U+017F>t of the Liquor was run out; but, before this
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:63097:65"/>
happened, it had <U+017F>o far corroded the in<U+017F>ide of the Gla<U+017F>s, that in <U+017F>ome places it was eaten almo<U+017F>t as thin as a piece of Paper; and this part which yet continued Gla<U+017F>s, was lin'd with a much thicker white <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, that <U+017F>tuck to the <U+017F>ides of it, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ta<U+017F>ted like a kind of odd Salt; <U+017F>o that it invited me to conjecture, that it proceeded from the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Gla<U+017F>s, which you know con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts of an <hi>Alcali</hi> as well as of <hi>Sand</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roded by the Saline Spirits of the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> and coagulated with them into this odd kind of Concrete; and 'twas remarkable in our ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, that the upper part of the vial, to which the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> did not reach, was not corroded, nor alter'd, tho the operation of the Liquor reached as high as the Liquor it <U+017F>elf. And I remember, that when I related all this to <U+017F>ome experienced Chymi<U+017F>ts, one of them that was a more heedful ob<U+017F>erver, a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me, the like had once or twice, happened to him, as <U+017F>ince that time it hath likewi<U+017F>e done to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:63097:66"/>I had al<U+017F>o, if I mi<U+017F>remember not, another Vial, corroded by a di<U+017F>tilled Liquor of Vitriol, that had in it more of the Phlegm than of the Oil; which you will <U+017F>omewhat the le<U+017F>s wonder at, if you con<U+017F>ider, that <U+017F>ome Corro<U+017F>ive <hi>Men<U+017F>truums</hi> will <U+017F>carce work on <U+017F>ome Bodys, if they be too well dephlegmed, or at lea<U+017F>t will not corrode them <U+017F>o readily and powerfully, if they are very <U+017F>trong, as when they are diluted with a convenient quantity of Water. And, as to Oil of Vitriol it <U+017F>elf, which is the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> I am <U+017F>peaking of, when we employ it to make <hi>Vitriolum Martis,</hi> we are wont to weaken it with Water, that it may the better di<U+017F><U+017F>olve that Metal. And perhaps you will <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect, that Vitriol has <U+017F>ome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar faculty of penetrating and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gla<U+017F>s, when to the Experiment newly recited I <U+017F>hall add that which follows, as I find it regi<U+017F>tred among my Notes.</p>
               <p>[A pound of <hi>Dantzick</hi> Vitriol and a pound of Sea Salt, after the former had been very lightly calcined, and the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63097:66"/>
latter decrepitated, that they might not boil in, or crack the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el; we cau<U+017F>ed to be di<U+017F>tilled in a well coated Retort by degrees of Fire, giving at length a very <U+017F>trong one, then taking off the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, we were not much <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to find, that the heat had here and there melted it, and that the fluxed <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> had corroded the Gla<U+017F>s, fetching off as 'twere films from it, and tho<U+017F>e parts which did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Eye thus manife<U+017F>tly wa<U+017F>ted, <U+017F>eemed yet by their great brittlene<U+017F>s, to have been penetrated, <U+017F>o that their Texture was <U+017F>poiled by the <U+017F>aline and vitriolate Corpu<U+017F>cles.]</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Prop II.</hi> Common Gla<U+017F>s is not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily permeable by Chymical Liquors, though <U+017F>trong and <U+017F>ubtile, nor by the directly vi<U+017F>ible or odorable Expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Bodies tho ab<U+017F>olutely <U+017F>peaking it be pervious to <U+017F>ome Corporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances.</q>
               <p>This Propo<U+017F>ition con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of two parts, we <U+017F>hall allow each of them its di<U+017F>tinct Proofs.</p>
               <p>And as for the fir<U+017F>t part, 'tis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nife<U+017F>tly
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63097:67"/>
agreeable to the Common Experience of Chymi<U+017F>ts; who dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find, that in well <U+017F>topt Vials, or at lea<U+017F>t in Hermetically <U+017F>eal'd Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, they can pre<U+017F>erve their <U+017F>ubtile<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t piercing <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> as Spirit of <hi>Nitre, Aqua Fortis,</hi> Spirit of Salt, Spirit of Vinegar, and Oil of Vitriol. And this they find to be true, not only as to Acid and Corro<U+017F>ive Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, like tho<U+017F>e I have newly nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but al<U+017F>o in tho<U+017F>e Spirits that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Fugitive Salts, as the Spirit of Urine, of Blood, and of <hi>Sal-Armoniack</hi>; and in the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile &amp; highly rectified Spirit of Wine; as al<U+017F>o in the Ethereal Oil, or, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny call it, Spirit, of Turpentine: as likewi<U+017F>e in the Liquors of Salt of Tartar, and other fixt Alcalies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved by <hi>Deliquium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Re<U+017F>ult of the<U+017F>e Ob<U+017F>erva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be much confirmed by con<U+017F>idering, how often it happens in the De<U+017F>tillation of more Wild and Fugitive Spirits, as of Nitre, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and Sugar; that, though they
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63097:67"/>
are much agitated, and perhaps <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilized, by Heat, yet, if the Lute, that joins the Receiver to the Retort be very firm &amp; clo<U+017F>e, the Receivers, though large, are often broken in pieces; which probably would not happen, if the Spirits could in<U+017F>inuate &amp; croud them<U+017F>elves, through the pores of Gla<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>But, whereas it may be pretended, that <U+017F>uch Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els are <U+017F>trong and thick, I <U+017F>hall add, that I have had the Curio<U+017F>ity to cau<U+017F>e very fine bubbles to be blown at the flame of a Lamp, purpo<U+017F>ly that they may be made extreamly thin, and of but a <U+017F>mall part of the thickne<U+017F>s we meet with in the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els made at the Gla<U+017F>s hou<U+017F>e; and <U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e I caus'd to be exactly <U+017F>topt, and others to be Hermetically <U+017F>eal'd; but could not find, that either dry Salt of Tartar would relent in one, that was kept a good while under water, or that <U+017F>trong Spirit of <hi>Sal Armoniack,</hi> which is one of the <U+017F>ubtile<U+017F>t Spirits that we know, would penetrate one of the<U+017F>e thin films of Gla<U+017F>s, which we kept
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63097:68"/>
a great while immer<U+017F>ed in it, though to di<U+017F>cover whether it would at all penetrate the thinne<U+017F>t Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, we employed <U+017F>ome which were of that fine <U+017F>ort that is called <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ence Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The<U+017F>e and <U+017F>ome other Tryals have, I confe<U+017F>s, made me very diffident of the Experiments, that have been delivered by <U+017F>ome men of Note, and built upon by others, of the Permeablene<U+017F>s of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gla<U+017F>s Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to Chymical Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, as, that Mercury and <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> being dige<U+017F>ted together in a Bolt-head may, by rubbing the out<U+017F>ide of the Gla<U+017F>s, be made vi<U+017F>ibly and palpably to tran<U+017F>udate. Which Experiment (if my Memory do not much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me,) I purpo<U+017F>ely tryed with care, but without <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>But after all this I mu<U+017F>t de<U+017F>ire, that it may be remembred, that in wording the Propo<U+017F>ition of the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of Gla<U+017F>s, I intimated that I would have it under<U+017F>tood of what <hi>Ordinarily</hi> happens. For in <U+017F>ome <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> ca<U+017F>es, which I take to be exceeding rare, I do not ab<U+017F>olutely
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:63097:68"/>
deny, but that the General rule may admit of Exceptions. And, if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to conjecture, the<U+017F>e exceptions are likelie<U+017F>t to take place, when the peculiar Texture of this or that Gla<U+017F>s, is more <U+017F>light or lax than ordinary; or when the Bodies that are to pervade it, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently agitated by heat; or when, be<U+017F>ides a great <U+017F>ubtlety, and perhaps degree of heat too, their particles chance to have a <U+017F>pecial congruity, to the relaxed Pores of that particular Gla<U+017F>s they are to pa<U+017F>s through. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I have <U+017F>een, not without <U+017F>ome wonder, a <U+017F>ort of Gla<U+017F>s of <U+017F>o <U+017F>oft and re<U+017F>oluble a Texture, that Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of it of a competent thickne<U+017F>s, would be manife<U+017F>tly prejudiced and wrought upon by Liquors, that were not con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably Sharp or Corro<U+017F>ive, if they were put in very hot. I have al<U+017F>o heard of another <U+017F>ort of Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, made in a certain Forre<U+017F>t, complained of by a De<U+017F>tiller, as <U+017F>ubject to be <U+017F>ometimes injured by Corro<U+017F>ive Liquors. I once knew a Doctor of Phy<U+017F>ick, that by divers credulous Alchymi<U+017F>ts was <U+017F>u<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63097:69"/>
to have, what they call the <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophers Stone,</hi> becau<U+017F>e of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Book, Ingenious enough, that he was <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed to have written on that <U+017F>ubject. But when after <U+017F>ome acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I happened to debate his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples freely with him, he confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed to me, that he had been mi<U+017F>taken, and to invite me to give him my thoughts upon <U+017F>uch like works, he frankly made me an ingenuous relation of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, wherein the main thing that dazled him, and kept him from <U+017F>eeing his Error, was, that he had reduced the matter he wrought on, which was real Gold, to that degree of Fu<U+017F>ible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>ubtlety, that when he gave too <U+017F>trong a Fire, as mi<U+017F>take or curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity made him <U+017F>everal times do, the finer part of the Metal would <U+017F>weat through his Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, and <U+017F>tick <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the out<U+017F>ide of them, and <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the Neighbouring Bodies. And, when I objected, that he might be mi<U+017F>taken in this, and that what he thought had come forth by tran<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, rather i<U+017F><U+017F>ued out at <U+017F>ome
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63097:69"/>
<U+017F>mall unheeded crack, he replyed that he had made the ob<U+017F>ervation <U+017F>o often, and with <U+017F>uch care, that he was fully <U+017F>atisfied it was a real penetration of the Gla<U+017F>s, by the attenuated Metal, which he was to have convinced me of by Tryal. But, before he could come to make it, by an Errour of his own he unhappily died.</p>
               <p>But, whatever be judged of this penetrating Gold, I el<U+017F>ewhere relate, that I having upon a time de<U+017F>tilled Spirit of Harts-horn with a very <U+017F>trong Fire, into a Receiver that was large and thick enough, but of a cour<U+017F>e kind of Gla<U+017F>s, it did appear, upon my be<U+017F>t examination, that the Gla<U+017F>s it<U+017F>elf was penetrated by <U+017F>ome vehemently agitated Fumes, or <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ubtile Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, that <U+017F>etled in <U+017F>trongly <U+017F>cented drops on the out<U+017F>ide of the Receiver. But <U+017F>uch In<U+017F>tances being very rare, and happening but in <U+017F>ome ca<U+017F>es or conjunctures of circum<U+017F>tances, that are not like to be at all frequent, they cannot hinder the fir<U+017F>t part of our Propo<U+017F>ition to be true, in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63097:70"/>
the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e wherein 'tis laid down.</p>
               <p>And, as to the <U+017F>econd part of the Propo<U+017F>ition, which <hi>a<U+017F><U+017F>erts Gla<U+017F>s to be pervious to <U+017F>ome Corporeal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances,</hi> it may be proved <hi>ad hominem</hi> again<U+017F>t any Epicurean that <U+017F>hould deny it, and the Carte<U+017F>ians mu<U+017F>t not) by the free ingre<U+017F>s and egre<U+017F>s, which our <U+017F>eal'd Thermo<U+017F>copes <U+017F>hew, that the Atoms or Corpu<U+017F>cles of Cold and Heat are allowed, through the Pores of the Gla<U+017F>s, that contains the ri<U+017F>ing or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lng Tincture, or other Liquor. And without proceeding upon the peculiar Principles of the Epicureans, we may give more certain proofs of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meablene<U+017F>s of Gla<U+017F>s by certain Bodies. For I have el<U+017F>ewhere manife<U+017F>tly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tone will attract and invigorate Steel, though inclo<U+017F>ed in Hermetically <U+017F>eal'd Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es; nay, I have al<U+017F>o <U+017F>hewn by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, that the <hi>Effluvia</hi> of <U+017F>o gro<U+017F>s and dull a Body as the Earth, are readily tran<U+017F>mitted through Gla<U+017F>s, and will operate on Iron, in Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els hermeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <U+017F>ealed. If Light be, as probably
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63097:70"/>
'tis, either a <U+017F>ubtile and rapidly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Body, or at lea<U+017F>t require <U+017F>uch an one for its Vehicle, it mu<U+017F>t not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that 'tis po<U+017F><U+017F>ible for a Body without difficulty to pa<U+017F>s through the Pores of Gla<U+017F>s; <U+017F>ince 'tis by its help that we can clearly <U+017F>ee the Dimen<U+017F>ions, Shapes, and Colours of Bodies inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es. To this I <U+017F>hall add, that far le<U+017F>s <U+017F>ubtile Bodies than tho<U+017F>e that con<U+017F>titute or convey Light, may be made to permeate Gla<U+017F>s, if their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures being congruous enough to the Pores of it, their penetration be a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an impetuous motion, or a brisk impul<U+017F>e; as I have found by the increa<U+017F>e of weight in <U+017F>ome Metals, expo<U+017F>ed for divers hours in Hermeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <U+017F>eal'd Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, to the action of a Flame. On which occa<U+017F>ion I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that having <U+017F>ome years ago tryed the <U+017F>ame Experiment with <U+017F>ome Filings of Copper, they had indeed their colour much alter'd, being beautified with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vivid Dyes, which they yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but did not evidently appear to be increa<U+017F>ed in weight, as if, becau<U+017F>e
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63097:71"/>
they were not of a Texture loo<U+017F>e enough to be melted, the Igneous particles could not pierce them enough to <U+017F>tick fa<U+017F>t in them, at lea<U+017F>t in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers great enough, to amount to a <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible weight.</p>
               <p>But without the help of Fire, or any <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Heat, I think it not impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible that Gla<U+017F>s <U+017F>hould be freely penetrated by <U+017F>ome kind of Corpu<U+017F>cles, (though I do not yet know of what <U+017F>ort they are) that <U+017F>ometimes happen to roave about in the Air. This you will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be <U+017F>urprized to read; but perhaps not more than I was at the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> that induce me to write it. But becau<U+017F>e the<U+017F>e are very unu<U+017F>ual, and can <U+017F>carce be di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>ed of without <U+017F>ome odd reflections hinted by them, I thought fit to <U+017F>et down a Circum<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial account of them in another Paper, to which it more directly belongs than to this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay; and therefore <U+017F>hall now only tell you, what may be <U+017F>ufficient for my pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, namely, that having in two or three Vials clo<U+017F>ely <U+017F>topt, kept a certain limpid and colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63097:71"/>
Liquor, it would by fits acquire and lo<U+017F>e a high Colour, though I could not rea<U+017F>onably impute the Changes to any manife<U+017F>t ones in the Air, nor to any other cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>o proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the Ingre<U+017F>s and Rece<U+017F>s of <U+017F>ome very <U+017F>ubtle and uncommon particles, which at that time happened to <U+017F>wim to and fro in the Air, and now and then to invade, and <U+017F>ometimes to de<U+017F>ert, the Liquor.</p>
               <p>There is another <U+017F>ort of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments relating to the Poro<U+017F>ity of Gla<U+017F>s, to <U+017F>hew that it may be pierced into by Bodies that are not corro<U+017F>ive in ta<U+017F>t, and are not Liquors, but only have a forced and temporary Fluidity, if they have <U+017F>o much as that.</p>
               <p>The<U+017F>e Experiments may be drawn from <hi><U+017F>ome of the ways</hi> of colouring Panes of Gla<U+017F>s, for the Windows of Churches and other buildings; I <U+017F>ay, <hi><U+017F>ome of the ways,</hi> becau<U+017F>e, to deal can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly with you, I think, and <U+017F>o I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ume will you ere long, that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of tho<U+017F>e Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, the Colour doth not pierce at all deep into the Gla<U+017F>s,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:63097:72"/>
but is produced by the clo<U+017F>e adhe<U+017F>ion of a deep Red, but thin and tran<U+017F>parent, Pigment, to the <U+017F>urface of a Gla<U+017F><U+017F>y Plate, through both which the Beams of Light pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing to the Eye, receive in their Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age the colour of the Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But, as by <U+017F>ome operations the Gla<U+017F>s is rather Painted, or externally enamelled, than tinged, <U+017F>o in <U+017F>ome others the Pigment or dying <U+017F>tuff ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to pierce a little beneath the very <hi><U+017F>uperficies</hi> of the Gla<U+017F>s, and the Yellow Colour will not only go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or deeper, but <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>eems (for I do not yet po<U+017F>itively affirm it) to penetrate the whole Gla<U+017F>s from <U+017F>ide to <U+017F>ide.</p>
               <p>The Methods of Painting and <U+017F>taining Gla<U+017F>s, having been hitherto the Practices of a particular Trade that is gainful enough, and known but to few, the Artificers are wont to be <U+017F>hy of communicating their <U+017F>ecrets, thô we know in general that Gla<U+017F>s is <U+017F>tained, by having the Plates covered with Mineral Pigments, laid on Beds of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:63097:72"/>
beaten Lime, or <U+017F>ome other conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Powder, and kept for divers Hours in a <U+017F>trong fire, but yet not <U+017F>trong enough to make the Plates melt down, by which means the Pores of the Gla<U+017F>s being much opened by the Heat, and the Pigments being likewi<U+017F>e agitated, and <U+017F>ome of them as it were vitrified with it, they are made either to pierce into the Plate, or at lea<U+017F>t to <U+017F>tick very clo<U+017F>ely and firmly to it. But becau<U+017F>e the Practices of Gla<U+017F>s Painters require, be<U+017F>ides skill and experience, a particular Furnace, and divers Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, I <U+017F>hall add, that to try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gla<U+017F>s may not, without <U+017F>o much ado, be <U+017F>o <U+017F>tained, as to <U+017F>hew it to be Porous, we took prepared Silver, (that Metal having, of all the Minerals I have tryed, the be<U+017F>t Ingre<U+017F>s into Gla<U+017F>s) and having laid it upon a piece of Gla<U+017F>s, not thick, nor yet <U+017F>o thin as to Melt very ea<U+017F>ily, we laid this Gla<U+017F>s (with the Pigment uppermo<U+017F>t) wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily upon a few Quick-coals, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <U+017F>uffered it to neal a while we gave it about <U+017F>uch a degree of heat, as might
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63097:73"/>
make and keep it red hot, without bringing it to compleat fu<U+017F>ion, and then, <U+017F>uffering it to cool by degrees, we found, as we expected, that the Gla<U+017F>s had acquired a Yellow, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t Golden, Colour, which was not to be wa<U+017F>hed off, or to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, without <U+017F>uch <U+017F>craping as would injure or <U+017F>poil the Gla<U+017F>s it <U+017F>elf. The way of preparing Silver for this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is not always the <U+017F>ame, the Gla<U+017F>s Painters commonly add to the calcined Silver <U+017F>ome Mineral Bodies, as Antimony, Yellow Oker, or the like. But I, who take the penetration of the colour to proceed from the Silver it <U+017F>elf, do <U+017F>ometimes imploy only <U+017F>ome thin piece of Silver, <U+017F>uch as an old Groat, upon which a little Sulphur being put, and kindled in the open Air, the Metal is pre<U+017F>ently calcined, and the Powder made u<U+017F>e of. And this it <U+017F>elf I do not <U+017F>o much out of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ity, as becau<U+017F>e the Calcination re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the Metal into <U+017F>mall parts, and gives it a form, that makes it more ea<U+017F>y be laid on, as one thinks fit. For
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63097:73"/>
otherwi<U+017F>e, going upon this my <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Silver was the true Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Gla<U+017F>s, I have more than once made Gla<U+017F>s Yellow by Leaf-Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver laid flat on the <U+017F>urface of it, and a little moi<U+017F>tened, to keep <U+017F>o light a Body from being blown off. And (to note that upon the by) 'tis pretty, that if the Fire be made too <U+017F>trong, which 'tis hard to avoid doing, when we will make it <U+017F>trong enough, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a Furnace, it has <U+017F>everal times happened to me that the dyed Gla<U+017F>s, though when held again<U+017F>t the Light it appeared of a Golden or Yellow Colour, yet when held from the Light it appeared Blew, <U+017F>o that here we have in a Mineral, <U+017F>omewhat that is very like that we admire in the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Lignum Nephriticum,</hi> which <U+017F>hews almo<U+017F>t the like difference of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, as 'tis held again<U+017F>t or from the Light, which may <U+017F>erve for a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what I have el<U+017F>ewhere <U+017F>aid to <U+017F>hew that colours may be derived from Mechanical Principles: But that only upon the by. Whether the Gold
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63097:74"/>
colour produced by Silver, do favour the hopes of tho<U+017F>e Alchymi<U+017F>ts that work on that Metal, upon pre<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that 'tis but unripe Gold, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper here to examine. But <U+017F>ince Yellow is not the Colour of Silver, it <U+017F>eems the Yellowne<U+017F>s, acquired by our Gla<U+017F>s Plates, argues, that there has been <U+017F>ome ingre<U+017F>s of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the particles of the Silver into the Gla<U+017F>s, there appearing no way <U+017F>o ready, to give an account of the change of Colours, as by <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing the Particles of the Silver to be wrought on by the fixt Salts, and other fine parts, of the Gla<U+017F>s; <U+017F>ince we know, that Metals may afford differing colours, according to the Saline and other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that work upon them, as Copper with Spirit of Urine, which abounds in Volatile Salt, gives a deep Blew; with Spirit of Salt, a fair Green; and with <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> a Colour that participates of both. And in the making of Gla<U+017F>s of Lead with <hi>Minium</hi> and White-Sand, or Cry<U+017F>tal, the Gla<U+017F>s, it <U+017F>elf if well made, is u<U+017F>ually of an Amethy<U+017F>tine Colour. But
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63097:74"/>
if you put a due Proportion, (which is a very <U+017F>mall one,) of calcined Copper to it, this Metal will not communicate to the Gla<U+017F>s its own reddi<U+017F>hne<U+017F>s, but be <U+017F>o changed by it, as to give it a good green, and <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>o good an one, that pieces of this Gla<U+017F>s, <U+017F>uch as we have cau<U+017F>ed to be cut and <U+017F>et in Rings, might, among tho<U+017F>e that Judge of Stones but by the Eye, pa<U+017F>s for no bad <hi>Emeraulds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On this occa<U+017F>ion, 'tis likely 'twill be asked, whether there be any way of tinging Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es quite through, with a true and beautiful red, and whether the Art of dying Plates of Gla<U+017F>s, which the windows of many old Churches <U+017F>hew to have formerly been practi<U+017F>ed, be now (as 'tis commonly <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed) altogether lo<U+017F>t?</p>
               <p>This Que<U+017F>tion, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of 2 Parts, I <U+017F>hall quickly di<U+017F>patch; the former, by an<U+017F>wering it without he<U+017F>itancy in the affirmative. Yet adding withal, that the red tincture being communicated to Gla<U+017F>s, not properly by mere penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pigment, but by the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63097:75"/>
of it with Gla<U+017F>s or its Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, by the help of fu<U+017F>ion, I think the Experiment of no <U+017F>uch great u<U+017F>e in our pre<U+017F>ent Inquiry, as to hinder me from re<U+017F>erving what I have ob<U+017F>erved about it to a more opportune place. And as to the <U+017F>econd Part of the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it being rather a Hi<U+017F>torical than a Philo<U+017F>ophical que<U+017F>tion, I <U+017F>hall not here meddle with it; only I <U+017F>hall wi<U+017F>h the que<U+017F>tion may be cautiou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>tated. For, upon the burning the famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> many pieces of the red Gla<U+017F>s that adorned the windows, were found broken and <U+017F>cattered about, <U+017F>ome of which I procur'd from a Chymi<U+017F>t, that had carefully pre<U+017F>erved them, de<U+017F>ign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to retrieve the lo<U+017F>t Invention of making the like. But when I came to examine them narrowly, I was confirmed in the <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion I had, that the redne<U+017F>s did not penetrate the whole Gla<U+017F>s, but proceeded from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphanous Pigment very artificially laid on, for though in other Po<U+017F>tures no <U+017F>uch thing could be di<U+017F>cerned, yet
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:63097:75"/>
when I <U+017F>o held it, according to my Cu<U+017F>tom in examining painted Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, that the <U+017F>urfaces of the Plate lay in the <U+017F>ame level with my Eye, between it and the window, <U+017F>o that a broken edge was next my Eye, I could plainly <U+017F>ee, and made the Chymi<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>ee, the lower part of the Plate to be of ordinary uncoloured Gla<U+017F>s, upon which there lay a very thin Plate or Bed of a Diaphanous red Pigment, which, though it were not ea<U+017F>ily, was not impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be here and there <U+017F>craped off.</p>
               <p>But, to return to tho<U+017F>e colorations that <U+017F>eem to pierce into the Pores of Gla<U+017F>s, I remember that I had once oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ion to de<U+017F>til in a <U+017F>mall Retort <U+017F>ome Gold, amalgamed with <U+017F>uch a fine and <U+017F>ubtile Mercury, that being (without the addition of any Salt) put to the Gold in the cold, they pre<U+017F>ently grew hot together. And in the de<U+017F>tillation of this uncommon mixture, I found the matter had, before it flew a way, permanently died or <U+017F>tained, about an Inch in Diameter of the bottom of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:63097:76"/>
Gla<U+017F>s, with a colour that, looked on from the Light, was like that of the better <U+017F>ort of Turquoi<U+017F>es; but beheld when 'twas interpo<U+017F>ed between the Window and the Eye, appeared of a <U+017F>omewhat Golden colour. And this Gla<U+017F>s, with <U+017F>ome others oddly colored, I have yet by me to <U+017F>atisfy the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though I cannot but give Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>ement, that the colorations of Gla<U+017F>s may be much better performed with <U+017F>uch Plates, and in <U+017F>uch Furnaces, as the Gla<U+017F>s Painters u<U+017F>e, than without them.</p>
               <p>Since the Writing of the foregoing Paragraph, I was vi<U+017F>ited by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<U+017F>trious per<U+017F>on, much addicted to <U+017F>ome Chymical Operations, who had formerly advi<U+017F>ed with me about a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s, of which I had had <U+017F>ome Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that he conceived might be u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him. I then acquainted him with <U+017F>ome of my thoughts about it, and he having afterwards united Gold with Quick-Silver, (which by its Effects will be ea<U+017F>ily concluded not to have been common,) he kept them in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<U+017F>tion
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63097:76"/>
for <U+017F>ome Months, &amp; afterwards coming to me with a Melancholy look, told me that the Fire having been once immoderately increa<U+017F>ed in his ab<U+017F>ence, the <U+017F>ealed-Gla<U+017F>s bur<U+017F>t with an affrighting noi<U+017F>e, and the included Amalgam was <U+017F>o <U+017F>trangely di<U+017F><U+017F>ipated, that <U+017F>carce the le<U+017F>t fragment of it could be retrieved. But the Decoction hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued <U+017F>o long a time, it <U+017F>eems the matter was <U+017F>ubtiliated enough to have a notable operation upon the Gla<U+017F>s. For, though the upper part of the Bolt-gla<U+017F>s were blown of, and <U+017F>hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into many pieces, yet the lower part <U+017F>caped well enough, and when he brought it me, to ob<U+017F>erve what change had been made in it, I took notice with much delight, that the Gla<U+017F>s <U+017F>eemed to be tinged throughout, with <U+017F>o fine and glorious a Red colour, that I have <U+017F>een <U+017F>everal Rubies them<U+017F>elves, in that point, inferiour to it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

