<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great Scanderberg a novel / done out of French.</title>
            <title>Scanderberg. English. 1690</title>
            <author>Chevreau, Urbain, 1613-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16992999</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16992999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A32798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1611:54)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great Scanderberg a novel / done out of French.</title>
                  <title>Scanderberg. English. 1690</title>
                  <author>Chevreau, Urbain, 1613-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of the author's Scanderberg.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained, and tightly bound, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:105648:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:105648:1"/>
THE GREAT <hi>SCANDERBERG:</hi> A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>Done out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> at the <hi>Po<U+017F>t-Hou<U+017F>e,</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>el-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105648:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105648:2"/>
            <head>To the Honoured Madam <hi>JEPHSON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COuld the exactne<U+017F>s of this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance but equal the greatne<U+017F>s of my Subject, or that Goodne<U+017F>s that put me upon it, I <U+017F>hould then have done that out of Choice, which I do now out of Obedience.</p>
            <p>Nothing le<U+017F>s than your Commands could have ingag'd me in the Attempt, and nothing le<U+017F>s than your Character could have protected me in it.</p>
            <p>Indeed my Hero is all Glory and Triumph, but yet he a<U+017F><U+017F>ures me this is his highe<U+017F>t; and that he is more warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with the Dedication, than with the Succe<U+017F>s of his Adventures. But, Madam, what e're his Satisfactions may be, mine mu<U+017F>t be allow'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them, on whom you have lain
<pb facs="tcp:105648:3"/>
<U+017F>o many Obligations, that I mu<U+017F>t own them greater than all things, but the Genero<U+017F>ity that conferr'd them, or the Humility that receiv'd them; and which to acknowledge, <U+017F>hall be as much the endeavours, as 'tis now the de<U+017F>ires of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your mo<U+017F>t Oblig'd, mo<U+017F>t humble, and mo<U+017F>t devoted Servant.
N. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105648:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IF Love is a Weakne<U+017F>s, one mu<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>s there is none that ought <U+017F>ooner to be excu<U+017F>ed, or that is Authori<U+017F>ed by <U+017F>o many Examples. It would be a hard matter to find a Man of any Note, who has never been in Love: The greate<U+017F>t Heroes could not defend them<U+017F>elves again<U+017F>t its Power, and they valued their Crowns of Myrtle, no le<U+017F>s than tho<U+017F>e of Laurel; the Plea<U+017F>ures which aro<U+017F>e to their Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Minds from their many Exploits, and Illu<U+017F>trious Conque<U+017F>ts, did not <U+017F>eem to them <U+017F>o <U+017F>weet, as tho<U+017F>e of Love. <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Ce<U+017F>ar,</hi> who had under their Command almo<U+017F>t half the World, thought it Glorious for them<U+017F>elves to obey that Sex, which has always been the faire<U+017F>t part of it. <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> him<U+017F>elf, that Prodigy of Strength and Valour, preferred the Fetters of a Woman, to the Honour of upholding Heaven, and the Gods them<U+017F>elves. One of <hi>Omphala</hi>'s threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning looks could make this invincible Hero
<pb facs="tcp:105648:4"/>
tremble, his Armour was no Proof again<U+017F>t her Charms; her Di<U+017F>taff ea<U+017F>ily took place of his Club, and his Lyons Skin <U+017F>urrender'd to a Woman's Attire. <hi>Mars</hi> him<U+017F>elf the God of War, could not re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the Charms of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<U+017F>s of Love, and he never thought him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>o happy, as when he <U+017F>har'd with <hi>Vulcan</hi> the Favours of <hi>Venus.</hi> Since then the greate<U+017F>t <hi>Heroes,</hi> and the Gods them<U+017F>elves, have been thus enamour'd; how can any wonder, that the Victorious <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> <U+017F>hould yield to the Charms of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a?</hi> This formidable Captain, who never fought without Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, killed near two thou<U+017F>and <hi>Turks,</hi> with his own hand, without receiving the lea<U+017F>t wound; but Love did what all his Enemies could not do, and wounded the Heart of this Invulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conquerour. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> tho' but a Slave, loaded with Chains that Vanqui<U+017F>her of the mo<U+017F>t powerful Emperour in the World. But how pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate <U+017F>oever this King of <hi>Albania</hi> was, Love could never draw one word from him, or compel him to an Action, unworthy of him<U+017F>elf. The per<U+017F>on who in<U+017F>pires him with the<U+017F>e Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>es, and the<U+017F>e De<U+017F>igns, is u<U+017F>ed to make <hi>Heroes</hi> both Speak and Act. And I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that the Amours of <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> will be as plea<U+017F>ant to the Ladies, as the great Tran<U+017F>actions of his Life have <U+017F>eem'd won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful to tho<U+017F>e who have read them in his Hi<U+017F>tory.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="novel">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105648:4"/>
            <head>The Great <hi>Scanderberg.</hi> A NOVEL.</head>
            <p>VAlour and Virtue, appeared never with more Splendour, than in the Per<U+017F>on of the Invincible <hi>Scanderberg.</hi> This Prince was Bred up in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Cruel <hi>Amurat,</hi> pre<U+017F>erv'd there his Manners uncorrupt, and his Vertue may be propo<U+017F>ed for an Example to all the Monarchs in the World. After he had freed him<U+017F>elf from a <U+017F>hameful Slavery, recovered his Father's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, <U+017F>truck Terrour, by his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Actions, into the heart of him who had Captivated his Youth, he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105648:5"/>
<U+017F>aw all his Lands Invaded by the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, which the angry <hi>Sultan</hi> led in Per<U+017F>on to the <U+017F>ight of the Walls of <hi>Croya,</hi> a Famous City, and the ordinary abode of the Kings of <hi>Albania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scanderberg</hi> <U+017F>ince his return, had led there a Life which might have been called happy, if Love had not mixed its <U+017F>ad Di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ures with the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of reigning over the hearts of all his Subjects; he had bore the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulle<U+017F>t brunts of War with unimagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble con<U+017F>tancy; he had won Battels, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Provinces, vanqui<U+017F>hed every where, and given Matter enough to Po<U+017F>terity for celebrating his Prai<U+017F>es, there were <U+017F>till remaining <U+017F>ome formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Enemies, powerful by their number, and dreadful for their fury, who<U+017F>e only intent was to oppre<U+017F>s him; but the fear of their Arms was not the thing, that di<U+017F>turbed his re<U+017F>t: Some more tender concerns, ca<U+017F>t him into a <U+017F>orrowful Condition, and if care of his Subjects, by whom he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly beloved, had not kept him at <hi>Croya,</hi> he had gone him<U+017F>elf to the Camp of the Enemy, to <U+017F>eek out the ab<U+017F>ent and unfortunate <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105648:5"/>
the moments which he gave to other Affairs, <U+017F>eem'd to him as <U+017F>o many Crimes again<U+017F>t his Love; and <hi>Croya,</hi> which he could not leave with Honour, was a <U+017F>orrowful abode for him, by rea<U+017F>on of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Ab<U+017F>ence.</p>
            <p>Notwith<U+017F>tanding the care of tho<U+017F>e, that feared for his Liberty, he did <U+017F>eek <U+017F>ometimes Solitary Places, to <U+017F>igh there with more Freedom, and would go a con<U+017F>iderable way from <hi>Croya.</hi> One Morning going out with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus</hi> only, he <U+017F>teer'd his cour<U+017F>e towards a Vally that <U+017F>eem'd more agreeable with his Melancholy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> had made already many Incur<U+017F>ions, and gain'd <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, which the Sorrow of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi> <U+017F>eem'd to neglect. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus</hi> being <U+017F>olicitous for his Ma<U+017F>ter's danger, who was come <U+017F>o near his powerful Enemy, and having given him a con<U+017F>iderable while to think by him<U+017F>elf, <U+017F>topt him at la<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>hewing him <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Tents, <U+017F>pake thus to him; Do you intend, My Lord, to go to the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Camp, and do you <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly reflect upon that nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Army, which bears <U+017F>uch an ill will to your Per<U+017F>on: That Life for which thou art <U+017F>o <U+017F>olicitous, an<U+017F>wer'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105648:6"/>
the King of <hi>Albania,</hi> is not dear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to me, to take any care of it; and my Eyes, deprived of the <U+017F>ight of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> long to be deprived of that of the day: What, will you, My <hi>Lord,</hi> reply'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus, expo<U+017F>e to a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fate, a thing which is <U+017F>o dear to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a? <hi>I know what your Valour can do; but in our pre<U+017F>ent Condition—In our pre<U+017F>ent Condition,</hi> <U+017F>aid <hi>Scanderberg, do you think that the Army of</hi> Amurat <hi>can make me tremble? Was I but certain of <U+017F>eeing</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>again, I would venture to fight it my <U+017F>elf alone: yes <U+017F>ure</hi> (added he, with one of tho<U+017F>e threatning looks, which had been often the Pre<U+017F>ages of his Victories) <hi>I would endeavour it.</hi> As he was going on, <U+017F>ome groaning that he heard from behind the Trees inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted him. The Prince was Naturally bountiful, and thinking that might be <U+017F>ome oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Per<U+017F>on who wanted help, he run thither with ha<U+017F>te, and found a Man wallowing in his Blood, this Man was a <hi>Turk,</hi> but <hi>Scanderberg</hi> whom no prejudice could hinder from being kind, drew nearer him, and knew pre<U+017F>ently (tho' in the Pangs of Death) <hi>Aradin,</hi> the fir<U+017F>t of the Eunuchs of <hi>Amurat,</hi> who had taken care of him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105648:6"/>
in his Infancy, and by whom he was tenderly beloved; the unfortunate <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radin,</hi> tho' dying, knew al<U+017F>o the Features of the King of <hi>Albania,</hi> and, fetching a deep <U+017F>igh, he <U+017F>aid, <hi>Oh,</hi> Scanderberg! Amurat! Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a! <hi>Knave and perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman, <hi>I dye.</hi> And really he did <U+017F>o. This <U+017F>trange event was but a new increa<U+017F>e of Grief for <hi>Scanderberg:</hi> The Nanies which <hi>Aradin</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, pa<U+017F>s'd to his very heart; he perceived the <hi>Eunuch</hi> had not <U+017F>poke, but after he had known him, and that he was nearly concerned in all tho<U+017F>e things, which Death had forced him to <U+017F>uppre<U+017F>s: <hi>Ju<U+017F>t Heavens,</hi> cry'd he, <hi>what News do you intend to tell me? Is</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>Alive, or Dead? Ala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>s!</hi> Ura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>my dear</hi> Uranus, <hi>what perplexity do I find my <U+017F>elf now in? What can I do? What can I think? My Lord,</hi> reply'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus, if I may conjecture any thing,</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>is not far from hence. Then <U+017F>he is in</hi> Amurat<hi>'s Camp,</hi> reply'd the Amorous Prince of <hi>Albania, where <U+017F>he <U+017F>uffers the trouble<U+017F>ome Solicitations of a Barbarous Emperour; or tho<U+017F>e of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy</hi> Mu<U+017F><U+017F>ulman. <hi>Suppo<U+017F>e it was <U+017F>o, am I the happier for it? Yes certainly,</hi> added he, <hi>for I would go and take</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105648:7"/>
               <hi>her away from the</hi> Ottomans.</p>
            <p>Whil<U+017F>t <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was <U+017F>peaking, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus</hi> went to look whether <hi>Aradin</hi> did breathe <U+017F>till, he found him cold, and without motion; but turning him, he perceived a Paper, like a Letter, ju<U+017F>t over his Heart, and delivering it to his Ma<U+017F>ter, <hi>My Lord,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>this Note will tell you, may be, a part of that which the <U+017F>udden Death of</hi> Aradin <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him from uttering;</hi> the Prince opened the Letter, and <U+017F>aw there a Sentence more cruel, than if it had been again<U+017F>t his own Life.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To the Great <hi>Vi<U+017F>ier Orcan.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY Love hath been prevailed upon at la<U+017F>t by my Wrath: Such a Man as I, ought not to hearken to pity; go then<hi> Orcan, </hi>and Sacrifice the ungrateful<hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, </hi>to the Shame of having made me <U+017F>igh to no purpo<U+017F>e; her Blood will quench the re<U+017F>t of my Flame. Fear <U+017F>ome oppo<U+017F>ition from<hi> Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman, </hi>and whil<U+017F>t I <U+017F>hall van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<U+017F>h the Rebellious<hi> Scanderberg, </hi>begin my Revenge that way, which will prove <U+017F>o <U+017F>orrowful to him. This is the Ab<U+017F>olute Command of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Amurat.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105648:7"/>
No Man could expre<U+017F>s the <U+017F>ad effects the Reading of this Letter produced in the Soul of <hi>Scanderberg:</hi> In the fir<U+017F>t fit of his Rage, he was ready to run to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army; but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus,</hi> after a long, but fruitle<U+017F>s oppo<U+017F>ition, laying a<U+017F>ide his wonted re<U+017F>pect, told him at la<U+017F>t: <hi>Do you <U+017F>eek an Inglorious Death, My Lord, and will not this Triumph of the</hi> Turks, <hi>blot out all the Splendour of your pa<U+017F>t Life? Having lo<U+017F>t</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, reply'd the Prince, <hi>I am re<U+017F>olv'd to dye in her Revenge.</hi> His De<U+017F>pair had likely prevailed over <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus</hi>'s Zeal, if <hi>Thopia,</hi> a young Prince, and much addicted to <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> who was looking for him, becau<U+017F>e he knew he was gone out of <hi>Croya</hi> without his Train, had not come in the <U+017F>ame place. <hi>Thopia,</hi> <U+017F>aid the King of <hi>Albania</hi> to him, <hi>None is more worthy your pity than I: You, My Lord,</hi> an<U+017F>wered <hi>Thopia</hi> amazed, <hi>you! the Love, the Terrour, and the Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole World, in your fir<U+017F>t Youth, what Mi<U+017F>chiefs can cro<U+017F>s <U+017F>o great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages? I perceive,</hi> reply'd <hi>Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, you judge of the Felicity of my Life, by tho<U+017F>e Actions which have made a great noi<U+017F>e in the World; but do not decide it upon meer appearances. My Lord,</hi> added
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105648:8"/>
               <hi>Thopia, the</hi> Turks <hi>may <U+017F>urprize your Valour in this place: Let us go to</hi> Croya, <hi>where your Pre<U+017F>ence is wi<U+017F>hed for.</hi> And <U+017F>o jointly with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus,</hi> they obliged the Prince to go towards the City, but fir<U+017F>t they took care of the Corps of <hi>Aradin,</hi> <U+017F>ome <hi>Albanian</hi> Troopers, who were riding about the City, to ob<U+017F>erve the Motion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd it away by the King's Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thopia</hi> knew very well that <hi>Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> was in Love, but he was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Particulars of his Life, and <U+017F>hew'd a great De<U+017F>ire to know them. <hi>Scanderberg</hi> conde<U+017F>cended ea<U+017F>ily to call again to mind, his mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>orrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ideas, that he might <U+017F>atisfie <hi>Thopia,</hi> whom his Friend<U+017F>hip di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>ht from all the other Princes of his Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thopia,</hi> (<U+017F>aid he, when they were come to the Palace of <hi>Croya) you will help me to bewail</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a<hi>'s, Fate, when you <U+017F>hall hear me, and you will confe<U+017F>s, that if For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hath be<U+017F>towed <U+017F>ome Favours upon me, they have been Poy<U+017F>oned by many bitter di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ures. Scanderberg</hi> gave Order none <U+017F>hould interrupt them, and began his Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e after this Manner.</p>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105648:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Hi<U+017F>tory of</hi> Scanderberg.</head>
               <p>YOU know my Mother was Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Prince of the <hi>Triballians,</hi> and that <hi>John Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> my Father did Reign in <hi>Epirus,</hi> and <hi>Albania;</hi> he was envy'd for his Valour by <hi>Amurat,</hi> who rendered him<U+017F>elf Formidable in <hi>Greece;</hi> after he had been the Terror in <hi>A<U+017F>ia; Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> forced to yield to the <U+017F>wift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of his pro<U+017F>perous Fortune, made Peace with him, and <U+017F>ent my three Brothers and me for Ho<U+017F>tages, to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drianople. Vor<U+017F>ana</hi> my Mother, keeping <U+017F>till by her <U+017F>elf four Daughters, to wipe off her Tears: She expected much from my Birth, by rea<U+017F>on of a Dream, which <U+017F>he had when <U+017F>he was Big of me; She Dreamed <U+017F>he was Delivered of a Serpent, <U+017F>o great; that he covered all <hi>Epirus,</hi> his head did reach to <hi>Turkey,</hi> which he <U+017F>wallow'd up, and he did dip his Tail in the Sea towards <hi>Venice. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triot</hi> having heard the Relation of this Dream from <hi>Vor<U+017F>ona,</hi> a<U+017F><U+017F>ured her <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould bring forth a Man fatal to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and u<U+017F>eful to <hi>Chri<U+017F>tendom.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthele<U+017F>s I was delivered into the hands of the fir<U+017F>t, Nothing but the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105648:9"/>
regard of the <U+017F>afety of his Dominions, could ever have brought him to this Re<U+017F>olution, I being but eight years old, all my Brothers were Elder than I; this Age expo<U+017F>ed me to the Ceremonies of the <hi>Turks,</hi> wherein they changed my Name, that was <hi>George,</hi> into that of <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> which is as much in the <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Tongue, as <hi>Alexander</hi> Lord, concerning my Brothers, their Riper Age free'd them from this Violence.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sultan</hi> who had a good Opinion of my youth, took all the imaginable care, to make me an Hone<U+017F>t Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: The unfortunate <hi>Aradin</hi> was made my Governour, and never man performed his Duty, with more Zeal and Diligence. But tho' his kind u<U+017F>age made me forget, that I was beholding for it to a Slave, yet my Condition, and the fir<U+017F>t Impre<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion, which I had received, could never be blotted out of my Memory.</p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hall not relate to you what I did, from eight years, to <U+017F>ixteen. I learn'd all Exerci<U+017F>es nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, both for the Body and the Mind; and <hi>Aradin</hi> did all his Endeavours to in<U+017F>pire me with the love of Glory and Vertue. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105648:9"/>
who took <U+017F>ome delight in my Sight and Conver<U+017F>ation, <U+017F>eem'd always plea<U+017F>ed with me: I had the advantage of Signalizing my <U+017F>elf in his pre<U+017F>ence, in the fir<U+017F>t War wherein I was allowed to fight; and kind Fortune waiting every where upon me, being yet but nineteen years old, I was made a <hi>Sangiac</hi> by <hi>Amurat,</hi> that is to <U+017F>ay, a Leader, and I was tru<U+017F>ted by him, with the Command of five thou<U+017F>and Hor<U+017F>es; a little while after, I was nominated a <hi>Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> which was a Dignity that made the <hi>Sangiacs</hi> inferiour to me. I confe<U+017F>s, my Advancement was very <U+017F>udden, but the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who fore<U+017F>aw I <U+017F>hould prove u<U+017F>eful to him, had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to my Youth.</p>
               <p>In this pa<U+017F>s I acquired more Glory in <hi>Natoly.</hi> I was feared by the Enemies, loved by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and e<U+017F>teemed by the Emperour; and I can hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, without Blu<U+017F>hing, that after <U+017F>ome important Victories, where cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Amurat</hi> had had a great <U+017F>hare, he would call me his Right Arm, his Heart, his Eye, and the Defender of his E<U+017F>tates. I enjoy'd all the <U+017F>weet Plea<U+017F>ures of Liberty, becau<U+017F>e I was look'd upon as a <hi>Turk.</hi> My Brothers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105648:10"/>
Slavery would <U+017F>ometimes vex me, but <U+017F>eeing that they did not <U+017F>uffer much by it, and being be<U+017F>ides re<U+017F>olved to make my <U+017F>elf famous for the future, that was not able to put a <U+017F>top to my Ambition.</p>
               <p>Heaven puni<U+017F>hed me for this hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of Heart, and permitted that the Cares of Love, <U+017F>hould have their <U+017F>hare in my Heart, as well as tho<U+017F>e of War: Nay, <U+017F>hould wholly po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s it. I had not gone for a long while near the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Women, and my Age did deprive me of tho<U+017F>e Care<U+017F><U+017F>es, I was wont to receive from the Lovelie<U+017F>t <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es:</hi> I felt in my heart, neither Aver<U+017F>ion nor love for their Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And in this quiet State of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, I <U+017F>pent in <U+017F>ome Exerci<U+017F>es very plea<U+017F>ant to the Emperour, that lea<U+017F>ure we injoy'd at <hi>Adrianople:</hi> Tho<U+017F>e that were then mo<U+017F>t in favour with him, were <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman, Bo<U+017F>tangi Ba<U+017F><U+017F>i,</hi> or great Gardener, <hi>Mu<U+017F>tapha, Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> of the Sea, and <hi>Orcan,</hi> the now <hi>Grand Vi<U+017F>ier.</hi> They po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd infinite Riches, and <U+017F>tately Palaces, and their Families lived in great Splendour. <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> prevailed over the others, becau<U+017F>e in all times and in all places, he had a free acce<U+017F>s to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105648:10"/>
the <hi>Sultan,</hi> his Clo<U+017F>et, his Coun<U+017F>el, and his Gardens were equally opened to him: Proud of the<U+017F>e advantages, he entertain'd other Courtiers <U+017F>o coldly, that he <U+017F>eem'd to de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e I was loved by <hi>Amurat,</hi> and he de<U+017F>ired to keep in his Favour, I did not find the <U+017F>ame reception as the re<U+017F>t. I had a Natural aver<U+017F>ion again<U+017F>t him, but I had learnt Di<U+017F><U+017F>imulation, in a Court, where that Art was <U+017F>o ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary.</p>
               <p>About this time there came to <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> a <hi>Tartar</hi> Prince, whom Curio<U+017F>ity had brought thither, the like man had never been <U+017F>een before, he was of a prodigious height; being a foot taller than any of the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>Turks.</hi> Tho' he was Proud, and Rude, yet he was received like a Prince, by <hi>Amurat;</hi> it was reported he was famous over all <hi>Tartary</hi> for his Exploits; and he had never fought without Victory; proud of his own Reputation, he little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded others civility; unfortunately for him, he contradicted me in any thing that I <U+017F>aid; we were u<U+017F>ed to talk about Warlike Matters, and one day he was <U+017F>o pre<U+017F>umptuous, as to tell me that the Victory over twenty <U+017F>uch Men as me,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105648:11"/>
would be no difficult attempt for him; being impatient, I defied him to fight me in a Duel, in the Emperour's <U+017F>ight. The <hi>Tartar</hi> was amazed at my boldne<U+017F>s, and accepted of the Challenge: <hi>Amurat,</hi> who feared the lo<U+017F>s of my Life, oppo<U+017F>ed it: But I craved his leave <U+017F>o in<U+017F>tantly, that at la<U+017F>t he con<U+017F>ented to it.</p>
               <p>The <U+017F>eeming unequality between my Adver<U+017F>ary and me, affrighted all tho<U+017F>e who loved me, and I was likely the only man who was not alarmed: The Field for the Fight, was appointed in a <U+017F>pacious piece of ground, which lay over again<U+017F>t the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> The Emperour gave leave to the <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es,</hi> and Slaves, to get upon the Towers, to <U+017F>ee this Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; and other Women, who<U+017F>e Hou<U+017F>es look'd upon that place, had the <U+017F>ame Licen<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>At la<U+017F>t the hour appointed for the Fight came, and we appeared before a numberle<U+017F>s multitude of Spectators. The <hi>Tartar</hi> began to jeer me bitterly, for my Age and Weakne<U+017F>s, but it was not long before I puni<U+017F>hed him for it, and my blows were <U+017F>o fortunate, that after an hours Re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, he expired in the <U+017F>ight of all the A<U+017F><U+017F>embly. There were never heard <U+017F>o many Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105648:11"/>
of joy among the <hi>Turks,</hi> as after my Victory; they e<U+017F>teem'd it a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy, and I was lookt upon with great Re<U+017F>pect: I carry'd the <hi>Giant</hi>'s Sword to the Emperour's Feet, who imbraced me, and tho' <U+017F>ome Per<U+017F>ons envy'd me for the Honour of that day, tho<U+017F>e that were the Wi<U+017F>e<U+017F>t, followed ea<U+017F>ily <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi>'s Example.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Tartars</hi> took away their Ma<U+017F>ter's Corps, of which they di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed as they plea<U+017F>ed; and for my part, I followed the <hi>Sultan</hi> to the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> the Prince <hi>Mahomet,</hi> his elde<U+017F>t Son, had received from Heaven <U+017F>ome eminent Parts, which had been cultivated to a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; we lived very freely between us, and tho' one could not <U+017F>ee that <U+017F>tore of <U+017F>incere Friend<U+017F>hip, which tyes clo<U+017F>ely two hearts together, yet we were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different one to another; he prai<U+017F>ed my Action, and civily congratulated me for it.</p>
               <p>That <U+017F>ame night to avoid the Crowd, of which I was already weary, we went together, at the Moon-Shine, upon the Sea Shore, ju<U+017F>t behind the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Women; after we had walk'd a long while, in a very plea<U+017F>ant place, incompa<U+017F><U+017F>ed one way by the River, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105648:12"/>
towards the <hi>Seraglio</hi> with a Hedge <U+017F>o thick, that it rendred the Gardens more inacce<U+017F><U+017F>ible, than any <U+017F>trong wall. We were ready to retire, when a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Voice, Sung di<U+017F>tinctly the<U+017F>e words in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Since here a Captive, void of all relief,</l>
                  <l>I bend beneath the weight of deadly Grief;</l>
                  <l>Why, cruel Love, do'<U+017F>t thou increa<U+017F>e my pains,</l>
                  <l>And add new Slavery to my former Chains?</l>
               </q>
               <p>The <U+017F>ound of this Voice pa<U+017F>s'd through my Ears, to my very Heart. I had never felt before any tender motions, and my free and indifferent Soul was capable of any impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion. That! Song was repeated many times: <hi>Mahomet</hi> hearkned to it with as much attention as my <U+017F>elf, we knew well there were in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> many Fair <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es,</hi> and Lovely Slaves, whom <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>A<U+017F>ia,</hi> had offered; but they were altogether unknown to us: One hath never the more Priviledge in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> for being either the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Son, or his Favourite; for their jealou<U+017F>ie is <U+017F>o careful, in hiding what they de<U+017F>ign for their Plea<U+017F>ures, that unle<U+017F>s kind For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105648:12"/>
favours a man, he can never come to know it.</p>
               <p>The Prince, and I having heard this Charming Voice, we knew the per<U+017F>on who had <U+017F>ung it, was not alone, becau<U+017F>e another began to <U+017F>peak in <hi>Greek,</hi> but with a Barbarous pronunciation, Does that Song concern you, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have you lo<U+017F>t your Heart in this place, where we <U+017F>ee but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plea<U+017F>ant Objects? <hi>Suppo<U+017F>e what you <U+017F>aid was true;</hi> an<U+017F>wered another, <hi>it would be a hard matter for my Heart to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain its thoughts in a Song; you have de<U+017F>ired me to Sing, and I have done it: How happy are you,</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <hi>to keep your Heart <U+017F>o free, and repre<U+017F>ent anothers Di<U+017F>temper, without fear of being infected with it; how happy are you, but how unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate is</hi> Selimana? <hi>You are the Object of the</hi> Sultan<hi>'s mo<U+017F>t tender Affection,</hi> an<U+017F>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, and that is the only thing that may well <U+017F>atisfie you, in this Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<U+017F>ting Retirement. What can you de<U+017F>ire more, Madam, <U+017F>ince you are the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s of him, who can di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of all? Tho' Ambition is well plea<U+017F>ed with that advantage,</hi> continued <hi>Selimana,</hi> <U+017F>ighing, <hi>a Soul as nice as mine cannot be contented; and if you had ever been in Love, you</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105648:13"/>
                  <hi>would quickly apprehend my meaning. Alas, Madam, I have had <U+017F>o many Misfortunes in my Life, that I willingly renounce to that Experiment,</hi> reply'd <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, with a Charming Sweetne<U+017F>s; well,</hi> interrupted <hi>Selimana, <U+017F>ince you do not know the cau<U+017F>e of my <U+017F>uffering, at lea<U+017F>t do not condemn it. A power which I cannot re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t, forces me to utter this Secret without blu<U+017F>hing. I love, I love,</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <hi>the Prince</hi> Scanderberg, <hi>and his Victory over the</hi> Tartar, <hi>is not the only one he has got to day; he has <U+017F>eem'd to my Eyes as Lovely, as he was formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to his Enemy, and that <U+017F>hort <U+017F>pace of time, has a<U+017F><U+017F>ured to him the po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of my heart for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot relate to you <hi>Selimana</hi>'s Kindne<U+017F>s without blu<U+017F>hing: But you mu<U+017F>t be acquainted with it, that you may the better under<U+017F>tand how ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the young <hi>Sultan</hi> and I were. I was loved without knowing by whom, and <U+017F>uch a man as I might have been well plea<U+017F>ed with the Idea of this Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but be<U+017F>ides that, <hi>Selimana</hi> <U+017F>eem'd too pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate to de<U+017F>erve my Heart; <U+017F>he was a Sacred Object for me, being the beloved <hi>Sultane<U+017F>s</hi> of <hi>Amurat,</hi> I was more taken with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Mode<U+017F>ty, and tho' I did not wi<U+017F>h her <U+017F>o pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate
<pb facs="tcp:105648:13"/>
as the other, I could have de<U+017F>ired <U+017F>he had not been in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible.</p>
               <p>Some noi<U+017F>e made them retire; the Prince drew nearer me, when he heard them no longer, and cla<U+017F>ping his Arm about my Neck, <hi>whatever good Opinion you entertain of your <U+017F>elf,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>did you think,</hi> Scanderberg, <hi>that</hi> Mars, <hi>and Love, <U+017F>hould intend to be<U+017F>tow their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon you at the <U+017F>ame time? My Lord,</hi> reply'd I <U+017F>miling, <hi>if we had more Freedom at</hi> Adrianople, <hi>I would tell you that this adventure is but a <U+017F>ham. You <U+017F>ee,</hi> added <hi>Mahomet, that there is nothing but what is Natural in it; the hour, the place, and the per<U+017F>on who <U+017F>poke, in a word, all things witne<U+017F>s your good Fortune, and you have nothing to do, but to rejoice. Alas, My Lord,</hi> <U+017F>aid I, <hi>though my Heart was <U+017F>u<U+017F>ceptible enough, to fall <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>ily in Love, I <U+017F>hould never forget what I owe to the</hi> Sultan. Selimana <hi>may be a charming Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, what <U+017F>he <U+017F>aid may flatter me, but</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat <hi>is Emperor, and worthy of my Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. You think,</hi> reply'd <hi>Mahomet, that a great Zeal for his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, will make me betray yours. No, My Lord,</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted I <U+017F>omething ha<U+017F>tily, <hi>I know you are generous, and di<U+017F>creet, and I <U+017F>peak what I think.</hi> We went then into
<pb facs="tcp:105648:14"/>
the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and we parted at the <U+017F>ame time.</p>
               <p>I did never go to Bed without <U+017F>eeing <hi>Aradin;</hi> that day plea<U+017F>ed with the Honours I had received, he did not fail to be in my Chamber; as becau<U+017F>e I had no acquaintance in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Women, and all things were changed there, <U+017F>ince my Infancy, I asked him <U+017F>everal que<U+017F>tions, which <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed him. I inquired of him concerning <hi>Selimana;</hi> he an<U+017F>wered me, that <U+017F>he was always the deare<U+017F>t Object of <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Love, who had preferred her to all things, and he drew her Picture with great care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulne<U+017F>s: After that, I asked him about <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> and my Curio<U+017F>ity about a Slave, who probably was unknown to me, <U+017F>eem'd the more <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ing to him. <hi>I don't know,</hi> Scanderberg, <U+017F>aid he to me, <hi>what is your De<U+017F>ign, but I can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure you, that among all the Women in the World, I think there is none more Lovely, than</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a; <hi>with a perfect Beauty <U+017F>he po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es a wonderful Wit and Virtue, and I cannot but wonder, that the Emperour has not yet ca<U+017F>t his Eyes upon her:</hi> I hearken'd to <hi>Aradin,</hi> with a trouble which I had never felt before; what ever he <U+017F>aid about <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> were <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105648:14"/>
many plea<U+017F>ant wounds to my heart, and I may <U+017F>ay, I was in Love, before I had <U+017F>een whom I loved; after a long Conver<U+017F>ation, I thought I could not hide it from <hi>Aradin;</hi> he was afflicted at it, and knowing how dear <hi>Selimana</hi> was to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> and his jealous, and violent Temper, he u<U+017F>ed his utmo<U+017F>t care to make me under<U+017F>tand, how dangerous to me <U+017F>uch a concurrence would prove. I a<U+017F><U+017F>ured him, I had no di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition to love <hi>Selimana,</hi> however I di<U+017F>covered not my thoughts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> but pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed the whole night in fancying her to my <U+017F>elf, as lovely, as the Eunuch had de<U+017F>cribed her; I found not my <U+017F>elf the following day, as I had been hitherto; is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible that <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>hould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed with <U+017F>ome tender Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi><U+017F>aid I <U+017F>ighing,</hi> and can my Heart, which <U+017F>he takes from me, hope any comfort from her? I had no <U+017F>ooner ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered tho<U+017F>e words, but I found them unworthy of a man, who<U+017F>e only Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition was to be great. I knew that violent Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions were look'd upon as a weakne<U+017F>s, and my Love for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Object, <U+017F>eem'd to me <U+017F>trange and worthy; neverthele<U+017F>s, it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105648:15"/>
and I could not conquer it as I had done the <hi>Tartar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was forced to open my Heart to <hi>Aradin,</hi> who condemned me to think never upon her, <U+017F>ince I could not hope to have any Conver<U+017F>ation with her.</p>
               <p>There happen'd then an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> and which is <U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <U+017F>een among the <hi>Turks:</hi> The <hi>Sultan</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> had <U+017F>ent a magnificent Emba<U+017F><U+017F>ie; and <U+017F>ome rich Pre<U+017F>ents to <hi>Amurat,</hi> who to <U+017F>hew his Grandure to Strangers, in the <U+017F>eat of his Empire, gave them a publick Audience, that day the Women went from their <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> to that of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s adorned with the mo<U+017F>t precious things the <hi>Ea<U+017F>t</hi> could afford, <hi>Selimana,</hi> the beloved, as I told you before, appeared <U+017F>hining with her Natural Beauty, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Ornaments; She was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by a hundred, in the <U+017F>ame Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and by an infinite number of young Slaves, dre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with le<U+017F>s Art, but certainly worthy of another Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: To make this Spectacle <U+017F>eem the greater, they wore golden Chains, and they had been loaded with E<U+017F><U+017F>ences, and Baskets full of Flowers, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105648:15"/>
they <U+017F>pread in a great Hall, at who<U+017F>e end, the <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es</hi> sat upon rich Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hions, the<U+017F>e Slaves <U+017F>tood round about them, and the Emperour <U+017F>ate upon a Splendid Throne, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>teps were oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy'd by his chiefe<U+017F>t Officers.</p>
               <p>After this manner, <hi>Thopia,</hi> we <U+017F>aw the Secret Court of <hi>Amurat,</hi> when the Turks and <hi>Egyptians</hi> had a free acce<U+017F>s to the Hall. <hi>Selimana</hi> <U+017F>ate in a higher place than the others, and her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as her Rank, di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h'd her from the re<U+017F>t: But among the Slaves who were round about her, the young <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> neglected, and blu<U+017F>hing, for appearing before <U+017F>o many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es, in a condition <U+017F>o unworthy of her, was remarkable, in <U+017F>pight of her <U+017F>elf, for her Charms. I could not know her as being <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> but my heart took notice of her, as of an Object which it was re<U+017F>olved to adore. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what I had conceived of her, upon <hi>Aradin</hi>'s Relation, I wi<U+017F>hed <hi>Arani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and that Slave might be the <U+017F>ame; upon that account I abandoned my <U+017F>elf to the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion that po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es me, and which will never end.</p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hall not relate to you what was done there, having taken no notice of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105648:16"/>
the Ceremony; <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> only had all my looks and my attention, neither did I mind whether <hi>Selimana</hi> ca<U+017F>t her eyes upon me, as caring little for her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>I ran to <hi>Aradin</hi> as <U+017F>oon as the Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es and the Slaves were retired. Love which fir<U+017F>t had engaged me by the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I had had with <hi>Mahomet,</hi> made me feel now all its power: The Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch was amazed at the violence of my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and was almo<U+017F>t angry. <hi>My dear</hi> Scanderberg, <U+017F>aid he to me, <hi>you know me well enough, not to que<U+017F>tion the <U+017F>incerity of my advices; what can you hope from an affection, who<U+017F>e con<U+017F>equences mu<U+017F>t needs be unfortunate? Fortune condemns</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>to be a Slave for ever; will you confine the Glory of your life in an hopele<U+017F>s Love? And don't you de<U+017F>erve to be blamed for the unrea<U+017F>onablene<U+017F>s of the de<U+017F>ign? I confe<U+017F>s,</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>is a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Per<U+017F>on, and according to all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility her Birth is not mean: But what can you hope from her as long as <U+017F>he is in the</hi> Seraglio, <hi>where all things breathe only for</hi> Amurat<hi>'s Plea<U+017F>ure? Can you fetch out</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <hi>in <U+017F>pight of <U+017F>o many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons, who watch always to <U+017F>atisfie the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's jealou<U+017F>ie? And will you not de<U+017F>erve</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105648:16"/>
                  <hi>his hatred, for breaking the<U+017F>e Laws, the lea<U+017F>t violation of which de<U+017F>erves Death; reflect upon your <U+017F>elf,</hi> Scanderberg, <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <hi>who can ruine you. Con<U+017F>ider you are a Prince de<U+017F>igned for extraordinary things, and covered already with a Glory which you ought to pre<U+017F>erve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of <hi>Aradin,</hi> which his affection created, confounded my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, but did not per<U+017F>wade my heart: My Love for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was too <U+017F>trong, and it could not be prevailed on by his Advices, no more than by my own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections; he perceived well my <U+017F>ad Condition, but <U+017F>eeing it was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to alter my mind, he exhorted me not to rule my Conduct according to my blind Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, but to have a <U+017F>pecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Severity, and to take my mea<U+017F>ures accordingly.</p>
               <p>I felt all the griefs of Love, as <U+017F>oon as I knew <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> the impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of <U+017F>eeing her was to me a mo<U+017F>t cruel pain, de<U+017F>pair often makes us <U+017F>light tho<U+017F>e things we de<U+017F>ire to obtain, but the difficulties I met with here, did but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame me the more.</p>
               <p>As if the Ob<U+017F>tacles before mentioned, bad not been enough, there aro<U+017F>e again<U+017F>t me three formidable Rivals. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105648:17"/>
who had never before look'd upon <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> found her <U+017F>o Beautiful the day of the Publick Audience of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> that <hi>Selimana</hi> <U+017F>eemed to him le<U+017F>s Charming. Prince <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who had not till then entertain'd any other thought, but the fear of the common Fate of the Princes of his Blood, and who had carried him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>o well, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Sultan,</hi> as not to give him any ju<U+017F>t cau<U+017F>e of Anger or Jealou<U+017F>ie, paid to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Beauty, what was due to her from all tender Hearts. And <hi>Mu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elman,</hi> who ought to have re<U+017F>ted <U+017F>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with the amorous intrigues, which either his Inclination or good Fortune had procured him, look'd upon her with the <U+017F>ame eyes as we did.</p>
               <p>I knew not for a long while their thoughts, and I was very careful to hide mine. <hi>Mahomet</hi> became melancholy; and for my part, I loved Solitude <U+017F>o much, that I could <U+017F>carce ca<U+017F>t my eyes upon tho<U+017F>e things which formerly had <U+017F>o much plea<U+017F>ed me; we neglected our Warlike Exerci<U+017F>es, we minded no more tho<U+017F>e Plea<U+017F>ures which we had been <U+017F>o de<U+017F>irous of before, and Solitude was the only thing we <U+017F>ought after: All admi<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Women being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105648:17"/>
forbidden to us, we were continually in the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages to it; where ever my Love guided me, I did meet there <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet: Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> was happier than we, his Employ, who<U+017F>e Authority is almo<U+017F>t unlimited, did give him acce<U+017F>s where we could not go, and we may think he made u<U+017F>e of his advantages.</p>
               <p>As I was u<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>pend mo<U+017F>t part of the day and night about tho<U+017F>e places, which hide <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> from my <U+017F>ight, I did <U+017F>ometimes forget my <U+017F>elf there. One night I tarried <U+017F>o long in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's Garden, which was next to that of the Women, that the Gates were <U+017F>hut up: All the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi</hi>'s had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, no body was up any longer in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> no light appeared there, and I was fain to <U+017F>tay there till day, after I had endeavoured to no purpo<U+017F>e to get out towards the Sea.</p>
               <p>As I was withdrawing in a retired place, to <U+017F>pend there the re<U+017F>t of the night, I <U+017F>aw a man cro<U+017F><U+017F>ing the great Flower Garden, and marching towards me with all po<U+017F><U+017F>ible ha<U+017F>te: By avoiding him, I had confe<U+017F>t my <U+017F>elf guilty, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore going towards him, I perceived it was the Emperour. <hi>What do you do here,</hi> Scanderberg, <U+017F>aid he to me, <hi>with a <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105648:18"/>
Countenance? being bred up in Our Palaces, and well in<U+017F>tructed with our Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>toms, ought you to <U+017F>hew this Example of boldne<U+017F>s to <U+017F>o many Per<U+017F>ons, who can make an ill u<U+017F>e of it, and have you <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ecret de<U+017F>ign again<U+017F>t my Re<U+017F>t, my Life, or my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? I have nothing to <U+017F>ay to thy High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s for my Ju<U+017F>tification,</hi> an<U+017F>wered I, <hi>and I appear guilty enough, to de<U+017F>erve thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; but I mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>ay this, that a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy humour is the cau<U+017F>e of the fault for which thou blame<U+017F>t me, and I <U+017F>wear I have tarryed here minding not the place where I was. You are <U+017F>o dear to me,</hi> reply'd the Emperour, <hi>that I am concern'd with all your <U+017F>orrows, and if you have any rea<U+017F>on for any, not only I forgive you this fault, but <U+017F>hall do my endeavours to <U+017F>atisfie you. Thine Highne<U+017F>s,</hi> <U+017F>aid I, <hi>is too kind, and ought not to trouble it <U+017F>elf about <U+017F>o <U+017F>mall trifles; the want of Employment is the cau<U+017F>e of my <U+017F>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and thy Highne<U+017F>s, leaving nothing to do for us, makes my young Courage grumble at its being idle. You have done enough to de<U+017F>ire Peace, and enjoy <U+017F>ome Re<U+017F>t,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Sultan, but if your Valour wants ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erci<U+017F>e, I promi<U+017F>e you <U+017F>ome. Go home qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and expect from me <U+017F>uch Employments, as are worthy of a Hero, who intends to <U+017F>urpa<U+017F>s all the</hi> Ottomans.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105648:18"/>
I made a very humble bow to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, glad I had pacify'd him, and went away as he directed me; but that Night was to bring forth other adventures. Prince <hi>Mahomet,</hi> brought there by the <U+017F>ame motives as I, had been al<U+017F>o <U+017F>hut in, and we <U+017F>aw him coming towards us, thinking we were <U+017F>ome <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi</hi>'s, or <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs: Is this a fit time for you to be here,</hi> <U+017F>aid the angry Emperour to him, <hi>and are you my Son, only to <U+017F>hew your <U+017F>elf unworthy of being <U+017F>o?</hi> The young Prince was <U+017F>truck with the<U+017F>e words, he <U+017F>aw me, and thought concerning me the <U+017F>ame thing I did concerning him. <hi>I have <U+017F>inned again<U+017F>t my own will, My Lord,</hi> an<U+017F>wered he to the <hi>Sultan, but I prote<U+017F>t to thy Highne<U+017F>s I <U+017F>hall come hither no more.</hi> A third man who did <U+017F>teal behind the Hedge more <U+017F>lily than we had done, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s reply; he did go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Womens Lodgings, a place which had always <U+017F>eem'd <U+017F>u<U+017F>picious to <hi>Amurat,</hi> but chie<U+017F>ly now in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his new Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; but his fear and vexation increa<U+017F>ed when he heard <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s fine voice, with which he was already acquainted, <U+017F>ing the<U+017F>e words.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105648:19"/>
                  <l>Go on, ob<U+017F>erve the Dictates of your Love,</l>
                  <l>The Favours of the <U+017F>hady night improve.</l>
                  <l>Suppre<U+017F>s the<U+017F>e <U+017F>ighs which from di<U+017F>orders flow,</l>
                  <l>And let your noble Flame yet higher grow,</l>
                  <l>Yield him your heart, his plea<U+017F>ing rules obey,</l>
                  <l>Who is a God, and does direct your way.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The <hi>Sultan</hi> felt then all the powers of jealou<U+017F>ie, e<U+017F>teeming that Song to be the <U+017F>ignal: we were guilty all three, and never did an innocent Adventure afford greater cau<U+017F>e of <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion to a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate Lover: He ran to the third Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and knew him pre<U+017F>ently to be <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> whom <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s voice had <U+017F>topt.</p>
               <p>None of us was a contemptible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, and tho' <hi>Mahomet</hi> and I had <U+017F>ome advantages above <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> by rea<U+017F>on of our Youth, and natural parts, yet his Authority in the Gardens might be of a great u<U+017F>e to a forward man. Tho' the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> had <U+017F>ome priviledges and few <U+017F>et hours, yet <hi>Amurat</hi> thought him more guilty than us. <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to him, with that pride which is natural to all the <hi>Sultans, what brings</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105648:19"/>
                  <hi>you hither at an hour, when no duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires your pre<U+017F>ence? Was it to introduce you to the</hi> Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es, <hi>that a Slave <U+017F>ung ju<U+017F>t now, and do you leave your hou<U+017F>e only to come and trouble me in mine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> was not amazed at this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding, he is Naturally bold, and an<U+017F>wering without any commotion, <hi>I thought, my Lord,</hi> reply'd he, <hi>I could not have too much Zeal for thine Highne<U+017F>s, and that all the hours of the day and night, were free for my Loyalty; by thy Kindne<U+017F>s I command in the Gardens, but I know how to <U+017F>tay in mine, as <U+017F>oon as I <U+017F>hall perceive that my Services are <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected. I believe,</hi> <U+017F>aid the Emperor, <hi>I <U+017F>hall not be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle this Mi<U+017F>tery; I will moderate my own Temper, let us retire, and let us be more careful for the future:</hi> So we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into the <hi>Seraglio:</hi> I don't que<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected both the Prince's Love and mine. <hi>Amurat</hi> whom his reflect thoughts had brought to the Garden at that hour again<U+017F>t his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tome, doubled the Guards towards the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the Women, and gave more <U+017F>evere orders to the <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> which <U+017F>ome faithfully ob<U+017F>erved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aradin</hi> upbraided me the next day for my wandring: We concluded <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105648:20"/>
and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> were my Rivals, and hoping to cure me, he a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me the Emperour was deeply in Love with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a:</hi> That Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>troy mine, tho' it ruined all my hopes, I feared neither the Prince nor <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who<U+017F>e condition was not better than mine: But I ought to fear all things from the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who<U+017F>e inclinations were violent, and who<U+017F>e will nothing was able to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t. I <U+017F>ighed for this with <hi>Aradin,</hi> I became more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pect before the Prince; and avoiding the Gardens, contented my <U+017F>elf with the Entertainment my Melancholy Thoughts enjoy'd upon the Sea Shoar.</p>
               <p>I under<U+017F>tood one day, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was going to bathe with <U+017F>ome <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es,</hi> in a little I<U+017F>land, from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drianople</hi> about an hours journey; he was u<U+017F>ed to take <U+017F>ecretly <U+017F>uch Pa<U+017F>times, and then he would put off for a while all <U+017F>orts of Gravity; his Galley was <U+017F>o <U+017F>hut, that the <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es</hi> could neither <U+017F>ee nor be <U+017F>een; it was led by <U+017F>ome <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi's,</hi> and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> by vertue of his place was at the head of them, but that honour procured him no advantage, <U+017F>ince he could <U+017F>ee nothing but his <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105648:20"/>
But my Jealou<U+017F>ie was <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong, that I went all along the Sea a very great way from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> and ca<U+017F>ting my looks as far as they could reach, I <U+017F>aw <U+017F>omething over the water, carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the <U+017F>tream: I thought I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Vail, and believing it might be a Woman ready to be drowned, I threw my <U+017F>elf pre<U+017F>ently into the water, and u<U+017F>ing my little Skill, I <U+017F>wam with all po<U+017F><U+017F>ible diligence, and took really into my Arms a woman, who was almo<U+017F>t choak'd.</p>
               <p>I doubled my efforts to get to the Shore, and as <U+017F>oon as I was there, I perceived it was <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a:</hi> You may judge, Dear <hi>Thopia,</hi> what was my grief when I <U+017F>aw the only thing that was dear to me, in <U+017F>uch a lamentable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Mercile<U+017F>s Fate,</hi> cry'd I, <hi>ought you to have offered her to me in <U+017F>uch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? O fair, but unwi<U+017F>e</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <hi>why did you <U+017F>eek your death, in <U+017F>o little important a Plea<U+017F>ure?</hi> This tran<U+017F>port of mine did not hinder me from a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ting her. I lifted her head, and bending a little the re<U+017F>t of her body, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of water ru<U+017F>hed out of it, and within a <U+017F>hort while, <U+017F>he recovered her Breath; this relief called again the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105648:21"/>
natural heat which <U+017F>eem'd to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aken her, and drove away part of my Allarms, after a deep <U+017F>igh, <U+017F>he open'd her Eyes, and <U+017F>eeing her <U+017F>elf alone with a man, having but a thin gown on, <U+017F>he was willing to change her po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture. Knowing her De<U+017F>ign, and de<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to plea<U+017F>e her, I let her <U+017F>et down upon the Gra<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>eeing <U+017F>he was able to under<U+017F>tand me; <hi>Fair</hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <U+017F>aid I, <hi>that Fate which hath expo<U+017F>ed your Life, hath been favourable to my Affection, but let not this adventure trouble you, <U+017F>ince</hi> Scanderberg <hi>would <U+017F>ooner lo<U+017F>e his Life, than his re<U+017F>pect towards your Per<U+017F>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a <U+017F>ighed twice or thrice, and was <U+017F>ome while without an<U+017F>wering me, but at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>he reply'd: <hi>Tho' my Life be not dear to me, My Lord, I am not the le<U+017F>s beholding to you; if you had not been <U+017F>o generous, you had freed me from many Misfortunes; but you could not have gue<U+017F>t my condition.</hi> I was as much moved with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s words, as with her langui<U+017F>hing Charms. <hi>I know not what Fate Heaven de<U+017F>igns for you, but I <U+017F>hall think my <U+017F>elf happy for ever, <U+017F>ince I have been <U+017F>erviceable to you; in another time, and under another Government, I <U+017F>hould take other mea<U+017F>ures, and <U+017F>hould not let you</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105648:21"/>
                  <hi>know my Love, till my Services and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pect had <U+017F>ufficiently demon<U+017F>trated it; and de<U+017F>erved your con<U+017F>ent; but as things <U+017F>tand now, how is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible to <U+017F>ee you in a Palace, where we can have no admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion? and how can one <U+017F>peak with you, <U+017F>ince it is in vain to hope to come near you? I Love you, I am forced to acquaint you with it, and if this free Confe<U+017F><U+017F>ion renders me guilty, I <U+017F>hall never repine at my Puni<U+017F>hment, I was the <U+017F>ame before I had <U+017F>een you, and I adored your Vertue, without knowing your Per<U+017F>on. What Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e is this, My Lord,</hi> interrupted <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> with a charming Sweetne<U+017F>s? <hi>Is this to try me? Do you con<U+017F>ider that I am a Slave, <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Emperour of the</hi> Turks, <hi>loaded with Chains by</hi> Selimana, <hi>and who likely <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>ee you any more in all her life time? as for your pre<U+017F>ent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> <U+017F>aid I, <hi>it is an injury of Fortune, which may ea<U+017F>ily be repaired, and if you de<U+017F>ire to put an end to your Captivity, do but tru<U+017F>t me, and, follow me. What can you do, Scanderberg,</hi> cry'd that fair Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive? <hi>You have Valour enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> Amurat<hi>'s Enemies, but you are not <U+017F>trong enough to deliver me from his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I had done, may be, more than <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105648:22"/>
could hope for, if on one <U+017F>ide <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> who had followed my <U+017F>teps, had not arrived near us, and on the other, we had not <U+017F>een the Emperour's Galley, returning to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantinople</hi> grievou<U+017F>ly afflicted, to have <U+017F>een <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> carried away by the Stream wherein <U+017F>he had fallen, advancing too far in the Bath: Too happy <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> <U+017F>aid the jealous Prince to me, why don't you content your <U+017F>elf with <hi>Selimana</hi>'s Favours? <hi>I</hi> was vexed at this Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> Blu<U+017F>hed: <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>aw the young <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> had no mind to oblige me, but I had not time to let him know my anger. <hi>Amurat,</hi> in a kind of De<U+017F>pair, who<U+017F>e eyes <U+017F>ought <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> every where, perceived us upon the Shore, and came to deprive me of what <hi>I</hi> had acquired, with the hazard of my own life: He told me confu<U+017F>edly, <hi>I</hi> had done him a good piece of Service; and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing into the Galley, a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ured me by a kind look, <U+017F>he was not in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of what <hi>I</hi> had done for her. <hi>I</hi> cannot expre<U+017F>s what my amorous heart <U+017F>uffered at this parting. Tho' I had feared it, yet <hi>I</hi> thought it would not be <U+017F>o <U+017F>udden, and <hi>I</hi> could hardly hide my <U+017F>orrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105648:22"/>
                  <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> <U+017F>aid <hi>Mahomet</hi> to me, we are both in Love with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> but tho' the Laws render our Fortunes equal, by forbidding us from <U+017F>eeing her, yet you have <U+017F>ome advantages that may comfort you for that Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. <hi>I</hi> could deny to you, what are my Sentiments, concerning <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> an<U+017F>wered I, <U+017F>ince any generous man ought to have done what <hi>I</hi> did, and that <hi>I</hi> knew not it was <U+017F>he, when I went about to <U+017F>erve her, but I cannot di<U+017F><U+017F>emble, and <hi>I</hi> mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s that I love her. <hi>I</hi> perceived, My Lord, you were my Rival, and a jealous Rival too, who cared not to oblige me, when you <U+017F>poke to me concerning <hi>Selimana.</hi> Can you wonder, <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould promote my own heart's intere<U+017F>t, reply'd the young <hi>Sultan? Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> is not beloved by the Emperour, and were you not my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, may be <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould have none. You are mi<U+017F>taken, <hi>Mahomet,</hi> added <hi>I;</hi> the Emperour has changed his Love: What is he in Love with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> reply'd he? Yes, <U+017F>aid <hi>I.</hi> Alas! continued he <U+017F>ighing, what hope can flatter us? and <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e we <U+017F>hould follow the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the mo<U+017F>t violent jealou<U+017F>ie, what advantage will that afford us? Then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105648:23"/>
we entered into <hi>Adrianople,</hi> where the Emperour was already returned, and we put an end to our Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> met <hi>Aradin</hi> who was looking for me, knowing what had pa<U+017F>t. Having done <U+017F>o much for my per<U+017F>on, <U+017F>aid I to him, embracing him, will you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nothing for my re<U+017F>t? will you abandon me to tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>orrows, that Love threatens me with? and will all your acquaintance in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> prove fruitle<U+017F>s? <hi>I</hi> ought to employ them only for the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Service, reply'd <hi>Aradin,</hi> and my Zeal can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford you but a weak a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance; tho' you are infinitely dear to me, <hi>I</hi> am forced to <U+017F>ee you <U+017F>uffer, without at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting any thing in your behalf. I <U+017F>ee <hi>Amurat</hi> is mad becau<U+017F>e you have <U+017F>een <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> he fears without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing why, and we <U+017F>hall become Slaves to his jealou<U+017F>ie. Is that your way of comforting me, dear <hi>Aradin,</hi> cry'd I? But what will you have, reply'd the Eunuch, and what can one do under a Ma<U+017F>ter <U+017F>o powerful, and <U+017F>o formidable as <hi>Amurat?</hi> Do you think <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> will be able to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t him? and <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e <U+017F>he had no real Love for him, <U+017F>he mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>till fear and obey
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105648:23"/>
him. <hi>Aradin</hi>'s di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, filled my mind with <U+017F>o dreadful Ideas, that <hi>I</hi> was like to dye for Grief, and he <U+017F>aw me <U+017F>o much afflicted, that he could not deny me the Favour of carrying a Letter from me to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> 'Tis likely <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hall pay dear enough, <U+017F>aid he, for what I am going to do for you; but <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hall ea<U+017F>ily comfort my <U+017F>elf, if you are fully per<U+017F>waded of my <U+017F>incere Friend<U+017F>hip. <hi>I</hi> embraced <hi>Aradin,</hi> and having wrote what Love dictated to me, <hi>I</hi> delivered the Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let to his care: There are but the<U+017F>e few words in it.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Prince <hi>Scanderberg</hi> to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I </hi>Could wi<U+017F>h, fair<hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, </hi>for my heart's re<U+017F>t, that you were le<U+017F>s amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or le<U+017F>s beloved; pity me for having <U+017F>o many misfortunes to <U+017F>uffer, and <U+017F>o ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Enemies to overcome: You cannot but be <U+017F>orry for my condition, <U+017F>ince for the reward of my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate and Faithful Heart, which I pre<U+017F>ent you with, the only thing I ask, is the leave of telling you, I <U+017F>hall adore you for ever.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105648:24"/>
The officious <hi>Aradin</hi> took all the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable care to come near <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> but he could not that day, <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o wearied by her la<U+017F>t Misfortune, that <U+017F>he was forced to keep her Bed. The Emperour took no longer any care to hide his new Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, but owned it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> had a private Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for her <U+017F>elf; and <hi>Selimana,</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with other cares, was not <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible at fir<U+017F>t of the <U+017F>hame of being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aken.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of the marks of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Love, <U+017F>o much wi<U+017F>hed for by the other Women of the Seraglio. <hi>Amurat</hi> <U+017F>ighed like other Lovers at the fir<U+017F>t growth of his Pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion; after that he would fain go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was equally di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plea<U+017F>ed with his Sighs and Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>hewed a repugnancy which he little expected, and which was look'd upon by him as a Prodigy in a Girl of her Age and condition; the more becau<U+017F>e his violent de<U+017F>ires had never met before with <U+017F>uch a re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aradin,</hi> a zealous and diligent Friend, perform'd his errand as <U+017F>oon as he could; he found <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> alone, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and thinking doubtle<U+017F>s upon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105648:24"/>
what <U+017F>he was to <U+017F>uffer from the <hi>Sultan.</hi> Fair <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to her, all moments are here precious, and I ought not to neglect them. <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> famous for his Valour, and remarkable for his rare and great Qualities, (forgive me, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> if I u<U+017F>e <hi>Aradin</hi>'s words, to avoid all digre<U+017F><U+017F>ions) <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> <U+017F>ay I, kept far from you by a barbarous Law, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ires you might know his Zea and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tancy; and to that purpo<U+017F>e he is forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make u<U+017F>e of this innocent means. Then the Eunuch offered her the Billet: But <U+017F>he who knew not our intimate friend<U+017F>hip thought he was come to try her. The<U+017F>e Intreagues are not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Seraglio, an<U+017F>wered <U+017F>he; we might pay both dear enough for them; and your Ma<U+017F>ter is not <U+017F>o kind a Prince as to permit them. Leave off therefore this Playing, which cannot but di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plea<U+017F>e me, and may prove fatal to your <U+017F>elf: And believe, that I care neither to love nor to be loved. You may <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect me of Perfideou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Aradin,</hi> <U+017F>eeing it is <U+017F>o common among the <hi>Turks,</hi> and becau<U+017F>e I am altogether unknown to you. But, <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> do not entertain <U+017F>uch a thought concerning me; and do not wrong <U+017F>o
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105648:25"/>
far the Prince <hi>Scanderberg;</hi> he loves you, and you cannot, but with a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty blame-worthy, deny him the favour to read what he writes to you. <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> after a long re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, took at la<U+017F>t the Paper, and kept her eyes fix'd upon it a con<U+017F>iderable while; <U+017F>o that likely <U+017F>he read it more than once. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radin</hi> ob<U+017F>erved her, and told me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, that he had perceiv'd in her looks a trouble which favoured me, that <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ighed, and <U+017F>eem'd to feel <U+017F>ome tender motions in her heart; and con<U+017F>idering her and my own condition, <U+017F>he had <U+017F>aid, alas, <hi>Aradin,</hi> what can the Prince <hi>Scanderberg</hi> expect from me, who can di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of nothing, and find my <U+017F>elf bound in that unfortunate place where my ill Fortune detains me? All his de<U+017F>ire, replyed <hi>Aradin,</hi> is, you would permit him to love you, and that your kindne<U+017F>s might be concerned in all his misfortunes. Suppo<U+017F>e I <U+017F>hould do what he de<U+017F>ires, added <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> would his condition be the happier? Bid him, <U+017F>ooner forget me, and if he finds in me any thing that de<U+017F>erves his affection, let him con<U+017F>ider, that all <U+017F>orts of Conver<U+017F>ation is forbidden us; let him take care, not to attempt any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105648:25"/>
enterprize that may either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do him or endanger my <U+017F>elf; let him be careful chiefly of his own life. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> interrupted <hi>Aradin,</hi> is your heart <U+017F>o much concerned for his life as to de<U+017F>ire its pre<U+017F>ervation? Ask me no <U+017F>uch que<U+017F>tions, replyed the fair Slave blu<U+017F>hing, and do only what I bid you. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid the officious <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> one word from your hand would do more with him than any thing I can tell him. You ask for too much, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and you know your <U+017F>elf, I ought not to do what you de<U+017F>ire; that all things are dangerous here, and that very often the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ecret Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons become publick. I tremble even now for rea<U+017F>on of this conver<U+017F>ation; be gone, <hi>Aradin,</hi> and leave me to my dreadful <U+017F>orrow. I leave you to the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s love, replyed <hi>Aradin.</hi> Cruel misfortune of my Life, and cau<U+017F>e of all my Mi<U+017F>eries, cryed <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> how dearly have I paid for that love which I abhor? and what <U+017F>orrows I am like to <U+017F>uffer upon its account? Some body coming, obliged them to part. <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> kept my Letter, and <hi>Aradin</hi> came to me to acquaint me with what had pa<U+017F>s'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105648:26"/>
The Emperour's love was too violent not to be followed by an extraordinary jealou<U+017F>ie; his <U+017F>u<U+017F>picious increa<U+017F>ed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ively; and con<U+017F>idering <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s coldne<U+017F>s, he thought that either her heart was not free when <U+017F>he came to the Seraglio, or that <U+017F>ince <U+017F>he had fallen in love. His meeting me in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, my good fortune upon the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hoar, and my deep melancholy, which I was no more able to hide, rais'd great <U+017F>u<U+017F>picions in his mind. And though my condition was but little different from <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s, or the Prince's, yet I <U+017F>eem'd to him more formidable than they, by rea<U+017F>on of my good Fortune: He ob<U+017F>erv'd carefully all my <U+017F>teps, took notice of my Eyes, which were always turned towards the Seraglio, explained to him<U+017F>elf the meaning of my troubles, and of my Sighs; and in a word, did not que<U+017F>tion but I was in love. You may ea<U+017F>ily conjecture whether it was an ea<U+017F>ie matter for me to attempt any thing, being watch'd by <U+017F>uch an <hi>Argus. Aradin,</hi> who perceived his jealou<U+017F>ie, was continually advi<U+017F>ing me how I ought to <U+017F>teer my Conduct, and in this unea<U+017F>ie condition I <U+017F>pent many <U+017F>ad and u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s days.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105648:26"/>
But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> I was not the only Man who was troubled. <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> loved exceedingly <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a:</hi> The <U+017F>ame Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion wholly po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and <hi>Selimana</hi> being for<U+017F>aken by the Emperor, began to be <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of the injury done her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thought the only way to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, was to get a new Lover.</p>
               <p>There is always a prodigious number of Eunuchs in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> who<U+017F>e duty is to ob<U+017F>erve the Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es, and to <U+017F>erve them, and tho<U+017F>e are pickt out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the uglie<U+017F>t. <hi>Selimana</hi>'s favour had gained her the zeal of the mo<U+017F>t con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of them: <hi>Amaldan</hi> had always <U+017F>tuck to her intere<U+017F>t; and <U+017F>ince <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi>'s new Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion gave her time to mind her own, <U+017F>he manag'd <U+017F>o well the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch's Zeal, that he was willing to do her any Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaldan</hi> was about forty years old, he was black and ugly, but witty and bold, and in a word, a fit Confident to <U+017F>erve <hi>Selimana:</hi> It had look'd a little odd, if he had acquainted me without any more ado with <hi>Selimana</hi>'s tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. She knew not what the Prince and I had heard, and therefore <U+017F>he could make no u<U+017F>e of that Adventure; had <U+017F>he directly written to me, it was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105648:27"/>
likely my Heart had not been plea<U+017F>d with that freedom; <U+017F>he therefore whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relyed upon <hi>Amaldan</hi>'s wit: Having been bred up a Schollar, he under<U+017F>tood Greek perfectly well, and was well nough acquainted with the niceties of Poetry; he thought therefore his be<U+017F>t way at fir<U+017F>t, was to <U+017F>hew me <U+017F>ome wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ver<U+017F>es; and having made <U+017F>ome fit for his purpo<U+017F>e, he acco<U+017F>ted me upon a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<U+017F>s in the great <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s Gardens where, in a melancholly Humour, I was looking upon the Stream that water'd the foot of the Walls. Who could believe, my Lord, <U+017F>aid he to me, that a Prince of your Age and Parts would <U+017F>eek <U+017F>olitary places without being in love? Was your Heart free, you would not <U+017F>hun with <U+017F>o much care other Men's Conver<U+017F>ation. I beg your pardon, my Lord, for my boldne<U+017F>s; but your natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bounty will excu<U+017F>e this freedom, which is not ordinarily u<U+017F>ed towards Per<U+017F>ons of your rank, but in whatever condition you are, either free, or not, tho<U+017F>e that honour you as much as I do, ought to do always their endeavours to divert you. I blu<U+017F>hed, hearing <hi>Amaldan,</hi> <U+017F>peak thus, fearing le<U+017F>t he <U+017F>hould <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect <U+017F>omething. My Lord, <U+017F>aid he then, one
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105648:27"/>
does not blu<U+017F>h except he hath <U+017F>ome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on for it, and this commotion proceeds likely from your Heart. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out piercing too far into a Secret which I ought to reverence, give me leave to con<U+017F>ult you upon a nice point. And then he offered me <U+017F>ome Ver<U+017F>es, which I could not deny to read, and which I remember yet, they were tho<U+017F>e:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Love, like a dangerous Tyrant <U+017F>till ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,</l>
                  <l>His fancy'd Laws <U+017F>ound har<U+017F>h to tender Ears.</l>
                  <l>Women, if fair, we mu<U+017F>t avoid, they <U+017F>ay,</l>
                  <l>Like fatal Rocks at Sea, which oft de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>troy.</l>
                  <l>Such feign'd Advice puts out the glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire,</l>
                  <l>And turns the edge of ev'ry brisk De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ire.</l>
                  <l>The Fears of Shipwraek thro' the fancy rove,</l>
                  <l>And fright the Youth from off the Seas of Love.</l>
                  <l>But when he <U+017F>ees the way before him's clear,</l>
                  <l>When he is cho<U+017F>e and loved, what needs he fear?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105648:28"/>
If he would then enjoy a happy State,</l>
                  <l>He mu<U+017F>t give up his yielding Heart to Fate:</l>
                  <l>When he is Conqueror own'd, then Arms are vain;</l>
                  <l>To u<U+017F>e the Conque<U+017F>t is the <U+017F>weete<U+017F>t gain.</l>
                  <l>The greater then his Zeal does prove,</l>
                  <l>The more's the glory of his Love.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I lik'd them well enough, and I read them more than once; but I never <U+017F>u<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the meaning of them. <hi>Amaldan</hi> was glad I was plea<U+017F>ed with them, and thought it was now time for him to tru<U+017F>t me with his Secret. Is it not true, my Lord, that Love is commonly drawn af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a <U+017F>trange manner? and that, if we will hearken to the Wits, it is a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mon<U+017F>ter, which ought carefully to be avoided? I confe<U+017F>s, it appears un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plea<U+017F>ant to tho<U+017F>e that have nothing that renders them worthy to be beloved; but I imagine thou<U+017F>ands of Charms in the <U+017F>incere and tender love of two Hearts. I mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s, <U+017F>aid I to <hi>Amaldan,</hi> that your Ver<U+017F>es and your Opinion <U+017F>eem to me to be in the right; but I am <U+017F>o little ver<U+017F>ed in Love Matters, that I am no competent Judge of its Effects. My Lord, reply'd the Eunuch, when you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105648:28"/>
plea<U+017F>e you may be a great proficient therein, and I know a certain way for that purpo<U+017F>e. I cannot di<U+017F><U+017F>emble with a Prince, as di<U+017F>creet as you are. I'll tell you therefore, you are loved by <hi>Seli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana, Amurat</hi>'s beloved Sultane<U+017F>s; <U+017F>he acquaints you, what way it is be<U+017F>t for you to follow, by her order I <U+017F>peak to you, and you ought not to be di<U+017F>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged at the <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s Maximes, <U+017F>ince I can overcome the greate<U+017F>t Difficulties. I did not expect <U+017F>uch a Complement from <hi>Amaldan,</hi> which did not an<U+017F>wer my Inclinations, and I was a little while without an<U+017F>wering him. You bring your <U+017F>elf into no danger by your freedom, <U+017F>aid I at la<U+017F>t to him. I take it for a token of your E<U+017F>teem and Friend<U+017F>hip, nor am I willing to make an ill u<U+017F>e of it. <hi>Seli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana</hi> may be fair and kind, but <hi>Amurat</hi> is a formidable Prince, and my Loyalty obliges me to all <U+017F>orts of re<U+017F>pects. You don't <U+017F>peak, reply'd the Eunuch <U+017F>miling, like a young Prince favour'd by Love, but like a fearful Politician, or a moro<U+017F>e Philo<U+017F>opher. This mode<U+017F>ty which ought to be prai<U+017F>ed in a Dervi<U+017F>e, <U+017F>eems to me in you the <U+017F>trange<U+017F>t things in the world; what can all <hi>Amurat</hi>'s power do, <U+017F>ince your beloved <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Plea<U+017F>ures
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105648:29"/>
ea<U+017F>ily obtained, lo<U+017F>e much of their <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s? Be<U+017F>ides, was I not certain to <U+017F>erve you, I am not <U+017F>o much out of love with my own life, as to expo<U+017F>e my <U+017F>elf to an unavoidable Death: Let me then be your Guide, and tru<U+017F>t me with the carrying on of your Intregue. All <hi>Amaldan</hi>'s fair words could not per<U+017F>uade me to it. I was not willing to expo<U+017F>e my <U+017F>elf to <U+017F>o many Dangers for <hi>Selima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s <U+017F>ake, and I alledged <U+017F>till in my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, Cu<U+017F>tom, and my Loyalty to the Emperor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaldan</hi> did not acquaint the Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s with the unhappy i<U+017F><U+017F>ue of his fir<U+017F>t Negotiation, le<U+017F>t he <U+017F>hould drive her into De<U+017F>pair; her hatred again<U+017F>t <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi> increa<U+017F>ed, as his love for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a;</hi> <U+017F>he was capable of any violent Action, had not <hi>Amaldan</hi> allay'd her Rage.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who <U+017F>eem'd to act nothing, and <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman,</hi> who<U+017F>e proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were very <U+017F>ecret, had neverthele<U+017F>s <U+017F>ome private Intelligences, and gain'd <U+017F>ome Friends in the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> Covetou<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s is <U+017F>o natural to the <hi>Turks,</hi> that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere<U+017F>t often makes void the <U+017F>everity of their Laws. <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Ba<U+017F><U+017F>i</hi> being a rich Man, gained by his liberality almo<U+017F>t all the Eunuchs; and except <hi>Aradin</hi> who<U+017F>e
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105648:29"/>
Hone<U+017F>ty was proof again<U+017F>t all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the re<U+017F>t yielded ea<U+017F>ily to his Gold; having a free occa<U+017F>ion in the Gardens, he could freely Conver<U+017F>e with them; he intru<U+017F>ted the cunning <hi>Amaldan</hi> with his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> Another had been <U+017F>tarted at this Propo<U+017F>ition. But <hi>Amaldan</hi> harken'd to it without the lea<U+017F>t Commotion, and his exaggerating to the grand Gardner, the difficulties they <U+017F>hould meet with, was only to <U+017F>et an higher value upon his Services.</p>
               <p>You may judge, <hi>Thopia,</hi> thereby, how Pernicious is idlene<U+017F>s; had the <hi>Eunuchs</hi> a different Employment from that of ob<U+017F>erving the Women in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> they <U+017F>hould never apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves to barter their Favours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaldan,</hi> who knew <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to perceive her good Nature, feared not in the lea<U+017F>t to be puni<U+017F>hed by her for his boldne<U+017F>s. He did <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ulman</hi>'s Errant, as <hi>Aradin</hi> had done mine, and repre<U+017F>ented the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F><U+017F>i</hi>'s Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion to her, as the only way to free her from her <U+017F>lavery; <U+017F>he did not entertain him as <U+017F>he had done <hi>Aradin,</hi> but with a Noble Pride, <U+017F>he let him under<U+017F>tand that it was in vain for the grand Gardner to hope any thing from
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105648:30"/>
her. The covetous <hi>Amaldan</hi> was little troubled at this, and was not <U+017F>uch a Fool as to di<U+017F>courage any body, as long as he could obtain his Ends. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved in <U+017F>pight of my <U+017F>elf, to bring me one Night into <hi>Selimana</hi>'s compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and little <U+017F>olicitous of her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Fortune, <U+017F>o he might <U+017F>atisfie him<U+017F>elf. He tru<U+017F>ted <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> with this Secret. He told him that if he could bring me into the private Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, for him<U+017F>elf, he would get <hi>Selima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> to take a walk, which might be favourable to us, making the grand Gardner believe, that I was in love with the <hi>Sultane<U+017F>s,</hi> and that fear only hindred me from courting her. <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman,</hi> who had <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected I loved <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> was glad to under<U+017F>tand this Mi<U+017F>tery, and promi<U+017F>ed to do whatever <hi>Amaldan</hi> de<U+017F>ired.</p>
               <p>The grand Gardner was well enough acquainted with the Maxims of the Country; the effects of which he ought to fear, but his Love prevailed over his Rea<U+017F>on. He found me out, as he had promi<U+017F>ed to <hi>Amaldan,</hi> and asked me, whether I was willing to walk. I could not gue<U+017F>s his intentions, and tho' <hi>I</hi> looked upon him as my Rival, yet, at la<U+017F>t <hi>I</hi> followed him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:105648:30"/>
We took many turns in the <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s Garden, and the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Ba<U+017F><U+017F>i,</hi> who was well acquainted with all the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, brought me into that of the Women, through a door which we found open'd; <hi>I</hi> was not <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible at fir<U+017F>t of my wandring, but coming near a labyrinth, which <hi>I</hi> had not <U+017F>een <U+017F>ince my Infancy. <hi>I</hi> was <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>ee my <U+017F>elf in that place. <hi>You are mi<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or you have a mind to ruine me,</hi> <U+017F>aid <hi>I</hi> to <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman, and the<U+017F>e places are not free for <U+017F>uch per<U+017F>ons as we. Do you think I am capable of betraying you?</hi> An<U+017F>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman, and do you believe I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>hare here the <U+017F>ame Fortune with you? Your pre<U+017F>ence is de<U+017F>ired by</hi> Selimana, <hi>and her kindne<U+017F>s will protect you.</hi> As I was going to an<U+017F>wer, di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ed with his proceedings, we <U+017F>aw Prince <hi>Mahomet</hi> coming, who had no more priviledge than we, and who was not there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <U+017F>ome De<U+017F>ign. He was as much <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>ed as we. We could not think but we were guilty all three; yet pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would have us hide our Re<U+017F>ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and had we had a mind to fall out, we had been hindered by <hi>Abaci</hi> the Eunuch, who had introduced the young <hi>Sultan,</hi> and who knew nothing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105648:31"/>
of our being there. My Lord, <hi><U+017F>aid he to him, loud enough to be heard by us Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> is coming, make u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>u<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a favourable moment. <hi>Abaci</hi> went hi<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way, and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who had parte<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from <hi>Selimana,</hi> came. Tho' Night de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived us of the <U+017F>ight of her Charms, yet by rea<U+017F>on of its favourable <U+017F>ilence we could the better hear her <U+017F>ight. <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> curbed by <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s pre<U+017F>ence did not enjoy the happine<U+017F>s he hoped for. And the Prince in a maze by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on of <hi>Abaci</hi>'s di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, tarried in the <U+017F>ame place. For my part, I was al<U+017F>o put to a <U+017F>tand. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>at her <U+017F>elf down upon the gra<U+017F>s, and thinking <U+017F>he was heard by no body, <U+017F>he let go the<U+017F>e <U+017F>ad Complaints. Unfortunate <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he,</hi> Prince<U+017F>s expos'd to ever la<U+017F>ting Sufferings, what can<U+017F>t thou expect from <hi>Amurat?</hi> What can<U+017F>t thou do for <hi>Scanderberg?</hi> Did Cruel Fate take thee from <hi>Albania,</hi> to offer him here too Charming for thy Re<U+017F>t? <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot,</hi> why don't you ask all the Princes of the World <U+017F>ome Succour, to deliver <U+017F>uch an Illu<U+017F>trious Son from tho<U+017F>e Hands, who likely, for a Reward of his Glorious Exploits, will one day <U+017F>acrifice him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105648:31"/>
The<U+017F>e <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s words made a deep impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion upon both our Hearts. But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> tho<U+017F>e two Rivals were not the only I ought to fear, a third more formidable heard them. <hi>Amurat</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted by <U+017F>ome Traytor, that <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> were in the Garden, was <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed at it, becau<U+017F>e they were not u<U+017F>ed to go there, running there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with all po<U+017F><U+017F>ible ha<U+017F>te, he heard what I have already told you. Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, cryed he in a jealous rage,</hi> thou telle<U+017F>t every moment I <U+017F>ee thee, and tho' thou ha<U+017F>t my mo<U+017F>t ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Affections, yet wi<U+017F>he<U+017F>t thou my Ruine. Thy imprudent Heart hath condemned <hi>Scanderberg</hi> to dye, and I will puni<U+017F>h him for having plea<U+017F>ed thee, as I ought to do. I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of thy Anger, <hi>replyed the coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and I am <U+017F>o far from pacifying it, that I confirm to thee what thou ha<U+017F>t already heard by chance. A Power above thine will defend that Prince thou intende<U+017F>t to Oppre<U+017F>s, and for my part, I <U+017F>hall be plea<U+017F>ed better with Death than with thy Love.</p>
               <p>About that time, <hi>Thopia,</hi> did the Emperor perceive us. I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F>s his Rage to you. His Son, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105648:32"/>
                  <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulmon</hi> <U+017F>uffered but little by it. It fell heavy only upon me. Take away that Slave, <U+017F>aid he, to a great many <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> and be re<U+017F>pon<U+017F>ible of the lea<U+017F>t of her Actions: and for thee, <hi><U+017F>aid he, turning towards me,</hi> Knave, and per<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> unworthy Object of <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Favours, and the fatal cau<U+017F>e of all his pre<U+017F>ent grief, go, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <U+017F>uch a death as thou de<U+017F>erve<U+017F>t. If thine Injuries proceeds from thy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ie, <hi>an<U+017F>wered I,</hi> I forgive them upon that account, becau<U+017F>e that Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion is u<U+017F>ed to blind our Rea<U+017F>on. Think of my moderation what thou plea<U+017F>et, but know, that had any other Man <U+017F>poke to me after this manner, be<U+017F>ides thee, he <U+017F>hould not e<U+017F>cape unpuni<U+017F>hed.</p>
               <p>The proud Emperor harkned no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to me. He commanded I <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>hut up in the dreadfulle<U+017F>t Pri<U+017F>on, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by what he had heard, <hi>I</hi> entertain'd <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ecret Corre<U+017F>pondence with <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> As for <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman,</hi> he <U+017F>hew'd them only an angry Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, without Arre<U+017F>ting them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selimana</hi> ran away hearing this noi<U+017F>e, and <hi>Amaldan</hi> was not <U+017F>uch a Fool as to come and <U+017F>hew his Face. As <U+017F>oon as we were out of the Gardens, <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105648:32"/>
threatned the <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> and <U+017F>truck Terror every where. He <U+017F>ent the ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<U+017F>t of his <hi>Seraglio</hi> to ob<U+017F>erve the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and <U+017F>uch a va<U+017F>t number of them was placed in <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Appartment, that all admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion there became impo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> was <U+017F>hut up in a Dungeon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <U+017F>eeing <hi>Aradin,</hi> whom my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was like to ca<U+017F>t into a de<U+017F>pair. He under<U+017F>tood the Adventure <hi>I</hi> have relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, by <hi>Amaldan</hi>'s means, who<U+017F>e imprudence and di<U+017F>loyalty he much blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Aradin</hi> did not que<U+017F>tion the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine<U+017F>s of my grief, in <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>orrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful place, where <hi>I</hi> had <U+017F>o many rea<U+017F>ons of being afflicted. <hi>Amurat</hi> upbraided him with my pretended treachery, and accu<U+017F>ed him to have bred me up in tho<U+017F>e, ill di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions, being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with hiss Temper, he yielded to the fir<U+017F>t tran<U+017F>ports of his rage, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to condemn me, and by the<U+017F>e means prevented his own di<U+017F>grace. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <U+017F>till his wonted freedom, he made u<U+017F>e of it, he <U+017F>aw <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> in <U+017F>pight of all her Ob<U+017F>ervers, comforted her, and obliged her to write to me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting her with my deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. She did not que<U+017F>tion in the lea<U+017F>t,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105648:33"/>
but <hi>I</hi> had heard her in the Garden, and therefore was the ea<U+017F>ier re<U+017F>olved to it. <hi>Aradin</hi> <U+017F>ent me this Note by one of my Guardians.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a </hi>to the Prince<hi> Scanderberg.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I </hi>Am fain to let you know I pity your misfortune, and no con<U+017F>ideration can di<U+017F>wade me from it; tho<U+017F>e Powers that Tyrannize over you do not <U+017F>pare me. But, my Lord, I prote<U+017F>t your Pains are my greate<U+017F>t Evils; if this a<U+017F><U+017F>urance may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, you may intirely enjoy the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure of it. I am concerned for your Re<U+017F>t, I am grieved, and even weep for your mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. Tho' I dare not tell you any thing as concerning my heart, you may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthele<U+017F>s think thereupon what you <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e will the be<U+017F>t <U+017F>atisfie you. This favour<hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a </hi>begs from you,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, </hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to<hi> Aranit Conino, </hi>a Prince beloved by the King your Father.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Having read this Letter, <hi>I</hi> was no longer <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of the heavine<U+017F>s of my Chains. <hi>I</hi> enjoyed my hearts de<U+017F>ire. <hi>I</hi> was beloved of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> born of one of the mo<U+017F>t Illu<U+017F>trious Families in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania. I</hi> knew <hi>Aranit</hi>'s name, and tho'
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105648:33"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> had but a feeble Idea of my Father's Court, yet <hi>I</hi> could remember him. It was quite impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for me to an<U+017F>wer <hi>Ariant<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Note. And all that <hi>I</hi> could do was to read it over a thou<U+017F>and times a day.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> Fortune, which intended to cro<U+017F>s me, afflicted me <U+017F>till with new msifortunes. <hi>I</hi> learnt from that man whom <hi>Aradin</hi> had di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to favour me, that my Father was dead, that <hi>Amurat</hi> was incen<U+017F>ed again<U+017F>t me, and to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s him<U+017F>elf of <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, had poi<U+017F>oned my three Brothers, de<U+017F>igning me for another Sacrifice; but altho' he was violent to exce<U+017F>s; he dur<U+017F>t not de<U+017F>troy me, in the Pre<U+017F>ence of the Turki<U+017F>h Souldiers, by whom <hi>I</hi> was loved, and who began to grumble at my Captivity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Cruelty produced in my heart that effect which could be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onably expected; yet <hi>I</hi> mu<U+017F>t tell you, to ju<U+017F>tifie my re<U+017F>entments, that <hi>I</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver projected any De<U+017F>ign again<U+017F>t him, unworthy of a Man of Courage; all that <hi>I</hi> de<U+017F>ired, was to <U+017F>ee my <U+017F>elf free, and to declare an open War again<U+017F>t the proud <hi>Sultan,</hi> who regarded <U+017F>o little the Blood <hi>I</hi> had lo<U+017F>t in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105648:34"/>
Whil<U+017F>t I was thus griev'd and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, both by Nature and Love, the <hi>Turks,</hi> who had <U+017F>een me venture my life for their Emperour's Glory, pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Fate, and demanded my Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Amurat</hi> de<U+017F>ired my death, but feared the con<U+017F>equences thereof, and therefore was obliged by rea<U+017F>on of the Grumbling of the Nation, to put an end to my Captivity.</p>
               <p>Going out of Pri<U+017F>on, I retired to <hi>Acomat,</hi> a young <hi>Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and the only Man among<U+017F>t the Turks, upon who<U+017F>e Friend<U+017F>hip I did mo<U+017F>t rely. I met there with a generous reception; he approved my Re<U+017F>entment, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>ed me to go my <U+017F>elf, and upbraid the <hi>Sultan</hi> for his ungratefulne<U+017F>s. But I could not abide his <U+017F>ight, I could not think without horror on my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death. My Mother's <U+017F>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the mi<U+017F>erable Life the young Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es my Si<U+017F>ters lead in <U+017F>ome retired place of <hi>Albania.</hi> I heard before it was long, the violent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Emperor's Tyranny; I had a true Relation thereof from <hi>Aradin,</hi> whom I <U+017F>aw by <hi>Acomat</hi>'s means, he a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me al<U+017F>o of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s towards me, and added, that tho'
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105648:34"/>
the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Rage had not fall'n <U+017F>o heavy upon <hi>Mahomet</hi> or <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> as upon me, yet they had <U+017F>marted for his Jealou<U+017F>ie.</p>
               <p>Tho' I was fully at liberty, I did not know what to re<U+017F>olve. <hi>Amurat</hi> had po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd him<U+017F>elf of all my Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and the only thing I could own, was my Sword; after a long Con<U+017F>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with <hi>Acomat</hi> and <hi>Aradin,</hi> at la<U+017F>t I intended to depart, tho' I felt a great reluctancy in leaving <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tho' I had conceived a mortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred again<U+017F>t <hi>Amurat,</hi> yet I re<U+017F>olved to <U+017F>peak to him. I met him one day, as he was going out of the <hi>Divan.</hi> He had been vexed at <U+017F>ome important deliberation there, and di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ed with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s continual rigour, <U+017F>o that one could ea<U+017F>ily read his Rage in his Eyes. <hi>I thought,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>you <U+017F>hould make a better u<U+017F>e of the Liberty I grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you at</hi> Adrianople, <hi>than to offer your <U+017F>elf to my pre<U+017F>ence, and that your remor<U+017F>e <U+017F>hould free me from the <U+017F>ight of <U+017F>uch an odious Object.</hi> This Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, like the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Pride, was too outragious to me, to be born patiently. <hi>If thine ungrateful Eyes had never <U+017F>een me,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wered I, <hi>it is likely you had paid dear</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:105648:35"/>
                  <hi>enough for it. You are no longer an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tage,</hi> interrupted the unju<U+017F>t <hi>Amurat, but a Captive, of whom the</hi> Jani<U+017F><U+017F>aries, <hi>are to be re<U+017F>pon<U+017F>ible. If thou had<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>idered Ho<U+017F>tages as <U+017F>acred,</hi> replyed I, <hi>thou had<U+017F>t never poi<U+017F>on'd my Brothers, and nothing can hide the Horror of this Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous action from Po<U+017F>terity. I pity thy young age,</hi> replyed the Sultan, with a <U+017F>cornful <U+017F>mile, <hi>and the trouble thou take<U+017F>t of de<U+017F>cribing my Actions, de<U+017F>erves a fit Reward; get far from me and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <hi>and repent of having offended me. I <U+017F>wear to thee by our mo<U+017F>t Holy Laws, I <U+017F>hall never call thee back again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So he left me <U+017F>pightfully. I <U+017F>aw pre<U+017F>ently, that it was now time for me to depart, and to perform for my own Family, and that of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> what Honour required from me; it was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for me to <U+017F>ee that Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Beauty, whom <hi>I</hi> recommended a thou<U+017F>and times to the care of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate <hi>Aradin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurat,</hi> to cloak his inju<U+017F>tice, and not to di<U+017F>oblige the <hi>Jani<U+017F><U+017F>aries,</hi> who had declared them<U+017F>elves my Protectors, offered me by <hi>Orcan,</hi> his Favourite, and already Grand <hi>Vi<U+017F>ier,</hi> in the room of the decea<U+017F>ed <hi>Her<U+017F>ecoli,</hi> the Command
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105648:35"/>
of <U+017F>ome Forces, which he kept in the entrance of <hi>A<U+017F>ia,</hi> and <U+017F>ent me word, to tarry there for his Orders, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould never attempt any thing again<U+017F>t him, <U+017F>ince all the Garri<U+017F>ons in <hi>Epirus,</hi> and <hi>Albania</hi> were filled up with <hi>Turks. Aradin</hi> did not que<U+017F>tion but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat's</hi> de<U+017F>ign was to <U+017F>hut me up in <U+017F>ome remote Fortre<U+017F>s. <hi>Croya</hi> it <U+017F>elf <U+017F>eemed well affected for him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding all the Efforts of the Princes Loyal to our Intere<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> was ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, <U+017F>eeming to accept of <hi>Amurat</hi>'s proffer, Fortune procured me the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine<U+017F>s of <U+017F>eeing <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> once more.</p>
               <p>There happenned one night a fire in the <hi>Seraglio, Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> was <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the Author of it. It increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed <U+017F>o much, that it ca<U+017F>t all <hi>Adrianople</hi> into a great Con<U+017F>ternation. The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment of the Women began to burn, and the like Confu<U+017F>ion was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <U+017F>een; they laboured but in vain to put it out in the Emperor's pre<U+017F>ence, who encouraged tho<U+017F>e that laboured; all the Water of the Sea, Channels, and Rivers, had never been able to <U+017F>ave <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> had I not <U+017F>hewed my <U+017F>elf more eager, and more Couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the re<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:105648:36"/>
You may judge how much I was affrighted at this Accident, and with what ha<U+017F>te I ran to a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t her. All the <hi>Jani<U+017F><U+017F>aries, Spahis,</hi> and other Souldiers, and all the Officers of the <hi>Seraglio</hi> were bu<U+017F>ied in quenching the Flame, but dur<U+017F>t not venture any farther to <U+017F>ave the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men threatned with a cruel Death. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat</hi>'s fair Promi<U+017F>es were in vain, fear rendred them all deaf to his words, and I was the only Man whom Love emboldened; I ran upon high Piles of burning Cinders to the Gallery, where the Women with the <hi>Eunuchs</hi> expected their la<U+017F>t hour. And mo<U+017F>t part of them did cry after a <U+017F>trange rate, for fear of Death. <hi>Selimana</hi> her <U+017F>elf looked very pale and fearful. But <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved <U+017F>till her mage<U+017F>tick and <U+017F>erene Countenance, and look'd upon death without the lea<U+017F>t Commotion. As <U+017F>oon as <hi>Selimana</hi> perceived me, <U+017F>he came to tru<U+017F>t her <U+017F>elf into my arms, but <U+017F>he found them not opened. <hi>Aradin, <U+017F>aid</hi> I <hi>to the Eunuch who had followed me,</hi> <U+017F>ave the beloved <hi>Sultane<U+017F>s,</hi> whil<U+017F>t I <U+017F>hall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to do the <U+017F>ame to <U+017F>ome more expo<U+017F>ed Per<U+017F>on; he took her away, and I ran to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who had ob<U+017F>erved my behaviour, and I carried her away
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105648:36"/>
ea<U+017F>ily; reproaching the <hi>Eunuchs</hi> with their weakne<U+017F>s, and exhorting them to do the <U+017F>ame to the re<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman,</hi> who had <U+017F>een me going into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> were a<U+017F>ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <U+017F>tay idle, and not follow my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, but I was more diligent than they, and brought <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> into a <U+017F>afe place. I pa<U+017F>s'd <U+017F>lily towards the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens to conver<U+017F>e with her in Secret, whil'<U+017F>t the faithful <hi>Aradin</hi> carried <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana</hi> into another place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was almo<U+017F>t choaked with the <U+017F>moak, and tho' <U+017F>he had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a purer Air, yet <U+017F>he could not <U+017F>uddenly recover her lo<U+017F>t Speech; I had al<U+017F>o <U+017F>uffered much by it, and all my Cloths were <U+017F>poiled; but the plea<U+017F>ure of being with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to reflect on <U+017F>uch an incon<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable lo<U+017F>s. I think, my Lord, <hi><U+017F>aid <U+017F>he to me, when <U+017F>he was a little recovered,</hi> that Heaven had de<U+017F>ign'd you for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervation of my Life; for as often as it is threatned with a danger, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard your own to <U+017F>ecure it. How for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <U+017F>hould I e<U+017F>teem my <U+017F>elf, <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg,</hi> if I could acquit my <U+017F>elf of tho<U+017F>e great Obligations. Tho' you prolong but an unfortunate Life, yet
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105648:37"/>
that do's not le<U+017F><U+017F>en the dangers, to which you expo<U+017F>e your <U+017F>elf. Madam, interrupted I, had I done a thou<U+017F>and times more, you <U+017F>hould not be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the lea<U+017F>t to me, your dangers are mine own, and acting for your Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I promote my own re<U+017F>t. Alas! <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> let not your kindne<U+017F>s bu<U+017F>ie it <U+017F>elf in taking notice of <U+017F>uch <U+017F>mall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; but con<U+017F>ider rather, how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous your ab<U+017F>ence will prove to me, you know <hi>Amurat</hi>'s barbarous proceedings towards our Family; my Mother <U+017F>tript of all her E<U+017F>tate and Dignity, leads an uncomfortable life, in <U+017F>ome corner of <hi>Albania,</hi> with her Daughters, and the illu<U+017F>trious <hi>Aranit,</hi> that Prince your worthy Progenitor, is forced to <U+017F>ubmit to a Foreign Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly moved at my Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, and her Tears te<U+017F>tified it. Go, my Lord, into <hi>Albania,</hi> an<U+017F>wered <U+017F>he <U+017F>adly to me, revenge your Royal Blood, deliver tho<U+017F>e great Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es, who<U+017F>e only comfort you are, po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s your <U+017F>elf of <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s Throne, protect <hi>Aranit,</hi> and never forget <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> If you were willing, Madam, replied I, I <U+017F>hould not fly alone. Alas! my Lord, an<U+017F>wered <U+017F>he, I could follow you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105648:37"/>
repugnancy, was it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible for you to take me from hence; but <U+017F>uch an attempt can never <U+017F>ucceed well here at <hi>Andrinople.</hi> To prevent tho<U+017F>e Griefs and Alarms which ab<U+017F>ence might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in you, I pa<U+017F>s my word to you, I <U+017F>hall re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the Emperour; let him pray or threaten, 'tis all one. I embraced then <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Knees, and could not refrain Tears. I <U+017F>wore an inviolable Con<U+017F>tancy to her, and I bade her Adieu for the la<U+017F>t time, I went away accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Command, for fear of being <U+017F>urprized with her.</p>
               <p>I went to <hi>Aradin,</hi> and to <hi>Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a Acomat,</hi> and I acquainted them with what had pa<U+017F>s'd: The fire was put out, the <hi>Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es</hi> <U+017F>hut up again, and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> more clo<U+017F>ely than the re<U+017F>t: At la<U+017F>t I departed from <hi>Andrinople,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending my Amorous concerns to <hi>Aradin;</hi> and in<U+017F>tead of going to the place appointed to me by <hi>Amurat,</hi> I entered <hi>Albania</hi> with three hundred men, who came over to my party: There I performed tho<U+017F>e happy Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which have amazed the whole world; I turned the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power out of <hi>Croya,</hi> and other places of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi> where I was proclaimed King:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105648:38"/>
the Valiant <hi>Aradin,</hi> Loyal to Our Blood, and concerned for his dear <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> did for me all that I could expect from an affectionate Father. <hi>Vranus,</hi> Illu<U+017F>trious both for his Birth and Merit, <U+017F>tuck very clo<U+017F>e to me, I did not enjoy the plea<U+017F>ure of <U+017F>eeing my Mother again, who was dead for grief, <U+017F>he had given three Illu<U+017F>trious Husbands to three of my Si<U+017F>ters, and <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> only was not marry'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurat</hi> fell into a rage, as <U+017F>oon as he heard my advantages, and <U+017F>aw him<U+017F>elf deprived in few days of a great number of fine Provinces. He <U+017F>ent a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Army to regain them. But fir<U+017F>t I defeated <hi>Seba<U+017F>ia,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Alibeg,</hi> who commanded fourty thou<U+017F>and Men. After this, I won an immortal Fame in <hi>Varna</hi>'s Battel: <hi>Amurat</hi> wrote to me like a Ma<U+017F>ter, and <hi>I</hi> an<U+017F>wer'd him like a King, who de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>ed him. In one word, without mentioning all other pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, <hi>Amurat</hi> came in per<U+017F>on, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by a numberle<U+017F>s Army, after <hi>I</hi> had defeated <hi>Mu<U+017F>tapha</hi> his <hi>Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could never learn <U+017F>ince <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s condition, tho' I have done all my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to be in<U+017F>tructed by tho<U+017F>e <hi>Turks,</hi> who are faln into our hands, becau<U+017F>e
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105648:38"/>
they know but little what <hi>Amurat</hi> does. I have been told only, that <U+017F>he is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <U+017F>till, that <hi>Mu<U+017F>ulman</hi> is di<U+017F>graced, and ab<U+017F>ent, and that <hi>Mahomet</hi> does not well agree with his Father. You know, <hi>Thopia,</hi> what has pa<U+017F>t <U+017F>ince we <U+017F>aw <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi> about <hi>Croya,</hi> and by my la<U+017F>t cruel adventure you may judge of my grief.</p>
               <p>Here the King of <hi>Albania</hi> made an end of his Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>ighed after <U+017F>uch a manner, that <hi>Thopia,</hi> who really loved him, could not but pity him. <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was not concerned alone for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s misfortunes. <hi>Aranit,</hi> her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father, had been extreamly <U+017F>en<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of her Captivity, and coming to <U+017F>ee <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> he heard the cau<U+017F>e of his extraordinary <U+017F>adne<U+017F>s. We mu<U+017F>t all die, my Lord, <U+017F>aid he to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Father; but before we die, let us render our Arms formidable to <hi>Amurat,</hi> let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn on him that terrour he <U+017F>trikes into our hearts, and let whole Torrents of Turki<U+017F>h blood wa<U+017F>h off the Crime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted again<U+017F>t the innocent <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was not able to go on. <hi>Thopia</hi> informed Prince <hi>Aranit,</hi> what was the rea<U+017F>on of his cruel rage, he was amazed at it, but could not believe what he feared was true. My Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:105648:39"/>
<U+017F>aid he to the King, <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Note <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a <U+017F>ign of his rage; but it is likely, an Command hath not been executed: And I cannot imagine, Heavens Ju<U+017F>tice could permit <U+017F>uch a Sacrifice. If <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> is dead, we <U+017F>hall have time enough to be wail her lo<U+017F>s; in the mean time, let us inform our <U+017F>elves about her De<U+017F>tiny <hi>Aranit</hi>'s Con<U+017F>tancy, who could not be accu<U+017F>ed of loving coldly the mo<U+017F>t amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Daughter in the World, pacified i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little <hi>Scanderberg.</hi> Well, <U+017F>aid he, let us get <U+017F>ome in<U+017F>tructions about that, but let it be with our Arms, and all out Forces. If our Subjects de<U+017F>ire to <U+017F>ee a glorious Battel, let them come to this. Go, <hi>Thopia,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to the young Prince, encourage the Army to do its duty, carry there mine Orders, and the News of my Di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ure: do not le<U+017F><U+017F>en to them the height of my grief: Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Captains and Souldiers, and help me to go in a Conque<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thopia</hi> obey'd the King's Orders, and within a <U+017F>hort time <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was filled with Per<U+017F>ons of Quality, who were ready to <U+017F>ignalize their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, <U+017F>eeing him re<U+017F>olved to attack the <hi>Turks</hi> in their Retrenchments in what time and po<U+017F>ture <U+017F>oever. <hi>Thopia's,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:105648:39"/>
Commotion did not differ much from that of <hi>Scanderberg.</hi> And <hi>Aranit</hi> in <U+017F>pight of Age <U+017F>hew'd all the vigour de<U+017F>ired in a man of younger years. The famous <hi>Ducagins,</hi> the renowned <hi>Spani, Du<U+017F>mani, Zacharia, Cernoniqui,</hi> and many others appeared at the head of their <hi>Albanian Forces:</hi> The orders having been given every where, the invincible <hi>Scanderberg</hi> appeared at the head of his Army wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing black Feathers; there was to be <U+017F>een <U+017F>uch a mixture of grief and pride in his Eyes, that his <U+017F>ight would move <U+017F>ome to pity, and <U+017F>trike terror into Others. Having ca<U+017F>t his looks upon his Forces, and having ob<U+017F>erved the con<U+017F>tancy, which appeared in the lea<U+017F>t of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a, <U+017F>aid he, <U+017F>ighing,</hi> your precious blood will be expiated by that of your barbarous murthers. After that he <U+017F>pake thus to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Generous Princes, Valliant Captains, brave Souldiers, Loyal Subjects of<hi> Epirus, </hi>and<hi> Albania; </hi>he that <U+017F>peaks to you, is going to lead you again<U+017F>t an Enemy, who might affright another Nation, and tru<U+017F>ts your noble Courage with his Glory and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.<hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a </hi>was born among<U+017F>t you, you know her illu<U+017F>trious Family; and<hi> Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit's</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105648:40"/>
actions have made him famous all the World over: you are to fight to day for the innocent blood of that illu<U+017F>trious, but unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Prince<U+017F>s; let the Daughters Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Fathers Sorrow, and the Lover's Di<U+017F>pair, in<U+017F>pire you with an extraordinary Bravery. You want no examples, but had you need of any,<hi> Scanderberg </hi>may <U+017F>hew you <U+017F>ome, worthy to be follow'd, come, Freinds, let us vanqui<U+017F>h or dye for<hi> Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
                  </q> When he had <U+017F>aid the<U+017F>e words, he let his Hor<U+017F>e go, and the re<U+017F>t of that mighty Body followed his motions.</p>
               <p>The Scouts of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Camp <U+017F>oon di<U+017F>covered <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s March, and brought word to <hi>Amurat.</hi> He was well experienced in Warlike Matters, and knew well what he ought to do, <hi>Orcan</hi> brought his orders to the re<U+017F>t of his Officers. Every one went where his pre<U+017F>ence was required, and <hi>Sultan Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> hating <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> and de<U+017F>iring to keep in his Fathers favour, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the readie<U+017F>t, and the willinge<U+017F>t to fight. <hi>Aconot,</hi> the King of <hi>Albania</hi>'s generous Friend, did not go there to fight again<U+017F>t him. There was as many Souldiers left in the Camp, as were nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to <U+017F>ecure it, and all the other
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105648:40"/>
Forces, which were to encounter <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi> went out.</p>
               <p>As <U+017F>oon as he perceived their Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, he <U+017F>ent forth a Cry, which was an<U+017F>wered by all his Men; and with a threatning Look, and naked Sword, he went to meet the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks,</hi> who had <U+017F>een him van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<U+017F>h <U+017F>o often, trembled at his fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight. <hi>Amurat</hi> him<U+017F>elf, notwith<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his Pride and Cruelty, was much concerned. <hi>Mahomet,</hi> jealous of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi>'s Glory, and of the other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he had above him, a<U+017F>pired to an immortal Fame by killing him. And <hi>Orcan,</hi> de<U+017F>iring to keep to him<U+017F>elf the Sultan's favour, wi<U+017F>hed nothing <U+017F>o much as to <U+017F>acrifice that Illu<U+017F>trious Victim to his Ma<U+017F>ter's re<U+017F>entment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> <U+017F>pared no body in his fir<U+017F>t tran<U+017F>port; even <hi>Amurat,</hi> who<U+017F>e Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had re<U+017F>pected till then, had felt him<U+017F>elf the <U+017F>trength of his Arm, had he not been encompa<U+017F>s'd by a crowd of <hi>Turks.</hi> How formidable is a valiant Man, when Love and Revenge encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him to fight! What abundance of Blood was <U+017F>pilt in few moments! What va<U+017F>t number of <hi>Turks</hi> did the King of <hi>Albania</hi> kill? And how many
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105648:41"/>
fine Exploits were that day, performed by his Friends? <hi>Aranit</hi> was not at all <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of his old Age; and the young <hi>Thopia</hi> let the <hi>Ottomans</hi> know there was more than one Hero in <hi>Albania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They had already defeated <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Van-guard, took his Standards, made Pri<U+017F>oners many of his Captains, and Victory did already begin to incline on <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s <U+017F>ide, when Night put an end to their Fighting, tho' the Quarrel was not fully decided. <hi>Scanderberg</hi> would have pur<U+017F>ued the <hi>Turks,</hi> but the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s became <U+017F>o thick he was fain to <U+017F>tay till to Morrow.</p>
               <p>After the Lights had been kindled, as <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was going to enjoy a little re<U+017F>t, there was a kind of Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy <U+017F>een; his Semitar had cleaved <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t to his hand in the heat of the Fight, that it could not be pluck'd off but with extraordinary pains: This was taken for an a<U+017F><U+017F>ured <U+017F>ign of his Strength and Valour.</p>
               <p>His fir<U+017F>t care was to enquire about <hi>Aranit,</hi> who was no more to be <U+017F>een, he was <U+017F>ought for to no purpo<U+017F>e; and <hi>Scanderberg</hi> feared either he was dead or taken: He was thinking upon this when he perceived <hi>Acomat</hi> coming,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105648:41"/>
who to <U+017F>ee him, had revolted in the dead of the Night to his Party.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> embraced him with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<U+017F>tations of joy; and the generous <hi>Turk</hi> received his Care<U+017F><U+017F>es with all <U+017F>orts of re<U+017F>pect. My dear <hi>Acomat,</hi> <U+017F>aid the amorous <hi>Scanderberg</hi> to him, do you come to confirm <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s death, or to reproach me with my weakne<U+017F>s. No, my Lord, replyed <hi>Acomat,</hi> I do not bring you <U+017F>o <U+017F>ad news. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> is <U+017F>till alive in the Sultan's Camp. You have a mind, <U+017F>aid the King of <hi>Albania,</hi> to deceive my grief. I have <U+017F>een <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Command, replyed <hi>Acomat;</hi> and then he <U+017F>hew'd him the Paper found upon <hi>Aradin,</hi> who<U+017F>e unfortunate Fate he acquainted him with. I took that faithful Eunuch to be with you, my Lord, and he left <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Camp, only to pa<U+017F>s into yours. But without doubt, <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> who hides him<U+017F>elf not far from hence, had kill'd him. As for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>he is alive, and you may rely upon my word for that.</p>
               <p>One cannot expre<U+017F>s how much then was <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s joy. <hi>Aranit</hi> was <U+017F>ought after; but <U+017F>ome Souldiers <U+017F>aid, they thought he had been made Pri<U+017F>oner,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105648:42"/>
having <U+017F>een him venture too far among the Turks.</p>
               <p>They took that night the mo<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient mea<U+017F>ures for their <U+017F>afety, tho' it was not likely that <hi>Amurat,</hi> half van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<U+017F>hed, would come again to a Battel; there were Sentinels plac'd every where, and the news of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Life were brought to <hi>Croya. Scanderberg</hi> enjoy'd more re<U+017F>t that night than u<U+017F>ually; at break of Day they vi<U+017F>ited all the Corps, but could never find <hi>Aranit</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was re<U+017F>olved to fulfill his Victory, and to free <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> and her Father from his Enemies. <hi>Acomat</hi> a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ured him <hi>Amurat</hi> expected a con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <U+017F>uccour. <hi>Scanderberg</hi> was but little alarm'd with this; and the hope of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> prevail'd more upon his mind than any other con<U+017F>ideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aranit</hi>'s Captivity was <U+017F>oon confirmed; and there were news brought to <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi>'s Camp that <hi>Amurat</hi> had more rejoyced at it than at the gaining of <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Battels, having now in his power what to affright <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> with: That fair Prince<U+017F>s had <U+017F>uffered a thou<U+017F>and <U+017F>orrows <U+017F>ince <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s departure; and the Emperour's violent de<U+017F>ires could not have been re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ted but by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:105648:42"/>
Virtue, <U+017F>uch as hers: But all her pa<U+017F>s'd <U+017F>ufferings were but <U+017F>light, compar'd with her affliction for her Father's Captivity. <hi>Amurat</hi> <U+017F>ent for him; and <hi>Aranit,</hi> who had not <U+017F>een <hi>Acomat,</hi> and was not acquainted with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s condition, look'd extreamly <U+017F>ad. Thou art vanqui<U+017F>h'd and <U+017F>ubdu'd to our Power, <U+017F>aid the Sultan to him, and notwith<U+017F>tanding all the pride of thy Family, thou mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>toop before us. Thou needs not thank Fortune, reply'd <hi>Aranit,</hi> which hath delivered into thy hands an unfortunate Victim, and which longs to be <U+017F>acrificed: So many great Men as <U+017F>till remain in our Party, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Conduct will find thee work enough. Tho' they have <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>ed us, replyed <hi>Amurat,</hi> yet thou may'<U+017F>t judge by thy pre<U+017F>ent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the incon<U+017F>iderablene<U+017F>s of their advantages; and that I have no great rea<U+017F>on to fear them. But that is not the thing now: I will propo<U+017F>e unto thee a <U+017F>afe way to free thy <U+017F>elf. Thou can<U+017F>t not propo<U+017F>e any, <U+017F>aid <hi>Aranit,</hi> but what is <U+017F>hameful; and he that had murdered <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>—hold, interrupted <hi>Amurat,</hi> and do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<U+017F>e me of a crime I was never guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105648:43"/>
of <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> lives, but <U+017F>till <U+017F>o cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, that I want thy a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance to change her mind; thou <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee her, but thou mu<U+017F>t u<U+017F>e this liberty for my <U+017F>ervice: I love her, I adore her, but the Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>es my flame with a cruel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tinacy. Reflect, <hi>Aranit,</hi> how <U+017F>hame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it is for <U+017F>uch a Man as I to <U+017F>igh, and <U+017F>uffer to no purpo<U+017F>e, nor any take care of my re<U+017F>entments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aranit</hi> was no fit confident for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat: Scanderberg,</hi> his King and his Friend was in love with <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and was belov'd by her: The<U+017F>e being thus, he was not capable of a ba<U+017F>e com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance: Thou knowe<U+017F>t, <U+017F>aid he, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tians are <U+017F>eldom fearful, and that they <U+017F>eldom act again<U+017F>t their Parole or Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; how dear <U+017F>oever <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> may be to me, I would <U+017F>ooner <U+017F>ee her dead than to bring her to grant thee thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<U+017F>t. Hearing this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, which could be <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>ily under<U+017F>tood, <hi>Amurat</hi> grew mad again<U+017F>t <hi>Aranit:</hi> Tarry my Pri<U+017F>oner, <U+017F>ince thou de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e<U+017F>t my Prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, <U+017F>aid he to him; all <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Power <U+017F>hall not be able to deliver thee, and thou <U+017F>hall quickly feel what de<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I prepare for thee. Then he <U+017F>ent him back into a private Tent, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105648:43"/>
he <U+017F>hould be kept clo<U+017F>ely.</p>
               <p>Having found the Father <U+017F>o re<U+017F>olute, he went to try whether the Daughter would prove al<U+017F>o inflexible: Therefore he went to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who knew not what had pa<U+017F>s'd; Cruel <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to her, I pro<U+017F>trate my <U+017F>elf to your feet, for the la<U+017F>t time of my life, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ire <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall favour from you, which I promi<U+017F>e to retaliate, by relea<U+017F>ing <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit</hi> your Father, who is now my Pri<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Heavens! cry'd <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> is this the la<U+017F>t Affliction you prepared again<U+017F>t me? And do you for<U+017F>ake the ju<U+017F>t party, to ca<U+017F>t me <U+017F>till into new Troubles? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<U+017F>s! dear Father, Why did not my Death prevent your Misfortune? You may di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of his De<U+017F>tiny, reply'd <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> and it depends wholly upon your Behaviour. Reflect earne<U+017F>tly upon this, do not de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e mine Anger; and tho you need not fear the lo<U+017F>s of your Death, yet fear that of <hi>Auranit</hi>'s. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, reply'd the Prince<U+017F>s full of <U+017F>orrow and indignation, what hath my Father done again<U+017F>t thee? Is this the u<U+017F>e thou oughte<U+017F>t to make of what Power the chance of War hath given thee over him? Ala<U+017F>s! he is falln into this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger only to deliver me: Endeavour then
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105648:44"/>
on your <U+017F>ide his Deliverance, reply'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat,</hi> <U+017F>ince I am re<U+017F>olv'd to be cruel except you favour me; either you mu<U+017F>t love, or <U+017F>ee <hi>Aranit</hi> dye. Is this thy way of gaining love, reply'd the fair <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a?</hi> is Cruelty <U+017F>uch a plea<U+017F>ing Charm, and mu<U+017F>t we offend the Per<U+017F>on by whom we de<U+017F>ire to be loved? Give <U+017F>ome occa<U+017F>ion to my Heart to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, boa<U+017F>t <U+017F>ooner of thy Services than thy Rage, to the end thou may'<U+017F>t up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid me with <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>on. You have taken <U+017F>o little notice of my Sufferings, reply'd the Sultan, that I intend to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low no more that cour<U+017F>e. If you are <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame, I will not warrant you of my Fury; but if you change, you may expect any thing from me, and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e at your plea<U+017F>ure, of my Soul and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: Well, an<U+017F>wered <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> let me <U+017F>ee my Father. Tho' I ought to refu<U+017F>e this Favour, to a per<U+017F>on who never granted me any; yet interrupted <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> I give you leave to <U+017F>ee him, but do not forget when you embrace him, that his Life depends upon this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view: Take together <U+017F>uch Re<U+017F>olutions as may be agreeable with my De<U+017F>igns. The Sultan went away without <U+017F>peaking any more, and ordered <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>hould
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:105648:44"/>
be brought to <hi>Aranit</hi>'s Tent, not far from her's.</p>
               <p>Four Years ab<U+017F>ence had made but an advantagious alteration in the Prince<U+017F>s: And <hi>Aranit</hi> who knew well her Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, wondred to find her <U+017F>o fair. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently <U+017F>he embraced her Fathers Knees, and weeped there abundantly: He em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced her a thou<U+017F>and times, and took her up very lovingly. After he had <U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the fir<U+017F>t motions of Nature, I <U+017F>ee you again at la<U+017F>t, <U+017F>aid he, dear <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> after I have <U+017F>o long bewailed your lo<U+017F>s, and lived in a <U+017F>orrow proportioned to the cau<U+017F>e thereof. If I have taken any care of my days, it was only to the end they might be <U+017F>erviceable to you. I have <U+017F>een the Emperour of the <hi>Turks;</hi> I have heard, but I find not my <U+017F>elf di<U+017F>pos'd to do what he de<U+017F>ir'd.—Forgive me, my Lord, if I interrupt you to prai<U+017F>e your Con<U+017F>tancy, it is worthy of your <U+017F>elf; but <U+017F>hall I <U+017F>ee you dye, rather than give my <U+017F>elf to <hi>Amurat?</hi> And ought I not to <U+017F>acrifice the Peace of my Life to the <U+017F>afety of yours? What <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Aranit,</hi> could you re<U+017F>olve your <U+017F>elf to be the Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s of a <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Prince? How <U+017F>orrowful would this <U+017F>ign of your love prove to me, and by pre<U+017F>erving my
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105648:45"/>
life, how intollerable would you render it? I can lo<U+017F>e it a thou<U+017F>and ways with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out glory; and you ought not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve it by <U+017F>o ba<U+017F>e means, <U+017F>ince <U+017F>hould I con<U+017F>ent to it, I cannot but lo<U+017F>e my good Fame among<U+017F>t all hone<U+017F>t Men. In a word, <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> for<U+017F>ake <U+017F>ooner both my Life and yours, if there is any need. I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble giving you this advice, but I <U+017F>hould blu<U+017F>h <U+017F>hould I do otherwi<U+017F>e. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what you owe to the King of <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> to that Prince who before he knew you, had <U+017F>erved you with <U+017F>o much re<U+017F>pect. Ala<U+017F>s! My Lord, I have forgotten nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Valour, nor his Services. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider to what dreadful pa<U+017F>s I am brought: Shall my love upbraid for ever my <U+017F>evere Vertue, by rea<U+017F>on I have not <U+017F>aved your life when I could do it? And if I grant <hi>Amurat</hi>'s de<U+017F>ire, will not the whole World look upon me as upon a Prince<U+017F>s perfidious, both to Heaven and <hi>Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg?</hi> Ala<U+017F>s! my Lord, what <U+017F>hall I do? That which I have advi<U+017F>ed to, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wered the con<U+017F>tant <hi>Aranit:</hi> But then I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee you dye, <U+017F>aid the Prince<U+017F>s; no matter for that, reply'd <hi>Aranit,</hi> I <U+017F>hall dye without <U+017F>hame: Then both began to weep in a <U+017F>ad manner. The Eunuch's Witne<U+017F><U+017F>es of this <U+017F>orrowful
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105648:45"/>
Conver<U+017F>ation, put an end to it, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was like to dye, taking her la<U+017F>t leave from her Father: Did I <U+017F>ee you only, my Lord, to bid you an eternal farewell, cry'd the de<U+017F>olate Prince<U+017F>s. Cruel <hi>Amurat,</hi> let me dye with <hi>Aranit:</hi> Moderate your Grief, reply'd the Prince, <U+017F>oftly: We are not <U+017F>o far from <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg,</hi> you know what his Valour can do; go away my dear <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver de<U+017F>pair as long as he lives.</p>
               <p>'Tis impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to expre<U+017F>s <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Rage, when he heard in what manner the Father and Daughter had <U+017F>poke one to another: Am <hi>I</hi> Soveraign only, <U+017F>aid he, to be hector'd by my Enemies? And <U+017F>hall <hi>I</hi> always <U+017F>ee my Power in<U+017F>ulted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? Let them dye <U+017F>ooner; and tho' <hi>I</hi> cannot quench a Flame which <hi>I</hi> abhor, let my Rea<U+017F>on at lea<U+017F>t condemn to an everla<U+017F>ting Grief the per<U+017F>on that cau<U+017F>es it; let the World <U+017F>ee what Revenge <hi>I</hi> will take of a Captive, who does but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>e <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s hatred again<U+017F>t me: Let him dye, <hi>I</hi> don't que<U+017F>tion but <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg,</hi> whom my Arms <U+017F>hall puni<U+017F>h as a Fugitive Rebel, will re<U+017F>ent this lo<U+017F>s. Let <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> have a ju<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>on to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of me; heretofore <U+017F>he had only been the witne<U+017F>s of my weakne<U+017F>s, but now
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105648:46"/>
<U+017F>he <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee me <U+017F>pill her own Blood.</p>
               <p>As <U+017F>oon as he had re<U+017F>olved this, he thought upon the means of bringing it to execution: He cho<U+017F>e his Camp to be the Stage where that Tragedy was to be acted. The mo<U+017F>t u<U+017F>ual kind of Death among the <hi>Turks</hi> is Strangling; but <U+017F>uch Executions are frequently very private: That would not <U+017F>erve the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's turn, who intended to <U+017F>hew pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly his Cruelty, that <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> might be the witne<U+017F>s thereof.</p>
               <p>The next day all things were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for <hi>Aranit</hi>'s death; a Scaffold was erected in the middle of the Camp, which was encompa<U+017F><U+017F>ed by the <hi>Jani<U+017F><U+017F>ary</hi>'s, and other Souldiers of the Guard; <hi>Amurat</hi> took a convenient place to <U+017F>ee his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders executed, and the de<U+017F>olate <hi>Ariani<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a</hi> was brought near him. The Sultan kept always his dreadful looks upon her, but <U+017F>he turned hers towards Heaven to implore its A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance.</p>
               <p>A <U+017F>trange Spectacle was offer'd to their <U+017F>ight. <hi>Aranit</hi> appeared in <U+017F>uch a mi<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition, that it could not but <U+017F>hake his Daughter's Con<U+017F>tancy: He was loaded with huge Chains, had his hands tyed, and his head uncovered, but he <U+017F>eemed neither ca<U+017F>t down nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:105648:46"/>
at this barbarous u<U+017F>age: He walk't with a <U+017F>edate countenance, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pi<U+017F>ing his Enemies; but when he <U+017F>aw <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>o frighted, almo<U+017F>t drowned in her Tears, and almo<U+017F>t dead for Grief, he grew pale, and pityed the deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition of that lovely Prince<U+017F>s, who had always been the deare<U+017F>t Object of his Hopes and Love; he wept, but his great courage could not allow of <U+017F>uch Tears, and pre<U+017F>ently he wiped them off. He was no more di<U+017F>countenanced then, than if he had been at the head of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and recovering his former Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, he lifted up his Voice that he might be heard by the Sultan, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s, and the re<U+017F>t of the A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to her, do not think this <U+017F>eems either cruel or <U+017F>hameful to me; I find therein both glory and plea<U+017F>ure, <U+017F>ince you <U+017F>ee there an Example of which you can make <U+017F>ome u<U+017F>e: Hide tho<U+017F>e Tears from me, which argue your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s: You are my Daughter, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber al<U+017F>o that you are a Prince<U+017F>s, that rank where Heaven has <U+017F>et you, requires both con<U+017F>tancy and a great re<U+017F>olution; you will <U+017F>ee me no more, 'tis true, but let this con<U+017F>ideration comfort you, That no ba<U+017F>e Action will blemi<U+017F>h the Glory
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:105648:47"/>
of my Life; come to your <U+017F>elf, dear <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> live for <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s <U+017F>ake; nay, dye for him, if there is need, as I am confident he would do for you. As for the Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, turning him<U+017F>elf towards <hi>Amurat,</hi> a Prince born from <U+017F>o many Heroe's, from whom thou degenerates <U+017F>o much, and who<U+017F>e Cruelty thou only imitate<U+017F>t; learn from my Death to de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e Life. Ye<U+017F>terday I was with the valiant <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> who<U+017F>e very pre<U+017F>ence di<U+017F><U+017F>ipates Fear and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and behold now I am <U+017F>ubmitted to a Tyrant who trembles at the lea<U+017F>t thing.</p>
               <p>Let him dye and peri<U+017F>h, cry'd out the Emperour, and let him be puni<U+017F>hed for his pride. Then the Executioners went about to obey his Orders, and the fair <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> falling into a Swound, was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the Tent where <U+017F>he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been.</p>
               <p>But whil<U+017F>t they were preparing to execute <hi>Aranit,</hi> many repeated out-cry's of the farthe<U+017F>t Sentinels, <U+017F>ignify'd <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi>'s coming, who had enjoyed no re<U+017F>t <U+017F>ince <hi>Aranit</hi>'s Captivity: His Forces brought again to fight, did march with a warlike Con<U+017F>tancy, which <U+017F>truck terror into the fir<U+017F>t that <U+017F>aw them. <hi>Amurat</hi>'s
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105648:47"/>
Camp was <U+017F>oon in a great fright; he was re<U+017F>olved to ha<U+017F>ten <hi>Aranit</hi>'s Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but <hi>Orcan,</hi> who could prevail the be<U+017F>t upon his mind, got it to be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, judging it would be convenient to keep him alive: He was therefore brought back again, and <hi>Amurat</hi> put on his Arms, having <U+017F>till con<U+017F>iderable For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces left, which were <U+017F>oon in a po<U+017F>ture of Defence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> broke like Thunder through whole Squadrons; <hi>Amurat</hi> was mightily afraid of his rencounter, and therefore went another way, leaving <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> to deal with <hi>Scanderberg:</hi> The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Thopia</hi> attacked the Sultan, and let him know the King of <hi>Albania</hi> was well <U+017F>econded. The <hi>Turks</hi> turned back every where, confu<U+017F>ion and horrour had <U+017F>eized them; <hi>Amurat</hi> <U+017F>eeing there was no hope of the Victory left him, ran to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Tent with a barbarous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but could not find her there; and was <U+017F>trangely amazed when he heard, that <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> whom he took to be far from thence, had <U+017F>toln her away: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides this Grif, he was put to a <U+017F>hameful flight; <hi>Scanderberg</hi> remained the only Ma<U+017F>ter of the Field and Bagage; he <U+017F>aw <hi>Aranit,</hi> but could not find <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> Who
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105648:48"/>
can expre<U+017F>s his Sorrow, when he <U+017F>aw all his Attempts fruitle<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>o much Blood <U+017F>pilt to no purpo<U+017F>e, and when he heard in who<U+017F>e hands <U+017F>he had faln? He took this at fir<U+017F>t for a trick of the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, who being defeated, hided <hi>Ariani<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a</hi>'s condition: Con<U+017F>idering this, he was re<U+017F>olved to root out his Souldiers before they had time to breath, but <U+017F>ome <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Pri<U+017F>oners told him for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> had gotten her away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> could not but think, that <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> had no de<U+017F>ign to bring her into <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Territories, or tarry in <hi>Albania;</hi> he feared all things; and the knowledge he had of <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s temper, did but increa<U+017F>e his dreadful trouble: To comfort him<U+017F>elf, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced <hi>Aranit,</hi> who acquainted him with his pa<U+017F>t Dangers. After he had <U+017F>ettled his Camp, and left the di<U+017F>tribution of the Pillage to the greedy Souldiers, every one endeavoured to divert his Sorrow. <hi>Thopia</hi> was more bu<U+017F>ie in it than any: You were never acquainted with Love, <U+017F>aid the Prince of <hi>Albania</hi> to <hi>Thopia,</hi> and therefore you cannot imagine my Sorrow; <hi>Thopia</hi> blu<U+017F>hed at this reproach, which he was <U+017F>o far from de<U+017F>erving, <U+017F>ince
<pb facs="tcp:105648:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
no heart was more addicted to that Pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion than his. I am more acquainted with Love than you think, my Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he; and becau<U+017F>e I know its effects, I pity you more than any. My Lord, reply'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus,</hi> who<U+017F>e only de<U+017F>ire was to divert the King from tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ad thoughts, to convince the King of the truth of what you <U+017F>ay; pray let him hear your love Adventures. I <U+017F>hall hear them, <U+017F>aid the King to <hi>Thopia</hi> with plea<U+017F>ure and attention, how<U+017F>oever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed I may be; and if you are not a fortunate Lover, my own Experience will teach me to commi<U+017F>erate you. My Lord, an<U+017F>wered <hi>Thopia,</hi> both my Love and Fortune wholly depend upon your plea<U+017F>ure, and the account which I am to give you by your Command, will make you more <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of that Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Hi<U+017F>tory of</hi> THOPIA.</head>
               <p>WAS Love a voluntary Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, my Lord, and could we rule the motions of our Hearts according to the advices of Rea<U+017F>on, we <U+017F>hould never pich upon any choice without fir<U+017F>t con<U+017F>ulting her. Fir<U+017F>t of all, <hi>I</hi> mu<U+017F>t needs tell you, my Lord, that I love the Prince<U+017F>s <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105648:49"/>
and that all my re<U+017F>pect could never <U+017F>top my pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion. I beg humbly your Pardon.—I do forgive you with all my heart, reply'd the King, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire my Si<U+017F>ter's Happine<U+017F>s, to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s <U+017F>uch a Noble Heart. <hi>Thopia</hi> then fell upon his Knees, but being taken up by <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> he went on after this manner.</p>
               <p>I hell'd a con<U+017F>iderable rank in King <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s Court, upon my Fathers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and after you had been <U+017F>ent to <hi>Amurat,</hi> I was look't upon as the chiefe<U+017F>t of the Princes of <hi>Albania.</hi> I was <U+017F>urnamed <hi>Carlomus,</hi> which <U+017F>ignifies in the <hi>Sclavoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Tongue <hi>happy,</hi> either becau<U+017F>e I was very aimable in mine Infancy, or becau<U+017F>e I was <U+017F>prung from the Noble Blood of <hi>Charlemayne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King who could <U+017F>ee you no more, never look't upon me without <U+017F>ighing, and without complaining of that cruel Law, which deprived him of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence. The Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es <hi>Angelina, Zella,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lacia,</hi> your Si<U+017F>ters, comforted the Queen <hi>Vor<U+017F>ana,</hi> being already come to years of rea<U+017F>on, <U+017F>ince they were <U+017F>oon after marry'd to three illu<U+017F>trious Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands: But the young <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was <U+017F>till in her fir<U+017F>t Infancy, <U+017F>o fair and charming,
<pb facs="tcp:105648:49"/>
that one could not look upon her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loving and admiring her. <hi>I</hi> fell in love with her as <U+017F>oon as I was <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of any Rea<U+017F>on, and our free Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ation did but increa<U+017F>e my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
               <p>The Prince <hi>Mu<U+017F>achius</hi> my Father, who had had me in his old Age, when he had no hopes of any Son, was <U+017F>o over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed with the advantage of having a <gap reason="illegible: damage" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, that all the care he took, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: damage" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t mine Education.</p>
               <p>All <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Actions <U+017F>eemed charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, and <hi>I</hi> wi<U+017F>ht mine had not di<U+017F>pleas'd her: <hi>I</hi> was a long while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I</hi> could acquaint her with my Pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion, and what<U+017F>oever my complai<U+017F>ance towards her might be, <U+017F>he was to young to gue<U+017F>s the meaning of it.</p>
               <p>As for me, a little more Age and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience had taught me to di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h Love from Friend<U+017F>hip; and Time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Prince<U+017F>s, that one doe's not <U+017F>igh without Love: In my younger Age I had <U+017F>hewn but a quiet joy at her <U+017F>ight, but as <U+017F>oon as I came to my <U+017F>ix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year, <U+017F>he ob<U+017F>erved I was melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly and perplexed.</p>
               <p>She was u<U+017F>ed to go very often with her Governants, to divert her <U+017F>elf a fi<U+017F>hing in the great Pond, which was in
<pb facs="tcp:105648:50"/>
the middle of the Palace of <hi>Croya; I</hi> follow'd her there one day, and whil<U+017F>t her waiting Women were talking at <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance from us, I <U+017F>aw her longer than an hour apply only her <U+017F>elf to that Exerci<U+017F>e: She was <U+017F>o fair, that I look'd upon her with an extraordinary atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in that plea<U+017F>ing occupation, I <U+017F>ighed <U+017F>o loud, that <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> who could catch nothing, and was vexed at it, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned angrily her head towards me; <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pia,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he to me, <hi>I</hi> think you affright the Fi<U+017F>hes, and the noi<U+017F>e of your Sighs <U+017F>poils all my <U+017F>port. Alas! Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd I, how can they hear what you do not hearken to. 'Tis po<U+017F><U+017F>ible enough, reply'd <U+017F>he, that I hear you without hearkning to you: If you hear my Sighs, Madam, <U+017F>aid <hi>I, I</hi> am certain you do not under<U+017F>tand the meaning of them, and <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould be too happy were you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that Secret. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s left her Fi<U+017F>hing to look upon me more earne<U+017F>tly; and ca<U+017F>ting one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging look upon me, <hi>I</hi> e<U+017F>teem you <U+017F>o far as to pity you for your misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, and to rejoyce at your advantages: And <hi>I</hi> am willing to know that Secret, if you think <hi>I</hi> may <U+017F>erve you therein. Madam, reply'd <hi>I, I</hi> will
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:105648:50"/>
then impart it to your kindne<U+017F>s, and tell you, that you are the cau<U+017F>e of my <U+017F>uffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I the cau<U+017F>e of your <U+017F>ufferings, <hi>cry'd the young Prince<U+017F>s, with a kind of amazement, mixed with fear,</hi> Alas! <hi>Thopia,</hi> how can that be, <U+017F>ince I bear you <U+017F>o good a will? I do not tell you, Madam, <hi>added I,</hi> that they are cau<U+017F>ed by your will. I <U+017F>uffer, tho' you do not intend to make me <U+017F>uffer. You puzzle me <U+017F>trangely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and I mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s my Wit is not piercing enough, to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that My<U+017F>tery. I perceive, Madam, <hi>added I, trembling,</hi> that my mouth mu<U+017F>t be my heart's interpreter. I love you, and tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ighs which trouble your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <U+017F>port, proceeds only from that extraordinary love you have in<U+017F>pir'd me with; this pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion is almo<U+017F>t as old as I, and I was <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of it, before I did know my <U+017F>elf. Alas! <hi>Thopia, replyed the Prince<U+017F>s with a charming innocence,</hi> do not talk to me about Love, it has been repre<U+017F>ented always to me, after <U+017F>uch a manner, that I will <U+017F>hun it like a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ter, and if you de<U+017F>ire I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ee you, you mu<U+017F>t rid your <U+017F>elf of it. 'Tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, Madam, <hi>reply'd</hi> I, I <U+017F>hould part with it, and I perceive, I am its <U+017F>lave for the re<U+017F>t of my life. But, Madam,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:105648:51"/>
do you think, a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, which you in<U+017F>pire me with, can be any thing frightful? that Love which hath been drawn to you, was no <U+017F>uch Love as mine, nor the effect of divine <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Charms. If there is any horror to be found therein, it concerns me alone, and it proceeds from the fear of di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ing you. But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> replyed the Prince<U+017F>s, what do you de<U+017F>ire from me? Your pity, Madam, added I, and a Confe<U+017F><U+017F>ion from your mouth, that you accept of my Services with <U+017F>ome joy. I profe<U+017F>s to you, <hi>an<U+017F>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Prince<U+017F>s,</hi> that I do not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend half of what you <U+017F>ay, and that I want many Le<U+017F><U+017F>ons to under<U+017F>tand this matter; did your heart tutor you <U+017F>o well, <hi>added I,</hi> as mine does me, you would be <U+017F>oon as great a Scholar in it as I, I promi<U+017F>e you replyed <U+017F>he <U+017F>miling, to impart to you all that it <U+017F>hall teach me, in the mean time <U+017F>uppre<U+017F>s your <U+017F>ighs, and help me to conquer the ill luck I have to day.</p>
               <p>I was well plea<U+017F>ed with this conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ation, and I did what ever I could to <U+017F>atisfie <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> At la<U+017F>t the enchantment ended, and we caught fi<U+017F>hes a pace, <U+017F>o that we entered into the Palace very well contented.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:105648:51"/>
Since that day, the Prince<U+017F>s made <U+017F>ome Reflections, which opened her eyes. She had always looked upon me, as upon a young Prince, with whom <U+017F>he was allowed to live familiar, but after that my di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, my actions, and her own rea<U+017F>on had acquainted her, that I was in love with her, and when <U+017F>he con<U+017F>idered the con<U+017F>equences which would follow the Court<U+017F>hip of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Lover, <U+017F>he took a <U+017F>evere Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and tho' <U+017F>he never <U+017F>hew'd any hatred again<U+017F>t me, yet I could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in her that innocent kindne<U+017F>s, which till then had flatter'd my hopes.</p>
               <p>I was <U+017F>oon <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of this Change, which is imputed to indifferency; <U+017F>ome time pa<U+017F>s'd before I could complain, but my grief prevailing upon my patience, at la<U+017F>t I <U+017F>poke thus to the Prince<U+017F>s. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi><U+017F>aid I to her,</hi> you have taught me to love, but I am afraid, I have taught you to hate, and except your kindne<U+017F>s take my part, I fear le<U+017F>t your rigour deprives me of the Liberty of <U+017F>eeing you. Are the<U+017F>e the le<U+017F><U+017F>ons you have learnt from your heart, and did you con<U+017F>ult it only to render it mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my? You will never be able to teach me to hate; but, My Lord, <hi>replyed <U+017F>he,</hi> I
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:105648:52"/>
don't care you <U+017F>hould teach me to love; but <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e I am now a little more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved, ought you to wonder at it? 'Tis enough, <hi>Thopia, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he,</hi> ca<U+017F>ting an obliging look upon me, that there is no other difference between what I was, and what I am. I know not whether this Kindne<U+017F>s is a Le<U+017F><U+017F>on from my heart, but as long as it <U+017F>hall not in<U+017F>pire me with any thing incon<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with my Duty, you need not fear I <U+017F>hould take any re<U+017F>olutions contrary to your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<U+017F>t. I found <U+017F>o much rea<U+017F>on in this di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e, that it increa<U+017F>ed both my Love and Re<U+017F>pect. It would be both ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and rude in me, <hi><U+017F>aid</hi> I, to ask any more, <U+017F>ince only my <U+017F>ervices, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<U+017F>ty ought to <U+017F>peak for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>eemed plea<U+017F>ed with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wer, but whil<U+017F>t I was abandoning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely my <U+017F>elf to that pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and <U+017F>he look'd upon me, as a man who was worthy to <U+017F>erve her, Fate prepared it <U+017F>elf to cro<U+017F>s us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot,</hi> who had married the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>es his daughters with <U+017F>ome <hi>Albanian</hi> Princes, could hardly have found a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily more worthy of his Alliance than ours. The Queen, who loved more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> than the others, fearing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:105648:52"/>
le<U+017F>t <U+017F>ome Rea<U+017F>on of State <U+017F>hould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move her into a Forreign Country, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked my pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion well enough; but the King, who had <U+017F>ome different de<U+017F>igns, took mea<U+017F>ures quite oppo<U+017F>ite to hers.</p>
               <p>Among tho<U+017F>e that were of <U+017F>ome note at <hi>Croya, Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> a Prince as well as I, had become <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s Favourite, he was no man of great Vices, nor of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Virtue, and the only thing that got him in favour, was his affected complyance. He was ten years older than I, and was not hand<U+017F>ome to plea<U+017F>e the Eyes of a nice Prince<U+017F>s. Yet <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triot</hi> had cho<U+017F>en him for <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Hu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and had thought that his Sons being ab<U+017F>ent, <hi>Epirus</hi> and <hi>Albania</hi> could not have a better Protector.</p>
               <p>Some Broils then call'd us to the War, I was none of the unwillinge<U+017F>t to go, <U+017F>acrificing my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion to Glory, and to the de<U+017F>ire of de<U+017F>erving <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> I did not part from her without Sorrow, and I believe <U+017F>he was al<U+017F>o <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of my departure. <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> commanded our Army, and becau<U+017F>e there were but few Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiere-places revolted, it was not very Numerous. I did not then look upon him as my Rival, yet I had no love for him; he had, may be, no greater
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:105648:53"/>
<U+017F>hare in the Victories we got, than I, and the others that <U+017F>erved, but he was rewarded a great deal better. Arriving to <hi>Croya,</hi> I found the Prince<U+017F>s <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, for <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s lo<U+017F>s, whom a <hi>Caravanne</hi> of <hi>Turks</hi> had <U+017F>toln away in a Voyage, which her Father had impo<U+017F>ed upon her without any nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity.</p>
               <p>About that time, My Lord, the whole world <U+017F>pake of you with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your Conque<U+017F>ts, both in <hi>A<U+017F>ia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> amazed the mo<U+017F>t experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Souldiers. <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> had then good rea<U+017F>on to <U+017F>igh, <U+017F>eeing that what Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices you did for an Infidel, might have proved <U+017F>o u<U+017F>eful for <hi>Chri<U+017F>tendom.</hi> The Prince<U+017F>s wi<U+017F>hed your return, and when I would commend you in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence, Pity that Illu<U+017F>trious Brother, <hi>would <U+017F>he <U+017F>ay,</hi> that his valour <U+017F>hould be engaged to <U+017F>erve a man of a barbarous extraction, and who knows little what belongs to gratitude, and friend<U+017F>hip. Pity me at the <U+017F>ame time for loving him as much as I do, and for having no hopes to <U+017F>ee him again.</p>
               <p>But, My Lord, 'tis time to relate to you my Sorrows; the King your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who thought he was mightily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> prepared to do any thing for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:105648:53"/>
This formidable Rival for rea<U+017F>on of <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s protection, began to court the Prince<U+017F>s in <U+017F>uch a manner, that I was deprived of the liberty I had before. As <U+017F>oon as I <U+017F>aw he had declared him<U+017F>elf, I was <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of my misfortune, and tho' he was a King's Favourite, yet I defired my Father to do <U+017F>omething for my love. He loved me too tenderly to deny me any thing I asked, and without object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me all that I ought to fear, he did partly what I de<U+017F>ired.</p>
               <p>I went to expect with the Prince<U+017F>s the event of my Father's de<U+017F>ign. I <U+017F>ound her <U+017F>orrowful, and melancholy. You are afflicted, Madam, <hi><U+017F>aid I to her,</hi> and that trouble which appears in your eyes <U+017F>ignifies as much. Yes, Prince, <hi>replyed <U+017F>he, with a <U+017F>ad Countenance,</hi> I am cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perplexed. Can I without offending you, ask you the Cau<U+017F>e thereof, <hi>reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I?</hi> You will know it too <U+017F>oon, and if you are a little concerned for me, what will you <U+017F>ay, when you hear I am near to marry <hi>Bal<U+017F>é?</hi> This di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, like a thunder, <U+017F>truck me almo<U+017F>t dead, and I was <U+017F>o little prepared for it, that this <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>e <U+017F>topt my blood, and one could <U+017F>ee upon my Face, the <U+017F>igns of a real de<U+017F>pair. The Prince<U+017F>s
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:105648:54"/>
was moved at it. Alas! <hi>Thopia, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, looking <U+017F>adly upon me,</hi> how dear am I like to pay for my Obedience to my Fathers Commands? Madam, <hi><U+017F>aid</hi> I, are you then re<U+017F>olved to marry <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> and by a Scruple of Virtue will you <U+017F>ooner renounce your own happine<U+017F>s, than re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s will? Would you have me, <hi>replyed <U+017F>he,</hi> incur his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by a rebellious re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance? Tho' you might love me the better for it, yet I am <U+017F>ure you would e<U+017F>teem me the le<U+017F>s, and you know your <U+017F>elf well enough, that a Daughter of my rank, cannot di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of her own Fate. I know, I adore you, Madam, <hi><U+017F>aid</hi> I, and I <U+017F>hall dye for grief, if <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> injoy a Fortune he has never de<U+017F>erved. What great advantages above me can that Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Rival boa<U+017F>t of? I am certain, I give him none, interrupted <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and were you only to <U+017F>trive with my inclination, you would <U+017F>oon be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> you know <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> is my Father, and what power he has over me. What <U+017F>hall I do, replyed I, if you marry <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> you <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee me no more, or at mo<U+017F>t? You <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee me only in publick places, replyed the Prince<U+017F>s. And if I live, I <U+017F>hall live the mo<U+017F>t un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:105648:54"/>
per<U+017F>on in the World. Can you, Madam, give your <U+017F>elf to him, <hi>replyed I, <U+017F>omewhat angry?</hi> Yes, without doubt, <hi>interrupted Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and I <U+017F>ee nothing can di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e me from that Duty, if <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triot</hi> requires it of me. Cruel Prince<U+017F>s, <hi><U+017F>aid I,</hi> you know well enough I cannot live after that; mu<U+017F>t I al<U+017F>o adore your Fortunate Husband, as I do every thing that belongs to you? Did you know my hearts Condition, <hi>replyed <U+017F>he,</hi> you would not be <U+017F>o pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate, and you would <U+017F>ooner endeavour to comfort it. My trouble does not proceed from any affectation. However you are more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate then I, <U+017F>ince you are not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to give your <U+017F>elf to one you hate, and <U+017F>ince you may <U+017F>igh without crime. In my pre<U+017F>ent confu<U+017F>ion, I know not, <hi><U+017F>aid I,</hi> what to <U+017F>ay, nor what to think. All things <U+017F>eem guilty to me, and I cannot but accu<U+017F>e my <U+017F>elf, believing heaven would never puni<U+017F>h me unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervedly. After that I asked the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s, how <U+017F>he came to know <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi>'s good Fortune? And <U+017F>he told me, that after he had often <U+017F>poke to her about his love, but in vain, the King at la<U+017F>t had declared him<U+017F>elf for him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding the Queen's aver<U+017F>ion to it,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:105648:55"/>
and that he had commanded the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s to look upon <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> as upon a Prince whom he de<U+017F>igned for her future Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
               <p>I perceived then that all my Father's endeavours would prove fruitle<U+017F>s, and I was grievou<U+017F>ly afflicted at this. <hi>Ami<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>eemed al<U+017F>o very <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of my <U+017F>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and her kindne<U+017F>s did but give me a greater <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of my lo<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>Again<U+017F>t my cu<U+017F>tom I was glad to leave her, intending to go to the Queen, who had always been kind to me, to implore her a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance. I was told <U+017F>he was in the Gardens, therefore going that way, I met my Father, who<U+017F>e me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Countenance did but increa<U+017F>e my trouble: He confirm'd unto me the King's re<U+017F>olution in <hi>Bal<U+017F>e</hi>'s behalf, and exhorted me to take patiently a mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune which could not be helpt. In the <U+017F>ame minute I <U+017F>aw my Rival appear, follow'd by many Courtiers, drawn there by his fair hopes; my colour chang'd, and my Father <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of my violent commotion, forbad me to enter into any conver<U+017F>ation with <hi>Bal<U+017F>é:</hi> what could I have promi<U+017F>ed him, <U+017F>ince I was ma<U+017F>tered by a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion I could no longer bridle? It was well I did not attack
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:105648:55"/>
my Rival in his pre<U+017F>ence; but as <U+017F>oon as he di<U+017F>appear'd I abandoned my <U+017F>elf to Wrath and Jealou<U+017F>ie. I found <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> in the Garden where <hi>I</hi> was looking for the Queen. Could <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>peak one word with you, <hi><U+017F>aid I?</hi> Yes, replyed he, without any apparent amazement. I know, <U+017F>aid I, that you are de<U+017F>ign'd to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s the only thing that may render you the mo<U+017F>t glorious Man in the World: But you don't know, it may be, that I <U+017F>igh for the Prince<U+017F>s <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> the<U+017F>e many years ago, and that you mu<U+017F>t deprive me of my life <U+017F>ooner than obtain her. I did not think, replyed <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> in a <U+017F>cornful manner, which vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to the very heart, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igns of a great King were to be cro<U+017F>s'd thus. For my part, I, who know how I am to obey, ought to take the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t care to perform my duty. Do not conclude from hence, that I don't care to fight with you; you <U+017F>hall have that <U+017F>atisfaction: But, <hi>Thopia,</hi> you will not take it ill if I defer it till Marriage hath given me a full po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus <U+017F>poke to me, he left me <U+017F>cornfully; and I was <U+017F>o much ca<U+017F>t down at tho<U+017F>e words, that I could not attack him at pre<U+017F>ent. The Place was
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:105648:56"/>
a Sacred Place, and I was fain to curb my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions. As they were acting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me with the greate<U+017F>t violence, the Queen came, and I went to her in a trouble which <U+017F>he ea<U+017F>ily took notice of. That generous Prince<U+017F>s ca<U+017F>t a <U+017F>ad look upon me; and leaving her Gentleman-U<U+017F>her to give me her hand, <U+017F>he did not ask the rea<U+017F>on of my <U+017F>orrow, which <U+017F>he ea<U+017F>ily gue<U+017F><U+017F>ed, but let me know how afflicted <U+017F>he was at the King's prepo<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion in <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi>'s behalf, a<U+017F><U+017F>uring me, that if <U+017F>he had had the di<U+017F>po<U+017F>al of my good Fortune, <U+017F>he had not deferred it a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I wi<U+017F>h, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your <U+017F>atisfaction with the lo<U+017F>s of my own Blood; but we have a Ma<U+017F>ter ob<U+017F>tinate in his re<U+017F>olutions, and who will be obeyed. I have <U+017F>trove again<U+017F>t them as much as I could, but all to no purpo<U+017F>e, and I cannot but condole with you. The palene<U+017F>s and the de<U+017F>pair that appeared upon my face at the hearing of the<U+017F>e words ca<U+017F>t the Queen into a great fright. Madam, <U+017F>aid I to her, my misfortunes are <U+017F>o great that 'tis like they will al<U+017F>o prove fatal to <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> and all the re<U+017F>pect I owe to the King's order can never prevent my re<U+017F>entment. <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> came afterwards, follow'd by
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:105648:56"/>
the Prince<U+017F>s, and I retir'd in that <U+017F>ad condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who <U+017F>aw me retire, ea<U+017F>ily perceiv'd my trouble, <U+017F>ince I <U+017F>eemed to <U+017F>hun her pre<U+017F>ence. I <U+017F>pent that night in the greate<U+017F>t trouble imaginable. I had a thou<U+017F>and <U+017F>everal Projects in my Head; at la<U+017F>t I re<U+017F>olved to render <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for <hi>Bal<U+017F>é.</hi> I had <U+017F>een him in <U+017F>everal occa<U+017F>ions, but I never had the lea<U+017F>t fear his arms <U+017F>hould triumph over me as his favour did: In fine, I ro<U+017F>e up at the break of day, and went to tarry for him near the Palace where he was u<U+017F>ed to go every Morning. <hi>Bal<U+017F>é,</hi> <U+017F>aid I, as <U+017F>oon as I <U+017F>aw him, we mu<U+017F>t fight for <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and you will never be happy before you have killed me. Then I drew my Sword, my Rival was forced to do the <U+017F>ame, and we fought with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual courage and advantage; we wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one another in <U+017F>everal places; and tho' they endeavour'd to part us, yet our fight la<U+017F>ted <U+017F>o long, that it exhau<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the greate<U+017F>t part of our <U+017F>trength. <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> at la<U+017F>t fell at my feet; and tho' I <U+017F>tood up <U+017F>till, yet <hi>I</hi> was in a <U+017F>ad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; a crowd of people coming then carried us both away.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:105648:57"/>
The King <U+017F>hewed <U+017F>uch a great re<U+017F>ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my Father, who endeavour'd to ju<U+017F>tifie me, that his great grief ca<U+017F>t him into a Fever, which brought him to the Grave. <hi>I</hi> dur<U+017F>t not appear, and this increas'd my de<U+017F>pair. The Queen and Prince<U+017F>s <U+017F>ent me word how much concerned they were for me: But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could <U+017F>atisfie <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> but my death, <U+017F>hould <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi> live no longer; his wounds were more con<U+017F>iderable than mine; <hi>I</hi> was curld in a <U+017F>hort time, notwith<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my grief, but all the care they took of him could not prevent his death.</p>
               <p>Then, my Lord, <hi>I</hi> could no longer tarry in <hi>Croya,</hi> or in any other place of <hi>Albania; Ca<U+017F>triot</hi> had no regard for my Love, nor Services, nor Birth, and granting <U+017F>ome tears to <hi>Bal<U+017F>é</hi>'s death, he fully re<U+017F>olved my own. The Prince<U+017F>s, whom he <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected to favour me, felt his <U+017F>everity; even the Queen her <U+017F>elf underwent his reproaches.</p>
               <p>I thought it very hard to hide my <U+017F>elf for a glorious action, and <hi>I</hi> had fallen into a de<U+017F>pair, if the Prince<U+017F>s, who could obtain any thing from me, and who knew well <hi>I</hi> was not out of <hi>Croya,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> was carefully <U+017F>ought after, and who feared <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s re<U+017F>entment, had
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:105648:57"/>
not pre<U+017F>crib'd a Law which <hi>I</hi> could not re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t. <hi>I</hi> receiv'd her orders in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written with her own hand, which was delivered to me with a great deal of circum<U+017F>pection.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Prince<U+017F>s<hi> Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a </hi>to<hi> Thopia.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS one cannot rea<U+017F>onably expect any re<U+017F>t from violent actions, <U+017F>o we might have been happier had you not been <U+017F>o pa<U+017F><U+017F>io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. If I have any power over you, and if you put any tru<U+017F>t in me, avoid for a while the King's di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ure: The Queen wi<U+017F>hes it, and I beg it of you. Ab<U+017F>ent your <U+017F>elf,<hi> Thopia; </hi>I fear the lo<U+017F>s of your life; this Le<U+017F><U+017F>on proceeds from my heart: Remember our former conver<U+017F>ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and believe for your own comfort, that now it is you may be as good a Scholar as yours.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Tho' ab<U+017F>ence <U+017F>eemed to me a more cruel pain than any that <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s wrath could prepare, yet <hi>I</hi> re<U+017F>olved to obey the Prince<U+017F>s, and to acquaint her with it, <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>ent her this an<U+017F>wer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:105648:58"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Thopia</hi> to the Prince<U+017F>s <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe greate<U+017F>t demon<U+017F>tration both of Love and Re<U+017F>pect that I can give you, is, to go out of<hi> Croya </hi>and<hi> Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, </hi>where I leave you likely for ever. I do not repine at my <U+017F>ufferings, <U+017F>ince your plea<U+017F>ure will have it <U+017F>o. I <U+017F>hall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, Madam; but let me beg that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from your heart, without which I I <U+017F>hould never be able to endure the pains of ab<U+017F>ence. Adieu, I may dye without <U+017F>eeing you, but never without adoring your charms.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>I wi<U+017F>hed I could have taken my leave of <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> but the then pre<U+017F>ent Juncture of Affairs would not allow of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate interview. I parted from <hi>Croya</hi> with a <U+017F>ound body, but a heart full of grief. I took with me <U+017F>ome of my faithful Servants, abandoning whatever my Father had left me. There was then no War in any place of <hi>Europe,</hi> and having no certain De<U+017F>ign, I was led at la<U+017F>t by my profound Melancholy into a part of <hi>Greece;</hi> as I was thinking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a larger Journey, I heard of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triot</hi>'s death. How unju<U+017F>t <U+017F>oever he
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:105648:58"/>
had been again<U+017F>t me, I was afflicted at the News; I had returned to <hi>Croya,</hi> if <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Tyranny, who had po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd him<U+017F>elf of all <hi>Albania,</hi> had not put an invincible <U+017F>top to my De<U+017F>igns. The Queen and <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> were made Captives, and having no Forces to defend, I went every where to make <U+017F>ome intere<U+017F>t for them, and made at la<U+017F>t that Party, which I brought to you after the Queen's Death, which oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed me almo<U+017F>t with grief, entirely honouring her, and knowing how <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> would be of this Misfortune.</p>
               <p>In fine, my Lord, I was Witne<U+017F>s of your immortal Actions; I <U+017F>aw <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> again, whom I found the <U+017F>ame, and who told me, that my happine<U+017F>s whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depended upon your plea<U+017F>ure. This is that Hi<U+017F>tory, my Lord, you de<U+017F>ired to know, you are both my King and Ma<U+017F>ter, but be<U+017F>ides you are the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Umpire of my Felicity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> embraced <hi>Thopia</hi> as <U+017F>oon as he had made an end of his Relation, and a<U+017F><U+017F>ured him, that he might po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> when he plea<U+017F>ed, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would be <U+017F>o acceptable to him as his Union.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:105648:59"/>
But tho' <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s violent pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion had been diverted for a while by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi>'s Relation, yet it <U+017F>oon recovered its former <U+017F>trength, the <U+017F>orrowful <hi>Aranit</hi> was much concerned, and they were but little plea<U+017F>ed at the gain of the Battel, <U+017F>ince their hopes were fur<U+017F>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acomat</hi> wondred that <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> who had <U+017F>o many rea<U+017F>ons to fear the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s wrath, <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>o ra<U+017F>h as to enter his Camp, and carry away <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not acquainted with all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of his Life, he could give no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the King of <hi>Albania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time this Prince could <U+017F>ee the <hi>Turks</hi> had departed, that his Army was not much weakned, and that <hi>Croyae</hi> had nothing to fear; being thus free to act as he plea<U+017F>ed, he could not re<U+017F>olve him<U+017F>elf to tarry, till he had heard <U+017F>ome News concerning <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and re<U+017F>olved to venture any thing to find her out. My Lord, <U+017F>ays he to <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit,</hi> our common intere<U+017F>t requires mine ab<U+017F>ence; as things <U+017F>tand now, there is no danger <hi>Amurat</hi> <U+017F>hould attempt any thing, but we ought to fear all things from the treacherous <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman.</hi> We mu<U+017F>t deliver <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> from his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:105648:59"/>
and I am weary of my life, when I think <U+017F>he is in his power. <hi>Aranit</hi> was far from oppo<U+017F>ing this re<U+017F>olution, and <hi>Scanderberg</hi> prepared him<U+017F>elf to depart with the fortunate <hi>Thopia,</hi> who would never for<U+017F>ake him. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus</hi> followed them al<U+017F>o, and <hi>Acomat,</hi> who could not with Honour follow his Ma<U+017F>ter's Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, tarried with <hi>Aranit</hi> as a Pri<U+017F>oner of War.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Alhania</hi> would not take many Souldiers along with him, for fear of being known, his Equipage was not very great; but he found him<U+017F>elf in an exceeding trouble, concerning the way he ought to take; he was <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible that <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> had fled from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat,</hi> and that it was to no purpo<U+017F>e to <U+017F>eek him among the defeated Army; it was not likely neither, that this Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>her <U+017F>hould retire into the Emperour's Territories, or tarry in <hi>Albania.</hi> In this uncertainty he wholly tru<U+017F>ted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf to Chance: not certain of the <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s of his Enterprize, and going he knew not where, he found in <U+017F>everal places many Companies of the <hi>Turks</hi> <U+017F>cattered, and returning to <hi>Amurat.</hi> He was three days without taking any re<U+017F>t, and all his inquiries being to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, he began to de<U+017F>pair.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:105648:60"/>
But he was not the only man that <U+017F>ought <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> Prince <hi>Mahomet</hi> <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her out of his Father's hands, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ired to get her for him<U+017F>elf, and look'd upon <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> as upon a light ob<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, could he but meet with him. <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> tho' <U+017F>orely afflicted at his lo<U+017F><U+017F>es, <U+017F>ent <U+017F>everal Parties after him; but the young <hi>Sultan,</hi> led by his own heart's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere<U+017F>t, took that licence followed only by twenty men.</p>
               <p>At fir<U+017F>t he was not more fortunate than <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> and travelled over a <U+017F>pacious Country to no purpo<U+017F>e; at la<U+017F>t being arrived in a <U+017F>avage place, which properly may be called a Wilderne<U+017F>s, he heard <U+017F>ome noi<U+017F>e over his head, and <U+017F>aw <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> retrenched in a <U+017F>teep Rock hurrying <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> with violence, and <U+017F>triving to get her, notwith<U+017F>tanding all her re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, into a Den, where the Sun had never <U+017F>hone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> had an <hi>Ottoman</hi> Soul (that is, haughty and cruel) as the re<U+017F>t of his Life witne<U+017F><U+017F>ed. The injury done to a fair Prince<U+017F>s, whom he loved dearly, in<U+017F>pired him with the utmo<U+017F>t Fury, and crying very loud, he would fain have gone to <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> but he <U+017F>aw every where inacce<U+017F><U+017F>ible Precipices. <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:105648:60"/>
and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> hearing that noi<U+017F>e, look'd upon him. The Prince<U+017F>s hated all the Turks, but <U+017F>he had a le<U+017F><U+017F>er aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion again<U+017F>t <hi>Mahomet</hi> than again<U+017F>t the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi-Bachi;</hi> the Prince who <U+017F>aw her de<U+017F>olate, and oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with grief, made many attempts, which did not affright <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman;</hi> but Heaven, who had de<U+017F>igned that day for the puni<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the greate<U+017F>t Rogue in the World, brought <hi>Scanderberg</hi> and his Men in the place where the Prince <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> was, it vexed them to <U+017F>ee one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother there, but the King of <hi>Albania</hi> <U+017F>oon perceived <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> Who could expre<U+017F>s his commotion at this <U+017F>ight? or <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s rage? The Precipices that were round him, <U+017F>eem'd to <U+017F>ecure his Cruelty; but <U+017F>uch as they were, he did not think they were inacce<U+017F><U+017F>ible for the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate <hi>Scanderberg.</hi> Ju<U+017F>t Heavens, cry'd he, favour my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and <U+017F>ince you grant me to <U+017F>ee <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> grant me al<U+017F>o that I may deliver her from that cruel Tyrant. Then he ca<U+017F>t his eyes all round about, and <U+017F>eeing a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way difficult, but le<U+017F>s dangerous than the re<U+017F>t, followed it ha<U+017F>tily. <hi>Thopia, <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus,</hi> and the re<U+017F>t followed his <U+017F>teps, and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who would not be an
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:105648:61"/>
u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s Spectator, went after them, tho it was a long circuit, and tho' <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> affrighted, threatned to carry away <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> the couragious Prince<U+017F>s hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his de<U+017F>ign. <hi>Scanderberg</hi> <U+017F>aw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Men fall, and brui<U+017F>e them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves upon the Rocks; but this did not abate his Courage, and at la<U+017F>t he found a way ea<U+017F>ier and broader, which led him to <hi>Ariani<U+017F>sa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas! tho<U+017F>e were not all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tacles he was to met with, and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Fury was more to be feared than tho<U+017F>e Precipices he had overcome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. That barbarous man, tho' he had a far greater number of men, than tho<U+017F>e that had followed the two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet could not tru<U+017F>t on his own <U+017F>trength: a helli<U+017F>h rage po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd his Soul, and <U+017F>eeing he was undone, he re<U+017F>olved to undo all. With this re<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he <U+017F>eized <hi>Ariani<U+017F>sa</hi>'s arm, and drawing a Cymeter, <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> <U+017F>aid he to her, with his <U+017F>cared looks, <U+017F>hall never <U+017F>ee thee alive, or enjoy tho<U+017F>e fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours thou de<U+017F>igne<U+017F>t for him. Thou cannot affright me, in threatning me with death, replied <hi>Ariani<U+017F>sa,</hi> with a <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene countenance, but tremble for thine own. I look upon it as certain, replied
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:105648:61"/>
the Turk, but <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s hand <U+017F>hall never <U+017F>acrifice me.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Albania</hi> was <U+017F>till draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nearer, and could already hear them. <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> perceiving him, bad him <U+017F>top if he de<U+017F>ired <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s life. The Prince, who <U+017F>aw his Cymeter, and who was well enough acquainted with the Turks temper, to expect all <U+017F>orts of cruelties from them, was <U+017F>trangely <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed, and dur<U+017F>t go no farther. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>eeing him <U+017F>top, and fearing le<U+017F>t too much love <U+017F>hould make him ea<U+017F>ily leave her, exhorted him to advance. Come, my Lord, cryed <U+017F>he to him, <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> is too faint hearted to attempt any thing upon my life, but <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e he was not, I would <U+017F>ooner die than <U+017F>ubmit to him. <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who had al<U+017F>o drawn near, and who was not <U+017F>o much concerned for the lo<U+017F>s of her life, tho' he was migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily in love, would have advanced far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but <hi>Scanderberg</hi> bad him imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ly not to advance ra<U+017F>hly, le<U+017F>t he <U+017F>hould con<U+017F>ider him as <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer. The Prince advanced no more, and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> <U+017F>eeing the well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fear of his Rivals grew the more in<U+017F>olent. King of <hi>Albania,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, if thou love<U+017F>t <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s life, thou mu<U+017F>t al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:105648:62"/>
me to retire freely with her, <U+017F>ince I <U+017F>wear to thee by all that may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Oath inviolable, that I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>pare her, if thou goe<U+017F>t a <U+017F>tep farther. O barbarous! cry'd the Prince, is this your way of loving and de<U+017F>erving her? How cunningly thou knowe<U+017F>t how to make u<U+017F>e of my Love and thy Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardi<U+017F>e! Depart Mon<U+017F>ter, go far from hence, <U+017F>ince <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s <U+017F>afety requires it; but at lea<U+017F>t re<U+017F>pect her Virtue and Rank. Can you for<U+017F>ake me <U+017F>o, cryed out <hi>Aranit</hi>'s fair Daughter, and do you think, <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> that I am <U+017F>o much in love with my life as to chu<U+017F>e to live with this Mon<U+017F>ter? How blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy is your faint-heartedne<U+017F>s! Mu<U+017F>t my own example encourage you? If you do not come to me, I will go meet either Death or you; then <U+017F>he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to get loo<U+017F>e out of <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s hands, but her <U+017F>trength was not <U+017F>ufficient: <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> fore<U+017F>aw then his certain ruine: Love, <U+017F>aid he, without any more ado, guide mine Arm: Then he lifted it up to <U+017F>tab <hi>Arani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> in the brea<U+017F>t; and he had certainly done it, if the affectionate <hi>Thopia,</hi> who<U+017F>e mind was more <U+017F>edate than <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eeing the effects of <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s rage,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:105648:62"/>
had not taken <U+017F>ecretly a by way, and got in that critical minute <U+017F>o near him that he <U+017F>truck him, and <U+017F>ent both his Arm and Dagger to <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Feet; another blow divided <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s Face in two, <U+017F>o that he gave up his unclean Soul with his cruel Blood.</p>
               <p>Tho<U+017F>e that were there pre<U+017F>ent were <U+017F>o amazed at this wonderful Action that they took <hi>Thopia</hi> for a Man <U+017F>ent down from Heaven: But <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> who<U+017F>e terrour was converted into a <U+017F>udden joy, ran to embrace <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Deliverer before he went to her <U+017F>elf. 'Tis impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for us to relate all the obliging things they told one another. <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> to <U+017F>hew his great pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, pro<U+017F>trated him<U+017F>elf at <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Feet, and uttered the mo<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate expre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions that his heart could invent. She embraced him obligingly, at which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>Mahomet</hi> was <U+017F>orely vexed. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> received from <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>uch Prai<U+017F>es and Elogiums as his Action well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved; and <hi>Scanderberg</hi> <U+017F>hewed him all the imaginable demon<U+017F>trations of joy and friend<U+017F>hip. The Turks who had follow'd <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> fled away, but they were not pur<U+017F>ued. <hi>Mahomet</hi> did <U+017F>igh, having no hope left him; and <U+017F>eeing
<pb facs="tcp:105648:63"/>
there was now no likelihood to pa<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> from <hi>Scanderberg:</hi> Cru<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Fortune, cryed he, why mu<U+017F>t I be the witne<U+017F>s of their Felicity? Mu<U+017F>t I for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>ake for ever a Beauty whom I have <U+017F>o long ador'd? Having made this <U+017F>orrowful reflection, he came near <hi>Scanderberg</hi> with as much freedom as he might have done at <hi>Andrianople.</hi> Tho' we are both Enemies and Rivals, <U+017F>aid he to him, I fear nothing from thee which might be unworthy of a Prince whom all the World admires, and without any ba<U+017F>e <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion I mu<U+017F>t tell thee, I e<U+017F>teem thee, tho' without love. Compare my condition to think own, and grant that I am an unfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tunate Man, <U+017F>ince neither in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther's Dominions, nor in this place. I have any hopes left me. Could a rea<U+017F>onably expect to fight for her with <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, and gain her favour, the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood which runs in my veine <U+017F>hould never be allarmed at thy valour. <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>ee you mu<U+017F>t remain Conquerour, and <U+017F>ince thou ha<U+017F>t triumphed over <hi>Amurat,</hi> you can never be vanqui<U+017F>hed, and <hi>I</hi> cannot but be unfortunate for ever.</p>
               <p>The<U+017F>e words which could not pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed but from a noble heart, made a
<pb facs="tcp:105648:63"/>
deep impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion upon <hi>Scanderberg;</hi> he had always been <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s excellent Virtues, which an<U+017F>wered well his Illu<U+017F>trious Birth; and <U+017F>eeing that he could not in rea<U+017F>on upbraid him of his Pride; My Lord, <U+017F>aid he to him, <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hall never hate you, tho' you can never love me; and <hi>I</hi> would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part with any thing be<U+017F>ides <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> for your <U+017F>atisfaction. Time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted <hi>Mahomet,</hi> will without doubt afford us <U+017F>ome occa<U+017F>ions to <U+017F>ee one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother again. In the mean time, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> cannot take away from you. Having <U+017F>poke the<U+017F>e words, away he rode, and was <U+017F>oon out of <U+017F>ight with his Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg</hi> re<U+017F>olved to tarry no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in a place where <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> had been <U+017F>o <U+017F>adly allarmed, and which was like to have proved fatal to her. They told one another a thou<U+017F>and obliging things; and they cho<U+017F>e the faire<U+017F>t Hor<U+017F>e for the beautiful Prince<U+017F>s, who rode towards <hi>Croya,</hi> with her illu<U+017F>trious Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, leaving <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s Corps to be devoured by wild Bea<U+017F>ts, wherewith tho<U+017F>e De<U+017F>arts were full.</p>
               <p>Tho' <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> was not u<U+017F>ed to any hard exerci<U+017F>e, yet <U+017F>he rode a long way
<pb facs="tcp:105648:64"/>
within a <U+017F>hort time; and <U+017F>he cou<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hardly be per<U+017F>waded to take any <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap> at night; the <U+017F>trong de<U+017F>ire <U+017F>he <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap> to <U+017F>ee <hi>Aranit, Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and her other dear Relations, made her long to ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rive at <hi>Croya.</hi> During that Journey which la<U+017F>ted two days and a night, <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derberg</hi> had now the opportunity <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> knowing his own good fortune, and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s tender love. <hi>Thopia</hi> was as well plea<U+017F>ed as he; and never did <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> greater tranquillity <U+017F>ucceed trouble which were thought endle<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>In fine, <hi>Scanderberg</hi> brought into <hi>Croya</hi> without meeting with any oppo<U+017F>ition, his fair Prince<U+017F>s: All the People of the City went in great crowds to <U+017F>ee her, and to congratulate him upon his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turn. <hi>Aranit</hi> then the mo<U+017F>t fortunate of Fathers, told <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> That <U+017F>ince he had de<U+017F>erved <U+017F>o well his Daughter <U+017F>he belonged by right to him: <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> and <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> ki<U+017F><U+017F>ed and embraced one another for a long while; and <hi>Thopia,</hi> who had been <U+017F>o glorious an In<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in procuring <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, receiv'd from <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> <U+017F>uch prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tations of Love as he de<U+017F>erved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Croya,</hi> where Sorrow had reigned du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the War, and <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Grief,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:105648:64"/>
then quite alter'd, Plea<U+017F>ures and Sports had now their time, and all po<U+017F><U+017F>ible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours were made to divert <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who had led before <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>orrowful life. Among all the<U+017F>e plea<U+017F>ing Diver<U+017F>ions, <hi>Scanderberg</hi> neglected nothing concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his important Affairs; and whil<U+017F>t <hi>Amurat</hi> was hearing what had pa<U+017F>s'd, and was taking new re<U+017F>olutions, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t the Life and Fortune of the King of <hi>Albania,</hi> this Prince who now enjoy'd his dear <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> kept his Army in a capacity of re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces.</p>
               <p>He knew not what had pa<U+017F>s'd at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinople</hi> <U+017F>ince his departure thence: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> who had <U+017F>een <hi>Acomat,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed the Death of the Loyal <hi>Aradin,</hi> was willing to <U+017F>atisfy <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<U+017F>ity; one Evening being with <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi> and <hi>Thopia,</hi> who had heard her former Adventures, <U+017F>he thus related the la<U+017F>t to the King of <hi>Albania.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Hi<U+017F>tory of</hi> ARIANISSA.</head>
               <p>AS I had pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionately wi<U+017F>hed for your departure from <hi>Andrinople,</hi> <U+017F>o was I overjoy'd at the News of it, <U+017F>ince you ought not to expect there any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:105648:65"/>
and tho' I could not ab<U+017F>olutely flatter my <U+017F>elf with the Idea of a future Liberty, yet <hi>I</hi> had <U+017F>ome glimmering hope <U+017F>till left me. <hi>Aradin</hi> and <hi>I</hi> congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated one another upon this occa<U+017F>ion; but the fearful <hi>Sultan</hi> fell into an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rage, when he heard you had been proclaimed King by the <hi>Albanians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As his wrath increa<U+017F>ed, <U+017F>o did his trouble<U+017F>ome and imperious Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: He did not que<U+017F>tion, but <hi>I</hi> had <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ecret Intelligence with you; and he <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected <hi>Aradin</hi> of having favour'd our De<U+017F>igns; he threatned him with Death, and me with the utmo<U+017F>t Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and <U+017F>o ca<U+017F>t me often into dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fears.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selimana</hi> <U+017F>eeing <U+017F>he had lo<U+017F>t you for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, endeavoured to regain the Sultan's Love; <hi>I</hi> did what <hi>I</hi> could to facilitate that Conque<U+017F>t unto her, yet <U+017F>he hated me as a dangerous Rival, who deprived her of the Sultan's Affection, and who likely had hindred you from loving her: She conjectured from the words which you heard me <U+017F>ing, and which truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from my heart, that <U+017F>ince the day you fought the <hi>Tartar, I</hi> had not look't upon you with indifference.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:105648:65"/>
Prince <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who was no longer ob<U+017F>erved by you, and who feared only his Father's Jealou<U+017F>ie, re<U+017F>olved to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture any thing to <U+017F>ee me; and the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> got al<U+017F>o into the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> after the way <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hall relate to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurat</hi> thought, that having no hope left of your return, <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould never be able to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t him; but <U+017F>eeing all his moderation was to no purpo<U+017F>e, after he had <U+017F>ighed, he began to threaten, and <U+017F>hew'd me all that cruel Pride natural to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood. You try my patience too far, cruel and ungrateful <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid he one day to me, and you do not regard at all my kindne<U+017F>s for you. Do you think <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>pare you by rea<U+017F>on of my own weakne<U+017F>s? No <U+017F>ure, but my Heart protects you again<U+017F>t my Rea<U+017F>on; you ought therefore to own your <U+017F>elf obliged to me; otherwi<U+017F>e <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>wear by all the Powers above, that <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hall make u<U+017F>e of all mine Authority, if your unkindne<U+017F>s forces me to it.</p>
               <p>This Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e had been proceeded by <U+017F>o many of the like nature, that I did not look upon it as a new thing, but <hi>Amurat</hi>'s countenance was quite chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Thou knowe<U+017F>t well, that <hi>I</hi> never
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:105648:66"/>
abu<U+017F>ed thy Highne<U+017F>s, reply'd <hi>I,</hi> and that <hi>I</hi> never promi<U+017F>ed thee any thing; <hi>I</hi> am <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible both of thy Power and Dignity: But, my Lord, thou oughte<U+017F>t to know, That thou can<U+017F>t not require from me, but the re<U+017F>pect due to thy Rank; <hi>I</hi> am no per<U+017F>on of a mean Birth, and the Chains <hi>I</hi> am loaded with can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not depre<U+017F>s my Courage; tho<U+017F>e Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which are <U+017F>ubject to thy Power, afford thee Beauty's enough, who<U+017F>e on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly de<U+017F>ire is to plea<U+017F>e thee; thy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on allows them that liberty, and their Inclinations are agreeable with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; as for me, Fortune only had made me thy Slave; <hi>I</hi> am not thy Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, if thou art ju<U+017F>t, and there are Laws above thine, which forbid me to favour a <hi>Mahometan.</hi> If <hi>Scanderberg</hi> did <U+017F>it upon the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Throne, reply'd the angry Sultan, you would not be likely <U+017F>o nice; and all your Rea<U+017F>ons about Independance and Con<U+017F>tancy, would not prove <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong as you pretend them. Well, <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid he proudly, per<U+017F>i<U+017F>t in your re<U+017F>oluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but expect no longer from me any moderation, <U+017F>ince I will have no more regard to your Sex, your Religion, or your Birth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:105648:66"/>
Being in <U+017F>uch a humour, he left me; <hi>Selimana</hi> exa<U+017F>perated him by her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and both the <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s were witne<U+017F><U+017F>es of his violent Rage.</p>
               <p>Since the Conver<U+017F>ation I had had with the Sultane<U+017F>s in the Garden, and which you heard: Our Friend<U+017F>hip had not been great, becau<U+017F>e <hi>Amurat</hi>'s love changed <U+017F>oon after, and for rea<U+017F>on of the new rank which he forced me to take; <U+017F>he judged by what had happen'd in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, where <U+017F>he had de<U+017F>ir'd me to walk with her, when the Emperour met us, that you were no indifferent Per<U+017F>on to me; <U+017F>he had look'd upon the Sultane<U+017F>s love, as upon a thing which authorized in <U+017F>ome manner her freedom with me, and her in con<U+017F>tancy: But when <U+017F>he knew that you lov'd me, and that I had <U+017F>ome gratitude for you, <U+017F>he fell in a Rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t me, and call'd me perfidious and treacherous, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>he had tru<U+017F>ted me with the Secret of her own Heart.</p>
               <p>Jealou<U+017F>ie had <U+017F>oon in<U+017F>pir'd her with an immortal hatred again<U+017F>t me, and I was like to feel its cruel Effects: You have deprived me of all my comfort, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he one day to me, and you have rewarded the <U+017F>incere confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my Heart with Perfidiou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:105648:67"/>
but believe what I <U+017F>ay, this place in <U+017F>pires no moderation; and whatever kindne<U+017F>s I am forced to <U+017F>hew you, may be <U+017F>oon changed into hatred. Fear mine, <U+017F>ince you have <U+017F>o ba<U+017F>ely <U+017F>erved me. I am <U+017F>o far from de<U+017F>erving the<U+017F>e Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, reply'd I, with a <U+017F>edate mind, that I feel neither remor<U+017F>es of Con<U+017F>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor terrour at the hearing of them. My Behaviour had been always innocent; I never endeavoured to plea<U+017F>e the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; and as for your confidence, Heaven knows whether I have abu<U+017F>ed it: But you loved <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> reply'd <U+017F>he, and when I acquainted you with my pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; you hid your Sentiments from me with a criminal Di<U+017F><U+017F>imulation: Suppo<U+017F>e what you <U+017F>ay was true, an<U+017F>wer'd I, you have yet no rea<U+017F>on to accu<U+017F>e me, did not your Jealou<U+017F>ie blind you. Was I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to open my heart to you, by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>on of your confidence, which I <U+017F>o little de<U+017F>ired? And in<U+017F>tead of complaining of me, ought you not to commend my prudence for not declaring my <U+017F>elf your Rival? But <hi>Selimana,</hi> let us not trouble our <U+017F>elves any longer about what is pa<U+017F>t, or what is to come: Let us con<U+017F>ider, that <hi>Scanderberg</hi> is like to be King of <hi>Albania,</hi> that we are Slaves,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:105648:67"/>
and that I would willingly give mo<U+017F>t of my Blood to regain you the Sultan's love; if you are acquainted with my endeavour, you may know how I deal with him. Alas! reply'd <U+017F>he, your on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly de<U+017F>ire is to <U+017F>ee <hi>Scanderberg</hi> again, and that Crown you talk of, renders him more lovely to your Eyes: But tho' Fortune confines me here, you are al<U+017F>o like to <U+017F>hare the <U+017F>ame Fate.</p>
               <p>The Emperour who went by, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted us; he was that day in a rage that cannot be expre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, having heard of the new progre<U+017F>s of your Valour; he upbraided me for it, without con<U+017F>ider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the plea<U+017F>ure he gave me, by telling me of the<U+017F>e News.</p>
               <p>But, my Lord, 'tis time to acquaint you with a more remarkable pa<U+017F><U+017F>age: I was one night upon a little Terra<U+017F>s, which rendred mine Apartment very plea<U+017F>ant; the Emperour kept his Bed by rea<U+017F>on of a violent Feaver, which proceeded from his Anger. I was thinking upon your Advantages, and I had <U+017F>pent part of the night in that plea<U+017F>ing Occupation, had I not been interrupted. I heard at the foot of the Terra<U+017F>s, a Voice, which I knew pre<U+017F>ently to be <hi>Amaldan</hi>'s, becau<U+017F>e there
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:105648:68"/>
was none <U+017F>weeter than his in the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> and by rea<U+017F>on we had <U+017F>ung often together to divert <hi>Selimana,</hi> he <U+017F>ung but the<U+017F>e four Ver<U+017F>es, likely of his own making.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Awake, prepare for gentle Love's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm:</l>
                  <l>No, prying<hi> Argus </hi>now can do you harm.</l>
                  <l>And whil<U+017F>t all things are here by <U+017F>leep po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t,</l>
                  <l>May you in <U+017F>weet Delights of Love be ble<U+017F>t.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I hearkned to <hi>Amaldan;</hi> thinking he had no de<U+017F>ign; but turning my head at a little noi<U+017F>e, I <U+017F>aw a Slave, whom I took to be one of tho<U+017F>e Women that waited upon me; but it proved the bold <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> in that Di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>I cannot expre<U+017F>s my amazement and my wrath; this way going to break out again<U+017F>t the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Bachi,</hi> when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Woman (as I thought) drew near me, as ra<U+017F>h as the fir<U+017F>t, and in the <U+017F>ame Di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e; this was Prince <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had I followed my fir<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, I had ruined them both, and drawn like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon my <U+017F>elf the <U+017F>u<U+017F>pition of favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:105648:68"/>
one or the other; they were as much amazed as I at the Conformity of their Adventures. After I had look'd upon them a long while, to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a<U+017F><U+017F>ured, that <hi>I</hi> was not mi<U+017F>taken; at la<U+017F>t <hi>I</hi> told them, that they hazarded more than I, and that their Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes which rendred them <U+017F>o guilty towards the Emperour, could not prove pernicious to me. There is no need, <U+017F>aid I, I <U+017F>hould in<U+017F>truct you about the Laws, which you know well enough, and which you cannot violate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Crime or Danger. But, my Lord, <U+017F>aid I, turning my <U+017F>elf towards <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> I mu<U+017F>t needs tell you, that tho' my civility may hide your Actions from the Sultan, yet you ought to make a good u<U+017F>e of it: And as for thee, O <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> the perfidious Subject of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who had honoured thee with the fir<U+017F>t Diguities of his Hou<U+017F>e, if thou e<U+017F>cape<U+017F>t free; thank my Indulgence and <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Bachi</hi> felt a <U+017F>ecret Rage at the<U+017F>e words; he believed that your ab<U+017F>ence had changed mine Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and that I was in love with the young Sultan.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:105648:69"/>
I have interrupted your De<U+017F>igns, reply'd he, with a boldne<U+017F>s like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf: You wi<U+017F>h <hi>Mahomet</hi> <U+017F>hould come again; but I am not <U+017F>o little concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Intere<U+017F>t, as to hide from him what has pa<U+017F>s'd. You Rogue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the Prince, do not offend <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and acknowledge your fault as I do mine. Since our pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate Love hath brought us hither, again<U+017F>t all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prudence, let us confe<U+017F>s our <U+017F>elves guilty: Tho' you ought to que<U+017F>tion me about what I do, yet tho' I am your Prince, I'll give you what <U+017F>atisfaction you can de<U+017F>ire from me: Come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to another place. The<U+017F>e words did but confirm him in the Opinion he had, that I loved <hi>Mahomet;</hi> they were both forced to retire; and after I had <U+017F>een them go out, I went into my Chamber, re<U+017F>olved to tarry there for fear of the like Surpri<U+017F>al, <U+017F>eeing that all the Eunuchs in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> were debauched in their Duty. <hi>Amaldan,</hi> who de<U+017F>ign'd nothing el<U+017F>e by favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Bo<U+017F>tangi Bachi,</hi> than to make u<U+017F>e of his Liberality, cared little whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was plea<U+017F>ed or no; tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>erved <hi>Mahomet,</hi> were not more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:105648:69"/>
Some of my waiting Women had their Share in this Intreague, but for fear of communicating the<U+017F>e things to tho<U+017F>e that were innocent, <hi>I</hi> thought it fitter to be <U+017F>ilent; I got all the Pa<U+017F><U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to my Appartment clo<U+017F>ely <U+017F>hut up. <hi>Aradin</hi> did a<U+017F><U+017F>wage my di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ure, by telling me he had received News from you, and that nothing being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>t you, you would <U+017F>oon be Ma<U+017F>ter of <hi>Croya.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your happine<U+017F>s made me look le<U+017F>s melancholly than I was u<U+017F>ed to be, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat,</hi> who was <U+017F>ick but a little while, <U+017F>oon perceived it, and upbraided me for my <U+017F>edate mind, as if it had been a great Crime.</p>
               <p>In fine, My Lord, we heard at <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> your arrival to <hi>Croya,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expre<U+017F>s to you, what was <hi>Amurat</hi>'s rage, when he heard of the defeat of his <hi>Ba<U+017F>ha</hi>'s; he re<U+017F>olved to go in per<U+017F>on to fight you. But he was not willing to leave me behind him. <hi>I</hi> was not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted at this news, reckoning it a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine<U+017F>s to come near the place, where you and my Father were, <hi>Selimana</hi> mad at this Re<U+017F>olution, de<U+017F>igned to have killed me, and to make her <U+017F>elf cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that way, that <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>hould never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you, or to the <hi>Sultan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:105648:70"/>
I have told you already that we had no great corre<U+017F>pondance. She knew what preparations were made for my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and <U+017F>eeing <U+017F>he had quite lo<U+017F>t the Emperours love, <U+017F>he re<U+017F>olved to puni<U+017F>h me for it; by her liberality <U+017F>he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to induce <U+017F>ome <hi>Eunuchs</hi> to poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on me, <U+017F>ome were per<U+017F>idious enough to attempt again<U+017F>t my Life, but all to no purpo<U+017F>e, tho' I u<U+017F>ed but a little cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<U+017F>pection. The<U+017F>e <U+017F>low enterpri<U+017F>es, did not agree with the violence of her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; therefore one night, being mad at <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Scorn, <U+017F>he entered into my Chamber, with a dagger in her hand, which <U+017F>he had u<U+017F>ed without any mercy, had not my good Fate brought there <hi>Aradin,</hi> who, full of Zeal and Terror, threw him<U+017F>elf upon her, and hindred her de<U+017F>ign. The proud <hi>Sultane<U+017F>s</hi> turned her head, and perceived her own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he told us all that a violent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred can in<U+017F>pire. She cur<U+017F>ed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; reviled me ba<U+017F>ely, prote<U+017F>ted again<U+017F>t me, named you many times, and at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>tabbing her <U+017F>elf with two <U+017F>trokes, <U+017F>he fell dead at my feet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ran away at this cruel <U+017F>ight. The Emperour coming in was little concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her Death, tho' he had loved
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:105648:70"/>
her pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionately, becau<U+017F>e he could no longer abide her apbraiding humour.</p>
               <p>At la<U+017F>t, my Lord, we departed from the <hi>Seraglio</hi> at <hi>Andrinople;</hi> I was put in a covered Cart with two old Women, it was impo<U+017F>ible for any man to <U+017F>ee me, and no body was ever ob<U+017F>erved with greater care, notwith<U+017F>tanding all this, the ra<U+017F>h <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi> endeavoured to <U+017F>teal me away; he was di<U+017F>covered the fir<U+017F>t time, and forced to fly from the pre<U+017F>ence of the angry <hi>Sultan,</hi> who was re<U+017F>olved to have puni<U+017F>hed him; he <U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pected <hi>Mahomet</hi> al<U+017F>o, and that poor Prince was like to undergo the Fate, which hath ruined <U+017F>o many of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dece<U+017F><U+017F>ors.</p>
               <p>We arrived in <U+017F>ight of <hi>Croya,</hi> with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army. I felt <U+017F>ome tender motions, when I <U+017F>aw the<U+017F>e Towers, and <hi>Amurat</hi> redoubled then his Efforts to <U+017F>often my heart but never found me Kinder, than <hi>I</hi> had been at <hi>Andrinople.</hi> Vexed at this, he would always threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me with your or <hi>Arianit</hi>'s death. I was often alarmed at his: But the tru<U+017F>t <hi>I</hi> had in the Valour of you both, di<U+017F><U+017F>ipated my Terrors, and kept up my Courage.</p>
               <p>One day after he had extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:105648:71"/>
tormented me, he re<U+017F>olved to <U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice me to that rage my unkindne<U+017F>s had cau<U+017F>ed in him, he thought he <U+017F>hould forget me, when he <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ee me no more; and being loath to u<U+017F>e any other Executioner, than his loyal <hi>Orcan,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, worthy <U+017F>uch a Ma<U+017F>ter, he wrote the Note to him, which you found up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Aradin,</hi> and tru<U+017F>ted it to an <hi>Eunuch. Aradin,</hi> who knew the exceeding and violent wrath of <hi>Sultan,</hi> ob<U+017F>erved all his Actions, and meeting the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> who carried his orders to <hi>Orcan;</hi> he likely brought him out of the Camp, and fought him, having no other way to get his Note of him; I do not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tion but he went towards <hi>Croya,</hi> to acquaint you with my mi<U+017F>erable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but he was a<U+017F><U+017F>a<U+017F><U+017F>inated in the way by <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman,</hi> who had never loved him, according to what he told me, after he had <U+017F>tolen me away, that he had already <U+017F>acrificed that pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion to him<U+017F>elf.</p>
               <p>I expected nothing good from <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi>'s Anger, and <U+017F>eeing <hi>Aradin</hi> no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, I thought he had been arre<U+017F>ted by his Orders, as being too much affected for your Service and mine.</p>
               <p>As Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions are not always equally
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:105648:71"/>
violent he had no <U+017F>ooner ordered my death, but he thought with him<U+017F>elf, how cruel this was like to prove to him; he <U+017F>ent for the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but he was no longer to be found.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurat</hi> at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>aw <hi>Orcan,</hi> who had not received his orders, and who had never approved it. Con<U+017F>idering what advantage it would be to them to keep me alive, in a Country where the chance of War might not favour them always. <hi>Amurat,</hi> who had harkened to his own rea<U+017F>ons, more than to tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Orcan,</hi> gave me leave to live, but <U+017F>wore he <U+017F>hould have no longer any re<U+017F>pect for me.</p>
               <p>You know, my Lord, all the re<U+017F>t that had pa<U+017F>t, my Father's captivity, your own Victories, and <hi>Mu<U+017F><U+017F>elman</hi>'s <U+017F>tealing me away; he broke open the Tent where I was carefully kept, killed many men, and carryed me away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, a<U+017F><U+017F>uring me, that to make amends for what he had done, his only de<U+017F>ire was to deliver me into your hands; I could not tru<U+017F>t him, but that di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e flattered my hopes; that Traytor brought me away with all the immaginable <U+017F>wiftne<U+017F>s, whil<U+017F>t all the Camp was full of confu<U+017F>ion, and I lo<U+017F>t
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:105648:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
<U+017F>oon after the <U+017F>ight of the Walls of <hi>Croya,</hi> and that of <hi>Amurat</hi>'s Tents.</p>
               <p>You may judge, my Lord, of my grief, to fall from <hi>Amurat</hi>'s hands, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Traytor's, whom no con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration had been able to divert from <U+017F>uch a dangerous attempt. I weeped, but all to no purpo<U+017F>e, my Prayers were but in vain, he made me wander a long while, without letting me enjoy any re<U+017F>t, and hurried me in that place, whether Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven moved by my tears brought you in <U+017F>uch a Critical Minute.</p>
               <p>The Prince<U+017F>s made an end of her Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, <hi>Scanderberg</hi> <U+017F>hew'd how much moved he was at her <U+017F>everal <U+017F>ufferings; in the mean time, <hi>Aranit</hi> came to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the King, that the Turks forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd them<U+017F>elves, and did intend to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack them within few days; but <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi> was no le<U+017F>s formidable in his joy than in his <U+017F>orrow, and was not much frighted at <hi>Amurat</hi>'s de<U+017F>igns.</p>
               <p>All the moments he <U+017F>pent with the Charming <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> were attended with happine<U+017F>s, and joy. <hi>Thopia</hi> al<U+017F>o, who feared no longer any Rival, nor the King's oppo<U+017F>ition again<U+017F>t his Love, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd a perfect Tranquility, which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F><U+017F>a</hi>'s Prote<U+017F>tations a<U+017F><U+017F>ured him of.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:105648:72"/>
                  <hi>Amurat</hi> grievou<U+017F>ly vexed to know his Enemy's perfect happine<U+017F>s, offered him the Battle again, and made a new at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to oppre<U+017F>s him. <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> who was well acquainted with Fortune's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<U+017F>tancy, was afflicted at it; but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible <hi>Scanderberg</hi> a<U+017F><U+017F>uring her <U+017F>o con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently of the Victory, render'd her le<U+017F>s concerned at his departure.</p>
               <p>And really he triumphed again, but after <U+017F>uch a glorious and advantagious a manner, that the <hi>Sultan</hi> being van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<U+017F>h'd, and weakned, dyed <U+017F>ome days after for <U+017F>hame and di<U+017F>pair, after his la<U+017F>t defeat; <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who was not then in a capacity to make War any longer, <U+017F>eeing the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army exhau<U+017F>ted, left <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> and <hi>Albania</hi> in the Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Scanderberg</hi>'s hands, and went to <hi>Andrinople</hi> to be proclaim'd Emperor there. <hi>Acomat</hi> being at liberty to do what he plea<U+017F>ed, followed him and parted from <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> after he had promi<U+017F>ed him an everla<U+017F>ting Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hip, which he religiou<U+017F>ly ob<U+017F>erved, being neuter in all the Wars, between <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the King of <hi>Albania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> at the highe<U+017F>t degree of his glory, feared by his Enemies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored
<pb facs="tcp:105648:73"/>
by all his Subjects, and dearly beloved by the faire<U+017F>t Prince<U+017F>s in the World, married her publickly in <hi>Croya,</hi> with all po<U+017F><U+017F>ible demon<U+017F>trations of joy; the <U+017F>ame day was cho<U+017F>en for <hi>Thopia</hi>'s marriage with <hi>Ami<U+017F><U+017F>a. Aranit</hi> full of Satisfaction and Glory, took upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf the management of State Affairs, to give more time to <hi>Scanderberg,</hi> to enjoy Loves delights. All tho<U+017F>e that had been Loyal to <hi>Ca<U+017F>triot</hi>'s Family were fully rewarded, chiefly <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ranus.</hi> Never a King lived with more content, or performed <U+017F>uch famous Exploits as <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg</hi> did. But 'tis enough for us to have tyed him here for ever with his Charming <hi>Ariani<U+017F><U+017F>a.</hi> The great At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements of his Reign, are <U+017F>o com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known, that it would be to no purpo<U+017F>e to relate them here.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105648:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

