<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The differences, causes, and iudgements of urine according to the best writers thereof, both old and new, summarily collected / by I. Fletcher.</title>
            <author>Fletcher, John, d. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5192</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11794065</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11794065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A39798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 492:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The differences, causes, and iudgements of urine according to the best writers thereof, both old and new, summarily collected / by I. Fletcher.</title>
                  <author>Fletcher, John, d. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 134, [16] p. : ill.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First printed in Cambridge in 1598.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Urine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DIFFERENCES, CAVSES, AND IVDGEMENTS OF VRINE: ACCORDING TO THE BEST WRITERS THEREOF, BOTH OLD and new, <U+017F>ummarily collected.</p>
            <p>BY<hi> I. Fletcher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>Printed by<hi> Iohn Legatt.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49277:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:2"/>
            <head>The contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN admonition to the Reader of the order of the booke, and authors from whence it was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</item>
               <item>A preface wherein the judgement by urine is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before that by the pul<U+017F>e. Al<U+017F>o the generation of urine in mans body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. Generall con<U+017F>iderations in judgement of urines, how many things hinder judgement in re<U+017F>pect of the urinall, phy<U+017F>itian, and urine it <U+017F>elf to the 5. page, and how many things alter the urine in re<U+017F>pect of age,
<U+017F>exe, complexion, time of the yeare, kinde of life, &amp;c. to the 10. page.</item>
               <item>2. Of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of urine thin to the 14. page, thicke to the 17. page, and meane to the 19.</item>
               <item>3 Of clearene<U+017F><U+017F>e and darkene<U+017F><U+017F>e of urine to the 24. page.</item>
               <item>4. Of 21. colours of urine, pag. 25. where the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mu<U+017F>t adde after pale, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>picous, <U+017F>ubpallidus, the<U+017F>e words. If you <U+017F>eethe a piece of the rinde of pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granate, and then put to it thrice as much clean water, it will make a pale colour. Al<U+017F>o at flaxen, <U+017F>piceus, adde the<U+017F>e words. But if you put thereto a little or
none of cleane water, it will be flaxen colour.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:3"/>
5 Of <U+017F>ubstance and colour ioyntly together, and fir<U+017F>t of thin urine with his colours, to the 34. page, thicke with his colours to the 44. page.</item>
               <item>6 Quantity of urine much to the 48. page, little to the 49. page.</item>
               <item>7 Of the contents of the urine in generall, and fir<U+017F>t where contents want, the divi<U+017F>ion of the contents, page
53. of their colour, 53. <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thicke, 55. thin, 56. quantity, 57.</item>
               <item>8 Of contents in <U+017F>peciall, and fir<U+017F>t of the 15. defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med contents in the <U+017F>ediment to the 77. page. In the middle region, page 77. in the uppermo<U+017F>t region, pag. 79. and here of the colours, 80. deformed contents, 81. of the crowne, 82. his colours, 83. of fome, froth, bubbles,
85. and 3. differences, 89. Drops of fat, 90.</item>
               <item>9 Smell of urine, 90.</item>
               <item>10 Manner of pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, 95.</item>
               <item>11 Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine, 98.</item>
               <item>12 Of what parts of the body urine giveth <U+017F>ignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
101.</item>
               <item>13 Of concoct, crude, and dangerous urines, 101.</item>
               <item>14 A methodicall practi<U+017F>e in judgement of urine,
107.</item>
               <item>15 Of the qualities, commodities, and medicines of urine, and of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es touching urine, and the remedies thereof, 117.</item>
               <item>An Alphabeticall Table to the whole Booke.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:3"/>
            <head>An admonition to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treati<U+017F>e following I fir<U+017F>t dige<U+017F>ted into tables for mine own privat u<U+017F>e, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was by my friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into this forme to fit the pre<U+017F><U+017F>e. And therefore the <U+017F>tudious reader mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>till remember how one part followeth another in order: and that which is <U+017F>poken generally before a divi<U+017F>ion, to be under<U+017F>tood of all the members following under that head according to the law of method. A word is enough to him that is acquainted with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. The Treati<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elfe is an abridgement wholly gathered out of other mens writings, I challenge nothing to my <U+017F>elfe but the colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition hereof. Wherein for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<U+017F>atisfaction of the Reader, I have many times cited the Author, who<U+017F>e te<U+017F>timony I
<pb facs="tcp:49277:4"/> u<U+017F>e, and now and then I have quoted the page of <U+017F>uch books as I then followed, and whereof I <U+017F>et downe the catalogue, where, when, and in what forme they were printed.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Willichius <hi>and</hi> Reu<U+017F>ner Ba<U+017F>ileae, 1592. 8.</item>
               <item>Argenterius de urinis, 1591. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Record</hi> in Engli<U+017F>h. London. 8.</item>
               <item>Actuarius, Pari<U+017F>iis, 1548. 8.</item>
               <item>Aegidius Ba<U+017F>ileae, 1506. 8.</item>
               <item>Weckers Syntaxis, Ba<U+017F>ileae, 1582. fol.</item>
               <item>Fernelius. Francofurti, 1593. 8.</item>
               <item>Montanus de Excrementis. Venetiis,
1554. 8.</item>
               <item>Cappivaccius de urinis. Serve<U+017F>tae, 1595. 8.</item>
               <item>Va<U+017F><U+017F>aeus de urinis. Lugduni, 1645. 16.</item>
               <item>Io. Hasfurtus. Venetiis, 1584. 4.</item>
               <item>Salvianus. Romae, 1587. 8.</item>
               <item>Blo<U+017F>ii Hollerii theorica medicina. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentinae,
1565. 8.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong<U+017F>t all <U+017F>ignes of
<U+017F>icknes or health wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the skilfull Phy<U+017F>itian is led into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <U+017F>tate of the body, two are of mo<U+017F>t general and certain <U+017F>ignification which are taken from the pul<U+017F>e and urine, without which all the knowledge of phy<U+017F>icke be<U+017F>ides, is ob<U+017F>cure, doubtfull, and uncertain. Whereof the fir<U+017F>t
<U+017F>heweth the e<U+017F>tate of the heart and arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the <U+017F>econd of the liver and veins. Both of <U+017F>uch <U+017F>peciall u<U+017F>e in <U+017F>ignification of di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es incident to mans body; that joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they certainly in<U+017F>truct the Phy<U+017F>itian whether the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e tendeth to health or death, but whether of the<U+017F>e two <U+017F>everally con<U+017F>idered doth give more certain <U+017F>ignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I had rather leave it to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of others who can better doe it then my <U+017F>elfe: yet under their correction me thinke that the urine giveth the mo<U+017F>t ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nife<U+017F>t certaine and generall <U+017F>ignification of
<pb facs="tcp:49277:5"/> all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; becau<U+017F>e with the blood it is conveyed into all parts of the body, and from thence returneth backe againe in the veines to the liver and ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, bringing with it <U+017F>ome note of the <U+017F>tate and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of all tho<U+017F>e parts from whence it commeth. Neither is there any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement that hath <U+017F>o many differences as the urine, neither from which <U+017F>o many
<U+017F>ignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>s may be taken as from it, in the
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, colour, quantity, contents, <U+017F>mell, manner of pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, &amp;c. in which the Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian may with more profit exerci<U+017F>e him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elfe then in the <U+017F>ix differences of pul<U+017F>es, the art whereof <hi>Hippocrates</hi> either never knew, or neglected. And <hi>Galon</hi> confe<U+017F><U+017F>eth of him<U+017F>elfe, that he <U+017F>pent 20. yeares in <U+017F>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that way, before he could attaine the knowledge of the (<hi><U+017F>y<U+017F>tole</hi>) or contraction of the pul<U+017F>e in the arteries, which being unknowne, the pul<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o mu<U+017F>t remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne; and yet it is uncertaine whether
<hi>Galen</hi> indeed ever did attain therto. From
<hi>Galens</hi> time for 1200. yeares after, this knowledge lay buried in the black dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ignorance, untill <hi>Io<U+017F>ephus Struthius</hi> brought it to <U+017F>ome light: and no marvel; for the continuall mutability and alteration of the pul<U+017F>e cannot be comprehended by art.
<pb facs="tcp:49277:5"/> For as the affections of mans minde, anger, feare, joy, <U+017F>orrow, love, hatred, <U+017F>pringing from the heart doe vary; <U+017F>o the pul<U+017F>e diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in every moment. So we read that
<hi>Era<U+017F>i<U+017F>tratus</hi> the Phy<U+017F>itian perceived by the pul<U+017F>e of <hi>Antiochus</hi> <U+017F>on to the King of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria and Per<U+017F>ia, that he was in love with
<hi>Stratonica</hi> his <U+017F>tep-mother. And <hi>Galen</hi>
<U+017F>aith that hee perceived by the often change of the pul<U+017F>e of a woman, that <U+017F>he was in love with <hi>Pylades.</hi> Be<U+017F>ides that, the tunicles of the arteries, the skin and fle<U+017F>h in the wre<U+017F>t of the hand where the pul<U+017F>e is felt, and the skin and fle<U+017F>h of the Phy<U+017F>itians hand feeling the pul<U+017F>e, are in <U+017F>ome harder and in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ofter. Againe, the patients hand differing in heate or cold, or manner of po<U+017F>ition, higher, lower, or on the one
<U+017F>ide, and the Phy<U+017F>itians hand touching the arteries <U+017F>oftly, or pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing them, and infinit other circum<U+017F>tances which make <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and momentary alteration of the pul<U+017F>e that as in ancient time, <U+017F>o at this pre<U+017F>ent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<U+017F>t us there be very few skilfull in this part of judgement. But on the contrary
<U+017F>ide in urine there is no <U+017F>uch labour or cau<U+017F>e of doubt, for we may <U+017F>ee it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider well of it, for many houres together, and find no alteration therein. And of this
<pb facs="tcp:49277:6"/>
               <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Aegideus, Actuarius, Avicen,</hi> and infinite others in all ages have delivered precepts, and gathered judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and therefore as a part of phy<U+017F>icke better knowne, and of more certainty then the pul<U+017F>e, I have in this <U+017F>hort Treati<U+017F>e handled, divided into his differences, and to every difference I have added his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment together with a rea<U+017F>on thereof. And in many places I have more e<U+017F>pecially di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tingui<U+017F>hed it, not onely by other differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the urine, but al<U+017F>o by other accidents of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elfe. As for example, <hi>pag.
47.</hi> one <U+017F>ignification of much urine is a con<U+017F>umption of the whole body, whereto I have added other <U+017F>ignes by the urine, as that it is <U+017F>omewhat fatty, in colour palew, reddi<U+017F>h, high coloured, and without other
<U+017F>igns of concoction. And hereof I pre<U+017F>ently annexe this cau<U+017F>e; for <U+017F>o the profitable fat, moi<U+017F>ture, humors, and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiall parts of the body are molten, di<U+017F><U+017F>olved, and voided by urine. The re<U+017F>t I leave to the diligence of the <U+017F>tudious reader, who with <U+017F>mal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ideration may ea<U+017F>ily conceive the <U+017F>ame. And here I would make an end, but that I thinke it not ami<U+017F><U+017F>e in few words to <U+017F>hew the generation of urine in mans body, and the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els thereto belonging.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49277:6"/> The meat and drinke received by the mouth, and de<U+017F>cending downe into the
<U+017F>tomacke, and there concocted together, incorporated and made one <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance
(<hi>chylus</hi>) and thence pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing by an i<U+017F><U+017F>ue in the bottome of the <U+017F>tomacke (<hi>pylorus</hi>) to the fir<U+017F>t gut (<hi>duodenum</hi>) and from thence to the hungry gut (<hi>ieiunum</hi>) from thence againe five of the eight me<U+017F>araicall veines
<U+017F>ucke <U+017F>o much as is profitable nouri<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
(the re<U+017F>t being unprofitable for nouri<U+017F>hment is voided by <U+017F>toole) which againe is conveyed into <hi>vena porta,</hi> and at length after many purifications and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions in the parts before mentioned; to the liver, where it is converted into blood, and thence <U+017F>ent into the hollow veine, where it is againe more purified, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitious parts being <U+017F>eque<U+017F>tred,
<U+017F>eparated, and <U+017F>ent to other places, as the choler to the gall, melancholy to the <U+017F>pleen and the watery or wheyi<U+017F>h part to the emulgent or <U+017F>ucking veines, from whence againe it is drawne of the reines where it is altered perfectly into urine, which as unprofitable de<U+017F>cendeth into the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduits
(<hi>ureteres</hi>) and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>ce into the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which at length at a mans plea<U+017F>ure by help of the mu<U+017F>cle <U+017F>hutting the necke of
<pb facs="tcp:49277:7"/> the bladder is voided out by the yard. Yet
<U+017F>ome part of this thin wheyi<U+017F>h humor is not after this <U+017F>ort conveyed from the liver to the bladder, but as I have <U+017F>hewed, <hi>cap.</hi> 12. is together with the blood in the veines derived into all parts of the body, and at length returning backe againe the <U+017F>ame way, is expelled by the yard. Seeing then urine pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth through <U+017F>o many ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and receiveth <U+017F>o many concoctions and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations before it can be expelled, it mu<U+017F>t needs admit many alterations. And yet we
<U+017F>ee by daily experience that great drinkers, tho<U+017F>e which drinke <U+017F>ome diuretike potion, and e<U+017F>pecially tho<U+017F>e who are troubled with the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill, doe pi<U+017F><U+017F>e out pre<U+017F>ently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter drinke not concoct, nor much altered from the drinke received. Hereof <hi>Galen 3. de facult. nat. cap.</hi> 15. yeeldeth the<U+017F>e rea<U+017F>ons. The great de<U+017F>ire of the <U+017F>tomack to receive drinke, the thin, piercing, and <U+017F>ubtle <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance of the drinke <U+017F>peedily running into all parts: the widene<U+017F><U+017F>e of the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, and la<U+017F>tly the <U+017F>trong attractive faculty of the reines, all which concurring together, doe cau<U+017F>e the drinke received <U+017F>o quickly to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e through the parts of the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great alteration. Yet <U+017F>ome the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <U+017F>atisfie the<U+017F>e doubts have devi<U+017F>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:49277:7"/> and by arguments laboured to confirme a readier and <U+017F>horter cour<U+017F>e for the drinke received to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e to the reins by the wind-pipe, great artery (<hi>aorta</hi>) emulgent veines, and bladder. But becau<U+017F>e this opinion is <U+017F>o contrary to the reputed and received truth of <hi>Hippocrates, Galen,</hi> and all Phy<U+017F>itians, as al<U+017F>o that it imagineth another free pa<U+017F><U+017F>age
(be<U+017F>ide the meat-pipe, through the wind-pipe and lungs: whereas we find by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that a little du<U+017F>t in travelling, or a crum of bread in eating falling into the
<U+017F>ame is ready to choke a man, as a kernell of a rai<U+017F>on did <hi>Anacreon</hi> the Poet; and that therefore nature hath ordained a cover for the wind-pipe (<hi>epiglottis</hi>) le<U+017F>t in eating or drinking <U+017F>omething <U+017F>hould pa<U+017F><U+017F>e that way. And the Phy<U+017F>itians doe forbid much talke or di<U+017F>putation at meat, le<U+017F>t the cover being opened thereby <U+017F>hould let <U+017F>omthing pa<U+017F><U+017F>e that way. I cea<U+017F>e further to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:8"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Of the in<U+017F>truments and parts by which urine is engendred and pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth, marke this figure following.</head>
                  <p>A. is the liver.</p>
                  <p> B. the hollow veine. </p>
                  <p> C. veines by which the reins doe draw the urine, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee called the <U+017F>ucking veines, <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae emulgentes.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>D. the reines. </p>
                  <p>E. The water-pipes <hi>ureteres.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>F. is the bladder. </p>
                  <p>G. the <U+017F>pout of the yard.</p>
                  <p>All other parts be<U+017F>ide, appertaine to generation and
<U+017F>eed.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49277:8"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>A perfit forme of the urinall, wherein the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine according to his height is divided into three regions for the di<U+017F>tinction of the three contents mentioned, Chap. 7, 8.</head>
                  <p>1, 2, 3, 4. the lowe<U+017F>t region for the <U+017F>ediment.</p>
                  <p>5, 6, 7, 8. the middle region for the <U+017F>wimme.</p>
                  <p>9, 10, 11, 12. the uppermo<U+017F>t region for the cloud.</p>
                  <p>In the top whereof the black line going through the thicknes of the urinal is the circle or crown</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49277:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of generall con<U+017F>iderations in judgement of Vrines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdgements of an urine are con<U+017F>idered in re<U+017F>pect of the uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the Phy<U+017F>itian,
&amp; of the urine it <U+017F>elf.
1. <note place="margin">The urinal</note>In re<U+017F>pect of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinal, which ought not to bee of any colour, for <U+017F>o it would alter the apparent colour of the urine. Not <U+017F>trait or broad beneath, which alter the contents. Not open in the top, for <U+017F>o du<U+017F>t or other filth might fall in: aire, cold, or heat might <U+017F>oone alter it. Not <U+017F>topped with Woollen or Linnen, for
<U+017F>o lint or Cotten might fall in. Not too neere, nor too far off, for the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance too neere might appeare thicker: and too farre off, thinner. <hi>Aegid. 10. Argent.</hi> 91. contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwi<U+017F>e
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49277:10"/> in Wine and Vineger. <hi>Capivac.</hi> 88. Not uncleane within.</p>
            <p>The Vrinall therefore ought to be a cleare gla<U+017F><U+017F>e, or pure chry<U+017F>tall, without any colour at all or notable thickne<U+017F><U+017F>e. Broad, round, and oblonge below, and
<U+017F>traiter above, conically a<U+017F>cending like to a mans bladder which it repre<U+017F>enteth; that a fit place may remaine for the fa<U+017F>hion of the <U+017F>ediment: and <U+017F>topped at the top with leather, paper, &amp;c. that nothing fall in, nor ayre ea<U+017F>ily get in.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Phy<U+017F>itian.</note>2. In re<U+017F>pect of the Phy<U+017F>itian, who may not <U+017F>ee the urine in a place either too darke, or by candle-light, for <U+017F>o the colour will appeare altered. Or el<U+017F>e too light, as the Sunne-beames make the colour more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>Therefore put your hand or a blacke cloth betwixt the light and the Vrinall on the oppo<U+017F>ite part of the Vrinall, that the colour and contents may bee the better di<U+017F>cerned, and your eyes be not dazaled with the light.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Vrine.</note> 3. In re<U+017F>pect of the urine it <U+017F>elfe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are con<U+017F>idered, <list>
                  <item>1. Collection.</item>
                  <item>2. Things that hinder judgement.</item>
                  <item>3. Differences.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Collection.</note>Collection. 1. When nouri<U+017F>hment is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49277:10"/> perfectly dige<U+017F>ted, which is commonly that which is fir<U+017F>t made in the morning after the nights <U+017F>leep. For that which is made lately after eating or drinking, or fit of an ague, hath neither colour, con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tence, nor contents, being not concoct.
<hi>Argent</hi> 91.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take the whole urine and not the part, <U+017F>o much as is made at one time; but mingle not urines made at <U+017F>everall times, but keep them <U+017F>everall both for quantity, colour, and contents.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the urine is new made and yet warme, it is be<U+017F>t to <U+017F>ee the colour, <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, and per<U+017F>pecuity; at what time you may <U+017F>ee al<U+017F>o the quantity and <U+017F>mell.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When it is <U+017F>etled in the Vrinall fully it is be<U+017F>t to <U+017F>ee the contents and bubbles. You may well al<U+017F>o then <U+017F>ee the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.
<hi>Actuar. Fernel.</hi> 452.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let it not be kept pa<U+017F>t <U+017F>ixe houres, for being longer kept it waxeth corrupt.
<hi>Arg. 91. ex Avicenna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Yet it is good to <U+017F>ee the urine lately made, and oftentimes after to ob<U+017F>erve the per<U+017F>everance or alteration of the <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, froth, and per<U+017F>pecuity, &amp;c. <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.
222.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things which hinder judgement. 1.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49277:11"/> Much <U+017F>haking of it, or pouring it out of one ve<U+017F><U+017F>ell into another.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">Things which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 2. Cold or winde to congeale it and make it turne thicke as in Winter: but being chafed at the fire it returneth again, except it be too long kept. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Winde to move or <U+017F>hake it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Placed in the heate of the Sunne, or neere the fire, whereby that which is thin and <U+017F>ubtile is drawne out, and the re<U+017F>t remaineth thicke, dreggy: and <U+017F>o <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the urine that was made thicke and troubled, by great heate of the fire waxeth cleere, and the <U+017F>pume or bubble vani<U+017F>heth away, which otherwi<U+017F>e would continue.
<hi>Salvian.</hi> 227.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Meats and drinks lately taken before alter the colour, quantity, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and
<U+017F>mell <U+017F>ometimes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Medicines taken, as Rheubarb, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, Cinnamon, broth of Cherries, make the urine yellow; Ca<U+017F>sia, blacki<U+017F>h; Oyle of Bay, Henbane, or <hi>Vnguentum Martiatum</hi> anointed, <hi><U+017F>ena rubia maior, Cantharides<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi> applied to any part of the body, reddi<U+017F>h.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Exerci<U+017F>e, fa<U+017F>ting, watching, labour, anger, feare, vomiting, <U+017F>weating, purging,
&amp;c. alter the colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, quantity, contents.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49277:11"/>
8. Reines or Bladder affected hinder the judgement of the inner parts. <hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Differences are either principall in the urine, or le<U+017F><U+017F>e principall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Principall differences of the urin.</note> Principall are, 1. Sub<U+017F>tance. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Quality, and that either fir<U+017F>t as heate exceeding perceived by the patient in making it, as in inflammation of the liver, or by the Phy<U+017F>itian touching the urinall with his hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Heate moderate or temperate.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Deficient or under temperate.</p>
            <p>Or <U+017F>econd quality perceived. 1. by <U+017F>ight, as per<U+017F>picuity, light through, or darke and troubled. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Colour.</hi> Cap. 4.</p>
            <p>Ta<U+017F>te, but that being too ba<U+017F>e for the Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, we leave to <U+017F>peake of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smell.</hi> Cap. 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Sub<U+017F>tance and colour joyntly, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Quantity, <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Contents wanting three regions, <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment,
<U+017F>wim, cloud: where we al<U+017F>o con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, colour, quantity. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Contents deformed.</p>
            <p>Contents duely knit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Le<U+017F><U+017F>e prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</note> Le<U+017F><U+017F>e principall, which though they doe not immediately helpe to judge of the urine, yet they declare the nature of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49277:12"/> the urine and griefs of the body. Such ari<U+017F>e from the cau<U+017F>es; as choler, melancholy,
<U+017F>leep, watching, di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>From the effects, <U+017F>ignifying health, death, griefes of the <U+017F>tomacke, head, liver, brea<U+017F>t, veines.</p>
            <p>From the manner of pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing. <hi>Cap</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>From <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine. <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The be<U+017F>t urine <U+017F>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</note> The be<U+017F>t urine <U+017F>imply in a perfect and ab<U+017F>olute temperate whole man, which is the rule of all the re<U+017F>t, is that which is made without heate, as in burning agues.
<hi>Capivac.</hi> 83. without cold, <hi>Capivac.</hi> 11. paine, or <U+017F>tinch. Of colour palew or light
<U+017F>affron, per<U+017F>picuous moderately, <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vac.
113.</hi> Of <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance meane. Of quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity likewi<U+017F>e meane, like to the former dayes urine, and proportionable to the drinke received ye<U+017F>terday and other daies before, and <U+017F>omewhat le<U+017F><U+017F>e becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome is <U+017F>pent and wa<U+017F>ted in the body. Having contents white, <U+017F>mooth, equall, <U+017F>etling downe to the bottome of the urinall, not having bubbles, filaments, or any other evill contents. Having <U+017F>ediment likewi<U+017F>e white, <U+017F>mooth, equall, pyramidally a<U+017F>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor tattered, ragged, or di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed, neither cleaving together, <U+017F>o but that they depart a<U+017F>under, the urinall being <U+017F>haken,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49277:12"/> and a<U+017F>cend lightly without trouble of the urine. And all the<U+017F>e thus continuing long.
<hi>Montan.</hi> 46. B.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The be<U+017F>t urine in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pect of age</note> The be<U+017F>t urine in re<U+017F>pect of age, <U+017F>exe, time of the yeare, kinde of life, complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Fir<U+017F>t for children, urine is be<U+017F>t of <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance thicke. For thin is lethall. <hi>Salvian.
33.</hi> 206.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Of quantity much.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Of colour white a little by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feeding on milke, <hi>Salv.</hi> 204. or becau<U+017F>e choller or bloud to colour the urine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teth or is drowned by too much moi<U+017F>ture. Al<U+017F>o by debility, long <U+017F>leep, much re<U+017F>t, which becau<U+017F>e they cannot well move, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>eth moi<U+017F>ture and decaieth heate.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The be<U+017F>t for <U+017F>pringalls, hath <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heaped and increa<U+017F>ed, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thicke, but rather inclining to thinne. Colour yellow or light <U+017F>affron: blacke deadly <hi>Salvian.</hi> 93. contents moe then in men.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For men that which is <U+017F>et down fir<U+017F>t for a perfect rule of the re<U+017F>t.</p>
            <p n="4">4 For old men with <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thin, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour white, <U+017F>ediment little.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sexe.</note> 5 For women whole. In <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thicke then thin, darke, troubled,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49277:13"/> with many things <U+017F>wimming in it, not <U+017F>o cleere as in men.</p>
            <p>In colour declining from light or palew towards white with <U+017F>ome darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>Quantity much.</p>
            <p>Sediment impure, much thicker and whiter then in mens urine.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>tinction between men and womens urine is ea<U+017F>ily knowne by often comparing them together. <hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Time of the yeare.</note> 6 In re<U+017F>pect of the time of the yeare, be<U+017F>t urine beginning in the <U+017F>pring, of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour white and pale, quantity greater, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents more thicker and more raw. In the
<U+017F>pring proceeding, colour from pale and flaxen to palew and light; contents meane, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance equall. In <U+017F>ummer begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, colour palew and light <U+017F>affron, <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance thinner, <U+017F>ediment thinner, white,
<U+017F>mooth, equall. In Summer proceeding, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour yellow <U+017F>affron, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance very thin, <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment little, thinne and declining to white.</p>
            <p>In Autumne beginning, <U+017F>ediment little yet without fault. In Autumne proceeding all meane.</p>
            <p>In Winter beginning, colour white,
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thicker. <hi>Fernel.</hi> Contents moe and rawer. In Winter proceeding, colour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49277:13"/> white, quantity greater, contents moe and cruder.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">K<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde of Life.</note> 7 In re<U+017F>pect of the kinde of life, as wherein there is much exerci<U+017F>e, fa<U+017F>ting, anger maketh commotion of <U+017F>pirits and humours, watching, meats of hot ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the urine is more coloured, and <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments fewer at the beginning as long as tho<U+017F>e pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions doe inflame the heate of the body, and there is moi<U+017F>ture which may be kindled; but that failing, and the heate langui<U+017F>hing and decaying, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour waxeth more and more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e again.
<hi>Argent. 36. Salvian.</hi> 71. <U+017F>o in agues begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the urine is white, after that (heate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>ing) yellow, and red; and in declination the heate decaying, more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e again. So urine voided after large drinking is fir<U+017F>t white, after more coloured, and at length returneth to his former colour againe and con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence.</p>
            <p>And where there is much idlenes, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony,
<U+017F>urfeits, <U+017F>leep, drunkenne<U+017F><U+017F>e, u<U+017F>e of cold meates, the urine is white and thicke,
<U+017F>ediment much and crude, naturall heate being oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed and <U+017F>uffocated.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 8 In re<U+017F>pect of complexions, the flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike hath urine of colour white, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thicke, quantity increa<U+017F>ed, and the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49277:14"/> more raw.</p>
            <p>The chollericke yellow as pure gold, much coloured, and of <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thin.</p>
            <p>The melancholike white, with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dimne<U+017F><U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e melancholy is in quality cold and dry. But if melancholy be voided, in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance the urine is blacke, as in criticall evacuations of melancholy.
<hi>Aegid.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>The <U+017F>anguine reddi<U+017F>h with a certaine darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance indifferent thicke</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of Vrine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of urine is either
<list>
                  <item>thin,</item>
                  <item>thicke,</item>
                  <item>or meane.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Thin <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance.</note>Vrine thinne as water,
<U+017F>uch as every urine is of it owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
 neither can it waxe thicke by <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing having little earthly <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther congeale through cold in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which be hot as long as we live, is not of <U+017F>o good <U+017F>ignification as thicke urine, becau<U+017F>e it <U+017F>ignifieth crudity and debility: whereas thicke urine <U+017F>ignifieth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49277:14"/>
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>eparation and beginning of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, as al<U+017F>o <U+017F>trength of the expul<U+017F>ive faculty to expell gro<U+017F><U+017F>e matter, and mixt with urine: but thin urine doth <U+017F>ignifie either.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 1. Ob<U+017F>truction in the veines or liver with an ague, of the reines and ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine without an ague by tough and clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my humours, cloddes of bloud, tumors,
<U+017F>tone, fle<U+017F>h growing, whereby the thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker part of the urine is <U+017F>taied, and the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <U+017F>mall quantity, as it were through a colander or <U+017F>trainer is let pa<U+017F><U+017F>e, and may be knowne by the paine in the ob<U+017F>tructed part. <hi>Salv.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Crudity.</note> 2. Or crudity and lacke of concoction and <U+017F>eparation, through cold and want of naturall heate, or abundance of unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heate in an ague, and other <U+017F>ignes of heate, as in <U+017F>imple di<U+017F>temperatures without mixture of humours, as is <U+017F>eene in cold, much drinking of wine, water and drinke.</p>
            <p>Pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing pre<U+017F>ently after drinking, and e<U+017F>pecially which provoketh urine, and
<U+017F>taying not in the body untill humours be concocted to i<U+017F>hue with it to give it <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance and tincture: for the <U+017F>econd urine
<U+017F>taying longer, is thicker and more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49277:15"/> and <U+017F>o the third and the fourth, as
<U+017F>ooner or later, more or le<U+017F><U+017F>e thicke and coloured, as concoction and heate is more or le<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>trong. <hi>Capiv.</hi> 103. and at length returneth to his former <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es when all humors are raw and unfit to bee concoct, the urine is white and thin, and after that heate increa<U+017F>ing is yellow and red, and in declination the heate decrea<U+017F>ing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F><U+017F>e againe, untill he returne unto his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<U+017F>tate of health.</p>
            <p>In furfetting, drunkenne<U+017F><U+017F>e, gluttony, and e<U+017F>pecially pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing pre<U+017F>ently after.</p>
            <p>When the <U+017F>tomach is cold, whereby meate and humors are raw, and <U+017F>o <U+017F>ent to the liver.</p>
            <p>When the liver of it <U+017F>elfe is cold and weake, receiving them raw from the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and <U+017F>endeth them <U+017F>o to the reines. For the errour of the fir<U+017F>t concoction is not taken away in the <U+017F>econd.</p>
            <p>When the reines and ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine through weaknes are not able to draw or expell any humour but thin. <hi>Capiv.</hi> 86.</p>
            <p>Colour white in children <U+017F>ignifieth death. <hi>Salvian.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>Likewi<U+017F>e in weake per<U+017F>ons.</p>
            <p>And in <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. <hi>Argent.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49277:15"/> Continuance of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, in intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting agues, or <U+017F>trong per<U+017F>ons.</p>
            <p>Recidivation or returning againe of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, being made on the criticall day.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Conclu<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the humor.</note> 3. Or thin urine <U+017F>ignifieth conver<U+017F>ion of the humour another way with <U+017F>ignes of concoction, and more coloured urine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, as to the whole body with paine in the whole body, and thin water long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, the humour regurgitating into all places, as in the <U+017F>mall Pocks, Mea<U+017F>ils, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>tumes, Drop<U+017F>ie, Botches, and Felons.
<hi>Aegid.</hi> 230.</p>
            <p>Into the <U+017F>tomach, and cau<U+017F>eth upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and vomitings.</p>
            <p>To the braine in a frenzie with a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ague, and is mortall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen</hi> never knew any e<U+017F>cape, <hi>Mont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Liver with paine in the right
<U+017F>ide.</p>
            <p>To the pores of the skin in <U+017F>weat.</p>
            <p>To the <U+017F>hort ribbes, arme-holes, necke, privy parts, gathering to an head, making an impo<U+017F>tume.</p>
            <p>To the belly in drop<U+017F>ies beginning. For after the matter increa<U+017F>ing, the urine wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thicker.</p>
            <p>To the reines in Nephritide.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49277:16"/> To the <U+017F>eat in the Hemerodes.</p>
            <p>To the joynts, as to the huckle-bone in
<hi><U+017F>ciatica,</hi> knees, feet, hands in the gout, drawing humors to them. <hi>Argent</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>To the guts, as in dy<U+017F>enteries, flixes, laskes, loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>To the cods in Hydrocele.</p>
            <p>To the mother, as immoderate flux of the termes. <hi>Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To other parts that are weake and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved whither humors fall. Or being infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, draw humors to them much like cupping-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Thick <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance.</note> Vrine thicke as <U+017F>yrrup boiled to his height, or yellow choler in the gall. <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid.
23.</hi> is alwaies made by mixture of other humors, as bloud, choler, fleume not naturall, abounding melancholy, rawe humors, purulent matter, <U+017F>eed, gravell, or filaments. The farther placed from you the thinner it appeareth, and hath alwaies moates <U+017F>tirring up and downe contrary in both to Wine or Vineger, be<U+017F>ides the
<U+017F>mell. <hi>Argent.</hi> 29. which either may be cleered externally, being chafed at the fire, returning againe, (except it hath
<U+017F>tood too long, or <U+017F>tood too long by the fire or in Sunne, <hi>Arg.</hi> 47. or <U+017F>uch as waxe thicke, and are turned by <U+017F>tanding in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49277:16"/> cold extingui<U+017F>hing the heate and <U+017F>pirits of the urine:) or may be cleered of it <U+017F>elfe in the Vrinall, the thicker and gro<U+017F><U+017F>er part
<U+017F>etling downe to the <U+017F>ediment: and this hath alwaies a good <U+017F>ignification that good concoction now beginneth in the liver, and that which is concoct hath now
<U+017F>ome forme though unperfect: but while the heate is fervent in the veins, <U+017F>ome ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<U+017F>triall matter is mixed therewith, which is not yet perfectly <U+017F>eparated by the heate. Looke after in the declination of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e.
<hi>Wecker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or this thicke urine may not be clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed though chafed at the fire, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth either from the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els and pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of urine, as the reines, bladder, yard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng too open and large. <hi>Fernel.</hi> 449. or
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xulcerated and apo<U+017F>tumated, whereby
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he urine is tronbled, and with purulent
matter, raw humor, or <U+017F>eed is white, of
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loud red, and <U+017F>ometimes with gravell and
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laments. All to be knowne by <U+017F>mell and
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riefe in the part. <hi>Fern. 39. Arg.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Or el<U+017F>e it commeth from <U+017F>ome <U+017F>upe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our member, as liver, <U+017F>plene, veines, <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, where it is alwaies an argument
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f heate oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed and crudity; not that
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aturall heate is di<U+017F>tempered, but <U+017F>uffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49277:17"/> through abundance of humours. <hi>Fern.
449.</hi> and is to bee under<U+017F>tood either of one urine made at the <U+017F>ame time, or many, urines made on <U+017F>everall daies, and <U+017F>everall times of the <U+017F>ickene<U+017F><U+017F>e. As in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, where it <U+017F>heweth abundance of gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, raw, and flegmaticke humours: which cau<U+017F>e head-aches in tertian and quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian agues, and <U+017F>uch urine now made, when as nature hath made no concoction or <U+017F>eparation, it is through weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of nature, of unnaturall heat (<U+017F>ymptomaticall and ill) and other ill <U+017F>ignes joyned withall, as feeble pul<U+017F>e, old age, Winter weaknes: it is mortall, except in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of choler, and bloud, which are <U+017F>oon concocted. <hi>Arg.
29.</hi> but with good <U+017F>ignes, as youth, <U+017F>trength, good <U+017F>ediment, continuance of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e not de<U+017F>perate <hi>Weck. 13. Sal. 36. 138. Cap.</hi> 100.</p>
            <p>State, a better <U+017F>igne, becau<U+017F>e now natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat beginning to prevaile, doth <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and expell humors, which nouri<U+017F>h the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e in <U+017F>trength of the patient, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good <U+017F>ignes; otherwi<U+017F>e, that unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat putrefactive beginneth to move the humors, as chanceth often in pe<U+017F>tilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall agues, <hi>Weck.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Declining, if thinne water was made
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49277:17"/> before <U+017F>ome daies, and after it is made, it cleareth in the Vrinall. <hi>Sal.</hi> 201. when as naturall heate hath made <U+017F>ome concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <U+017F>o expelleth the humor offending, e<U+017F>pecially being made on the criticall day, it is a very good <U+017F>igne, for thus many di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es are cured, as the <U+017F>ciatica, gout. <hi>Sal.</hi> 37. paine in the joynts.</p>
            <p>And when the humour offending is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and the patient recovered, the urine returneth to his colour and meane con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tence againe. <hi>Arg.</hi> 25. But if it waxe thin and white too <U+017F>uddenly, or ha<U+017F>tily, before the humor be expelled, and the patient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, it <U+017F>eemeth the humor is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted another way, where it makes an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tume drawing to a head, or to the braine as before in thin urine: looke immediately before in thicke humor which cleareth of it <U+017F>elfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Mean <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance.</note> Meane urine, neither <U+017F>o thin as water, neither <U+017F>o thicke as bea<U+017F>ts water, but as white Wine or cleere Ale: which waxeth thicke in the gla<U+017F><U+017F>e, through cau<U+017F>e exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as cold or longer <U+017F>tanding: for <U+017F>o in Winter urines turne <U+017F>ooner then in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: and being neere the fire or heate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe, except the naturall heate of the urine be totally extinct by too long,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49277:18"/>
<U+017F>tanding, or by being in too hote a place as the <U+017F>un, or too long by the fire, or in warme water, whereby the heate and <U+017F>pirit of the urine is di<U+017F><U+017F>ipated, rarified, and evaporated out of the urine, <hi>Argent.</hi> 47. The<U+017F>e two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne not.</p>
            <p>Or through cau<U+017F>e internall, <hi>Videl.</hi> 1. want of naturall heate: as old mens urines and tho<U+017F>e that are in recovery of their health, doe ea<U+017F>ily change and waxe thicke, and being chafed at the fire returne again, except they have <U+017F>tood long, &amp;c. 2. Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of humors which nature can neither concoct nor detaine, but is almo<U+017F>t <U+017F>uffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith, as their urines which have crammed them<U+017F>elves with meat &amp; drink are more ea<U+017F>ily turned and waxe thicke. And both the<U+017F>e in whole men doe <U+017F>ignifie health impaired, becau<U+017F>e heate hath entred into <U+017F>ome raw matter in the veines, and cleareth it by rarifying the parts thereof, which heate and <U+017F>pirits being expelled by externall cold, the urine becommeth thick,
<hi>Wecker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <U+017F>icke men in the beginning, ill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e the concoction is of unnaturall heate. After the beginning with other good
<U+017F>ignes, concoction of naturall heate: but with ill <U+017F>ignes crudity of unnaturall heate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49277:18"/> But if the urine continue meane in the gla<U+017F><U+017F>e, and yet after it hath <U+017F>etled, the thicker part falleth to the <U+017F>ediment, it <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth good concoction in the <U+017F>tomacke, liver, veines, and lively naturall heate. <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.
449.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of clearene<U+017F><U+017F>e and darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e of Vrine.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Cleare urine.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Rine is al<U+017F>o either per<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous,
 light through or cleare, through which a man may di<U+017F>cerne his knockles. <hi>Record.</hi> and is not all one with thin u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine: for white wine is thin, and yet often darke, and not light through. Di<U+017F>tilled wine is thin in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, yet troubled and darke. This <U+017F>ignifieth in whole men (if it be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately per<U+017F>picuous) perfit dige<U+017F>tion, good humors, abundance of naturall heat, which at length doth <U+017F>eparate and di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h the hypo<U+017F>ta<U+017F>is.</p>
            <p>In <U+017F>icke men if it be too cleare and <U+017F>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron colour, <U+017F>ignifieth yellow choler, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall heate, as in agues. <hi>Weck.</hi> More
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49277:19"/> remi<U+017F><U+017F>e, or darker, crude, and white, fleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike, and watry matter, and <U+017F>ignifieth cold, crudity, and continuance of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, and the more coloured the better.
<hi>Cappivac.</hi> 113.</p>
            <p>But in judgement of cleere and per<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous urine in <U+017F>icke per<U+017F>ons, we mu<U+017F>t al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies con<U+017F>ider how their urine was in their health. For if it be the <U+017F>ame urine that was in their health, it <U+017F>ignifieth no ill: but if it change from le<U+017F><U+017F>e cleare to more cleare, and in colour <U+017F>affron; then choler is augmented: in white colour flegme, and contrariwi<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Dark urine</note> Or that is darke, troubled, not light through, through which one cannot <U+017F>ee his knockles, is not all one with thicke urine, as <hi>Galen</hi> thought. <hi>Salvian.</hi> For fi<U+017F>h-glew, horne, white of an egge, oyle, and gla<U+017F><U+017F>e molten, and blacki<U+017F>h wine are thick in <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, yet cleare per<U+017F>picuous, or light through. <hi>Fern.</hi> 450.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereof are three kindes, whereof the fir<U+017F>t is darke accidentally by outward cold after it is made, as by cold ayre, cold water, winter: and this of all other is mo<U+017F>t thicke and darke, and doth <U+017F>taine the Vrinall, e<U+017F>pecially in the crowne or top, with a certaine white clammy thin
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49277:19"/> humor, which being cha<U+017F>ted at the fire, or in warme water, returneth to it <U+017F>elfe againe as it was made (except it hath
<U+017F>tood too long, <hi>Cappivac. 107.</hi>) whereby the inward heate of the urine is wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingui<U+017F>hed. But that <U+017F>ome urines more,
<U+017F>ome le<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ooner, <U+017F>ome later, <U+017F>ome
<U+017F>carcely at all waxe dreggy, thicke, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and darke, is to be imputed to the impurity and want of heate in the urine it <U+017F>elfe, and outward cold extingui<U+017F>hing the internall heate, rarifying, di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ing, and drawing out the <U+017F>pirits and naturall heate of the urine, which being di<U+017F><U+017F>olved the urine waxeth troubled, thicke, and darke, <hi>Argent.</hi> 47. and this hath <U+017F>mall <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in judgement of urines, <U+017F>aving in
<U+017F>harpe di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es it <U+017F>ignifieth beginning of concoction. <hi>Fernel.</hi> 450.</p>
            <p>The other two kinds are darke when they are fir<U+017F>t made. Dreggy urine, and confu<U+017F>ed urine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Dreggy urine is, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of it <U+017F>elfe, or by <U+017F>ome internall mixture is thicke, and <U+017F>uch as come often from fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and uncleane reines: and this by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at the fire or other heate, cannot be altered and made cleere, and hath many meates flying, floating, and <U+017F>wimming in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49277:20"/> the urine, which by <U+017F>tanding <U+017F>ettle down to the bottome, and becommeth a thicke re<U+017F>idence, whereby the re<U+017F>t of the urine waxeth cleere. And this is like to wine troubled wirh mixture of dregges, <U+017F>uch commeth from the reines, or bladdder, troubled with humors, which urine brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth with it new ulcer, blood: old ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, rotten, purulent, and filthy matter.</p>
            <p>Tho<U+017F>e which bee troubled with ache in their reines, make u<U+017F>ually <U+017F>uch urines through blood, matter, or other filthy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity.</p>
            <p>Veines abounding with gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, which naturall heate can <U+017F>carcely concoct, and <U+017F>o <U+017F>ome part is voided: hereof ri<U+017F>e long di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, head-aches, pre<U+017F>ent or to come, and if it continue long lethargy or veternus.</p>
            <p>Criticall evacuation <U+017F>uddenly made after long ob<U+017F>truction of the veines, liver, reines,
<U+017F>pleene, in whole men after exerci<U+017F>e, in
<U+017F>ick men in declination of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in long continuing agues, as quartane, and in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the liver, <U+017F>pleene, and breaking <U+017F>orth impo<U+017F>tumes with ea<U+017F>e of the patient.</p>
            <p>Symptomaticall evacuation of humors raw, and <U+017F>uperfluous from the veines,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49277:20"/>
<U+017F>pleene, liver, as in jaundice, and <U+017F>o voiding with the urine, being in colour red or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, as in the beginning of continuall, and intermitting agues.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Confu<U+017F>ed urine is darke, wherein no moats are perceived to <U+017F>wim, or any other thing without di<U+017F>tinction, but the whole urine and every part thereof is all alike; neither by <U+017F>tanding <U+017F>etleth any re<U+017F>idence, or other thing to the bottome, whereby it may waxe clearer; and <U+017F>o continueth without alteration: yea, though it be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at the fire, and in warme water, and is like to wine which is changed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dead with thunder, or with age is waxed <U+017F>owre or tart, without clearene<U+017F><U+017F>e and brightne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and this never ri<U+017F>eth of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in the reines, nor only of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner parts, but alwaies commeth from di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the veines, neither doth it <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie abundance of raw humors, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly confu<U+017F>ion, putrefaction, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and that remedile<U+017F><U+017F>e (<hi>malignam</hi>) of the bloud and humors in the greater veines: for putrefaction doth confound and <U+017F>huffle all things together: wherefore it is found onely in continuall, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and maligne agues. By the<U+017F>e I would have you to under<U+017F>tand that <U+017F>uch urine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49277:21"/>
(although it be not polluted with unclean reines) doth not alwaies <U+017F>hew the <U+017F>tate of the bloud and humors. For oftentimes it is yellow, thicke, and troubled, and yet the blood comming out of the veines by blood-letting is perfectly pure, and red, as it often chanceth in a quartane and terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an intermitting, as al<U+017F>o in the jaundice, when <U+017F>uperfluous choler doth i<U+017F>hue out of the liver, and gall, and other places, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into the veines, and is not mixed with the blood, but onely with the urine: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are greatly deceived, which in thick and red urine do pre<U+017F>ently command blood-letting, as al<U+017F>o it happeneth many times, that the urine in colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and <U+017F>ediment is naturall, and yet blood let out is faulty, both in colour and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance:
<U+017F>uch as are for the mo<U+017F>t part in the <U+017F>tate, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and before the critick day of continuall agues, when the urines are perfectly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, but the humor offending not at all, moved and voided. <hi>Fernel. 451. &amp;</hi> 452.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49277:21"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of colours of Vrines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Olours of urines are 21. which argue and <U+017F>hew crudity and concoction.</p>
            <p>Crudity, both darke white, as milke white (<hi>Lacteus</hi>) as white of milke Horne-white, <hi>Glaucus,</hi> as the cleare part of a lanterne horne, Gray, <hi>Charo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, blandus color,</hi> like the white part of a mans naile next the joynt. But <hi>Galen</hi>
<U+017F>aith, <hi>Charoppus</hi> is like the colour of Lyons eyes.</p>
            <p>And light white, Chry<U+017F>talline, <hi>Chry<U+017F>tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus.</hi> Snowie, <hi>Niveus.</hi> Watery, <hi>Aqueus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concoction, but little or <U+017F>omewhat lacking, yet more then the former co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, pale, <hi><U+017F>ubpiceus, <U+017F>ubpalidus,</hi> flaxen, <hi><U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perfect and ab<U+017F>olute, be<U+017F>t, palew, or partly <U+017F>affron, <hi><U+017F>ubrufus, <U+017F>ubaureus, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus.</hi> Lighter then crowne gold, yellow as pure gold, <hi>Aureus. Actuar, Fulvus, rufus, Citrinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All degrees of colours following after yellow, doe <U+017F>ignifie heate. <hi>Sal. pag. 88. ex Avicon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49277:22"/> Exceeding the perfect and ab<U+017F>olute concoction in the<U+017F>e degrees in heate. <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.
88.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Light <U+017F>affron (<hi><U+017F>ubcroceus, <U+017F>ubflavus</hi>) like water wherein ba<U+017F>tard <U+017F>affron is di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved.</p>
            <p>Saffron (<hi>flavus, croceus</hi>) like to water wherein the flower of <U+017F>affron is di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Claret (<hi><U+017F>ubrubeus, palmeus</hi>) like to bole armoniake.</p>
            <p>Red (<hi>rubeus, puniceus</hi>) as red blood, cherries, red apples, <U+017F>affron it <U+017F>elfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Crim<U+017F>on (<hi>purpureus vineus</hi>) like blacki<U+017F>h redde wine, liver colour, water wherein fle<U+017F>h new killed hath been wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hed.</p>
            <p>Purple (<hi>pa<U+017F><U+017F>eus, cyaneus</hi>) of the colour of rai<U+017F>ons of the <U+017F>unne, cherries waxing blacke, like wine boyled, <hi>Salvian.</hi> 81.</p>
            <p>Blew (<hi>venetus, fu<U+017F>cus, caeruleus, brunus, blavus</hi>) halfe white and halfe blacke mixed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Greene (<hi>viridis, porracius, pra<U+017F><U+017F>inus</hi>) as leeke leaves, emeraude, coole-wort.</p>
            <p>Oylie green (<hi>oleaceus</hi>) popinjay greene.</p>
            <p>A<U+017F>h colour, colour of lead (<hi>lividus plumbeus.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Blacke (<hi>niger.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49277:22"/>
¶In colours of urines we mu<U+017F>t alwaies con<U+017F>ider whether better <U+017F>ucceed wor<U+017F>e or contrary, that <U+017F>o we may know the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of nature.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and colour ioyntly together.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinne <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, joyned with colour white, privately without mixture of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, as Snowe-water, or Chry<U+017F>tall <U+017F>ignifieth either crudity, ob<U+017F>truction or conver<U+017F>ion of the humor.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Crudity.</note> Crudity through decay of naturall heate, and then the urine is made freely without paine, which commeth either by
(<hi>Salv. 75.</hi>) Re<U+017F>olution of cau<U+017F>e externall, great hunger, long fa<U+017F>ting, or watching, great exerci<U+017F>e or labour, which if they be all moderate the urine is all more colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and thicker, <hi>vid. cap.</hi> 1. under kinde of life. So in old men which by age are me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholike, and other cold conditions of the body. <hi>Argent.</hi> 25. <U+017F>ome large evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sowning<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
               <hi>Weck<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49277:23"/> Or of cau<U+017F>e internall, as the ill quality of the humor offending, maligne and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tilent with other evill <U+017F>ignes. Or el<U+017F>e un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall heate overcoming the naturall heate, as fle<U+017F>h <U+017F>eething in a pot, being
<U+017F>et in the <U+017F>unne is le<U+017F><U+017F>e boiled<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the heate of the <U+017F>unne drawing out the heate of the water.</p>
            <p>Such heate is in the whole body, in the beginning of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, e<U+017F>pecially agues, when unnaturall heate prevailing, the humors are raw and not concoct, and as in a con<U+017F>umption and lingring ague, the moi<U+017F>ture of the body is re<U+017F>olved and moulten, which maketh the urine white,
<hi>Aegid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the reines and ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, as in the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill (<hi>Diabetes</hi>) when through unnaturall heate and <U+017F>trength of the attractive faculty of the reines, urine is drawne too fa<U+017F>t from the liver and <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke before it can receive any <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance and colour: and the retentive and dige<U+017F>tive faculties of the reines, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing feeble, and the expul<U+017F>ive <U+017F>trong, the urine is pre<U+017F>ently voided often and much; whereupon followeth great thir<U+017F>t<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> heate in the reines, wa<U+017F>ting of the body, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tivene<U+017F><U+017F>e,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49277:23"/> and if the griefe continue, death.
<hi>Aegid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Crudity through <U+017F>uffocation</note> Or <U+017F>uffocation, and that either of cau<U+017F>e externall, as eating or drinking immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately,
<U+017F>urfetting, quaffing, liberall fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<U+017F>mall exerci<U+017F>e, urine made <U+017F>hortly after meat and drinke received, e<U+017F>pecially much, or diuretike, whereby the urine is made before it be concocted in great and large quantity, without <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
            <p>Or of cau<U+017F>e internall, as multitude of humors offending nature, <U+017F>moothering and choaking the naturall heate, as too much oyle extingui<U+017F>hing the Lampe, and too great quantity of greene wood the fire, as in all humorall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es before concoction appeareth, urine is white and thin, but after as the matter is concoct, and heate increa<U+017F>eth, urines vary. <hi>Wec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi>
<U+017F>uch as appeare in great cruditie of cold in children, a mortall <U+017F>igne. <hi>Salvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.
24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not a good <U+017F>igne in declination of a di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, both for the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, but either <U+017F>heweth conver<U+017F>ion of the humor another way, or relap<U+017F>e and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciduation, except the urine was made
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49277:24"/> afore in great quantity, for <U+017F>o it is a good
<U+017F>igne. 31. <hi>Holler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Drop<U+017F>ie of cold di<U+017F>temperature of the liver at the beginning, for afterward the matter increa<U+017F>ing, the urine waxeth thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</p>
            <p>Apoplexy.</p>
            <p>Falling evill with leadi<U+017F>h darke, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>e colour.</p>
            <p>Swimming in the head with a certain greeni<U+017F>h colour.</p>
            <p>Pal<U+017F>ies.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of flegme, want of appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of melancholy of his cold, and dry quality, but being voided in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thicke and blacke. <hi>Aegid.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>Gout with little moats in the <U+017F>ediment.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the mother, whereunto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens cold con<U+017F>titutions are <U+017F>ubject.</p>
            <p>Ob<U+017F>truction of <U+017F>ome parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<note place="margin">Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> in, neere, or about the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine; as the liver, reines, water, conduits, the urine made with paine and little in quantity. Such ob<U+017F>truction ari<U+017F>eth of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, raw, gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, and indige<U+017F>ted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cending to the conduits of urine, as in a quartane with certaine rods or lines in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49277:24"/> it, and rhe <U+017F>pleen di<U+017F>tent with melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maketh the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of urine <U+017F>traight.
<hi>Aegid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Flegme gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and gla<U+017F><U+017F>y, de<U+017F>cending to the water conduits, as in women flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<U+017F>topped, and regurgitating to the ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els of urine, with skales or blacke du<U+017F>t in the <U+017F>ediment, but <U+017F>ometimes blacki<U+017F>h, and a red purulent matter.</p>
            <p>Choler mixt with gro<U+017F><U+017F>y and clammy moi<U+017F>ture, whereby it cannot i<U+017F>hue out with the urine, as in the jaundice <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
            <p>Sand, gravell, as in the <U+017F>tone of the reines and bladder, partly <U+017F>topping the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, as al<U+017F>o receiving nouri<U+017F>hment, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed of tough, vi<U+017F>cous <U+017F>lime, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e would i<U+017F>hue with the urine, and make it thicker.</p>
            <p>Slimy matter, as in the <U+017F>trangury.</p>
            <p>Tumors, impo<U+017F>tumes, growing either in the liver, or betwixt the reines and the bladder, or in places neere to the pa<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of urine, whereby they are made
<U+017F>traighter.</p>
            <p>Colicke or Iliate, the winde di<U+017F>tending the guts, and <U+017F>traitning the reines ob<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them, and continuing above <U+017F>even daies is mortall.</p>
            <p> 
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49277:25"/> 
               <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>ver<U+017F>ion of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</note>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor which <U+017F>hould give <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and colour another way, and <U+017F>o the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine are more de<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of heate and humor, as to the braine in phren<U+017F>ies mortall, except there be other good <U+017F>ignes. <hi>Argent.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>To impo<U+017F>tumes under the <U+017F>hort ribbes, arme-holes in the necke, about the privy parts.</p>
            <p>To the <U+017F>pleene inflamed in ill <U+017F>igne.
<hi>Weck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To other parts of the body as before in thin urine. See there.</p>
            <p>In all the<U+017F>e, if more coloured urines went before, and cea<U+017F>ing too <U+017F>uddenly and no evacuation <U+017F>ucceeded. <hi>Arg. 87. Actuar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Milk white.</note> Milke white hath the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ignification as was before of <U+017F>now-water, <U+017F>eeing they differ not in kinde but in degree, but here is le<U+017F><U+017F>e hurt, by rea<U+017F>on of better colour and tincture.</p>
            <p>Health in <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, if the colour of gold went before.</p>
            <p>Death, con<U+017F>umption of the lungs, if the colour of gold went not before, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with other bad <U+017F>ignes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pale flaxen</note> Pale flaxen, the beginning of conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Exulceration of the lungs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umption
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49277:25"/> if it be little, and have leadi<U+017F>h oily pale we; which is mortall with a laske.</p>
            <p>Flegmaticke complexion in a young man being often made in thicki<U+017F>h <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Palew, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, citrine</note> Palew, yellow, citrine, in whole men perfect health, and if the <U+017F>ediment be good in young men, by compari<U+017F>on of this all other are to be judged.</p>
            <p>Flegmaticke complexion if the <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance be <U+017F>ome what thicke.</p>
            <p>In <U+017F>icke men, hote and <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es imminent.</p>
            <p>In old men as a double tertian.</p>
            <p>In children as a quotidian.</p>
            <p>In young men flegmaticke, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike or crude contents if they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long <U+017F>o, becau<U+017F>e their urine <U+017F>hould na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally be more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e for abundance of moi<U+017F>ture.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the brea<U+017F>t, the region full of bubbles.</p>
            <p>Of the <U+017F>plene, when many rods or <U+017F>trikes appeare like meteors.</p>
            <p>Of the liver if it be much in quantity, the body leane, the belly bound.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Light <U+017F>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>, <U+017F>affron.</note> Light <U+017F>affron, <U+017F>affron, of cau<U+017F>e exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, much watching, great labour and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49277:26"/> travell, e<U+017F>pecially in the heate of the Sunne,
<U+017F>imple di<U+017F>temperature of heate without mixture of humors, if it be pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>picuous, medicines purging choler, as Rheubarb, al<U+017F>o <U+017F>affron, cinnamon, broth of cherries.</p>
            <p>Of cau<U+017F>e internall, as choler abounding as in a tertian.</p>
            <p>Di<U+017F>temperature of humors, e<U+017F>pecially blood if it be thicki<U+017F>h darke.</p>
            <p>Melancholike complexion in thicke
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and cholericke in thin.</p>
            <p>End of a <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e being made on the criticall day.</p>
            <p>Blew, melancholy.</p>
            <p>¶Vrines yellow, <U+017F>affron, red, do <U+017F>ignifie exceeding heate of <U+017F>imple di<U+017F>temperature, if they be pure and per<U+017F>picuous, but mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of humor withall, if they be thicke and troubled, <hi>Fer.</hi> 447.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.</note> Thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance joyned with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">White.</note> White po<U+017F>itively with mixture of humors, betokeneth abundance of raw humors, flegme, gla<U+017F><U+017F>y, <U+017F>alt, un<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory.</p>
            <p>Con<U+017F>umption in a wa<U+017F>ting ague, <U+017F>o the fatty nouri<U+017F>hment of the body, is molten and voided.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49277:26"/> Impo<U+017F>tumes breaking out, as in grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous agues, <U+017F>o rotten matter is voided,
<U+017F>etling to the bottome and <U+017F>tinking, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.
77.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>End of an ague, if blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ue out of the no<U+017F>e, and being made on the judiciall day in great quantity, and then no impo<U+017F>tume followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Milk white.</note> Milke white like water wherein a little meale is ca<U+017F>t, is good in the end of an ague, and rather if great quantity of urine was made before, <hi>B. Holler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matter of the <U+017F>tone voided out of the reines and bladder, looke more in the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in raw humors and matter of a <U+017F>ore.</p>
            <p>An ulcer in the in<U+017F>truments of urine, if it be thicke like a mu<U+017F>hrone, and matte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<U+017F>tinking and falling to the <U+017F>ediment;
<U+017F>eparation of raw and flegmie matter without corruption or <U+017F>tinch.</p>
            <p>Flux of <U+017F>eed in a man or woman, carnall copulation if it be without corruption and
<U+017F>tinketh not.</p>
            <p>Drop<U+017F>ie if the yellow jaundice continue through great crudity in the veines.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Horne white.</note> Horne-white, like the horne of an old lanthorne, darke through <U+017F>moke, or gray, like the darke colour of an oxe liver, not troubled, betokeneth that the body is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49277:27"/> full of gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, and flegmatike di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es of the whole body if it be troubled, which is like a bea<U+017F>ts water, and <U+017F>o con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing long, or alwaies, yet <U+017F>ometimes being chafed at the fire, it cleareth when it is broken by cold ayre, <U+017F>ignifieth that the veines are full of ill humors, head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache through agitation of humors a<U+017F>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. If it waxe cleare above, and clod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth in the <U+017F>ediment, if it be much in quantity, then it betokeneth the end of an ague: if little in quantity, an ill <U+017F>igne in an ague.</p>
            <p>All white urines <U+017F>ignifie <U+017F>ome good, if the patient be <U+017F>trong.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Claret.</note> Claret, continuing of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, yet without danger, if it hath a <U+017F>ediment of like colour and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Red like cherries.</note> Red like cherries, or red apples, of cau<U+017F>e externall, fore-<U+017F>heweth that the loynes or reines are beaten and brui<U+017F>ed, or <U+017F>ome vein neer the reins open or broken, with paine in the place grieved, <hi>Actuar.</hi> receipt of
<U+017F>ome purgation of rheubarbe, &amp;c. as pag. 4. died with priver, <hi>Avicen.</hi> which <hi>Mont.</hi> 19. beleeveth not.</p>
            <p>Internall, widene<U+017F><U+017F>e, rarity, thinne<U+017F><U+017F>e, or laxity of <U+017F>ome veines neere the reines, through which blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth, and <U+017F>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49277:27"/> out in great quantity, and weaknes of body, <hi>Actuar.</hi> the reines or bladder fretted, untill blood commeth, as in the <U+017F>tone, e<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after labour, with gravell.</p>
            <p>Abundance of blood, as rotten agues e<U+017F>pecially.</p>
            <p>Abundance of choler, as in agues terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, partly troubled with an uncleane and rough <U+017F>ediment, or <U+017F>emitertian with a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>h colour, and greene cloud.</p>
            <p>Abundance of heate unnaturall, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ting and melting the moi<U+017F>ture of the body into urine made in great quantity, with fatte <U+017F>wimming aloft, as in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umption.</p>
            <p>Vrine <U+017F>taying too long in the body, being not provoked to i<U+017F><U+017F>ue either by
<U+017F>harp quality, which lacketh in colde di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, or by great quantity being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted another way, and <U+017F>o at length by delay in the body, waxeth more colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and concoct: <U+017F>uch happeneth in the pal<U+017F>ie, apoplexy, epilep<U+017F>ie, phti<U+017F>icke, crampe, mortall, <hi>Haff.</hi> drop<U+017F>ie mortall, or el<U+017F>e the liver through debility, is not able to <U+017F>eparate the blood from the urines, as in <hi>hepatica pa<U+017F><U+017F>ione, Salvian. 87. Arg.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>Such al<U+017F>o happeneth in the laske, bloody flixe, <hi>Argent.</hi> 38. mortall, <hi>Haff.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49277:28"/> cholike, iliake, mortall, <hi>Haffurt,</hi> paine in the reines, or el<U+017F>e to the place grieved, blood and heate are drawne, or el<U+017F>e choler not de<U+017F>cending through the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the liver, and the guts being ob<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with flegme, and winde, i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth with the urine, <hi>Aegid.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Agues decaying, <hi>Fer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ob<U+017F>tructions, inflammations <U+017F>cirrous tumors of the gall (being the naturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of choler) ob<U+017F>tructed, the choler i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth at other parts, or el<U+017F>e that portion of choler, which <U+017F>hould be voided by <U+017F>tool, is here voided by urine, <hi>Argent.</hi> 37. as in the jaundi<U+017F>e, with paine in the necke and
<U+017F>hort ribs, and will colour a linnen cloath put into it.</p>
            <p>Of the <U+017F>pleene, and liver, as in the drop<U+017F>ie,
<U+017F>o choler goeth to the urine.</p>
            <p>Relap<U+017F>e, or recidivation of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, if it be made thicke, and <U+017F>traight after thin, before and after, the criticall day, becau<U+017F>e the heate which did at the fir<U+017F>t expell the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e now is overcome.</p>
            <p>In young men without danger, with a good <U+017F>ediment through length of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, but in old men death, not able to detaine the blood, <hi>Actuar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Crim<U+017F>on.</note> Chrim<U+017F>on betokeneth great labour and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49277:28"/> travell in whole men, e<U+017F>pecially in the heate of the Sunne or the fire, &amp;c. wherby the blood is inflamed and ro<U+017F>ted, <U+017F>o in an ague.</p>
            <p>Burning ague with thir<U+017F>t, watchings, cough, and other accidents of an ague,
<hi>Actuar.</hi> Adu<U+017F>tion of choler and turning into melancholy, yet not <U+017F>o ill if there bee a good <U+017F>ediment: but ill, if the contents be ill or none at all, and the urine thicke, and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e like a cloud.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Purple.</note> Purple betokeneth the yellow jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice if it continue long, if there be <U+017F>ignes of concoction, it betokeneth health be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e the cau<U+017F>e of the griefe is voided. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the reines onely after <hi>Fer.</hi> and not of weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the liver, whether the urine be red, bloody, or crim<U+017F>on, and like to the wa<U+017F>hing of raw fle<U+017F>h, which <hi>Reu<U+017F>.</hi> mi<U+017F>liketh.</p>
            <p>Abundance of blood <U+017F>ometimes in young men, with <U+017F>ome heavine<U+017F><U+017F>e or weight about the liver, and up to the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell bone, or necke bone, and here it is not a very evill <U+017F>igne, but in old men very evill, yea often mortall, becau<U+017F>e they are not able through debility to detaine the blood.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Blew.</note> Blew, beating, brui<U+017F>ing, <U+017F>tripes, where
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49277:29"/> it is a good <U+017F>igne, becau<U+017F>e the humor is voided. But <hi>Va<U+017F><U+017F>eus</hi> was deceived by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, mixing an oxe gall, <hi>Reu<U+017F>nerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Extreame cold, and mortification, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction of naturall heate, if the <U+017F>trength be weake, and no <U+017F>ignes of concoction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides.</p>
            <p>Great exerci<U+017F>e, and labour, great heate, and ro<U+017F>ting of the blood.</p>
            <p>Melancholy ari<U+017F>ing of a du<U+017F>t colour.</p>
            <p>Changing of the bladder from his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition in old men.</p>
            <p>Strangury at hand in tho<U+017F>e that have the <U+017F>tone.</p>
            <p>Recovery and health where the patient is mending in declination of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, or being made on the criticall day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Greene alone.</note> Green or rather greeni<U+017F>h, <hi>Argent.</hi> alone
<U+017F>eldome of good hope, <hi>Mont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cold, extreme, mortall: if leadi<U+017F>h co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and blacke follow <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, pul<U+017F>e feeble, in thir<U+017F>t, or <U+017F>hort breath, <hi>Cappiv.</hi> 147. contrary to <hi>Reu<U+017F>n.
136.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quotidian ague, melancholy a du<U+017F>t, yellow jaundice e<U+017F>pecially with an ague.</p>
            <p>Heate and adu<U+017F>tion of humors a long time: if greene hath blacke immediately
<U+017F>ucceeding, and not leadi<U+017F>h comming
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49277:29"/> betweene, and accompanied with great heate in the body, thir<U+017F>t, ague, <U+017F>hort breath, and <U+017F>ome <U+017F>plendent gli<U+017F>tring in the urine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Green oyly</note> Oyly, not <U+017F>uch wherein fat like <U+017F>piders webs floate, but <U+017F>uch who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance is clammy and thicke, as oyle or fat molten, and being <U+017F>haken is clammy and heavy as oyle, <hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Good,</hi> if it be made only after black urine, as better <U+017F>ucceeding the wor<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>Made on the criticall day, in great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, for <U+017F>o the matter is voided.</p>
            <p>After paine of the reines without an ague, e<U+017F>pecially appearing <U+017F>uddenly with great quantity.</p>
            <p>Drop<U+017F>ie, vehement cholike. This urine
<hi>Galen</hi> hath often <U+017F>eene without any great hurt following, <hi>Cappiv.</hi> 92.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ill,</hi> in a con<U+017F>umption of the body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medile<U+017F><U+017F>e through great imbecility of the parts of the body ri<U+017F>ing of great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temperature of heate, that they cannot containe nouri<U+017F>hment, which voiding, doth give this colour to the urine. <hi>Reu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in con<U+017F>umption of the lungs.</p>
            <p>Tertian ague in fat and <U+017F>oft tender bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<hi>Argent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49277:30"/> Convul<U+017F>ion of drine<U+017F><U+017F>e, madne<U+017F><U+017F>e, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting continuall thir<U+017F>t, heate, the tongue
<U+017F>corched, &amp;c. going before, yet if bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter colours follow, better hope, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A<U+017F>h colour</note> A<U+017F>h colour leadi<U+017F>h, <hi>good</hi> in beating, brui<U+017F>ings, if it <U+017F>ettle to the <U+017F>ediment, in blacke jaundice, becau<U+017F>e the cau<U+017F>e of the griefe is evacuated. <hi>Ill,</hi> extreme and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall heate in hot agues, if green colour was made before at other times. <hi>Contra Cappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vac.
145.</hi> E<U+017F>pecially without <U+017F>ediment and other <U+017F>ignes of heate.</p>
            <p>Mortall, <U+017F>trangury, following in a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ague.</p>
            <p>Extreme and mortifying cold, if the colour before was pale and other <U+017F>ignes of cold, <hi>Cappivac.</hi> 149.</p>
            <p>The <U+017F>ame judgement is of blew colour, but that here all things are greater and augmented.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Blacke.</note> Thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance with colour blacke, of cau<U+017F>e either externall or internall.</p>
            <p>Externall, eating of Ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia, <hi>Argent.</hi> 40.
&amp;c. as before <hi>pag. 4. cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Fall, brui<U+017F>ings, beatings, purgers of melancholy.</p>
            <p>Internall by mixture of <U+017F>ome humor, as melancholy, blood adu<U+017F>t, or choler
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49277:30"/> adu<U+017F>t, <hi>Mont.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Criticall evacuation with ea<U+017F>e of the patient after great di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>Quartane declining or rather burning ague, long or <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with bleeding at the no<U+017F>e and <U+017F>weat on the criticall day, els death, <hi>Actua.</hi> Child-birth, or with child,
<hi>Cap.</hi> 151.</p>
            <p>Womens flowers heretofore <U+017F>topped, and now voided if white or <U+017F>uch like went before.</p>
            <p>Splenetike di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with a tumor in the
<U+017F>pleene.</p>
            <p>Chronicall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the backe and matrix of melancholy.</p>
            <p>Melancholy, blacke jaundi<U+017F>e, <hi>Wec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Madne<U+017F><U+017F>e, fury, hemmoraudes.</p>
            <p>Reines and bladder troubled with the
<U+017F>tone, with <U+017F>tincke, by breaking <U+017F>ome little veines in the reines.</p>
            <p>Other griefes of gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, but if there be great heate, paine, ague, want of appetite, a po<U+017F>ie, <U+017F>ome dangerous canker, carbuncle, or naughty ulcers, <hi>Sal.</hi> 97.</p>
            <p>Symptomaticall extreame and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, heate and adu<U+017F>tion, as in <U+017F>harp agues, if greene urine went before or red, with heate, leanne<U+017F><U+017F>e and thir<U+017F>t,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49277:31"/>
<U+017F>tinke of the urine and <U+017F>mall quantity,
<hi>Cappiv. 111. 161. 169. Fern. Actuar.</hi> which may cau<U+017F>e a dangerous cramp or convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion after great labour, except it be made on the criticall day.</p>
            <p>Cold, if blew, green, or a<U+017F>h colour urine made before, with cold, and without <U+017F>tinch a little <U+017F>ediment, and united, <hi>Cappiv. 146. Selv.</hi> 94. but in this ca<U+017F>e the urine is rather darke then blacke indeed, <hi>Mont. vide mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial. varia. lect. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Blacke urines are mortall in all ages and per<U+017F>ons, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e they come of <U+017F>ome cau<U+017F>e externall, or criticall evacuations, <hi>Salv. 93.
96. Cap.</hi> 157.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A generall note.</note> ¶There be foure elementary qualities, whereof two be called active, and two pa<U+017F><U+017F>ive: the active be heate, and cold, and the<U+017F>e give colour unto the urine: for heate maketh the urine red and tinct with high colours (which by moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e are ob<U+017F>cured and darkned, by drine<U+017F><U+017F>e quickned &amp; made far more light<U+017F>ome:) and cold maketh the colour of the water more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e, as white and <U+017F>uch like.</p>
            <p>Now the two pa<U+017F><U+017F>ive qualities, are moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e and drine<U+017F><U+017F>e, which cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance in urines: whereof moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the urine, dulleth the colour, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49277:31"/> augmenteth the quantity: drine<U+017F><U+017F>e clarifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ratifieth it, and that either by dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>hing the quantity, contents, and <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, or by increa<U+017F>ing the thinne<U+017F><U+017F>e, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and brightne<U+017F><U+017F>e thereof, with meane colour and gro<U+017F><U+017F>er <U+017F>ediment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the quantity of Vrine.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Much quantity.</note> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vantity of urine. Much of cau<U+017F>e externall and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>Externall, moi<U+017F>t, and rainy weather, and all things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>ing moi<U+017F>ture in the body, as <U+017F>leepe, idlene<U+017F><U+017F>e, want of exerci<U+017F>e, moi<U+017F>t meates, or broaths, or other things which doe moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ten the body.</p>
            <p>Long and much drinking and quaffing of wine, water, color white, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thin,
<hi>Salv.</hi> 106.</p>
            <p>Medicines diuretike which provoke urine, breake the <U+017F>tone, or make the urine
<U+017F>harp and <U+017F>alt.</p>
            <p>For by their heate they draw much urine, and by <U+017F>ubtilty of their parts they attenuate gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors for expul<U+017F>ion<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49277:32"/>
<U+017F>ediment being <U+017F>lender and gli<U+017F>tering
<hi>Actua. Salv.</hi> 101.</p>
            <p>Internall evacuation, criticall or <U+017F>ympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall.</p>
            <p>Criticall, by <U+017F>trength of nature, ea<U+017F>e of the patient, and other <U+017F>ignes of conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as in drop<U+017F>ie, ana<U+017F>arca, or great cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, repletion of humors, when the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor hath been long <U+017F>hut up in a place and now findeth i<U+017F><U+017F>ue, <hi>Weck. Fern.</hi> <U+017F>o abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of raw humors made thinner are voided by urine as <hi>Fernelius</hi> ob<U+017F>erved, a drunkard, gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, fat, and well liking in 8. daies <U+017F>pace by continuall evacuation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<U+017F>lender and leane without any <U+017F>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e at all.</p>
            <p>Other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es colour, whither, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thinner, <U+017F>ediment mean, and where thicke urine went before, el<U+017F>e not good except nature be <U+017F>trong, <U+017F>o in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es declining.
<hi>Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Symptomaticall, through weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of nature without ea<U+017F>e of the patient, and other <U+017F>ignes of crudity, as when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive faculty is decayed in dangerous di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, or nature is wearied, di<U+017F><U+017F>olveth humors and voideth them <U+017F>uddenly by
<U+017F>weat, <U+017F>toole, or urine, <hi>Actua.</hi> 116. as in laskes, flixes, want of appetite, chronicall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49277:32"/> di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, convul<U+017F>ion of heate and drine<U+017F><U+017F>e in
<U+017F>harp agues.</p>
            <p>Con<U+017F>umption of the whole body <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what fatty, in colour palew, reddi<U+017F>h, high coloured, without <U+017F>ignes of concoction, for <U+017F>o the profitable fat, moi<U+017F>ture, humors, and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiall parts of the body are mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, di<U+017F><U+017F>olved, and voided by urine. <hi>Sal. 109. Fern.</hi> 445.</p>
            <p>Cau<U+017F>e internall, heate of the liver draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abundance of juice from the <U+017F>tomacke too fa<U+017F>t, and not able to dige<U+017F>t it.</p>
            <p>Heat of the reines drawing the urine too fa<U+017F>t from the liver and emulgent veines,
<U+017F>peedily expelling it as in the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing ill, colour white, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thin, <U+017F>ediment lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<hi>Actua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cold of the <U+017F>tomack breeding wateri<U+017F>h juice, and <U+017F>ending it to the liver, for errour in the fir<U+017F>t concoction is not taken away in the <U+017F>econd.</p>
            <p>Cold of the liver not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the profitable juice into nouri<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in all habit of the body, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ie, ana<U+017F>arca, the urine wateri<U+017F>h with raw and diver<U+017F>e <U+017F>ediment, <hi>Bl. Holle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other excrements not evacuated either by <U+017F>toole, colour meane <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49277:33"/> thicker and greater. <hi>Actuar.</hi> or by
<U+017F>weat, or by pores of the skin, by in<U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible per<U+017F>piration, &amp;c. <U+017F>o the moi<U+017F>t and thin parts are voided more abundantly by urine, <U+017F>o <hi>Ari<U+017F>t. 4. de gener. animal.</hi> 4. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth a cow (who<U+017F>e paunch-hole being
<U+017F>hut up) had her excrements turned into winde and urine, <hi>Salv.</hi> 111.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Little quantity.</note> Little of cau<U+017F>e externall or internall.</p>
            <p>Externall, as dry meats, colour palew, <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment
<U+017F>mall and thicker.</p>
            <p>Little drinking, tart, <U+017F>tipticke, thicke, or drying drinke.</p>
            <p>Much <U+017F>weat, vehement exerci<U+017F>e, or other things whereby the moi<U+017F>ture of the body is dried and made le<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>Internall, ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine <U+017F>topped or ob<U+017F>tructed by inflammation of the water conduits and necke of the bladder, tumor or <U+017F>welling, tough, gro<U+017F><U+017F>y, and clammy meates, as in the <U+017F>trangury, medicines, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors flegmaticke, <U+017F>tone, <U+017F>ee gravell in the
<U+017F>ediment, with paine and griefe about the place affected. <hi>Dolor o<U+017F>tendit locum,</hi> <U+017F>ee
<U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine.</p>
            <p>Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine hurt or weakened by old age, pal<U+017F>ie, ill di<U+017F>temperature, or <U+017F>ome in<U+017F>trumentall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the parts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the urine cannot bee attracted, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>received,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49277:33"/> expelled, <hi>Salv.</hi> 113.</p>
            <p>Internall cau<U+017F>e, as tran<U+017F>lation of the urine another way, as to the belly, feet, and nether parts in the drop<U+017F>ie.</p>
            <p>To the guts in laskes, flixes, purgations
<U+017F>ediment little, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance thin, color white and wateri<U+017F>h, <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>To the Hemeraudes, men<U+017F>truall evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the flowers.</p>
            <p>To the pores of the skin in <U+017F>weat and in
<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible per<U+017F>piration.</p>
            <p>Cods in the rupture, <hi>Hydrocele.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the whole body, in the <U+017F>mall pocks, mea<U+017F>ils, impo<U+017F>tumes, <U+017F>ee thin <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance. And in recovery of health after <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>o moi<U+017F>ture is turned into nouri<U+017F>hment of the body, <hi>Fer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Internall cau<U+017F>es, <U+017F>harp burning agues wa<U+017F>ting the moi<U+017F>ture of the body, colour tending to blacke, <hi>Cappivac.</hi> 111.</p>
            <p>Con<U+017F>umption of the body of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance whereby the moi<U+017F>ture is dried, as in <U+017F>harp agues, con<U+017F>umption of the lungs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Meane quantity.</note> Meane, proportionable to the drinke received the <U+017F>ame day, and other daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or <U+017F>omewhat le<U+017F><U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome is
<U+017F>pent in the body, Health.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49277:34"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the <U+017F>ignification of the contents of the Vrine in generall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ontents are, what<U+017F>oever is to be <U+017F>eene in the urine be<U+017F>ide colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, quantity, per<U+017F>pecuity, and darkene<U+017F><U+017F>e, and they oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy
<U+017F>ometime the top of the urine, as
<U+017F>pume, bubbles, circle, <U+017F>ometime the highe<U+017F>t part, or region (the whole urine according to his height being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into three equall parts, which are commonly called regions) as the cloud
(<hi>nubes.</hi>) <U+017F>ometime the middle region, as the <U+017F>ublation, or <U+017F>wimme: and la<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<U+017F>ometime, and that mo<U+017F>t often, the lowe<U+017F>t region, or <U+017F>ediment; as gravell, blood, <U+017F>eed, du<U+017F>t, &amp;c. as hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Contents are <U+017F>ometime lacking in the urine, and <U+017F>ometimes pre<U+017F>ent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Contents wanting for five cau<U+017F>es.</note> Contents want in the urine for five cau<U+017F>es. 1. For want of matter, which
<U+017F>hould make the contents. As in great exerci<U+017F>es, <U+017F>weat, in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible per<U+017F>piration,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49277:34"/> hunger, fa<U+017F>ting, laskes, purgations, either by vomite, or <U+017F>toole, emerauds, flowers, &amp;c. al<U+017F>o in meats which increa<U+017F>e choler, or cholericke di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Corruption of the matter, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in the body, whereby commeth neither nouri<U+017F>hment nor excrement, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Crudity, and lacke of concoction in whole men, by much quaffing, or thin,
<U+017F>mall drinke, or by diuretike potions, which provoke urine. Al<U+017F>o pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing <U+017F>hort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after drinking, before it receive any concoction, or mixture with meat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of contents come. In <U+017F>icke men, in whom, though humors doe abound, yet they doe not i<U+017F><U+017F>ue with the urine, but lurke in the veines, overloading nature, as in chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. Al<U+017F>o in <U+017F>harp agues in their beginning, or increa<U+017F>ing great weakene<U+017F><U+017F>e of nature, not able to expell the contents. And indeed in all humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es beginning, and increa<U+017F>ing the contents are none at all, or little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e nature as yet hath made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, or <U+017F>eparation, and in the <U+017F>tate of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e commonly contents are very few. But in declination, nature recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her <U+017F>elfe, and prevailing again<U+017F>t the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49277:35"/> di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, the contents, cloud, <U+017F>wimme, and
<U+017F>ediment al<U+017F>o returne, except in chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, where the cloud is <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<hi>Cappivac.</hi> 67.  67. Al<U+017F>o in deficient agues beginning, the contents want, as in a tertian, in thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low colour: but if a<U+017F>h colour, death fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. In a quartane the urine is thin, and white. In a quotidian, thin, white, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri<U+017F>h.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor another way, as, in impo<U+017F>tumes, in cold weather, weake bodies, and injudicable <U+017F>tate of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. In inflamations, which draw the contents and humors to them. In parts weake, or grieved whether humors fall, as before in thin urine. Looke there
<hi>cap. 2 pag.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Ob<U+017F>truction in white, and thin urines with <U+017F>ignes of concoction, or without crudity. See <hi>cap. 2. pag.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
            <p>¶Le<U+017F><U+017F>e to be di<U+017F>prai<U+017F>ed, if the colour and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance bee good, according to which, the humor abounding, <U+017F>trength of nature, and quantity of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e are to be judged, as before in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and colour, <hi>Actua.</hi> 94. But di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of choler are ended if the cloud onely appeare. But in flegmatike, and of repletion the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49277:35"/> pre<U+017F>ent mu<U+017F>t argue their di<U+017F><U+017F>olution,
<hi>Capiv.</hi> 67. 164.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Contents <U+017F>ometimes good and <U+017F>omtimes ill.</note> ¶Contents appearing in the urine are of two <U+017F>orts: for they are either partly naturall, partly unnaturall, <U+017F>ometimes good and <U+017F>ometimes ill. Or el<U+017F>e, they be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unnaturall, and alwayes ill.</p>
            <p>In contents which are partly naturall, partly unnaturall, we con<U+017F>ider (as in the whole urine before) colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and quantity.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colour of the Contents.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">White.</note> White duely knit, or hanging together equally, <U+017F>ignifieth good concoction in the liver, and veines, health, rule of all other.</p>
               <p>Not equally knit, but thicker in one part then in another, <U+017F>ignifieth weak dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tion, crudity, windine<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>White not duely knitte or hanging together, but ragged, tattered and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a<U+017F>under equally, crudity, windine<U+017F><U+017F>e. Not equally, but thinner in one place then in another, <U+017F>ignifieth the falling evill, windine<U+017F><U+017F>e, gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the body, mea<U+017F>ils, or <U+017F>mall pockes, where the colour waxeth red.</p>
               <p>White as <U+017F>now; <U+017F>ignifieth flegmaticke humors and crudities.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49277:36"/> 
                  <note place="margin">Pale.</note>Pale, flaxen, blood turned into choler and evacuated.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Saffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>, &amp;c.</note> Light <U+017F>affron, <U+017F>affron, red, claret, <U+017F>ignifie crudities, al<U+017F>o blood thin and wateri<U+017F>h, yet wherein concoction is to bee looked for <U+017F>hortly. Al<U+017F>o choler abounding in <U+017F>icke per<U+017F>ons, <hi>Reu<U+017F>n.</hi> 178. Continuance in tertian and quotidian agues e<U+017F>pecially ba<U+017F>tard. A good <U+017F>igne in agues, which ri<U+017F>e of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance either of blood or ill humors, in which the <U+017F>ediment is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary before recovery can be looked for. But in agues cau<U+017F>ed through heate of the Sun, much labour, or hunger, the <U+017F>wimme or cloud is <U+017F>ufficient to <U+017F>ignifie recovery of health, although the <U+017F>ediment doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.
¶For reddi<U+017F>h looke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bloody.</note> Blood, like to the wa<U+017F>hing of raw fle<U+017F>h,
<U+017F>ignifieth abundance of blood. Or el<U+017F>e flux of blood i<U+017F><U+017F>uing out, as out of <U+017F>ome veine broken. But yet we mu<U+017F>t not be ha<U+017F>ty in judgement by this colour, but rather looke after under the title of pure blood voided,
<hi>Reu<U+017F>n.</hi> 181. Al<U+017F>o it <U+017F>ignifieth imbecility, or ob<U+017F>truction of the liver, which cannot concoct the blood, and <U+017F>o it runneth to the bladder.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Blew.</note> Blew, leadi<U+017F>h, <U+017F>ignifieth naturall heate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49277:36"/> extingui<U+017F>hed or mortified, and therefore great danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Greene</note> Greene blacki<U+017F>h <U+017F>ignifieth great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding heate, or con<U+017F>umption and pining away.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Blacke.</note> Blacke <U+017F>ignifieth either great cold, if leadi<U+017F>h colour went before, and then the outward parts are cold, <hi>Salvian.</hi> 128. or great heate if greene colour went before, and then heate, thir<U+017F>t, and other tokens of heate accompany it. Both the<U+017F>e are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, as you may <U+017F>ee in thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and blacke colour.</p>
               <p>Or el<U+017F>e blacke contents <U+017F>ignifie melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, or melancholy, critically evacuated: where it is a good <U+017F>ign of health becau<U+017F>e the humor is voided.</p>
               <p>If <U+017F>ignifieth al<U+017F>o con<U+017F>umption of the reins with an ague, the <U+017F>ediment oyly and fatty, <hi>Reu<U+017F>n.</hi> 188.</p>
               <p>La<U+017F>tly, it <U+017F>ignifieth beating, brui<U+017F>ing,
<U+017F>tripes, and <U+017F>o come corrupt, blacke, and rotten blood is voided.</p>
               <p>Sub<U+017F>tance of the contents is either mean, thick or thin.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Meane.</note> Sub<U+017F>tance meane, is a good <U+017F>igne of health, becau<U+017F>e it is according to nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thicke.</note> Thicke contents generally <U+017F>ignifie gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, and raw humors much abounding<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49277:37"/> or imbecility of the <U+017F>econd concoction.</p>
               <p>And in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es beginning, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing an ill <U+017F>igne, becau<U+017F>e they <U+017F>ignifie abundance, and trouble of humors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore naturall heate hath concocted, and attenuated them. But in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a good <U+017F>igne, if the colour, and other
<U+017F>ignes be good, nature being now of
<U+017F>trength to make <U+017F>eparation, and expul<U+017F>ion of humors.</p>
               <p>Thicke contents, and of colour claret,
<U+017F>ignifie abundance of blood, or good and
<U+017F>trong operation in dige<U+017F>tion, <hi>Reu<U+017F>ner.
203.</hi> but contents of colour blacke, <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie great <U+017F>tore of blood, and the more blacke, the greater ade<U+017F>tion of blood,
<hi>Reu<U+017F>ner.</hi> 204.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin.</note> Thin contents which doe not ea<U+017F>ily ari<U+017F>e, nor trouble the urine, when the uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is <U+017F>haken and moved, <hi>Reu<U+017F>ner.</hi> 186.
<U+017F>ignifie raw humors, or want of heate in the <U+017F>econd concoction in whole men. But in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es ri<U+017F>ing of cold, or ill juice, thin <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, <U+017F>heweth great danger. Becau<U+017F>e naturall heate is choaked, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, that it cannot expell the humour offending. Contrariwi<U+017F>e in <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, or in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es which ri<U+017F>e of <U+017F>imple and bare di<U+017F>temperature without mixture of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49277:37"/> humors. They are not very ill, <U+017F>eeing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are not the cau<U+017F>e of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which voiding with the urine, <U+017F>hould make the contents thicke.</p>
               <p>If the <U+017F>ediment lightly ari<U+017F>e, the urinall being <U+017F>haken, it argueth more heate,
<hi>Va<U+017F><U+017F>.</hi> 71.</p>
               <p>¶If they continue either thicke, or thin, they <U+017F>ignifie weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of nature, which <U+017F>hould change them, <hi>Argent.
71.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quantity of contents is either much, little, or meane.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Much.</note> Much <U+017F>ignifieth. 1. Lacke of <U+017F>ufficient heate to attenuate and concoct the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er parts <U+017F>o in winter, drunkards, <U+017F>leepers, idle per<U+017F>ons, women and children contents are moe, <hi>Reu<U+017F>n.</hi> 64.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Much nouri<U+017F>hment, good and <U+017F>trong dige<U+017F>tion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Other evacuations <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, as ordure, <U+017F>weat, &amp;c. and e<U+017F>pecially in fleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike bodies, which are grieved with
<U+017F>ome di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which will end well.</p>
               <p>Little or few contents.<note place="margin">Little.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Want of matter, as in hunger, great heate, <U+017F>ummer, lu<U+017F>ty age, great exerci<U+017F>e, quartane and quotidian agues beginning for want of heate, <hi>Argent.</hi> 72. but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49277:38"/> much. Contrary in tertians.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ob<U+017F>tructions and <U+017F>toppings of the emulgent veines, water conduits, reines, bladder, &amp;c. <hi>Salvia.</hi> 120. As in thin urine
<U+017F>ee there.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Crudity and <U+017F>low concoction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All cau<U+017F>es which doe attenuate and make thinner any matters in the body, that <U+017F>o the thinner part may evaporate out, and the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er <U+017F>tay within, and make ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truction, al<U+017F>o all cau<U+017F>es which do wa<U+017F>t and con<U+017F>ume the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Meane.</note> Meane contents of good <U+017F>ignification becau<U+017F>e they are according to nature.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII</head>
            <head type="sub">Of contents in <U+017F>peciall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F deformed contents, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unnaturall, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ill; which appeare either in the <U+017F>ediment or lowe<U+017F>t region, or in the
<U+017F>wim or middle region, or la<U+017F>tly in the cloud or upper region. And fir<U+017F>t of unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and deformed contents in the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are commonly reckoned fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Popinjay greene.</note> 1. Popinjay greene or oyly <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49277:38"/>
<U+017F>ignifieth.</p>
            <p>Colliquation of the whole body, with paine, an ague, and pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed <U+017F>lowly by little and little: or el<U+017F>e collaquation of the reines or bladder onely with paine in the reines, no ague, and pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed fa<U+017F>t.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Spider webs.</note> 2. Spider webs or fatne<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>wimming in the urine, <U+017F>ignifieth</p>
            <p>Con<U+017F>umption of the whole body with an ague.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Red vet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> Red vetches or fitches, <hi>ervaceum, oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beum,</hi>
<U+017F>ignifie</p>
            <p n="1">1. Great inflammation of the liver.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Colliquation of the whole body: or of the reines onely, with conditions as before in popinjay greene.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Plates, <U+017F>cales, (<hi>folium, laminae,
<U+017F>quamae</hi>) having bredth and length one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like <U+017F>cales of fi<U+017F>hes, e<U+017F>pecially a goge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Plates, <U+017F>cales.</note> 1. Con<U+017F>umption or colliquation of the whole body, with an ague, <U+017F>low pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing,
<U+017F>tinch, and crudity in the re<U+017F>t. All concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Exulceration of the bladder, pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed thicke and fa<U+017F>t, with <U+017F>tinke, purulent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, paine, and concoction, <hi>Salvian.</hi> 176.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Inflammation of the bladder or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49277:39"/>
5. Gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and cour<U+017F>e branne, <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Thin.</note> 1. Con<U+017F>umption of rhe whole body with crudity and thin urine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Scabbedne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the whole body, without ague or other paine, <hi>Ha<U+017F>fur,</hi> or of the bladder onely, with concoction, no ague. And paine of the bladder, thicke and <U+017F>tinking, an itch about the root of the yard, and purulent matter was pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed before, <hi>Salv.</hi> 175.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Great heate wa<U+017F>ting the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the liver, and burning the blood, if the bran be red.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Fine bran, fine meale or flower (<hi><U+017F>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fine meale</note> 
               <hi>puls,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Colliquation of the <U+017F>ollid parts, if they be white.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Extreame adu<U+017F>tion of the blood, if they be red, and therefore long <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e,
<hi>Salvian.</hi> 179.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sharp <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and for the mo<U+017F>t part mortall.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Women with childe have fine meale
or <U+017F>tarch in the <U+017F>wimme, or <U+017F>etling to the
<U+017F>ediment of their urine, like fine carded wooll, the re<U+017F>t of the urine a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and greeni<U+017F>h, or a<U+017F>h colour, <hi>Fernel.</hi> Looke motes in the <U+017F>ediment.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49277:39"/>
7. Raw humor (<hi>crudus humor</hi>) clammy but not <U+017F>tinking like <U+017F>nevill of the no<U+017F>e, or white of an egge.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Raw hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</note> 1. Exulceration of the reines and blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der without paine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Impo<U+017F>tume or <U+017F>tone of the reins and bladder with paine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Multitude of raw humors <U+017F>omtimes cau<U+017F>ing an ague, and appearing in the
<U+017F>ediment, <U+017F>ignifie ache in the reins, <U+017F>ciatica, gout, <U+017F>trangury, tena<U+017F>mus. In the <U+017F>wimme, crudity and windine<U+017F><U+017F>e in the <U+017F>tomacke, with a noi<U+017F>e, and vomiting. In the cloud, griefe in the <U+017F>pirituall parts, <U+017F>hortne<U+017F><U+017F>e of winde, pur<U+017F>ivene<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>pitting of blood, <hi>Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fur. Aegid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Eating of meats hard to dige<U+017F>t, in
<U+017F>ore labouring men, <hi>Va<U+017F><U+017F>.</hi> 74, 75.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Rotten and purulent matter. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a <U+017F>ore (<hi>pus</hi>) <U+017F>tinking, but not much clammy, which when the urinall is <U+017F>haken, di<U+017F>per<U+017F>eth it <U+017F>elfe into fatty and oyly re<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and <U+017F>ignifieth,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Rotten matter.</note> 1. Exulceration of the reines without paine, <hi>Fernel.</hi> of the bladder with paine about the bladder. Of the liver with paine under the right <U+017F>hort ribs, and doth not alwaies <U+017F>tinke liver putrefied, if it be very dreggy, <hi>Aegid.</hi> 69.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49277:40"/>
2. Inflammation or impo<U+017F>tume of the lungs, who<U+017F>e purulent matter pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth by the left cavity of the heart into the great artery, and thence into the emulgent veins, and <U+017F>o to the reines.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Plurifie, who<U+017F>e matter pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. As al<U+017F>o by the veine without a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>) ri<U+017F>ing on the right <U+017F>ide of the hollow veine, neere the heart and by the backbone, nouri<U+017F>hing eight ribs on either
<U+017F>ide: and <U+017F>o to the midriffe, and at length by divers turnings into the left emulgent veine, and thence to the reine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Rhewme, which if it be thick, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the bladder it maketh difficulty in pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing by drops. 5. Al<U+017F>o the phren<U+017F>ie.
6. or <U+017F>quin<U+017F>ie, who<U+017F>e purulent matter of the<U+017F>e three is conveyed through the jugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar veines into the hollow vein, and thence into the emulgent veines, and <U+017F>o to the reines, if there be paine and griefe in the lungs, liver, bladder, in the<U+017F>e griefes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aid, otherwi<U+017F>e if purulent matter be voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and no paine in the<U+017F>e members, it is certaine that nature voideth it ri<U+017F>ing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammations.
7. or venerous and contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous flux of <U+017F>eed, <hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Haires like pieces of fle<U+017F>h, long,
<U+017F>lender, and hairy) <hi>poli, carunculae, filamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>)
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49277:40"/> onely in thicke urine, <hi>Salvian.</hi> 182. and
<U+017F>ignifie.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Haires or filaments.</note> 1. Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of the whole body, with an ague, colour oily or greene, <hi>Hasfurt.</hi> or of the reines onely without an ague, the haires fatty and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, and may bee felt betwixt the fingers, like a <U+017F>mall, <U+017F>lender, fle<U+017F>hy <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ob<U+017F>truction of the reins, with gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and clammy humors, as in the <U+017F>trangury, dy<U+017F>ury, pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing ill, &amp;c. with nummedne<U+017F><U+017F>e of that foot, which is on the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ide the reine is, right left.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Exulceration of the reines or blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whence commeth purulent matter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Flux of <U+017F>eed after carnall copulation, venerous pollutions on the night: or filthy and exulcerate gonorrhea, <hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Womens white flowers i<U+017F><U+017F>uing, or women having uncleane matrices, <hi>Fern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10. Gravell <U+017F>and, (<hi>Arenula, <U+017F>abulum</hi>) red, white, or duski<U+017F>h browne, <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Cravell <U+017F>and.</note> 1. Stone breeding or di<U+017F><U+017F>olving either in the reines, if the gravell be red, (yet <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times white by filth inclo<U+017F>ing the gravell,
<hi>Fernel.</hi>) and paine about the reines in the backe, no ague, and the gravell being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the urinall and dried in a <U+017F>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49277:41"/> place, are hard in touching. Or in the bladder if the gravell be white and pain in the bladder, about the <U+017F>hare where the haire groweth.</p>
            <p>¶Yet tho<U+017F>e men who<U+017F>e pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of urine are wide and open, and expul<U+017F>ive faculty <U+017F>trong, and making <U+017F>uch <U+017F>andy urine freely, and without paine, in good quantity, are <U+017F>eldome troubled with the
<U+017F>tone, becau<U+017F>e their reines and bladder are hereby clen<U+017F>ed, and the gravell not
<U+017F>uffered to <U+017F>tay <U+017F>o long to unite and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together to make the <U+017F>tone, but
<U+017F>uch gravell doth argue great heate of the liver or reines, and abundance of raw and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors fit to breed the <U+017F>tone, if the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of urine <U+017F>hould be ob<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or expul<U+017F>ive faculty, weakened,
<hi>Salv.</hi> For abundance of tough and vi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous
<U+017F>uperfluities, <U+017F>traitne<U+017F><U+017F>e of pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, and weakene<U+017F><U+017F>e of the expul<U+017F>ive faculty, are three e<U+017F>peciall cau<U+017F>es of the <U+017F>tone,
<hi>Aegid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hi<U+017F>tory of the <U+017F>tone.</note> ¶But lea<U+017F>t the contents mixed with urine, which for the mo<U+017F>t part come from the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, <U+017F>hould deceive him that would rightly judge of other parts of the body, I will repeat the whole cau<U+017F>e, and order of the effects from the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49277:41"/> beginning. Red gravell come from the reines, which being many, and thicke doe threaten the <U+017F>tone, of tho<U+017F>e growing together, groweth a <U+017F>tone as big as a graine of millet, or barley corne, which being extruded out of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the reines, into a larger place, doth make the urine thicke, troubled, red, or black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<U+017F>h, a forerunner of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of the reines, the <U+017F>ame being thru<U+017F>t into the head of the water pipe (<hi>ureter</hi>) cau<U+017F>eth great paine, and then the urine is white and thinne as in ob<U+017F>tructions, the <U+017F>ame growing bigger, is <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>tned in the reines, that it cannot be removed, and then after great labour and exerci<U+017F>e by fretting of the reines with the <U+017F>tone, the urine is not onely thicke, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but al<U+017F>o bloody, and <U+017F>ometime clods of blood <U+017F>etled downe: <U+017F>uch urines are
<U+017F>ometimes made after a fall, or beating, and <U+017F>eldome after great labour: when the ulcer is thus made, in re<U+017F>t, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e, the urine is thicke, and white: after labour more coloured, with a thicke <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment: after that the urine is thicke, white, and <U+017F>tinching, and purulent, not much unlike milk in which purulent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<U+017F>etleth, when as the ulcer is hollow and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49277:42"/> filthy; <U+017F>uch urine hinder judgement of all other parts of the body, <U+017F>ave the reines, and when as the ulcer groweth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry filthy, and commeth to a fi<U+017F>tula in this white, thicke, troubled, and <U+017F>tinking urine, oftentimes a thicke, <U+017F>limy, tough matter, like the <U+017F>nevill of the no<U+017F>e, or white of an egge <U+017F>etleth, and <U+017F>uch often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth when the <U+017F>tone is in the bladder, for though the matter thereof commeth from the reines, yet it groweth and wrappeth about the <U+017F>tone through fault, or weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the bladder, which may appeare, for that the urine continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<U+017F>o when the <U+017F>tone is voided: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over filthy ulcers of the necke of the bladder, and yard, and fluxe of <U+017F>eed in the French di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, doe cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch urines: but at the fir<U+017F>t certaine <U+017F>lender filaments appeare, then more gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, whereof the whole urine waxeth thicke, and la<U+017F>tly this filthy <U+017F>ediment that now we <U+017F>peake of. And although the ulcer be cured, yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain filaments remaine through imbecility of the bladder, and <U+017F>permatike ve<U+017F><U+017F>els,
<hi>Fernel.</hi> 455.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Adu<U+017F>tion of humors. As in di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es of choler, as burning agues, <hi>Salvian.
183.</hi> tertian agues, <U+017F>ingle and compound.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49277:42"/> Al<U+017F>o in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of melancholy, as quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane ague long continued. Gout after long drying and thickning of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. Paine of the joynts and reines. Lepro<U+017F>ie, morbus Gallicus confirmed, emeraudes<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> co<U+017F>tivene<U+017F><U+017F>e, <hi>Aegid.</hi> Al<U+017F>o heate of the liver, if there be no paine nor heavine<U+017F><U+017F>e about the reines.<note place="margin">A gr<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vell note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t <U+017F>uch <U+017F>and.</note> ¶Such
<U+017F>andy gravell floteth in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the urine, like motes in the Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beames, and after <U+017F>etling to the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, covering the bottome of the urinall, or in colour browne, or duski<U+017F>h red, and cleaveth to the <U+017F>ides of the urinall, and being dried in a <U+017F>hadowie place are <U+017F>omewhat <U+017F>oft and tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Looke after for gravell in the
<U+017F>wimme.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Receipt of <U+017F>harp diuretike medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which provoke urine, which skou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reines, doe bring <U+017F>uch gravell with them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wormes.</note> 11. Wormes, little dragons. (<hi>vermes, dracunculi.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Putrefaction, whereof they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred,
<hi>Argent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12. Blood, pure, thicke, gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, or cloddy, (<hi><U+017F>anguis, grumus <U+017F>anguinis</hi>) when the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of blood and urine
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49277:43"/> have their</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Blood, clods of blood.</note> 1. Orifice opened (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth, either becau<U+017F>e that the blood exceedeth in quantity, as in <U+017F>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine men. Or in criticall evacuation, though <U+017F>eldome, <U+017F>o womens flowers voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by urine are gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and cloddy, <U+017F>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the <U+017F>ediment, and no paine in any part of the body. So in declination of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the <U+017F>pleene, with much re<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and dregs, <hi>Hasfurt.</hi> Or el<U+017F>e when the blood exceedeth in quality, as when it is too thin, <U+017F>harp, or <U+017F>alt, tickling the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and provoking them to expul<U+017F>ion. Or el<U+017F>e when the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of blood and urine are either too large, wide, and open, as the veines emulgent carrying the urine from the hollow veine to the reins, being too open, doe receive blood from the hollow veine, <hi>Wecker.</hi> Or when the
<U+017F>aid ve<U+017F><U+017F>els are too weake in their reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty; as when the veines be too weake, <U+017F>o in the <U+017F>mall pockes (<hi>exanthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata</hi>) blood <U+017F>taied in other places, and overloading nature, is voided by urine, which if it <U+017F>tinke, and the pocks be blew or leadi<U+017F>h, mortall. Or the liver too weake,
<U+017F>o pure blood is voided by <U+017F>toole, or urine, as the hollow or round part of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49277:43"/> liver is affected, with paine under the right
<U+017F>hort ribs, and <U+017F>tinketh not. <hi>Ha<U+017F>.</hi> or the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low veine too weake, <U+017F>o pure blood is voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with paine about the <U+017F>eventh joynt in the backe, from <hi>os <U+017F>acrum</hi> upward. <hi>Aegid.</hi> Or la<U+017F>tly, the reines and bladder too weake and feeble, as in old men at the pits brinke.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Membranes or tunicles of the veines, laxe, thin, and full of pores, <U+017F>o thin, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and warme blood running between the skinne and the fle<U+017F>h, <U+017F>weating out
(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>) in proce<U+017F><U+017F>e of time ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth together into blacke and leadi<U+017F>h clods.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sub<U+017F>tance and membranes hurt
(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>) by a fall, beating, brui<U+017F>ing, leaping, violent exerci<U+017F>e, great burdens,
<U+017F>o cloddy blood voideth. Or by medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which are corro<U+017F>ives and cau<U+017F>tickes or openers of ob<U+017F>tructions, or by the
<U+017F>tone in the reines or bladder after exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<U+017F>e:
<U+017F>o the reines or bladder being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and exulcerated, filthy and cloddy blood voydeth with <U+017F>tinke and paine about the places grieved. <hi>Dolor o<U+017F>tendit locum. Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶If blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ue by any of the<U+017F>e wayes in the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the lungs, brea<U+017F>t, arteries,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49277:44"/>
<U+017F>tomacke, belly, or guts, there followeth vomiting of blood; but in other parts by the two fir<U+017F>t waies, it gathereth into clods. <hi>Ianus Cornarius</hi> in <hi>Gal. lib. &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>,
74.</p>
            <p>13. Seed (<hi><U+017F>perma, <U+017F>emen</hi>) which light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly floteth and a<U+017F>cendeth, the urinall being
<U+017F>haken. And i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth with the urine either for that the</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Seed.</note> 1. Seed aboundeth in quantity, as after carnall copulation, de<U+017F>ire of carnall copulation, or venerous dreames, &amp;c. Or when the <U+017F>eed in quality is either too
<U+017F>harp, hot, or <U+017F>alt, then the yard is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth with <U+017F>ome delight in good quantity, and <U+017F>tinketh, <hi>Wecker</hi> in gonorrhaea. Or when the <U+017F>eed is too thin or wateri<U+017F>h, which i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth without <U+017F>en<U+017F>e almo<U+017F>t and unwillingly, the yard not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and then the whole body waxeth leane, e<U+017F>pecially the loines. Or la<U+017F>tly, when the <U+017F>eed is virulent and contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as in <hi>morbo gallico,</hi> with <U+017F>tinch of the urine, and <U+017F>ometime gravelly or <U+017F>andy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els <U+017F>permatike are either too
<U+017F>lippery; or el<U+017F>e weake in their reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, with wa<U+017F>ting of the whole body, as in Apoplexy, pal<U+017F>ie in the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49277:44"/> falling <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e. For in the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es,
<U+017F>toole, urine, feed, &amp;c. are involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Du<U+017F>t.</note> 14. Du<U+017F>t, (<hi>cineres</hi>) black or leadi<U+017F>h and heavy, like a blacke pouder ri<U+017F>ing of melancholy, and <U+017F>ignifieth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Fluxe of the emeraudes pre<U+017F>ent or
<U+017F>hortly to follow, the colour of the urine remi<U+017F><U+017F>e. And <U+017F>ometime vomiting of blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Paine and di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the <U+017F>pleene, e<U+017F>pecially after purging of melancholy. The du<U+017F>t being <U+017F>omewhat browne or purple.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Stopping of the flowers. In <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, thicke, colour pale, flaxen, or white,
<U+017F>ediment little or lacking. And <U+017F>ometime vomiting of blood, and the du<U+017F>t gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and heaped together in the <U+017F>ediment or bottome.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Paine in the reines, loines, and other inferiour parts, by which the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike blood pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth in the hemorrhoidall veines to the <U+017F>eat.</p>
            <p>15. Motes (<hi>Atomi</hi>) <U+017F>uch as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Sunne-beames, little and round, red or white, little flockes. And the<U+017F>e appearing in the urine <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49277:45"/>
1. Putrefaction as in the plague,<note place="margin">Motes.</note> 
               <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gallicus,</hi> with <U+017F>tinch.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Great agitation and commotion of the humors, as in the <U+017F>mall pockes and mea<U+017F>ils.</p>
            <p>In the<U+017F>e two the motes flote all over the urine yet warme, and during t<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate thereof; and after <U+017F>etling to the
<U+017F>ediment, doe <U+017F>ignifie a doubtfull <U+017F>trife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt nature and the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, to be decided by age, <U+017F>trength of the patient, and other
<U+017F>ignes, <hi>Montan.</hi> 50.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Rhewme in the whole body, if the
<U+017F>aid motes doe appeare in the whole urine. Or in the <U+017F>uperiour parts of the body onely, if they appeare onely in the upper region of the urine. Or in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle parts of the body, if they appeare in the middle region. Or la<U+017F>tly, the lowe<U+017F>t part of the body, if they appeare onely in the lowe<U+017F>t region or <U+017F>ediment of the urine, the motes are rough and the urine troubled.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Gout with conditions, as before in rhewme.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the mother.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Conception in women, <U+017F>etling down to the <U+017F>ediment, which if they be red, through greater abundance of heate and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49277:45"/> blood, a male childe is conceived. If white through le<U+017F><U+017F>e abundance of heate and blood, a female is conceived.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Moe <U+017F>ignes of Conception.</head>
               <p>Becau<U+017F>e Phy<U+017F>itians vary in judgement, what urines doe <U+017F>ignifie conception (yea
<hi>Io. le. Bon.</hi> in his treati<U+017F>e <hi>de therapeia puer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purarum. Fore<U+017F>tus</hi> in his booke <hi>de incerto
&amp; falaci urinarum iudicio, lib. 2. cap.</hi> 3. and divers others, doe deny that any certaine judgement thereof can bee gathered by urine.) I thought good therefore not onely to <U+017F>et downe their <U+017F>everall opinions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by urine, but al<U+017F>o adde moe <U+017F>igns be<U+017F>ides urine. Both generally of conception, and
<U+017F>pecially whether it be of male or female.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Signes of conception by urine.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Divers opinions about wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</note> 1. Generally womens urine with child is le<U+017F><U+017F>e concoct, white, thin, with a little <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet the nearer they draw to childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, it waxeth more coloured.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some <U+017F>ay there appeareth in the urine, like fine flower or <U+017F>tarch, which after the urine is <U+017F>etled, hath a <U+017F>edimentor <U+017F>wim
<U+017F>omewhat thicke, like fine carded wooll, and the re<U+017F>t of the urine troubled, and <U+017F>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what greene or blacke.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49277:46"/>
3. Other hold that their urine is white with a cloud, <U+017F>wimming aloft, and many motes floting in the whole urine, <U+017F>uch as are in the Sunne-beames and e<U+017F>pecially in the fir<U+017F>t moneth; and when the urinall is
<U+017F>haken or moved they depart a<U+017F>under, like carded wooll. In the moneths following, the urine is red or yellow, and at length blacke, with a red cloud <U+017F>wimming aloft.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Other <U+017F>ome take their judgement by the <U+017F>ediment only, which they affirme is like cotten or fine carded wooll; or raw <U+017F>ilke. <hi>Reu<U+017F>ner</hi> thinketh that they bee little flockes or motes, &amp;c. as before in motes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Other <U+017F>ignes of conception, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides the urine.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The tearmes are <U+017F>taied without grief after they have i<U+017F><U+017F>ued eight or ten dayes after copulation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They feele a wringing, beating, and moderate paine about their navill, wombe, loynes, <U+017F>tomacke, backe, and thighes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their appetite to meat <U+017F>omewhat decayeth, yet longeth after <U+017F>trange things which affection is called <hi>Citta</hi> or <hi>pica, Aegid.</hi> 74.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:49277:46"/>
4. They have <U+017F>ometime bitter bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, vomitings, hardne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the paps, and redne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the teates, <U+017F>welling of the veines and arteries, e<U+017F>pecially within the no<U+017F>e and eyes, paine, or <U+017F>wimming in the head, dimne<U+017F><U+017F>e of <U+017F>ight, red pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the face, co<U+017F>tivene<U+017F><U+017F>e, no de<U+017F>ire of copulation, though before they had great delight.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If a very cleane needle be put into a womans urine with childe in a bra<U+017F>en ba<U+017F>on all night, and on the morrow be coloured and died with red <U+017F>pots, <U+017F>he hath conceived: but if it be blacke and ru<U+017F>ty, <U+017F>he hath not.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If after <U+017F>upper going to bed, <U+017F>he drinke water and honey <U+017F>odden together
(<hi>Hydromel</hi>) and feele a wringing in her guts <U+017F>he hath conceived, el<U+017F>e not, <hi>Hippoc. 5. Aphori<U+017F>.</hi> 57.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Speciall <U+017F>ignes of conception whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of male or female.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Whether male or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</note> 1. Motes in the <U+017F>ediment red and round,
<U+017F>ignifie a male: but motes white and round, a female.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Milke (in conception of male) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<U+017F>ooner into her brea<U+017F>ts, which being milked, and <U+017F>et in a gla<U+017F><U+017F>e in the Sunne, it
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49277:47"/> waxeth hard into a <U+017F>tone, not unlike a bright pearle.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All her right <U+017F>ide is better and more lu<U+017F>ty then her left, right eye fairer, right pap greater with milke, the pul<U+017F>e of her right artery <U+017F>wifter.</p>
               <p>If milke be ca<U+017F>t upon the womans wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with childe, it will <U+017F>ink to the bottome, neither will it depart a<U+017F>under, though <U+017F>alt be ca<U+017F>t in.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If a womans urine be kept three days in a gla<U+017F><U+017F>e bottle <U+017F>topped, and after <U+017F>train it through a fine, cleane linnen cloath, if there appeare, little quicke living creatures, and red, a male is conceived, if white a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Tearmes flow after the fourteenth day, and the childe is felt to <U+017F>tirre, and move after the fifty day. To be <U+017F>hort, all things are more quicke, lu<U+017F>ty, and
<U+017F>trong in the male, then in the female,
<hi>Reu<U+017F>n.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to be <U+017F>hort, becau<U+017F>e the <U+017F>eed of the male is hotter and livelier then of the female, therefore all things in the male are <U+017F>ooner performed, as the male recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all the lineaments of his body, and perfect <U+017F>hape of a man in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe in thirty dayes: the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49277:47"/> in forty. The male beginneth to
<U+017F>tirre in the wombe in three moneths: the female in foure. The male is borne and commeth forth of the wombe in nine moneths, the female in ten. And the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her <U+017F>elfe after birth of a male, hath forty daies a<U+017F><U+017F>igned for her purification; but after the birth of a female, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>core daies, <hi>Levit.</hi> 12. 4, 5. And that men are hotter in con<U+017F>titution then women, may ea<U+017F>ily appeare in that they have fewer excrements, larger veines, blacker colour, greater and lu<U+017F>tier members, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter voice, more audacity and courage then women, <hi>Bertinus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contents in the middle region of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Contents in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle region or <U+017F>wimme</note> The middle region of the urine, <U+017F>ubla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or <U+017F>wimme, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>) is the middle di<U+017F>tance of the urine divided into three equall parts: and here, (as before in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in generall, and in the <U+017F>ediment in
<U+017F>peciall) are con<U+017F>idered.</p>
               <p>Colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, quantity, contents,
&amp;c. All which have the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ignification for the mo<U+017F>t part, as before in the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49277:48"/>
<U+017F>ave in the<U+017F>e <U+017F>ixe differences fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Contents in the <U+017F>wimme, <U+017F>ignifie
<U+017F>ome windine<U+017F><U+017F>e, whereby they are eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<U+017F>o high.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Good contents in the <U+017F>wimme, which <U+017F>ignifie health (as white, <U+017F>affron, claret, light, and equall) are not <U+017F>o good as in the <U+017F>ediment, yet in agues of choler, heate of the Sunne, hunger, labour, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
&amp;c. Pre<U+017F>ence of the <U+017F>wimme, is a
<U+017F>ufficient <U+017F>igne of health, but of flegme or melancholy, (which are not <U+017F>o <U+017F>oone concocted) the pre<U+017F>ence of the <U+017F>ediment is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary before there can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<U+017F>ecurity of recovery, <hi>Cappivaccius,
67.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Ill contents in the <U+017F>wimme, which are <U+017F>ignes of <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, as blacke, greene, leadi<U+017F>h, <U+017F>olide, and deformed contents, are not <U+017F>o ill, as in the <U+017F>ediment, <hi>Cappivac.
171.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Contents in the <U+017F>wimme give <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the affections and di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in the middle parts of mans body, as about the <U+017F>hort ribs, <hi>hypocondria,</hi> inward en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals, as the <U+017F>pleene, liver, heart, lungs, bowels, &amp;c. <hi>vi<U+017F>cera,</hi> bre<U+017F>t, <U+017F>tomacke. <hi>Va<U+017F>.</hi> 81. As al<U+017F>o contents in the cloud, <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49277:48"/> di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the highe<U+017F>t part of mans body, and the <U+017F>ediment of the lowe<U+017F>t parts. Yet divers mi<U+017F>like this applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the three regions of the urine, to the three parts of mans body, <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Sand or gravell, (not in the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in the <U+017F>wimme) in colour red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>h, and <U+017F>ticking to the <U+017F>ides of the uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as though the urine <U+017F>hould thicken, or congeale into <U+017F>tones, <U+017F>ignifieth Adu<U+017F>tion of the liver, <hi>Va<U+017F>.</hi> 90.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Motes (<hi>Atomi</hi>) floting through the whole urine, and being elevated and puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up by unnaturall and flatuous heate, and after it be cold, <U+017F>etling to the <U+017F>ediment, or troubling the urine, <U+017F>ignifieth a great <U+017F>trife in the veins, betwixt naturall heate and the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, to be determined by age, <U+017F>trength, diet, complexion, and good order of the patient, <hi>Mont.</hi> 50.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the cloud or uppermo<U+017F>t region of the Vrine.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cloud.</note> The highe<U+017F>t or uppermo<U+017F>t region of the urine (being as I <U+017F>aid before divided ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his height, into three equall parts) is called the cloud (<hi>nubes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>) wherin we con<U+017F>ider (as in the two former
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49277:49"/> regions, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, quantity, colour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,
&amp;c. which have the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as before: <U+017F>ave that contents here in the cloud, compared with other regions, have lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>ignification of good, in good <U+017F>ignes: and contrary, lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>ignification of ill, in ill
<U+017F>ignes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colours of the Cloud.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>White.<note place="margin">White.</note>
                  </head>
                  <item>1. Not of very evill <U+017F>ignification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e all contents are naturally white.</item>
                  <item>2. In perfect tertian agues abundance of choler, and <U+017F>o continuance of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e.</item>
                  <item>3. In rotten agues (<hi><U+017F>ynochus</hi>) great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger through pain and griefe in the forepart of the belly about the <U+017F>hort ribs, <hi>Reu<U+017F>ner.
236.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Red.<note place="margin">Red.</note>
                  </head>
                  <item>1. Changing of the <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e into a quartane.</item>
                  <item>2. Concoction of humors, beginning to be on the <U+017F>eventh day or criticall day, if this red colour appeare on the fourth day or judiciall day.</item>
                  <item>3. Head-ache, through winde and flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<U+017F>pirits a<U+017F>cending up into the head, and
<U+017F>o continuance of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49277:49"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Blacke.<note place="margin">Blacke.</note>
                  </label>
Long watchings, and lacke of <U+017F>leepe whereof followeth the lightne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the braine, raving, doting, which in old men is mortall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Deformed contents in the cloud.</head>
               <p>Deformed contents of the cloud are of three <U+017F>orts, according to the places which they occupy, for 1. either they appeare in the whole region of the cloud. 2. or occupy onely the edge, ring or circle round about the urine. 3. or la<U+017F>tly they <U+017F>lote all over the top of the urine. And to begin with the fir<U+017F>t.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Deformed contents appearing in the whole region of the cloud are three.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">White cloud.</note> 1. Little white cloud (<hi>nebula</hi>) <U+017F>ignifieth flegmatick matter to be elevated by <U+017F>trong heate, and for the mo<U+017F>t part, a good <U+017F>igne and <U+017F>ignification of concoction, and which will <U+017F>hortly, as the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e declineth, <U+017F>etleth down to the <U+017F>ediment, by orderly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of nature.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Smoake.</note> 2. Smoake, in colour, blacki<U+017F>h, reddi<U+017F>h, or yellow, <U+017F>ignifieth vi<U+017F>cous and tough matter adu<U+017F>t, cholericke. Abundance of unnaturall heate, puffing up, and elevating
<U+017F>ome raw matter, and therefore conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49277:50"/> of <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es not without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Small graines, kernels, droppes or motes di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed, ragged (<hi>granula divul<U+017F>a</hi>) which if they appeare neere to the top of the urine, e<U+017F>pecially if they be blacki<U+017F>h, they
<U+017F>ignifie adu<U+017F>tion of the matter, and wa<U+017F>ting of the <U+017F>olid parts, as al<U+017F>o that they are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently puffed up by unnaturall heate of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne agues, which oftentimes are mortall,
<hi>Mont.</hi> 51.</p>
               <p>Deformed contents appearing in the circle round about the urine, commonly called the crowne (<hi>corona</hi>) which <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time is wanting, and <U+017F>ignifieth,</p>
               <p>Equall conflict betwixt nature and the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>The crowne appearing round about the urine <U+017F>ignifieth generally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some windine<U+017F><U+017F>e, wherof the crown is made.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Affections and griefes of the head.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the colour of the crowne diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the re<U+017F>t of the urine be better, it is a good <U+017F>igne, that nature overcommeth, but if it be wor<U+017F>e an ill <U+017F>igne, that nature is overcome.</p>
               <p>The placing of the urinall, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the <U+017F>ight, may cau<U+017F>e divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49277:50"/> in the crowne, becau<U+017F>e it con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth indifferently in the confines or common concur<U+017F>e of three diver<U+017F>e tran<U+017F>parent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums
(<hi>media</hi>) the urinall, the urine, and the aire; and therfore the colours of the crown may be variable according to the diver<U+017F>e po<U+017F>ition of the urinall, the urine, the aire, and the eye of a Phy<U+017F>itian beholding it. Like other apparent and not permanent colours, which are made of diver<U+017F>e mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of light and darke. (<hi>Lucidi &amp; umbro<U+017F>i</hi>) as colours of the rainbow, of a Doves neck, a Peacockes taile, changeable taffety, and morning clouds lightened with the Sunne-beames, infinitely variable, according to their diver<U+017F>e po<U+017F>itions and placings, taught in the precepts of optikes. Therfore <hi>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arius</hi> coun<U+017F>ell is, to looke into rhe crowne with one eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colours of the crowne.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Leadi<U+017F>h.</note> 1. Leadi<U+017F>h, blew, and blacke, <U+017F>ignifie the falling <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, or mortification of the braine, whereby the <U+017F>inewes doe not their duty in <U+017F>en<U+017F>e and motion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Fir<U+017F>t leadi<U+017F>h, then red certaine daies after, <U+017F>ignifieth head-ache, or recovery of the animall power.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Greene.</note> 3. Greene <U+017F>ignifieth choler greene
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49277:51"/> like leekes (<hi>porracea</hi>) or phren<U+017F>ie of green choler, if it be in a <U+017F>harp ague: or adu<U+017F>tion of hot choler a<U+017F><U+017F>aulting the head.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Black is of the <U+017F>ame judgement that blacke water is of. For it <U+017F>ignifieth mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, if leadi<U+017F>h colour went before: or adu<U+017F>tion, if greene.</p>
               <p>Thicke crowne joyned with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Saffron.</note> 1. Saffron <U+017F>ignifieth choler in the head, and head-ache thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">White.</note> 2. Wateri<U+017F>h and white, flegme in the hinder part of the head.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Claret.</note> 3. Claret, or crim<U+017F>on, abundance of blood in the head, pricking paine of the temples, fulne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the veines, and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing him<U+017F>elfe to <U+017F>ee little red motes flying before his eyes. Or head-ache through abundance of blood.</p>
               <p>Thinne crowne joyned with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Flaxen.</note> 1. Flaxen, <U+017F>ignifieth ache in the left <U+017F>ide, of the head of melancholy. Or the head, to be of cold and dry con<U+017F>titution. Or melancholike complexion, and therefore
<U+017F>u<U+017F>picious, fearefull, covetous.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Yellow.</note> 2. Yellow, head-ache of choler pricking in the <U+017F>ide of the head.</p>
               <p>Crowne trembling, <U+017F>haking, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49277:51"/>
<U+017F>ignifieth</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Crowne trembling.</note> 1. Paine all along downe the backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Windine<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thin humor.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Stopping of the flowers. Deformed contents floting in the top of the urine; either in the crowne, or all over the top, as <U+017F>pume, froth, bubbles, droppes of oyle, or droppes of fat like
<U+017F>pider-webs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fome<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> froth<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> Fome, froth, bubbles, is an exten<U+017F>ion,
<U+017F>welling, or puffing up of a vi<U+017F>cous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture in a thicke and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e vapour tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough agitation: either of heate, as in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<U+017F>eething. Or motion, as in the <U+017F>ea. Or both, as in running waters. In urine they are made as <hi>Montanus</hi> thinketh, of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or unnaturall heate rarefying and di<U+017F><U+017F>ipating, <U+017F>ome tough, vi<U+017F>cous, and fleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie matter in the veines re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the heate not finding ready i<U+017F><U+017F>ue, doth puffe up and extend it, making froth or bubbles. But <hi>Argenter</hi> mi<U+017F>liketh this opinion for that, in ba<U+017F>tard agues, quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and tertians, where both flegme and unnaturall heate abound, which might
<U+017F>tirre and puffe it up, and yet froth doth not alwayes accompany the<U+017F>e agues.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49277:52"/> Therefore hee thinketh that froth in the urine, is alwayes cau<U+017F>ed of motion, and gives <U+017F>ignification of rhewmes and de<U+017F>til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, de<U+017F>cending from the head into the inferiour parts, &amp;c. They appeare in the urine, being cau<U+017F>ed either of cau<U+017F>e exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, or internall.</p>
               <p>Externall cau<U+017F>e of fome, froth, and bubbles.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Externall cau<U+017F>e.</note> 1. Eating of pul<U+017F>e or fruit, <U+017F>urfetting,
<hi>Fernel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing with <U+017F>ome violence into the urinall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Shaking of the urinall, <hi>Aegid. 68. Salvian.</hi> 144.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Internall cau<U+017F>e.</note>Internall cau<U+017F>e of fome froth, or bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, wherein are con<U+017F>idered (as in other contents) colour, quantity, <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, time of their appearance, and their differences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colour of the fome, froth, and bubbles.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Diver<U+017F>e.</note> 1. Diver<U+017F>e. Signifieth crudity, <hi>Aegid.
68.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">White.</note> 2. White. Raw and flegmaticke mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Saffron.</note> 3. Saffron. Iaundice. But mixed with
<U+017F>ome whitene<U+017F><U+017F>e in the middle, di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the lungs.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49277:52"/>
4. Leade colour or blacki<U+017F>h,<note place="margin">Leadi<U+017F>h.</note> matter adu<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Blacke.</note> 5. Blacke. Extinction of naturall heate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quantity of the fome, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Much.</note> Much, many, or thicke together, long continuing, and <U+017F>carcely to be aboli<U+017F>hed with a rods end, wrapped about with flax<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and put into the urine, <hi>Aegid.</hi> 66. and <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth</p>
               <p>In whole men. Some tough and vi<U+017F>cous matter which naturall heate <U+017F>tirreth: wherefore good diet mu<U+017F>t be u<U+017F>ed, lea<U+017F>t more matter be increa<U+017F>ed, or naturall heate hindred.</p>
               <p>In <U+017F>icke men (if they appeare in the crowne or circle) abundance of raw tough matter mixed with vento<U+017F>itie and agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, which may <U+017F>ignifie colicke, head-ache, <U+017F>urfet. But if they appeare over the whole face of the urine, they <U+017F>ignifie weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the head, flux of <U+017F>eed, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e of nature, through ob<U+017F>tructions and raw humors. Al<U+017F>o if they appeare in the beginning of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, an ill <U+017F>igne, becau<U+017F>e
<U+017F>uch agitation, is of unnaturall heate, and accompanied with other ill <U+017F>ignes, as weaknes, old age, feeble, pul<U+017F>e, winter, &amp;c. mortall.</p>
               <p>But appearing in the urine after the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49277:53"/> beginning of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with other good
<U+017F>ignes, it is a good <U+017F>ignification of health, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch agitation is of naturall heate now prevailing again<U+017F>t the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. But with other ill <U+017F>ignes, as ill colour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,
&amp;c. it giveth ill <U+017F>ignification that
<U+017F>uch agitation is of unnaturall heate, and in weake per<U+017F>ons, Death, but in <U+017F>trong per<U+017F>ons, Long <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and great danger,
<hi>Week.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Little.</note> Little quantity of the <U+017F>pume, froth, bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>Little or few, and di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed, two or three together <U+017F>ignifie le<U+017F><U+017F>e head-ache and vento<U+017F>ity, &amp;c. except the colour be yellow, for <U+017F>o choler increa<U+017F>eth the griefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sub<U+017F>tance of the <U+017F>pume, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thicke.</note> Thicke, a better <U+017F>igne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thin.</note> Thin, a wor<U+017F>e <U+017F>igne e<U+017F>pecially in agues
<U+017F>ignifying great griefe, <hi>Bla<U+017F>. Holler.</hi> 162.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Time of appearance.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Time of appearance</note> Not appearing at the fir<U+017F>t, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards appearing, <U+017F>ignifie concoction or declination of an ague. As in thicke urine. See there.</p>
               <p>Differences of <U+017F>pume, froth and bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, be three.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49277:53"/>
1. Little bubbles (<hi>granula</hi>) like pinne-heads,
<note place="margin">Granula.</note> or little droppes of quicke-<U+017F>ilver, de<U+017F>cending downewards towards the
<U+017F>wimme under the crowne into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the urine, <U+017F>ignifie griefes of the head, as rhewme, which di<U+017F>tilling downe into the inferiour parts of the body, as to the no<U+017F>e, maketh the po<U+017F>e, to the eyes, and cau<U+017F>eth ophthalmie. To the eares, making a <U+017F>inging noy<U+017F>e, and deafene<U+017F><U+017F>e. To the pallat of the mouth, and maketh the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vula to fall downe. To the throat, and cau<U+017F>eth hoar<U+017F>ene<U+017F><U+017F>e. To the mouth, and cau<U+017F>eth exulcerations. To the jawes and mandible, tooth-ache. To the windepipe, the cough. To the lungs, <U+017F>hortne<U+017F><U+017F>e of breath: to the guts, the colike, iliake, whereof <U+017F>ometime followeth a laske or flixe. To the <U+017F>tomacke, crudity. To the huckle-bone, <U+017F>ciatica. To the joynts in the hands, knees, and feet, the gout. To the reines, the nephre<U+017F>ie. Al<U+017F>o the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages by which the rhewme di<U+017F>tilleth, are many, as the arteries, backbone, and veines: al<U+017F>o the meat-pipe, winde-pipe, and <U+017F>inewes. But the rhewme de<U+017F>cending from the head by any of the<U+017F>e three la<U+017F>t, doth not nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily cau<U+017F>e bubbles in the urine. <hi>We<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:49277:54"/>
2. Great bubbles (<hi>Ampullae</hi>) <U+017F>ignifie griefe in the reines (<hi>nephritis</hi>) for the reins being cold and farre di<U+017F>tant from the heart the fountaine of heate,<note place="margin">Ampullae.</note> and rhewmatike matter al<U+017F>o cold and heavy, and de<U+017F>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downeward, is al<U+017F>o drawne by the reines, and there for want of heate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth uncon<U+017F>umed, and <U+017F>o breedeth griefe in the reines, in urine thin, and white bubbles. Al<U+017F>o according to <hi>Rha<U+017F>is</hi> fluxe of blood at the no<U+017F>e. If they be round, pluri<U+017F>ie, Gout with rhewme and an ague.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Spume, foame.</note> 3. Spume, froth, <U+017F>ignifie griefe in the middle members of the body, as heart liver, <U+017F>pleene, &amp;c. ri<U+017F>ing of <U+017F>uch cau<U+017F>es as the colours of the urine <U+017F>hew, <hi>Fern.</hi> 453. Windine<U+017F><U+017F>e, collike. In yellow colour, the jaundice. In leadi<U+017F>h oyly and palew, the phthi<U+017F>icke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> ¶ But of fome, <U+017F>pume, aud bubbles, we can <U+017F>afely gather no generall precept, <U+017F>ave onely that they <U+017F>ignifie abundance of gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and raw humors, which being moved in the body, doe cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch
<U+017F>pume and bubbles, and <U+017F>o con<U+017F>equently length of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e in <U+017F>trong and lu<U+017F>ty per<U+017F>ons, and death in weake and feeble,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49277:54"/> e<U+017F>pecially the <U+017F>pume and bubbles long continuing in great quantity, <hi>Salvian.
152.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Drops of oyle or fat. Spider-webs.</note>Droppes of fat like <U+017F>pider-webbes, droppes of oyle <U+017F>wimming aloft, <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</p>
               <p n="1">1. Colliquation or con<U+017F>umption for the mo<U+017F>t part mortall of the whole body, with an ague, and then this fat is pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed <U+017F>lowly by little and little, at <U+017F>everall times, and in <U+017F>mal quantity, and well mixed or incorporated into the urine, but at the later end of the con<U+017F>umption when the patient is almo<U+017F>t
<U+017F>pent, this fat cea<U+017F>eth to i<U+017F><U+017F>ue with the urine, being already di<U+017F><U+017F>olved and voided, and the body decaying leane and dry, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Colliquation of the reines and blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der onely without an ague, the fat being pi<U+017F><U+017F>ed fa<U+017F>t, <U+017F>uddenly, in good quantity, at once, and not <U+017F>o perfectly mixed with the urine, and with paine and heate about the reines. Yet <hi>Cardan</hi> <U+017F>aith, that hee him<U+017F>elfe ob<U+017F>erved <U+017F>mall <U+017F>lender <U+017F>pider-webbes in his owne urine every day for
40. yeares together, and likewi<U+017F>e in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other urines without any hurt at all, and therefore he thinketh that the<U+017F>e <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-webbes which <U+017F>ignifie colliquation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49277:55"/> mu<U+017F>t be greater, <hi>Salvian.</hi> 164.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Inflamation of the liver.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Criticall evacuation in concoction and declination of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor offending, whereby <U+017F>ome fat member receiveth hurt, and <U+017F>o part of his fat is di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved,
<hi>Salvian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Oyle drunken, <hi>Fernel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the <U+017F>mell of Vrine.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">No <U+017F>mell.</note> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Mell of urine is either none at all. 2. or <U+017F>weet.
3. or <U+017F>tinking.</p>
            <p>No <U+017F>mell at all <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth extreame and mortall cold in <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, e<U+017F>pecially if
<U+017F>tinking<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> urines were made before, and no ea<U+017F>e of the patient <U+017F>ucceedeth, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.
60. Va<U+017F><U+017F>ae. 60. Argent. Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sweet <U+017F>mell of the urine is either of cau<U+017F>e externall, or internall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49277:55"/> Externall cau<U+017F>e, as</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Sweet <U+017F>mell.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 1. Perfuming of the urine after it, is made with muske, junipet, <U+017F>ylphium, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erpitium,
<U+017F>tyrax, ro<U+017F>en of larch tree, or other perfume, <hi>Fernel. Bertin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Eating of turpentine, &amp;c. becau<U+017F>e it is not ea<U+017F>ily changed in the body by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on of his vi<U+017F>co<U+017F>ity, nor draweth any <U+017F>tore of matter with it, <hi>Argent. 60. Salvian.</hi> 60.
&amp;c. <hi>Montanus</hi> thought, that by eating of
<U+017F>weet <U+017F>melling things, the urine <U+017F>hould
<U+017F>tincke, and contrariwi<U+017F>e by eating of
<U+017F>tinking things, the urine <U+017F>hould have a
<U+017F>weet <U+017F>mell, whom <hi>Argenterin</hi> confuteth. For garlike <U+017F>tinketh, and being eaten, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the urine al<U+017F>o <U+017F>tinke, and contrary turpentine, hath of him<U+017F>elfe a good <U+017F>mell, which being taken into the body, giveth the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>mell to the urine.</p>
            <p>Internall cau<U+017F>e, as</p>
            <p>Dominion of good blood not putrefied.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Ill or <U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <U+017F>mell.</note> 3. Ill, or <U+017F>tinking <U+017F>mell, is likewi<U+017F>e of cau<U+017F>e externall, or internall.</p>
            <p>Externall cau<U+017F>e, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. Perfuming it with <U+017F>tinking perfumes, as a<U+017F><U+017F>afetida, galbanum, <U+017F>agapenum,
<U+017F>moke of burnt feathers, brim<U+017F>tone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Eating of Carduus benedictus (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e it doth moove and <U+017F>tirre up the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49277:56"/> humors, and converteth them to the pa<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of urine:) of rue, onyons, anni<U+017F>e-<U+017F>eed, garlike, rotten chee<U+017F>e, <U+017F>talkes of <U+017F>perage, fenell, fengreeke, &amp;c. <hi>Argent. Salvian. 98. Aegid. 11. Fernel. vide P. Apon. in problem. Ari<U+017F>t.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Internall cau<U+017F>e.</head>
               <p>Mens urines according to the diver<U+017F>e con<U+017F>titutions of the bodies from whence they come, are in <U+017F>everall degrees of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or wor<U+017F>e <U+017F>mell: for tho<U+017F>e who have abundance of pure blood and other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors according to their naturall di<U+017F>po<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, free from putrefaction, and expell their excrements both univer<U+017F>all and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, in due time and quantity, and have a moderate u<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>ixe things not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, doe make urine (as all other excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) le<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>tinking, yet <U+017F>omewhat or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, becau<U+017F>e urine, as all other excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, come of impure matter, and in mens bodies, which be moi<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to putrefaction. Yet not in all bodies
<U+017F>tinking ill, <U+017F>eeing it is concoct, <hi>Argent.</hi> And though it is too ba<U+017F>e for the Phy<U+017F>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, yea <U+017F>ometimes dangerous to put his no<U+017F>e to the urine, to di<U+017F>cerne the <U+017F>tinch thereof: yet the knowledge hereof hath good u<U+017F>e among<U+017F>t other differences of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49277:56"/> yea, in demon<U+017F>trating putrefaction, ulcers, and impo<U+017F>tumes in mans body, is to be preferred before all other, <hi>Argent.</hi> But to come to the matter againe. Stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king urines are evermore an argument of putrefaction, 1. either of the humours,
2. or <U+017F>olid and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiall parts of mans body. Which you may di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h thus, for if the putrefaction be in the humors onely, the <U+017F>tinke began lately, and the urine is thicke or troubled, and chanceth by one of the<U+017F>e three waies: either for that the humors</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</note> 1. Breed crudity, through want of heat, as in tho<U+017F>e which are full of ill humors, as flegme and melancholy, becau<U+017F>e they make the urine thicker, and being cold, not provoking the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to expul<U+017F>ion, they <U+017F>tay longer in the body, and breed putrefaction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Stay too long in the body, as in the
<U+017F>trangury, dy<U+017F>ury, <U+017F>tone, when the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is full of filth, and paine in pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing,
<U+017F>o in exulcerations or impo<U+017F>tumes of the reines, or bladder and gonorrhoea, the urine white and thicke, and the <U+017F>ediment full of matter, <hi>Fernel. Salvian.</hi> 99. <U+017F>o in creticall evacuations of impo<U+017F>tumes, and inflamations, with ea<U+017F>e of the patient,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49277:57"/> and <U+017F>ignes of concoction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are infected with the plague, in a confu<U+017F>ed and troubled, red urine, with little motes much di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed. With <hi>morbus gallicus,</hi> with <U+017F>andy and gravelly red con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <U+017F>olid parts.</note> But if the putrefaction be in the <U+017F>olid and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiall parts of mans body, as the liver, <U+017F>pleene, veines, &amp;c. it is with paine, and in urine rather thin then thicke; and the <U+017F>tinch of long continuance, for which cau<U+017F>es there is great danger: for thin urine <U+017F>eldome <U+017F>tinketh, for want of putrefied humours and excrements. And <U+017F>tinch long continuing, <U+017F>heweth that the putrefaction is entred into the habit of the body, <hi>Cappivac. 112. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶Some <U+017F>ay that the urine <U+017F>tinketh in
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>harp agues,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> denieth, <U+017F>ave only in the plague.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49277:57"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the manner of pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anner of pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, is either hard and unea<U+017F>ie: or el<U+017F>e in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntary.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Painefull pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing.</note> Painfull, hard, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>ie pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing is either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e that the</p>
            <p n="1">1. Vrine is too <U+017F>harp (as in the <U+017F>trangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) by mixture of <U+017F>ome <U+017F>harp humours, as
<U+017F>alt, flegme, choler, purulent matter: or by ill diet, or <U+017F>ome hot di<U+017F>temperature in the veins, as in <U+017F>harp and continuall agues, or
<U+017F>ome criticall evacuations. Or when the glandulous parts about the bladder are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by immoderate venery, di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, or medicine, which <U+017F>hould mitigate the
<U+017F>harpne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the urine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, reines, bladder, yard, either too weake, or troubled with exulcerations, by which urine pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing cau<U+017F>eth paine and <U+017F>marting. 2. Al<U+017F>o with impo<U+017F>tumes, <U+017F>wellings, gatherings, in which the urine is fir<U+017F>t white, then filthy, and la<U+017F>tly rotten. 3. With inflammations, whereof followeth vomiting of choler, continuall ague, and paine in the reines,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49277:58"/>
               <hi>Bertin.</hi> 4. With ob<U+017F>truction of the <U+017F>tone and gravell (as you may read, <hi>pag. 64.</hi>) Of tough and clammy humors, and vento<U+017F>itie di<U+017F>tending the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els. 5. With di<U+017F>tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of heate and drine<U+017F><U+017F>e. 6. With convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion of (<hi><U+017F>phincter</hi>) the mu<U+017F>cle <U+017F>hutting the necke of the bladder, or of the <U+017F>inewes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Blood, or the wombe is inflamed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Guts, or the wombe di<U+017F>tended with tumors or vento<U+017F>itie, as in the colicke, whereby the reins and emulgent veins are pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed and <U+017F>traitned.</p>
            <p>In voluntary pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, when one maketh urine unwittingly, or again<U+017F>t his wil, which happeneth either for that the</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Involunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing.</note> 1. Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, bladder, reines,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> have their retentive faculty hurt, weakned, or decaied, as in the Apoplexy, falling <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, paul<U+017F>ey. Or when the mu<U+017F>cle (<hi><U+017F>phincter</hi>) <U+017F>hutting the necke of the bladder; Or <U+017F>inewes comming from the backe, <U+017F>erving thereto are hurt, by fall, beating, wound, &amp;c. Or made feeble and weake by cold di<U+017F>temperature, or by too much moi<U+017F>ture in children, or drine<U+017F><U+017F>e in old men, whereby the afore<U+017F>aid mu<U+017F>cle and <U+017F>inewes cannot detaine their urine, but many times they bepi<U+017F><U+017F>e their bed.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49277:58"/> So in great and <U+017F>udden feare, when the blood, heate, and <U+017F>pirits, fly to the heart, and inward parts, whereby the outward parts, and tho<U+017F>e which be far di<U+017F>tant from the heart, are de<U+017F>titute of blood, heate, and
<U+017F>pirits, <U+017F>o men <U+017F>uddenly terrified and a<U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, not only void urine, but other excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments again<U+017F>t their will. Likewi<U+017F>e in the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing ill, the urine white and much, and the patient thir<U+017F>ty, and the body decaying. See before, <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Principall Agent the braine not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the animall faculty, nor communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it the <U+017F>inewes and mu<U+017F>cles of the ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els of urine, whereupon they cea<U+017F>e from their function, and let the urine pa<U+017F><U+017F>e away by drops, as they receive it, as in mad men, raving, doting, in <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, but if there be other <U+017F>ignes of concoction, it <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth criticall fluxe of blood at the no<U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e the matter being drawn up to the braine, and yet <U+017F>ignes of recovery, mu<U+017F>t be voided at the no<U+017F>e, <hi>Salv.</hi> 113.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:49277:59"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Rine is <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed in whole men being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in <U+017F>ome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate bu<U+017F>ines, as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the barre, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, reading, &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o
<U+017F>leeping, whereby they cannot be at lei<U+017F>ure, or el<U+017F>e forget, and <U+017F>o for a <U+017F>pace their urine is wholly
<U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, but in proce<U+017F><U+017F>e of time mu<U+017F>t needs have i<U+017F><U+017F>ue, neither is it in mans free choyce alwaies to <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>e his urine, though for a time he may. For it is not
<U+017F>imply a voluntary action, as <U+017F>peaking and walking is, &amp;c. but mixt partly voluntary, partly naturall, as cough, nee<U+017F>ing, vomit, belching, <U+017F>ighing, re<U+017F>piration, &amp;c. whereto we refer, evacuation by <U+017F>tool, and urine, &amp;c. but <U+017F>eeing this <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine doth neither give <U+017F>ignification of <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e nor health, we leave further to <U+017F>peake of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of urine in <U+017F>icke men.</note> Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine in <U+017F>icke men is either becau<U+017F>e the,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine are weake and not able either to draw the matter of urine, or to expell it being made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Watery humor the materiall cau<U+017F>e
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49277:59"/> of urine is wanting, as in want of drinke or moi<U+017F>t meats. 2. Or el<U+017F>e is converted ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, as in the drop<U+017F>ie, <hi>Argenter.</hi> laskes, &amp;c. But in the<U+017F>e ca<U+017F>es the urine is rather little then none at all. See little quantity of urine before, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. 3. Or is ob<U+017F>tructed and <U+017F>topped that it cannot haue i<U+017F><U+017F>ue either by <U+017F>ome tumor or infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation accompanied with <U+017F>welling, paine, an ague, &amp;c. or of <U+017F>chirrous <U+017F>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without paine or ague: or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tume with paine or an ague, or la<U+017F>tly,
<U+017F>ome fle<U+017F>hly <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, de<U+017F>cending from
<U+017F>ome ulcer, with <U+017F>ome blood and <U+017F>mall fragments of fle<U+017F>h voiding with the urine, and a <U+017F>yringe put up at the yard into the necke of the bladder, and removing the fle<U+017F>hy fragments away, the urine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth: or with the <U+017F>tone, and then gravell was voided before: or by clods of blood, remaining after <U+017F>ome i<U+017F><U+017F>ue of blood, or by <U+017F>ome purulent matter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from an ulcer, or la<U+017F>tly by <U+017F>ome thicke and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, or filth and corruption de<U+017F>cending from the veines, liver, or other <U+017F>uperiour members, which
<U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urines in agues e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally continuall, <U+017F>ignifieth death more certainly, then any other <U+017F>igne in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49277:60"/> urine. In this ca<U+017F>e <hi>Argenterius</hi> <U+017F>carcely ever knew any e<U+017F>cape death; unle<U+017F><U+017F>e the fault be in the reines or bladder, <hi>Arg.</hi> 89.
4. Or when the bladder is <U+017F>o di<U+017F>tended, by too great quantity of urine too long kept, that it cannot unburden it <U+017F>elfe thereof,
<hi>Wecker in I<U+017F>churia,</hi> and therefore it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to pi<U+017F><U+017F>e, as often as need requireth, and not to keep it too long, for thereof ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eth
<U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine (that we <U+017F>peake of) and <U+017F>omtime the <U+017F>tone, or difficulty in pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, and <U+017F>ometime the drop<U+017F>ie; neither on the other <U+017F>ide do I commend their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<U+017F>e, who like dogs are <U+017F>till pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides many other inconveniences, they bring their ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine to <U+017F>uch an ill cu<U+017F>tome, that in old age (when the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty through want of heate decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) they can <U+017F>carcely hold their urine, but it will i<U+017F><U+017F>ue from them again<U+017F>t their will. But I wi<U+017F>h all men to void their excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both by <U+017F>toole (for being too long kept in the body, they annoy the head by their <U+017F>tinking fume a<U+017F>cending, breed ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<U+017F>ities, wringing in the guts, cholike,
&amp;c.) and by urine, that they may follow their ordinary cour<U+017F>e of life, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nature hath appointed mu<U+017F>cles to the neck of the bladder, and <U+017F>eat, that men may
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49277:60"/> at their plea<U+017F>ure detaine their excrements for <U+017F>ome <U+017F>pace. <hi>Placotomus de tuenda vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometime the greater guts are <U+017F>o ob<U+017F>tructed through tough and vi<U+017F>cous flegme, that the meat and drink concocted in the <U+017F>tomacke, cannot come to the liver to receive further concoction and <U+017F>eparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of urine, <hi>Holl. lib. 1. cap. 47. de morbis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Sometime the backebone is brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed, broken, or hath <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>location in the joynts: that thereby the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine cannot performe their duty, <hi>Wec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of what parts of the body urine gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<U+017F>ignification.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Rine giveth <U+017F>ignification of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of <U+017F>uch parts of the body,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whence it receiveth matter wherof it is made colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e, per<U+017F>pecuity, <U+017F>mell, as the
<U+017F>tomacke, guts, me<U+017F>araicall veines, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49277:61"/> all other parts of the body, for the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cau<U+017F>e of urine is drinke, or other liquor, which in the <U+017F>tomacke is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately mixed and incorporated toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the meat, and made one <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance and white juice called of the phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians
<hi>Chylas,</hi> which de<U+017F>cending into the winding capacity of the guts is <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated partly into excrement, and partly nouri<U+017F>hment. For the purer part thereof is <U+017F>ucked of the me<U+017F>araicall veines, and conveyed thence to <hi>vena porta,</hi> and at length to the liver, where being conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into blood, and the excrementitions parts thereof, <U+017F>eque<U+017F>tred and <U+017F>ent to their proper receptacles, as choler to the gall, melancholy to the <U+017F>pleene, and the watry thin part to the reines, but not all, for
<U+017F>ome part thereof together with the blood (which it maketh thinner for more ea<U+017F>ie conveyance) is di<U+017F>tributed into every member of the body. From whence <U+017F>o much as is not <U+017F>pent in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or evaporated out by <U+017F>weat, or in<U+017F>en<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble per<U+017F>piration, returneth backe againe the
<U+017F>ame way to the liver, whence it is drawn of the emulgent veines, and de<U+017F>cendeth to the reines and bladder. Therefore urine is not onely made of that watery
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49277:61"/>
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance which is drawne from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but al<U+017F>o from the greater and le<U+017F><U+017F>e veines, and from the whole body. As hee may ea<U+017F>ily and plainly perceive by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, who will for three or foure dayes together, either receive no drinke at all, or but little. The urine therefore, that is neither too thin by much quaffing, nor otherwi<U+017F>e polluted by mixture of other impurities, doth manife<U+017F>tly <U+017F>hew the <U+017F>tate and con<U+017F>titution of the humors which are in the liver and greater veines. And al<U+017F>o, though not <U+017F>o manife<U+017F>tly, in the <U+017F>maller veines and all other parts of the body,
<hi>Fernel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Where it is made, as the liver, and the hollow veine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By which it pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth, as the emulgent veines, reines, and water conduits.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wherein it <U+017F>tayeth, as the bladder with his mu<U+017F>cles and <U+017F>inewes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By which it is expelled, as the yard.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Which doe deprive it of any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, per<U+017F>pecuity, darkene<U+017F><U+017F>e, quantity, contents or <U+017F>mell, as when it is not made, or being made is not attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or not expelled, or ob<U+017F>tructed and <U+017F>topped in the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that it cannot have pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to be voided, as
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49277:62"/> by rumors, gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, <U+017F>tone, gravell, inflammations, ulcers, impo<U+017F>tumes, fle<U+017F>h growing, winde, or through weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e, di<U+017F>temperature, fractures, ruptures, di<U+017F>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, wounds of the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, either primary in them<U+017F>elves, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent of others, &amp;c. Or being made, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted another way, as to the head in phren<U+017F>ies, to the <U+017F>tomacke in vomitings, to the belly in drop<U+017F>ies, to the guts in lasks, to the mother in fluxe of tearmes, to the cods in ruptures, to the joynts in <U+017F>ciatica, gout, to the parts weak, grieved, inflamed, apo<U+017F>tomated, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Which doe exonerate them<U+017F>elves by urine, as the head in rhewmes, phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ies,
&amp;c. The throat in the <U+017F>quin<U+017F>ie, the lungs in inflammations, the <U+017F>olid parts in a con<U+017F>umption, the <U+017F>pleene in melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, the veines or arteries broken, in pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing of blood, the <U+017F>perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, in fluxe of <U+017F>eed, the mother in tearmes <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed and voided by urine the hemorrhoidall veins in the emeraudes, the joynts in the <U+017F>ciatica, or gout, and diver<U+017F>e other parts of the body in evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, criticall, <U+017F>ymptomaticall, or artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</p>
            <p>Of all the<U+017F>e you may finde <U+017F>everall
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49277:62"/> examples in this treati<U+017F>e precedent.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of crude, concoct, and dangerous urines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecau<U+017F>e mention is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made heretofore, of crude, concoct, and dangerous urines, as al<U+017F>o that they be very needfull to be known perfectly, &amp; alwayes had in memory; <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they comprehend in few words, the
<U+017F>um of all that hath heretofore bin <U+017F>poken. I thought good in the end to adde the de<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Concoct urine.</note>Concoct u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,
<U+017F>uch as men onely make who are in <U+017F>ome latitude of health, is in
<list>
                  <item>colour
<list>
                        <item>palew,</item>
                        <item>light <U+017F>affron.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, meane.</item>
                  <item>contents
<list>
                        <item>equall,</item>
                        <item>white,</item>
                        <item>light.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>mell, not <U+017F>tinking.</item>
                  <item>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing in due time without
<list>
                        <item>paine,</item>
                        <item>heate,</item>
                        <item>cold.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:49277:63"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Crude urine.</note> Crude u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines onely. Such as men
make incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <U+017F>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering after <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e, is in
<list>
                  <item>colour
<list>
                        <item>white,</item>
                        <item>pale,</item>
                        <item><U+017F>affron,</item>
                        <item>claret,</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance
<list>
                        <item>thicker,</item>
                        <item>thinner.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>contents
<list>
                        <item>whiti<U+017F>h,</item>
                        <item>pale,</item>
                        <item><U+017F>omewhat une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>mell, not much <U+017F>tinking.</item>
                  <item>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing not in due time.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Vrines<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> meane betwixt crude and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct, are of two <U+017F>orts. 1. For either they encline more to concoct. Such as have a good colour, but thin <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance. Al<U+017F>o a white and light <U+017F>ediment, but not equall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or el<U+017F>e they encline more to crude. Such as have reddi<U+017F>h colour, like to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherein raw fle<U+017F>h hath been wa<U+017F>hed, which are made of blood not perfectly concoct.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:49277:63"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Vrin crude and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note>Vrine, Crude and dangerous,
<U+017F>uch as men make who are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vou<U+017F>ly
<U+017F>icke and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger not to recover, is in
<list>
                  <item>colour
<list>
                        <item>greene,</item>
                        <item>a<U+017F>h colour,</item>
                        <item>blacke.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance
<list>
                        <item>very thin,</item>
                        <item>very thicke,</item>
                        <item>oyly.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>contents
<list>
                        <item>greene,</item>
                        <item>a<U+017F>h colour,</item>
                        <item>oyly,</item>
                        <item>blacke,</item>
                        <item>very unequall,</item>
                        <item>deformed.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item><U+017F>mell very <U+017F>tinging.</item>
                  <item>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing altogether out of due time. Or not at all,
<hi>B. Holler. 270. Cappiva<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.
195.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of methodicall practi<U+017F>e in iudgement of Vrines.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions fit for practi<U+017F>e.</note> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore you give judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the urine; it is needfull that you me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate with your <U+017F>elfe on the<U+017F>e precepts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Remember the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall con<U+017F>iderations in the fir<U+017F>t chapter,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49277:64"/> both concerning the urinall and the urine. As al<U+017F>o which be the be<U+017F>t urines <U+017F>imply, and in re<U+017F>pect of age, <U+017F>exe, complexion, time of the yeare, kinde of life, &amp;c. which you may have <U+017F>o perfectly in memory, that you can pre<U+017F>ently tell how farre that urine which is brought unto you, differeth from a good urine, in colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, contents,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the urine be altered by <U+017F>ome externall cau<U+017F>e mentioned in the fir<U+017F>t chapter and throughout the booke; or el<U+017F>e through default of the reines and bladder by which the urine pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth. For the<U+017F>e two impediments either <U+017F>everall or concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hinder the judgement of the inner parts, <hi>Fernel.</hi> 443.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Con<U+017F>ider what di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are incident to the countrey where the patient dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, or what common di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is their
<U+017F>tirrings: as for example, if the patient be an old man, and in winter, rainy weather, and in a moi<U+017F>t and fenni<U+017F>h countrey, it can hardly be otherwi<U+017F>e, but that he is troubled with a cough, rhewme, po<U+017F>e, and lacke of dige<U+017F>tion, and the rather if he be given to
<U+017F>urfetting, much drinking, and bee of a flegmatike complexion, and heretofore troubled with rhewmatike di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. But
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49277:64"/> contrariwi<U+017F>e, if hee be a young man, and cholerike, in the middle of <U+017F>ummer, hote weather, hote climate, after hote diet and immoderate exerci<U+017F>e, it is very likely, that he is troubled with a burning ague, tertian, flixe, or plure<U+017F>ie, to which of the<U+017F>e he is mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ubject, or which at that time is mo<U+017F>t
<U+017F>tirring in that countrey. After this <U+017F>ort you may judge of other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es without helpe of the urine.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Three cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es.</note> 4. If the urine be faulty, and yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through externall cau<U+017F>e, nor of the reines, then it mu<U+017F>t needs <U+017F>hew <U+017F>ome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temperature of the inward parts, heart, liver, <U+017F>pleene, lungs, veines, or other part of the body. Which di<U+017F>temperature is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<U+017F>imple, without mixture of humors, which colour of the urine in thin <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance will <U+017F>hew, or with mixture of humors in a thicke and troubled <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, or el<U+017F>e putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, in a confu<U+017F>ed urine. Which three be the internall cau<U+017F>es almo<U+017F>t of all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, whereby you have already attained no
<U+017F>mall knowledge, what to doe, or what evacuation is convenient for the cure of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, although you cannot as yet, particularly under<U+017F>tand the <U+017F>ame. <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Of all differences of urines colour
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49277:65"/> is mo<U+017F>t mutable and uncertaine of <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
<note place="margin">Which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of urine is to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of <U+017F>ignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wherein.</note> as being <U+017F>ubject to many alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of light cau<U+017F>e. As by much drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, thin drinke, as water, white wine, or by eating of hote <U+017F>pices, <U+017F>ena, ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia,
&amp;c. yea in one day every urine that a man maketh is unlike an other in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<U+017F>o that here e<U+017F>pecially the infamy that urine is a lying <U+017F>trumpet, hath <U+017F>ome appearance of truth. Contrariwi<U+017F>e the contents of urine are of mo<U+017F>t certaine and true <U+017F>ignification of all other, and lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>ubject to alteration, for that they are either fragments of the parts of the body, or contained in the parts. Of the<U+017F>e
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> e<U+017F>pecially make mention, not greatly regarding the re<U+017F>t. The other differences of urine, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, per<U+017F>pecuity, darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e, quantity, <U+017F>mell,
&amp;c. are of meane <U+017F>ignification betwixt colour and contents. And yet every dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference hath <U+017F>peciall <U+017F>ignification above the re<U+017F>t in <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es:<note place="margin">Smell.</note> for <U+017F>tinking
<U+017F>mell of urines giveth more perfit <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of putrefaction, ulcers, or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tumes, then either colour, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, or contents. Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine, in agues e<U+017F>pecially continuall,<note place="margin">Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> giveth more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<U+017F>ignification of death, then thin
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49277:65"/>
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, ill colour, or want of contents: for the<U+017F>e <U+017F>hew one crudity, which in time is curable: but the other happeneth through great ob<U+017F>tructions of the reines, liver, or other <U+017F>uperiour member, which at that time are incurable.<note place="margin">Colours.</note> Colours of urine colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in due time, from an orderly patient, giveth better <U+017F>ignification of the humor loffending in the body, then any other. La<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y,
<note place="margin">Contents.</note> contents i<U+017F><U+017F>uing with the urine, doe e<U+017F>pecially <U+017F>ignifie <U+017F>trength of nature, which in time will prevaile again<U+017F>t the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. For when the dige<U+017F>tive faculty is weake, the matter whereof contents ari<U+017F>e, cannot be overcome and prepared to be voided. So that every difference of urine hath
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>peciall <U+017F>ignification above the re<U+017F>t,
<hi>Arg.</hi> 89.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Al<U+017F>o you mu<U+017F>t often <U+017F>ee the patients urine on divers daies and divers times of his <U+017F>icknes, and diligently marke the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>everance or alteration of the urine from time to time, and whether it change from wor<U+017F>e to better or otherwi<U+017F>e.<note place="margin">How the urine alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es.</note> For as the patient recovereth, nature proceedeth orderly and by degrees from unperfect to perfect, from <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e to health, and <U+017F>o by little and little changeth the urine: fir<U+017F>t, the colour, which is ea<U+017F>ie<U+017F>t: <U+017F>econdly,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49277:66"/> it waxeth cleerer; thirdly, the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance waxeth meane betwixt thin and thicke; fourthly, when concoction is <U+017F>tronger, contents appeare. And therefore if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents appeare fir<U+017F>t before colour, cleerne<U+017F><U+017F>e or <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, there is the le<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>ecurity of health: becau<U+017F>e this is not the orderly cour<U+017F>e of nature, but <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ymptomaticall fit of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which will <U+017F>oone vani<U+017F>h away and decay. And therefore to good purpo<U+017F>e mu<U+017F>t you alwaies remember this theorem commonly received of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>itians, that nature ordinarily fir<U+017F>t confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the colour, then the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and la<U+017F>tly the contents, <hi>Mont.</hi> 52.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the colour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth.</note> This is the orderly cour<U+017F>e and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of nature in re<U+017F>pect of the colour. In the beginning of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, when all the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are raw, the urine is white. In the increa<U+017F>e and <U+017F>tate of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, higher and deeper colours. In the declining, more remi<U+017F><U+017F>e againe, untill at length it returneth to his meane colour againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance altereth.</note> In re<U+017F>pect of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it is thin, for nature hath yet made no <U+017F>eparation. In the increa<U+017F>e and <U+017F>tate it waxeth more thicke and troubled, through naturall heate now beginning to worke
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>eparation and expul<U+017F>ion of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49277:66"/> in declining it waxeth cleerer and thinner againe, when naturall heate doth attenuate, rare<U+017F>ie; and de<U+017F>ipate the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, and <U+017F>o the urine waxeth le<U+017F><U+017F>e troubled. To conclude, for
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of urine marke the<U+017F>e foure diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Fir<U+017F>t thin, and <U+017F>o continuing, is wor<U+017F>t of all, <U+017F>ignifying extreame cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Fir<U+017F>t thin, and afterwards waxeth thicker, and more troubled, better then the former both for heate and <U+017F>trength of nature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Fir<U+017F>t troubled and thicke, and <U+017F>o continuing, better then the two former, for better heate, and more lively <U+017F>trength of nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fir<U+017F>t thicke and troubled, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards clearing and waxing thinner, the thicker part <U+017F>etling downe to the <U+017F>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be<U+017F>t of all in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, as now almo<U+017F>t returning to a meane <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, <U+017F>uch as is in whole mens urines.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the contents alter.</note> In re<U+017F>pect of contents not altogether unnaturall. In beginning of humorall di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es through crudity there appeare no contents at all<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> in increa<U+017F>e and <U+017F>tate, the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e continuing <U+017F>trong, and naturall
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49277:67"/> heate weake, <U+017F>ome though few in decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, when nature waxeth <U+017F>tronger pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing again<U+017F>t the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, moe contents appeare, and fir<U+017F>t in the cloud or upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t region, then in the middle region or
<U+017F>wimme, and la<U+017F>tly in the <U+017F>ediment.</p>
            <p>¶ And this is the ordinary alteration of urine in all humorall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es wherein is good hope of recovery (except it be acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally hindred by ob<U+017F>truction or conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion another way, and which have di<U+017F>tincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time of beginning, increa<U+017F>e, <U+017F>tate and declination. For <U+017F>harp di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es through their vehement and furious a<U+017F><U+017F>aults, do not admit <U+017F>uch <U+017F>peciall di<U+017F>tinction.</p>
            <p n="8">8. La<U+017F>tly, it is good for him that now beginneth to practi<U+017F>e, and hath not as yet attained to <U+017F>ome good mea<U+017F>ure of skill, to exerci<U+017F>e him<U+017F>elfe in the<U+017F>e three, as princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall guides of all his judgements, &amp;c. The be<U+017F>t urine, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. Crude, concoct, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous urines, <hi>pag.</hi> 105. and e<U+017F>pecially mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall urins which have <U+017F>ignification of death, wherein the credit of the Phy<U+017F>itian chiefly con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth. For which purpo<U+017F>e in the alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beticall index under death I have collected all mortall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, whereof urine giveth
<U+017F>ignification in this treati<U+017F>e. But yet it is not the <U+017F>afe<U+017F>t way re<U+017F>olutely to progno<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49277:67"/> death by them, e<U+017F>pecially in a young and lu<U+017F>ty man, except other ill <U+017F>ignes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, as want of <U+017F>trength, pul<U+017F>e, feeble, and inordinate ra<gap reason="illegible: over-inked" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> breathing with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, lacke of re<U+017F>t, hollow eyes, <U+017F>harp no<U+017F>e, in voluntary weeping, gathering of <U+017F>traws and flocks, want of <U+017F>leep and appetite, cold
<U+017F>weat, trembling of the nether lip, excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <U+017F>toole, blacke, greene, or <U+017F>tinking,
&amp;c. But contrariwi<U+017F>e<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> if the patient draw his breath with ea<U+017F>e, have a good pul<U+017F>e, be
<U+017F>trong, lye in bed decently, have a cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance, his <U+017F>leep and appetite not much decayed, and his excrements not altogether unnaturall, doe confirme good hope of recovery. And in like <U+017F>ort in all
<U+017F>ignifications of urine be not too confident, but adde other pathog<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>monicall <U+017F>igns for better confirmation and more certaine <U+017F>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the kinde, nature, and quality of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. <hi>Et qu<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non pro<U+017F>unt <U+017F>ingula, multa i<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>va<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:49277:68"/>
            <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the qualities, commodities, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines of urine: and of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching urine, and the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto we have compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ly handled the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, cau<U+017F>es, and judgements of urine. But that the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>e may be more ab<U+017F>olute, we will adde <U+017F>omething more of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and benefit of urine which it hath either inwardly received, or outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to mans body.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The quality of Vrine.</head>
               <p>All urine (as <hi>Galen</hi> <U+017F>aith, <hi>lib. 10. de <U+017F>impl. medie. facult. de urina</hi>) is hot and <U+017F>harp (as
<hi>Aegineta</hi> thinketh) but yet differing in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree according to them that make it. For the hotter they are that make it, in complexion, age, time of the yere, and diet, the hotter it is al<U+017F>o; yet mans urine (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we <U+017F>peake) is the weake<U+017F>t of all other, except tame barrow-hogs, which in many points agree with man, yet it is al<U+017F>o of a
<U+017F>trong clen<U+017F>ing or ab<U+017F>ter<U+017F>ive vertue, as any thing el<U+017F>e, which <hi>Galen</hi> proveth by the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49277:68"/> example of fullers, who u<U+017F>e it to skoure and clen<U+017F>e their cloath.</p>
               <p>The commodity and medicines of urine being taken inwardly.</p>
               <p>A mans owne urine drunken is good again<U+017F>t the biting of vipers, and poy<U+017F>on, and again<U+017F>t the drop<U+017F>ie lately begun. <hi>Dio<U+017F>c. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>A childes urine under the age of 14 yeares being drunken, helpeth tho<U+017F>e that are troubled with <U+017F>traitne<U+017F><U+017F>e of breath
(<hi>orthoponea</hi>) which though <hi>Galen</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting derideth as in<U+017F>ufficient and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome, yet <hi>Avicen. lib. 2. can. cap. proprio.</hi> doth greatly commend, for that by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in many di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed per<U+017F>ons he found it true.</p>
               <p>A mans urine is good for diver<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es of the wombe and bowels, e<U+017F>pecially for the collicke: becau<U+017F>e that partly with provoking of vomit, and partly by occa<U+017F>ion of <U+017F>ieges, it expelleth <U+017F>trongly all noy<U+017F>ome humors, and for the <U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>e doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practitioners keep it <U+017F>till in daily u<U+017F>e.
<hi>Recordè Marcello.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vldericke Hutten</hi> al<U+017F>o witne<U+017F><U+017F>eth, that he did drive away the ague above eight times with the only drinking of his owne urine, at the beginning of his <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>e,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49277:69"/> which practi<U+017F>e many <U+017F>till doe u<U+017F>e, and it proveth well.</p>
               <p>Likewi<U+017F>e <hi>Galen, Paul Aegin<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta</hi> and
<hi>Mar<U+017F>ilius Ficinus</hi> write that diver<U+017F>e drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king urine did think them<U+017F>elves pre<U+017F>erved and cured from the pe<U+017F>tilence.</p>
               <p>Vrine as <hi>Cardan</hi> <U+017F>aith, through his heate is of a thin and piercing <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance,
<U+017F>o that it is lighter then <U+017F>ome water, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding his <U+017F>altne<U+017F><U+017F>e, for which cau<U+017F>e it is good again<U+017F>t the colicke and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<U+017F>itie in the guts farre above <U+017F>alt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for through his <U+017F>ubtle and piercing
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance it findeth pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to the inward parts, and through his <U+017F>altnes it <U+017F>cattereth, breaketh, and di<U+017F>per<U+017F>eth the vento<U+017F>itie, and
<U+017F>trengtheneth the inward parts. But to this purpo<U+017F>e a childes urine under four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen yeares old, and lately made is be<U+017F>t, for that is mo<U+017F>t piercing and hot. <hi>Cardan de
<U+017F>ubtilitate, lib.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Medicines of urine outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
               <p>Vrine is good again<U+017F>t the itch, and clen<U+017F>eth the lepro<U+017F>ie, mixt with <U+017F>alt-peter:
<U+017F>tale pi<U+017F><U+017F>e clen<U+017F>eth running ulcers of the head, <U+017F>curfe, mangine<U+017F><U+017F>e, and hot breakings out, it <U+017F>tayeth eating ulcers e<U+017F>pecially in the privy members, and being put into
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49277:69"/> the eares, it clen<U+017F>eth the rotten and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent matter, and being <U+017F>odden in the rinde of a Pomegrante killeth the wormes thereof, <U+017F>odden in a bra<U+017F>en ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ell with honey, doth clen<U+017F>e the <U+017F>carres of the eyes, and cleereth the dimne<U+017F><U+017F>e there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the dregs of urine is good for Saint
<hi>Anthonies</hi> evill, if it be anointed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<U+017F>o that (as as <hi>Galen</hi> doth wi<U+017F>ely adde) the <U+017F>ore being cooled fir<U+017F>t with <U+017F>ome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, and be not burning. If it bee heated with oyle of privet, and layd to the wombe of a woman, it will a<U+017F><U+017F>wage the griefe of the mother, and cureth the ri<U+017F>ing of the <U+017F>ame, it clen<U+017F>eth the eye-lids, and <U+017F>carres of the <U+017F>ame, <hi>Dio<U+017F>cor. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> almo<U+017F>t to the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e
<U+017F>aith thus of urine: mens urine is of a <U+017F>trong clen<U+017F>ing vertue as any thing els, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with doe fullers u<U+017F>e to <U+017F>coure and clen<U+017F>e their cloath, which ab<U+017F>ter<U+017F>ive faculty Phy<U+017F>itians perceiving, did u<U+017F>e it to <U+017F>oke, and wa<U+017F>h mangine<U+017F><U+017F>e and <U+017F>cabbedne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and running <U+017F>ores that are full of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and filth, and e<U+017F>pecially if they have in them putrefied matter, &amp; for <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ores on the privy members it is good, and for mattering eares, and for <U+017F>cales and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49277:70"/>
<U+017F>curfe, if the head be wa<U+017F>hed therewith. I have healed with it many times <U+017F>ores on the tooes, namely which came of brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, and were without inflammation, and that in <U+017F>ervants and husbandmen, which had a journey to goe, and no Phy<U+017F>itian with them, bidding them to wet a <U+017F>mall clout with it, and put it into the <U+017F>ores, and then to binde a cloth about it: and as often as they li<U+017F>ted to make water, to let it fall on their <U+017F>ore toes, and not to take the cloath away till it were quite whole. That medicine which is made of childes urine, called <hi>chry<U+017F>ocolla,</hi> or gold <U+017F>ouder, which <hi>Galen</hi> there teacheth to make, is exceeding good for <U+017F>ores that are hard to heale: for this medicine doe I u<U+017F>e for the chiefe<U+017F>t, mixing therewith <U+017F>uch other things, as are good for <U+017F>uch like <U+017F>ores.
<hi>Galen, lib. 10. de <U+017F>implie. med. facult. cap. de urina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Childes urine will heale the <U+017F>ting of a Bee, Wa<U+017F>pe, and Hornet, if the place be wa<U+017F>hed therewith.</p>
               <p>It is good for travellers when they goe to bed to wa<U+017F>h their thighes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that they may be able to continue their journey the next day, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if afterwards they anoint them
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49277:70"/> with oyle and juice of rue.</p>
               <p>Mans urine is al<U+017F>o good again<U+017F>t the gout, which may appeare for that fullers are never troubled with the gout, by rea<U+017F>on that their feet are <U+017F>o often wa<U+017F>hed with it, and <U+017F>ome who have had good experience thereof with great <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>e, doe highly commend it for this purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>Seeing then urine hath <U+017F>o many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and was in antient time in <U+017F>o great u<U+017F>e (as <hi>Dio<U+017F>corides, Galen, Pliny, Columella,</hi> and all tho<U+017F>e that have written of cure of hor<U+017F>es, doe <U+017F>ufficiently te<U+017F>tifie) it came to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e, that the Emperours of Rome got yearely revenues by urines, as
<hi>Suetonius</hi> reporteth of <hi>Ve<U+017F>pa<U+017F>ian,</hi> who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wered
<hi>Titus</hi> reprehending him for <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after gaines by <U+017F>uch <U+017F>tinking wares, in this proverbiall <U+017F>entence, <hi>Bonus e<U+017F>t odor lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri ex requalibet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es touching Vrine, and the remedies thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REcord</hi> in the latter end of his judiciall of urines, <U+017F>etteth downe certain <U+017F>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple medicines for <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es which hinder urine, by who<U+017F>e example not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49277:71"/> impertinent to this treati<U+017F>e: I have likewi<U+017F>e collected a briefe hi<U+017F>tory of the <U+017F>aid di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with <U+017F>ome medicines thereof. And fir<U+017F>t of the <U+017F>tone.</p>
               <p>The <U+017F>tone is engendred in mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as a bricke which is fir<U+017F>t made of tough clay, and put into an hot furnace where it waxeth hard; <U+017F>o a <U+017F>tone is made of tough, vi<U+017F>cous, and <U+017F>limy flegme in the reines or bladder, where through heate thereof it is parched and baked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into the hardne<U+017F><U+017F>e of a <U+017F>tone. But that I may <U+017F>peake <U+017F>omewhat fullier thereof, and yet briefly, the materiall cau<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>tone is, as I <U+017F>aid, a tough
<U+017F>limy flegme, and all cau<U+017F>es which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ame, as all crudities and <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits, all meats gro<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>limy, and hard of dige<U+017F>tion, as milke, new chee<U+017F>e, all white meats made of milke, all cru<U+017F>ts of flower wherein meat is baked, bread not well baked, unleavened. All fle<U+017F>h of great bea<U+017F>ts, e<U+017F>pecially old, as beefe, veni<U+017F>on: and all water-foule. Great fi<U+017F>hes, e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tho<U+017F>e who abound in <U+017F>limy moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture, as eeles, all <U+017F>hell-fi<U+017F>h, oy<U+017F>ters, coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, lop<U+017F>ters, crevi<U+017F>es. All fruits which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors, peares, apples<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:49277:71"/> gourds. Roots which breed winde, as par<U+017F>neps, turneps. Al<U+017F>o all new and thicke wine and drinke. Likewi<U+017F>e becau<U+017F>e heate of the reines doth bake and harden the
<U+017F>aid flegme, and all cau<U+017F>es which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>e heate in the reines, as too warme apparell whereby the backe and reines are kept too hot, running, leaping, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent exerci<U+017F>e: al<U+017F>o riding e<U+017F>pecially with his backe towards the Sunne, <U+017F>tanding again<U+017F>t the fire with his backe, and meats, drinks, and <U+017F>pices which increa<U+017F>e heate. Al<U+017F>o when the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, the reines,
&amp;c. have too <U+017F>trait pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, whereby that <U+017F>limy flegme cannot have i<U+017F><U+017F>ue to be expelled, but <U+017F>taieth within, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough heate waxeth hard, whereupon fat men through moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and old men through drine<U+017F><U+017F>e, having <U+017F>traight pa<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the reines, are more <U+017F>ubject to the
<U+017F>tone in the reines, and le<U+017F><U+017F>e in the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: contrariwi<U+017F>e, children though they are hot and abound with flegme tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ill diet, yet becau<U+017F>e their reines are wider and expul<U+017F>ive faculty <U+017F>trong, whereby that flegmy matter is voyded, are le<U+017F><U+017F>e troubled with the <U+017F>tone of the reines, neither leane men for the <U+017F>elfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>e, but both of them are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49277:72"/> troubled with <U+017F>tone of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<hi>Hippor. 3. Aphori<U+017F>.</hi> 26. La<U+017F>tly, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>peciall cau<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>tone are the parents, from whom this grievous hereditary di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e doth de<U+017F>cend upon the childe: and this of all other is harde<U+017F>t to be cuerd. Now with like brevity to come to the cure, <U+017F>eeing there be foure cau<U+017F>es which help to breed the <U+017F>tone, tough and <U+017F>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my flegme, heate to parch and drie it,
<U+017F>traitne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, and weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the expul<U+017F>ive faculty. So many things as take away any of the<U+017F>e, helpe for the cure thereof, as fir<U+017F>t a good diet, brothes wherein borage, fenell, par<U+017F>ley, endive, or <U+017F>uccory is <U+017F>odden, bread well baked and leavened, hennes, capons, partridge, mutton. Of fi<U+017F>h, <U+017F>oles, plaice, trouts, <U+017F>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Of herbs, borage, endive, <U+017F>ucco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<U+017F>perage, beetes. And to come to the cure. A vomit at the beginning and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>e times, is of e<U+017F>peciall u<U+017F>e to draw the flegmy matter away from the reines and bladder: then a <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>itary, to draw
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>uperfluous excrements downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and a cly<U+017F>ter is to be preferred before a purgation becau<U+017F>e it draweth the excrements downewards from the reines, whereas a purgation taken by the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49277:72"/> mouth doth alwaies draw <U+017F>ome impurity downewards to the reines, but yet the cli<U+017F>ter may not be too great in quantity, le<U+017F>t it fill the guts, and di<U+017F>tend the reines, and <U+017F>o increa<U+017F>e the paine, and <U+017F>top the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age. After that, if the body be full of blood, open the veine under the anckle and not in the arme (as <U+017F>ome would) for all parts of the body grieved above the liver, would be ea<U+017F>ed by opening a veine in the arme, but under the liver, by opening the veine under the anckle or under the knee. <hi>Galen Comment. lib. 9. Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. de morbis vulneribus. Galen de vena <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione,</hi> and then if the body abound with other humors a purgation is convenient, but not <U+017F>trong at the fir<U+017F>t, le<U+017F>t it <U+017F>tirre the humors too much out of <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on before the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages be open. After this <U+017F>eeke to open the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages of urine about the reines partly with cly<U+017F>ter, partly outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <U+017F>ome fomentation, lineaments, in<U+017F>e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions, but yet too much u<U+017F>e of the<U+017F>e doth effoeminate the reines, and make them more <U+017F>ubject to the humors de<U+017F>cending. Then at length you may mini<U+017F>ter medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which provoke urine, breake and expell the <U+017F>tone. Of which medicines there is great diver<U+017F>ity. For <U+017F>ome help to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49277:73"/> mitigate the heate of the reins, a<U+017F><U+017F>wage the inflammation, and hinder the gravell to grow together into a <U+017F>tone, and <U+017F>uch be cooling, <U+017F>enifiers of roughne<U+017F><U+017F>e, but not a<U+017F>tringent, as the foure le<U+017F><U+017F>e cold <U+017F>eeds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some provoke urine either for that they augment it by attenuating the blood, and <U+017F>eparating it from the wheyi<U+017F>h <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, and carrying it to the reins, &amp; the<U+017F>e are hot and dry towards the third degree.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or <U+017F>ome provoke urine, becau<U+017F>e they mini<U+017F>ter much watery and wheyi<U+017F>h moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture to the body, which the reins drawing to them, doe al<U+017F>o draw <U+017F>ome humors out of the veines, as white wine, plantaine, and melons <U+017F>eed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or <U+017F>ome againe provoke urine, not by augmenting the quantity, but by clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing, skouring the reines, and di<U+017F><U+017F>olving and expelling gravell now beginning to grow together. As turpentine, root of re<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harrow, betony, fenell <U+017F>eed and root, <U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, juice of limmons, root of <U+017F>orrell, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den haire, ceterac.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Some againe provoke urine by both the<U+017F>e qualities, in mini<U+017F>tring much whey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<U+017F>h matter, &amp; al<U+017F>o by clen<U+017F>ing the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Some provoke urine by their rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e, clen<U+017F>ing the reines, and robbing or
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49277:73"/> fretting on the <U+017F>tone or gravell, as gla<U+017F><U+017F>e burned and beaten into pouder, egge<U+017F>hels, gromill, the <U+017F>tone it <U+017F>elf which came from a man beaten into pouder.</p>
               <p n="7">7<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> La<U+017F>tly, <U+017F>ome provoke urine by an hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and <U+017F>ecret property, as lapis Iudaicus, ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia, rheubarbe.</p>
               <p>Tho<U+017F>e medicines which provoke urine in the <U+017F>econd <U+017F>ignification by augmenting the quantity, are never to be u<U+017F>ed in any di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine as emulgent veines, reines, water-conduits, bladder or yard, for thereby they are more hurt and ob<U+017F>tructed by much quantity of urine pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing that way. But <U+017F>uch medicines which doe coole the heate of the reins, or which do clen<U+017F>e and mundefie them from impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, already gathered, and neither exceed in heat or drine<U+017F><U+017F>e, but in <U+017F>ubtle and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing quality. Or which by propriety of their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance help that way, as tho<U+017F>e in the fourth and <U+017F>eventh <U+017F>ignification, and yet the<U+017F>e are not at all, or <U+017F>eldome to be u<U+017F>ed, when the body is leane or in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umption, or full of blood and ill humors, neither when the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine are exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerated or ob<U+017F>tructed, or the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages
<U+017F>trait, or when the wombe or privy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have any <U+017F>welling or ulcer; or when
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49277:74"/> the urine is <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, the bladder being full, or i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth with <U+017F>mart burning. For in all the<U+017F>e the medicines bring more impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the places grieved, and <U+017F>o increa<U+017F>e the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, neither are they to be u<U+017F>ed in
<U+017F>wellings or breakings out of the skin, le<U+017F>t they draw the griefe to the inward parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <U+017F>trangury.</head>
               <p>The <U+017F>trangury is cau<U+017F>ed either for that the urine is too <U+017F>harp, which doth provoke the expul<U+017F>ive faculty to expell it, before any quantity be gathered together. Or for that the retentive faculty to the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is weakened through <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, e<U+017F>pecially of cold. Or el<U+017F>e through
<U+017F>ome ulcer or inflammation of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to which the urine comming doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timulate the expul<U+017F>ive faculty. Or la<U+017F>tly, when the wombe or bowels being infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or <U+017F>wollen, do trouble or di<U+017F>tend the bladder, as in women great with childe, who oftentimes pi<U+017F><U+017F>e little and often. Now as the cau<U+017F>e of the griefe is diver<U+017F>e, <U+017F>o the medicines is likewi<U+017F>e diver<U+017F>e for <U+017F>harpnes of the urine, whether it come of hot and
<U+017F>alt meats, too much heating the liver and reines, or of medicines which burne the blood, or of exerci<U+017F>e which likewi<U+017F>e heate
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49277:74"/> the reines and bladder, or la<U+017F>tly, that the moi<U+017F>ture in the glandulous parts is dried up by too much u<U+017F>e of venery, leanene<U+017F><U+017F>e or drine<U+017F><U+017F>e of the body, mu<U+017F>t bee cured with contrary diet, and medicine which moi<U+017F>ten, take away the <U+017F>harpne<U+017F><U+017F>e and coole the blood as new laid egges, chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, veale, meats made of wheat and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley meale, al<U+017F>o lettuce, pur<U+017F>lane, endive,
<U+017F>orrell, prunes, cherries, <U+017F>weet apples, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, melons, but mixe not here with too much <U+017F>alt, vineger, or other hot <U+017F>pices, and if the body abound with <U+017F>harp humors a gentle purgation is good of ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, whey, die<U+017F>eba<U+017F>ten, al<U+017F>o decoctions of lettuce, violets, <U+017F>orrell, pur<U+017F>lane, adding thereto <U+017F>ome licorize or prunes, the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or leaves of malowes, the root of holihoke. And if the paine be raging, it is good to make an injection by a <U+017F>yringe, of the white of an egge, with ro<U+017F>e water or womans milke, or the juice of pur<U+017F>lane, or plantaine, &amp;c. But if the glandulous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture be too much dried up, you mu<U+017F>t u<U+017F>e
<U+017F>uch meats and medicines inwardly and outwardly as doe moi<U+017F>ten the parts, as oyle of violets, almonds, hennes grea<U+017F>e, new butter al<U+017F>o to make plai<U+017F>ters to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the places about the privy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49277:75"/> or injections, to be <U+017F>quirted up into the yard or cli<U+017F>ters to the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill.</head>
               <p>The pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill is called, when the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient pi<U+017F><U+017F>eth as fa<U+017F>t as he drinketh, and in like quantity. Or when he pi<U+017F><U+017F>eth again<U+017F>t his will, and it chanceth either through default of the bladder or reines. As when the retentive faculty of the bladder is decaied through di<U+017F>temperature of cold and moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e: for too much cold doth extingui<U+017F>h the naturall heate of it, which is of a cold and <U+017F>inewie <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blood, and too much moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e doth loo<U+017F>en the <U+017F>mall <U+017F>trings, <U+017F>erving to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive faculty, or when the expul<U+017F>ive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is hurt through quantity or quality of the urine. Or la<U+017F>tly, when the mu<U+017F>cle
(<hi><U+017F>phincter</hi> <U+017F>erving for voluntary motion, is decaied or weakened either through cold or moi<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e, loo<U+017F>ening, or ob<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting or benumming the mu<U+017F>cle, as in the paul<U+017F>ie, or is rent or wounded that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe his duty, as <U+017F>ome time happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to tho<U+017F>e, who are cut for the <U+017F>tone in the bladder, where either the unskilfull Surgeon doth make too great inci<U+017F>ion, or the <U+017F>tone too big doth rent the mu<U+017F>cle in comming out. Whereupon though
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49277:75"/> the wound groweth whole againe, yet the weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the mu<U+017F>cle remaineth: this griefe is almo<U+017F>t familiar to children who bepi<U+017F><U+017F>e their beds in <U+017F>leep through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e and loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F><U+017F>e. Or this griefe happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth through default of the reines being too hot, and <U+017F>o draw the urine too fa<U+017F>t from the liver and veines, and the retentive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty weak cannot hold the urine, but <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it as fa<U+017F>t to the bladder.</p>
               <p>Now for the cure (but I can <U+017F>ay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the cure of the mu<U+017F>cle of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for that being cut or wounded, &amp;c. incurable.) Fir<U+017F>t the humor offending mu<U+017F>t be removed, and then the di<U+017F>tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture corrected, the humor offending if it be heate, mu<U+017F>t be removed by opening the liver veine in the right arme, or by a gentle purgation of manna ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia, tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rindes,
<U+017F>irupe of ro<U+017F>es <U+017F>olutine, dia<U+017F>ebe<U+017F>ten, and diaprunon, but all without <U+017F>cammony and rather often to be u<U+017F>ed, then much at once, that thereby nature by little and little may be framed to void tho<U+017F>e humors by <U+017F>toole which de<U+017F>cend to the reines, al<U+017F>o a vomite <U+017F>tronger for to draw the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors from the reines, and a <U+017F>weat is not inconvenient to draw them to the skin, and la<U+017F>tly to correct the di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49277:76"/> and <U+017F>trengthen the parts, u<U+017F>e
<U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e cooling medicines, as let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuce, endive, <U+017F>uckory, forrell, al<U+017F>o decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and <U+017F>irups of the <U+017F>ame, and be<U+017F>ides of pur<U+017F>lane, ro<U+017F>es, violets, and cooling meats and drinks. For <U+017F>trong wines, and which have power to provoke urine are not good. Al<U+017F>o a ceare-cloth applyed to the backe, loynes and veines to coole them, ceratum refrigerans, unguentum ro<U+017F>aceum &amp; <U+017F>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talinam me<U+017F>ue. But if the cau<U+017F>e came of cold, a vomit and <U+017F>weat is likewi<U+017F>e good, al<U+017F>o cly<U+017F>ters, wherein oyle of cammomill, dill and bitter almonds mu<U+017F>t be u<U+017F>ed. And now and then it is good to u<U+017F>e pils of aloes and rheubarbe. The diet mu<U+017F>t be of hote things, and wherein <U+017F>ome hot <U+017F>pices are put. La<U+017F>tly, u<U+017F>e of cupping gla<U+017F><U+017F>es without inci<U+017F>ion, friction of the outward parts, and moderate exerci<U+017F>e is convenient, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e they heate the body, as al<U+017F>o draw the humor away from the inward parts. And thus much briefly of the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending fully to handle the <U+017F>ame.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:76"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>Ache in the backbone, 85.</item>
               <item>Ache in the reines, 22, 61, 71, 90.</item>
               <item>Adu<U+017F>tion of blood, 40, 56, 60.</item>
               <item>Adu<U+017F>tion of choler, 39, 64, 84.</item>
               <item>Adu<U+017F>tion of humors, 40, 64, 87.</item>
               <item>Adu<U+017F>tion of liver, 67.</item>
               <item>Adu<U+017F>tion of melancholy, 40, 64.</item>
               <item>Agitation of humors, 72.</item>
               <item>Ague, 11, 13, 19, 35, 36, 40, 43, 51, 52, 59, 62,
90, 99.</item>
               <item>Ague beginning, 9, 28, 51.</item>
               <item>Ague burning, 6, 13, 49, 66.</item>
               <item>Ague continuing, 22, 66.</item>
               <item>Ague continuall, 22, 23.</item>
               <item>Ague dangerous, 23, 82.</item>
               <item>Ague intermitting, 23.</item>
               <item>Ague lingring, 28.</item>
               <item>Ague malignant, 23, 82.</item>
               <item>Ague of choler, 78.</item>
               <item>Ague of the heate of the Sun, 178.</item>
               <item>Ague quartane, 22, 24, 43, 52, 64.</item>
               <item>Ague quotidian. 33, 40.</item>
               <item>Ague rotten, 80, 37.</item>
               <item>Ague <U+017F>emitertian, 37.</item>
               <item>Ague <U+017F>harp, 43, 47.</item>
               <item>Ague tertian, 24, 33, 34, 37, 41, 52, 64.</item>
               <item>Agues mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Ague with a good <U+017F>igne, <hi>vide</hi> <U+017F>igne.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:77"/> Ana<U+017F>arca, 46.</item>
               <item>Animall faculty recovered, 85.</item>
               <item>Apoplexy, 30, 73, 66, 96.</item>
               <item>Apoplexy mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Appetite wanting, 43, 46.</item>
               <item>Appetite wanting with death, 46.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>Backbone pained, 85.</item>
               <item>Bladder altered, 40.</item>
               <item>Bladder exulcerated, 15, 61, 59, 65, 66,
68, 69.</item>
               <item>Bladder too open, 15.</item>
               <item>Bladder weake, 66, 69.</item>
               <item>Blood abounding, 37, 39, 55, 56, 70, 86.</item>
               <item>Blood adu<U+017F>t, 40, 56, 60.</item>
               <item>Blood cloddy, 13.</item>
               <item>Blood good, 90.</item>
               <item>Blood inflamed, 96.</item>
               <item>Blood too thin, 68.</item>
               <item>Blood turned into choler, and evacuated,
54.</item>
               <item>Bloody flixe, 37.</item>
               <item>Braine mortified, 83.</item>
               <item>Brea<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 33.</item>
               <item>Breath <U+017F>hort, 40.</item>
               <item>Brui<U+017F>ing, 40, 55, 65, 68.</item>
               <item>Bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e importunate.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Canker, 43.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:77"/> Carbuncle, 43.</item>
               <item>Ca<U+017F><U+017F>ia eaten, 42.</item>
               <item>Children pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing their beds, 96.</item>
               <item>Choler, 19, 31, 84.</item>
               <item>Choler abounding, 34, 37, 54, 81.</item>
               <item>Choler adu<U+017F>t, 39, 64, 84.</item>
               <item>Cholericke complexion, 10.</item>
               <item>Cholericke di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, 51.</item>
               <item>Cholericke meats, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cholicke, 38, 41, 90, 96.</item>
               <item>Cholicke mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Chronicall di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, 43, 47, 52.</item>
               <item>Cold, 11, 20, 40, 44, 55, 90.</item>
               <item>Cold mortifying, 40.</item>
               <item>Cold of the liver, 12, 45.</item>
               <item>Cold of the <U+017F>tomacke, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colliquati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bladder, 59, 90.</item>
               <item>Colliquati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the reines, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colliquati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <U+017F>olide parts, 60.</item>
               <item>Colliquati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole body, 59, 90.</item>
               <item>Colour of urines how they may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
110.</item>
               <item>Colour of urine of what it gives be<U+017F>t <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
111.</item>
               <item>Complexion, 9.</item>
               <item>Complexion cholericke, 10.</item>
               <item>Complexion flegmaticke, 9, 33.</item>
               <item>Complexion melancholike, 10, 34.</item>
               <item>Complexion <U+017F>anguine, 10, 68.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:78"/> Conception, 72, 42, 60, 63, 74, 75.</item>
               <item>Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of male, 72, 73, 75, 76.</item>
               <item>Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of female, 72, 73, 75, 76.</item>
               <item>Concoction, 19, 125, 53, 80, 88, 93.</item>
               <item>Concoction ab<U+017F>olute be<U+017F>t, 25.</item>
               <item>Concoction beginning, 21, 32.</item>
               <item>Concoction exceeding the perfect, 26.</item>
               <item>Concoction <U+017F>econd weake, 56.</item>
               <item>Concoction <U+017F>trong, 56, 57.</item>
               <item>Confu<U+017F>ion, 23.</item>
               <item>Con<U+017F>umption, 28, 34, 37, 55, 59.</item>
               <item>Con<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lungs, 32, 41.</item>
               <item>Con<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reines, 55.</item>
               <item>Con<U+017F>ump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole body, 55, 41, 47, 49.
60.</item>
               <item>Con<U+017F>umption mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Contents in urine, of what they give be<U+017F>t
<U+017F>ignification, 111.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor, 14, 17, 32, 51, 79,
99.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the belly, 14, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the braine, 14, 17, 32.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the brea<U+017F>t, 79.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the cods, 14, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the emeraudes, 49.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:78"/>
Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the fret, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the guts, 14, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the joynts, 14.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the liver, 14.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the lower parts, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the parts grieved, 14, 51.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the parts inflamed, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the parts weakned, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the pores of the skin, 14, 49.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the reines, 14,</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the <U+017F>pleene, 32.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the <U+017F>hort ribs, 14, 32, 79.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the <U+017F>tomacke, 14, 64.</item>
               <item>Conver<U+017F>ion of the humor to the whole body, 14, 49.</item>
               <item>Convul<U+017F>ion, 42, 44, 47, 96.</item>
               <item>Corruption, 23, 51.</item>
               <item>Cough, 39.</item>
               <item>Cramp, 37.</item>
               <item>Cramp mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Criticall evacuation, 10, 22, 42, 46, 68, 90,
93.</item>
               <item>Criticall fluxe of bloud at the no<U+017F>e, 97.</item>
               <item>Crudity, 11, 12, 16, 18, 20, 29, 51, 52, 53, 58,
59, 61, 86, 93.</item>
               <item>Crudity mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:49277:79"/>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Death in agues, 90.</item>
               <item>Death in agues burning, 40.</item>
               <item>Death in agues hote, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Death in agues maligne, 82.</item>
               <item>Death in agues <U+017F>harp, 43, 47.</item>
               <item>Death in agues teatian and quotidian, 16.</item>
               <item>Death in agues when urine is <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, 95.</item>
               <item>Death in apoplexies, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in appetite wanting. 46.</item>
               <item>Death in children, 7, 12, 29.</item>
               <item>Death in cholickes, 38.</item>
               <item>Death in con<U+017F>umptions, 32, 47.</item>
               <item>Death in cramps, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es beginning, 16, 88.</item>
               <item>Death in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es chronicall, 47.</item>
               <item>Death in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>harp, 12, 60, 90.</item>
               <item>Death in drop<U+017F>ies, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in epilep<U+017F>ies, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Death in exulcerations of the lungs, 32.</item>
               <item>Death in flixes, 37, 46.</item>
               <item>Death in fren<U+017F>ies, 32.</item>
               <item>Death in iliakes, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in laskes, 37, 46.</item>
               <item>Death in old men, 37, 39, 81.</item>
               <item>Death in paul<U+017F>ies, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in the pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill, 28.</item>
               <item>Death in the pti<U+017F>ike, 37.</item>
               <item>Death in <U+017F>mall pocks, 68.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:79"/> 
Death in <U+017F>pringals, 7.</item>
               <item>Death in <U+017F>tranguries, 41.</item>
               <item>Death in <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urines in agues, 99.</item>
               <item>Death of cold, 40, 43, 55, 84, 90.</item>
               <item>Death of heate, 40, 44, 55.</item>
               <item>Death of weakene<U+017F><U+017F>e in old men, 37, 39.
81.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e and heate <U+017F>triving in the veines,
97.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e and nature equall in conflict<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
82.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es beginning, 12, 28.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es declining, 29.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es continuing, 13, 16, 32, 20, 36, 55,
82.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es comming again, <hi>look</hi> recidiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es internall whereof they all ari<U+017F>e,
109.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of choler, 66.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of flegme, 30.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of melancholy, 30, 66.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the brea<U+017F>t, 33.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the liuer, 22, 23.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the lungs, 86.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the mother, 30, 73.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the <U+017F>pleene, 33, 22, 43, 71,
68.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the veines, 23.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:80"/> 
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>harp, 43. 33.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>centeries, 14.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of the reines, 63.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of the whole body, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>temperature of heate, 34, 46.</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>temperature of humors, 34</item>
               <item>Di<U+017F>temperature of blood. 34</item>
               <item>Drinking too much, 29, 45, 51, 52.</item>
               <item>Drinking too little, 48.</item>
               <item>Drop<U+017F>ie, 13, 30, 35, 37, 41, 46, 99.</item>
               <item>Drop<U+017F>ie mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Eating dry meats, 48.</item>
               <item>Eating immoderately, 29,</item>
               <item>Eating of turpentine, 90.</item>
               <item>Eating of <U+017F>trong <U+017F>melling things, 92.</item>
               <item>Emeraudes, 14, 51, 66, 71.</item>
               <item>Epilep<U+017F>ie, 37.</item>
               <item>Epilep<U+017F>ie mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Evacuation, 28,</item>
               <item>Evacuation criticall, 10, 22, 43, 46, 68, 90, 93.</item>
               <item>Evacuation <U+017F>ymptomaticall, 22, 43, 46.</item>
               <item>Exerci<U+017F>e great, 28, 50, 40.</item>
               <item>Exerci<U+017F>e<U+017F>mall, 29.</item>
               <item>Exulceration mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Falling evill, 53, 71, 83, 99.</item>
               <item>Fa<U+017F>ting, 50.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:80"/> Feare, 96.</item>
               <item>Felons, 13.</item>
               <item>Fi<U+017F>tula, 66.</item>
               <item>Flixes, 34, 37, 46, 49.</item>
               <item>Flixes mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Flegme abounding, 20, 34, 81, 86.</item>
               <item>Flegmatike complexion, 9, 33.</item>
               <item>Flegmatike di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, 36.</item>
               <item>Flowers i<U+017F><U+017F>uing, 63.</item>
               <item>Flowers <U+017F>topped, 43, 71, 85.</item>
               <item>Fluxe of <U+017F>eed, 35, 62, 63, 66, 93.</item>
               <item>French pockes, 66, 70, 71.</item>
               <item>Fren<U+017F>ie, 13, 32, 33, 62, 84.</item>
               <item>Fren<U+017F>ies mortall, <hi>vid.</hi> death.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Gall ob<U+017F>tructed, 38.</item>
               <item>Gall inflamed. 38.</item>
               <item>Gout, 14, 16, 30, 66, 72, 90.</item>
               <item>Gluttony, 12.</item>
               <item>Gravell, <hi>vide</hi> <U+017F>and.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Head cold and dry, 83.</item>
               <item>Head affected, 89.</item>
               <item>Head weake, 88.</item>
               <item>Head-ache, 36, 80, 82, 83, 87, 89.</item>
               <item>Head-ache pre<U+017F>ent, 22.</item>
               <item>Head-ache to come, 22.</item>
               <item>Head-ache by abundance of choler, blood or melancholy, 83.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:81"/> Health impaired, 18, 33.</item>
               <item>Health, 32, 39, 40, 50, 49, 78.</item>
               <item>Heate naturall plentuous, 19, 47, 81.</item>
               <item>Heate naturall wanting, 18, 27, 56, 57.</item>
               <item>Heate naturall extinct, 16, 40, 54, 87.</item>
               <item>Heate unnaturall, 16, 19, 28, 37, 55, 81, 87.</item>
               <item>Heate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the liver, 47.</item>
               <item>Heate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the reines, 28, 47, 66.</item>
               <item>Heate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, 28.</item>
               <item>Heate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the whole body, 28.</item>
               <item>Heate mortall, 40. <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Humors abounding, 18.</item>
               <item>Humors adu<U+017F>t, 40, 66.</item>
               <item>Humors clammy, 13.</item>
               <item>Humors good, 19.</item>
               <item>Humors moved, 60.</item>
               <item>Humor flegmaticke abounding, 20, 34, 81, 86.</item>
               <item>Humor offending maligne, 28.</item>
               <item>Humor raw abounding, 34, 57, 61, 86, 90.</item>
               <item>Humor thin, 85.</item>
               <item>Hunger, 28, 51.</item>
               <item>Hydrocele, 14, 49.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iaundice, 23, 86, 90.</item>
               <item>Iaundice yellow, 39.</item>
               <item>Iaundice blacke, 40.</item>
               <item>Iaundice blacke with a good <U+017F>igne, 40.</item>
               <item>Iliake, 38.</item>
               <item>Iliake mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:81"/> Inflammations, 5.</item>
               <item>Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the gall, 38.</item>
               <item>Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the liver, 38, 59.</item>
               <item>Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the bladder, 59, 48.</item>
               <item>Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the water-conduits, 48.</item>
               <item>Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the <U+017F>pleene, 38.</item>
               <item>Impo<U+017F>tumes, 13, 27, 31, 49, 51, 39, 95.</item>
               <item>Impo<U+017F>tumes breaking, 22, 35.</item>
               <item>Impo<U+017F>tumes of the lungs, 62.</item>
               <item>Iudgement of urines how to bee given,
107, 108, 109, 110, 111.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Labour, 28, 33, 38, 40.</item>
               <item>Laskes, 14, 37, 46, 49, 51.</item>
               <item>Laskes mortall.</item>
               <item>Lepro<U+017F>ie, 66.</item>
               <item>Lethargy, 22.</item>
               <item>Liver cold 12, 47.</item>
               <item>Liver di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 22, 33.</item>
               <item>Liver exulcerated, 61.</item>
               <item>Liver hot, 47, 66, 69.</item>
               <item>Liver ob<U+017F>tructed, 13, 55.</item>
               <item>Liver pained, 96, 69.</item>
               <item>Liver weakned, 37, 55, 68.</item>
               <item>Loynes brui<U+017F>ed, 36.</item>
               <item>Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F><U+017F>e, 14.</item>
               <item>Lungs di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 86.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Madne<U+017F><U+017F>e, 42, 43, 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:82"/> Matter adu<U+017F>t. 87</item>
               <item>Matter tough. 87</item>
               <item>Mea<U+017F>ils, 13, 49, 72.</item>
               <item>Melancholy, 39, 42.</item>
               <item>Melancholy adu<U+017F>t, 40.</item>
               <item>Melancholy indige<U+017F>ted, 30.</item>
               <item>Melancholy evacuated, 55.</item>
               <item>Melancholike complexion, 10, 83, 34.</item>
               <item>Mother di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 30, 73.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>Nature. weakned, 16.</item>
               <item>Nephre<U+017F>ie, 13.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructions, 51, 96.</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructions of the bladder. 58</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructions of the emulgent veins. 58</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructions of the gall, 38.</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructions mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the liver, 13, 30, 38, 55.</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the reines, 13, 30, 58</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the veines, 13.</item>
               <item>Ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of urine, 13, 30, 58, 96.</item>
               <item>Oyle drunken, 90.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Paine in the joynts, 66.</item>
               <item>Paine of the  heart. 90.</item>
               <item>Paine of the  liver. 90.</item>
               <item>Paine of the  middle-parts. 90.</item>
               <item>Paine of the  <U+017F>pleene. 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:82"/> Paul<U+017F>ie, 30, 37, 48, 71, 96.</item>
               <item>Paul<U+017F>ie mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Perfuming, 91.</item>
               <item>Pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing evill, 26, 47, 63, 97.</item>
               <item>Pi<U+017F><U+017F>ing what motion, 97.</item>
               <item>Plague, 72, 94.</item>
               <item>Pleuri<U+017F>ie, 62.</item>
               <item>Pocks french, 66, 78, 72.</item>
               <item>Pocks <U+017F>mall, 53, 49, 33, 68.</item>
               <item>Pocks mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Po<U+017F>e, 43.</item>
               <item>Pthi<U+017F>icke, 37, 90.</item>
               <item>Pthi<U+017F>icke mortall, 37.</item>
               <item>Purgations, 49.</item>
               <item>Purgations by <U+017F>toole, 51, by vomit, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pur<U+017F>ines, 6<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 91.</item>
               <item>Putrefaction, 23, 92.</item>
               <item>Putrefaction of the humors, liver, <U+017F>olide parts, <U+017F>pleene, veines, 94.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>Quartane ague, 22, 24, 43, 52, 64.</item>
               <item>Quotidian ague, 33, 50.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Recidivarion, 13, 30, 37,</item>
               <item>Reines affected, 36. brui<U+017F>ed, 36. di<U+017F>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
96. exulcerated, 15, 22, 61, 63, 66, 93,
96. fretted, 37, 65. hot, 28, 47, 66. ob<U+017F>tructed,
13, 31, 63. too open, 15. too weake, 12, 69. troubled with humors, 22. with ach, 22, 66,
<pb facs="tcp:49277:83"/>
71. uncleane, 15, 68.</item>
               <item>Rhewme, 62, 72, 89.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Sand, 23, 63.</item>
               <item>Sanguine complexion, 10, 68.</item>
               <item>Scabbedne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the bladder. 60.</item>
               <item>Scabbedne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the body. 60.</item>
               <item>Sciatica, 17, 14, 61.</item>
               <item>Scirrous humors of the <U+017F>pleene, 38.</item>
               <item>Seed abounding, 70. flowing, 35, 62, 63,
66, 63. <U+017F>harp, 70. virulent, 70. wateri<U+017F>h,
70.</item>
               <item>Semitertian, 73.</item>
               <item>Separation of raw humors, 35.</item>
               <item>Sickne<U+017F><U+017F>e continuing, 60, 88. ending, 34.
<U+017F>harp, 60.</item>
               <item>Signe be<U+017F>t in an urine to judge by, 110.</item>
               <item>Signe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in beginning of <U+017F>icknes, 18, 56.</item>
               <item>Signe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in a thicke <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, 56, 41.</item>
               <item>Signe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in a<U+017F>h colour, 40.</item>
               <item>Signe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in the cloud of the urine, 80.</item>
               <item>Signe good in agues, 55.</item>
               <item>Signe good in agues ending, 35.</item>
               <item>Signe good in the cloud of urines, 80.</item>
               <item>Signe good in jaundice blacke, 40.</item>
               <item>Signe good in <U+017F>tate of a di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, 33, 16.</item>
               <item>Signe good in <U+017F>icknes declining, 56, 88.</item>
               <item>Smell of urine whereof it gives be<U+017F>t <U+017F>igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
110.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49277:83"/> Squin<U+017F>ie, 62.</item>
               <item>Slimy moi<U+017F>ture, 31.</item>
               <item>Spermatike ve<U+017F><U+017F>els <U+017F>lippery. 71.</item>
               <item>Spermatike ve<U+017F><U+017F>els weake. 71.</item>
               <item>Spleene di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 22, 33, 42, 71, 94.</item>
               <item>Spleene pained, 90.</item>
               <item>Stomacke cold, 12, 47. raw, 61. windy, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Suppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of urine of what it gives be<U+017F>t
<U+017F>ignification, 110.</item>
               <item>Stone, 13, 35, 37, 43, 48, 63, 64, 65, 66, 63,
96, 99.</item>
               <item>Stone in the bladder, 43, 61, 64, 66, 68.</item>
               <item>Stone in the reines, 43, 61, 63, 68.</item>
               <item>Strangury, 40, 61, 63, 93, 95.</item>
               <item>Strangury mortall, <hi>vide</hi> death.</item>
               <item>Surfetting, 12, 29.</item>
               <item>Sweat much, 48, 50.</item>
               <item>Swimming in the head, 30.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Tena<U+017F>mus, 61.</item>
               <item>Tertian, 24, 33, 34, 37. 41, 52, 68.</item>
               <item>Thir<U+017F>t, 99.</item>
               <item>Tongue <U+017F>corched, 42.</item>
               <item>Turpentine eaten, 90.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>Veines abounding with gro<U+017F><U+017F>e humors,
22. broken, 36, 55, 68, 96. di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed, 23. ob<U+017F>tructed, 13, 31. orifice opened, 67. thin, and full of pores, 68. too open, 36.
<pb facs="tcp:49277:84"/> too weake, 67, 96. widened, 36, 68.</item>
               <item>Veternus, 22.</item>
               <item>Vlcers, 9.</item>
               <item>Vpbraidings, 13.</item>
               <item>Vomiting of blood, 70,</item>
               <item>Vrine of which part it gives <U+017F>ignification,
101, 102, 103.</item>
               <item>Vrine how it is made in the body, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vrine conduits ob<U+017F>tructed, 13, 30, 58, 96.</item>
               <item>Vrine in<U+017F>truments exulcerated, 35.</item>
               <item>Vrine ve<U+017F><U+017F>els benummed.</item>
               <item>Vrine ve<U+017F><U+017F>els exulcerated, 17, 61, 56 65, 66.</item>
               <item>Vrine ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to open, 15.</item>
               <item>Vrine ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to weake, 12, 48, 98.</item>
               <item>Vrine <U+017F>taying too long in the body, 37.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>Want of matter, 50, 57.</item>
               <item>Wa<U+017F>ting of the body, 28.</item>
               <item>Watching, 27, 33, 39, 50, 81.</item>
               <item>Weaknes of the body, 37.</item>
               <item>Weaknes of the head, 88.</item>
               <item>Windines, 54, 78, 80, 83, 85, 90.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y</head>
               <item>Yard too open. 15.</item>
               <item>Yard exulcerated, 15.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49277:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

