<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thw admirable virtues, and wonderful effects of the true and genuine tincture of coral, in physick; grounded upon reason, established by experience, and confirmed by authentical authors in all ages. Never found out plainly till now. By Theophilus Garencieres, doctor in physick, Colleg. Lond.</title>
            <author>Garencières, Theophilus, 1610-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826056</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A42395)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1759:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thw admirable virtues, and wonderful effects of the true and genuine tincture of coral, in physick; grounded upon reason, established by experience, and confirmed by authentical authors in all ages. Never found out plainly till now. By Theophilus Garencieres, doctor in physick, Colleg. Lond.</title>
                  <author>Garencières, Theophilus, 1610-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W.R. for Samuel Sprint at the sign of the Bell in Little Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On verso of title page: Licensed, Apr. 1. 1676. Ro. L'Estange.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the St. John's College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Celeste Ng</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Apr. 1. 1676.</date>
               <signed>Ro. L'Estrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:2"/>
            <p>THE ADMIRABLE
VIRTUES,
And Wonderful
EFFECTS
OF THE
True and Genuine Tincture
OF
CORAL,
In PHYSICK;
Grounded upon Rea<U+017F>on, e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by Experience, and confirmed by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentical
Authors in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Never found out plainly till now.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Theophilus Garencieres,</hi>
Doctor in Phy<U+017F>ick, <hi>Colleg. Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Io <U+017F>uon Medico non di Parole ma d'Effecto.</p> 
               <bibl>Cardan.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. R.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Sprint</hi> at the
Sign of the Bell in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Collegium Sancti Johannis
Evangeli<U+017F>tae in Academia
Cantabrigien<U+017F>i</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:3"/>
            <head>To the Honorable
<hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> WALTER LONG,</hi>
BARONET.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope not to incur
your blame, when I
prefix your Name to
this <U+017F>mall Treati<U+017F>e. The Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
is new, though long
<U+017F>ought after; the <U+017F>cope is the
<pb facs="tcp:30448:4"/>
publick good, and my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
aim is to <U+017F>hew my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
for <U+017F>o many obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
you have been plea<U+017F>ed to
lay upon me, be<U+017F>ides my
hopes, that the de<U+017F>ign of the
Subject may perhaps be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
by experiment, and
the <U+017F>malne<U+017F>s of the Volume
pa<U+017F>s among tho<U+017F>e things that
are not illu<U+017F>ory. And to
<U+017F>ay truth, under who<U+017F>e
Wings could I have <U+017F>hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
it better than yours?
Who<U+017F>e Affability and
Candor is open to the
<pb facs="tcp:30448:4"/>
greate<U+017F>t Strangers, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
my Self, with your
never enough to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
generous Ho<U+017F>pita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>But my intention here,
being not to make your
Panegyrick, I <U+017F>uper<U+017F>ede and
<U+017F>pare your Mode<U+017F>ty, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<U+017F>ufficient to me, if the
Author and the Work
can de<U+017F>erve your Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and the favorable
Looks of your worthy
Brother, Ma<U+017F>ter <hi>Robert</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30448:5"/>
               <hi>Long,</hi> and <U+017F>o ingage me to
remain the re<U+017F>t of my days</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your mo<U+017F>t humble
and affectionate Servant
Garencieres.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:5"/>
            <head>Ad Authorem
De Extracta <hi>CORALII</hi>
Tinctura Dodeca<U+017F>tichon.</head>
            <l>A Multis quae<U+017F>ita diu Tinctura Rubentis</l>
            <l>Coralii, nobis ecce reperta patet.</l>
            <l>Quod veluti rigidum dure<U+017F>cit in aêre marmor,</l>
            <l>Cardiacus mirâ jam datur arte Liquor.</l>
            <l>Lethiferi poto coguntur cedere morbi;</l>
            <l>Aufugiunt pe<U+017F>tis dira, maligna febris.</l>
            <l>Cedit &amp; infantum convul<U+017F>io; foemina Lae<U+017F>ae</l>
            <l>Matricis rabido laeta dolore vacat.</l>
            <l>I<U+017F>ta <U+017F>ub ingenti cre<U+017F>centia pharmaca ponto,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hippocratis</hi> dicant munera digna manu.</l>
            <l>Filum Parca <U+017F>ecet; non te vixi<U+017F><U+017F>e pigebit:</l>
            <l>Si tua tam rarum tempora finit opus.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Petrus Cottereau.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30448:6"/>
            <head>THE
CONTENTS
OF THE
BOOK.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. Of <hi>Coral,</hi> and of the divers
kinds thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Of the Nature, Faculties, and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
of <hi>Coral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Of the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> and what
is Tincture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Why in the Curing of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, we
chu<U+017F>e rather to make u<U+017F>e of the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> than of the whole Body in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance,
however prepared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. How the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> worketh
upon Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Of the Virtues of the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> in the Curing of all Malignant Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Of the dangerous and poy<U+017F>onous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
and u<U+017F>e of Bli<U+017F>tering Plai<U+017F>ters, and that
<pb facs="tcp:30448:7"/>
they ought to be exterminated out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
of Remedies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. Of the Virtues of the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> in all Feavers and Agues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. How the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> worketh
upon all tho<U+017F>e other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, we have <U+017F>aid it
was fit for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. How and in what <hi>Vehicles</hi> the Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
of <hi>Coral</hi> is to be admini<U+017F>tred.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30448:7"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of <hi>Coral,</hi> and of the divers kinds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oral</hi> is a Shrub, growing in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
of the Sea, which becometh
Stony when expo<U+017F>ed to the Air.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sic &amp; <hi>Coralium,</hi> quo primum contigit auras</l>
               <l>Tempore, dure<U+017F>cit; mollis fuit herba <U+017F>ub undis.</l>
               <bibl>Ovid. 4 Metamor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Therefore is it called by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>
and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>The Stony Tree,</hi> in
<hi>Latin Coralium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is divers <U+017F>orts of it according to
their <U+017F>everal colours; for there is a Red, a
White, a Black, a Green, a Yellowi<U+017F>h, of an
A<U+017F>h-colour and of mixed colours. The Red,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30448:8"/>
which is called the <hi>Male,</hi> is preferred above
all the re<U+017F>t, and is the <U+017F>ubject of this our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>e.
<hi>An<U+017F>elmus de Booth,</hi> Phy<U+017F>ician to the
Emperor <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the Second, affirmeth,
To have <U+017F>een in the <U+017F>aid Emperors Cabinet,
Branches of <hi>Coral</hi> of <U+017F>everal colours upon the
<U+017F>ame Body; <U+017F>o that the Body of it was <hi>Coral</hi>
and <hi>Stony,</hi> and the Branches <hi>Ligneous</hi> and
<hi>Woody,</hi> which is not improbable to me;
for I have <U+017F>een in the North of <hi>Ireland</hi> a
Lake called <hi>Lake Neaugh,</hi> wherein, if a
piece of Wood that groweth thereabout be
planted, that part which is in the Ground
<U+017F>hall be turned into <hi>Iron,</hi> that which is in
the Water into <hi>Stone,</hi> and what is above Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<U+017F>hall remain <hi>Wood.</hi> But let us come to
<hi>Coral</hi> again, who<U+017F>e generation is not much
unlike; for when that Juyce that is in it, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by the <hi>Latins, Succus Lapide<U+017F>cens,</hi> runneth
thorough the Body of the Vegetable, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth
it, and turneth it into a <U+017F>tony <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance.
Whence we may g<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<U+017F>s, That <hi>Coral,</hi>
under Water, is not altogether <U+017F>oft and flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
though it groweth <U+017F>tony, when expo<U+017F>ed
to the Air; which cannot be wondered at,
<U+017F>eeing there be many Stones, both in <hi>France</hi>
and <hi>England,</hi> which being newly digged out
of the Ground, are in a manner as <U+017F>oft as
Chee<U+017F>e: But having been a while expo<U+017F>ed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30448:8"/>
to the Air, grow to a con<U+017F>iderable hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
the Sun and the Air having exhau<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the wateri<U+017F>h part of them. Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Coral</hi> groweth out of the Petrifying
Juyce, or being ingendred as other Plants,
is at la<U+017F>t altered by the <U+017F>aid Petrifying Juyce,
is a que<U+017F>tion. For my part, I believe that
it doth not grow without that Petrifying
Juyce, no more then the <hi>Sea-fan,</hi> called <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallina,</hi>
the <hi>Alga,</hi> and other Herbs which
grow in the Sea, and that it doth not petrifie
till it dieth: By dying, I mean, that when
by the ordinary cour<U+017F>e of Nature, or by
the violent action of the Stony Juyce, pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating
the inmo<U+017F>t parts, the Plant is petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.
Now it is certain, that Nature maketh
u<U+017F>e <U+017F>ometimes of the Petrifying Juyce for
the producing of the Plant; for it hath been
ob<U+017F>erved by many, that <hi>Coral</hi> hath grown
out of the pieces and fragments of Earthen
Pots. And in the I<U+017F>land called <hi>Tabacco,</hi> near
<hi>Africa,</hi> which is half <U+017F>wallowed up by the
Sea, much <hi>Coral</hi> is found, having its Roots
in pieces of Earthen Pots. Now the rea<U+017F>on
why <hi>Coral</hi> <U+017F>hould petrifie, and other Plants
not, is becau<U+017F>e of its peculiar di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition: As
al<U+017F>o, becau<U+017F>e naturally there is a Petrifying
Juyce in it, which forceth the Plant to receive
a <U+017F>tony form; be<U+017F>ides the peculiar di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30448:9"/>
and preparation of it to receive <U+017F>uch a form.
No rea<U+017F>on can be given for its colour, no
more then for that of a <hi>Ro<U+017F>e;</hi> for it cannot
be referred to the fir<U+017F>t or <U+017F>econd qualities, no
more than the <U+017F>ight of the eye. God hath
been plea<U+017F>ed to adorn things with <U+017F>uch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
and hath <U+017F>o in<U+017F>erted them into their
Seeds, as their <hi>Archaeus</hi> can produce none
other; <hi>Coral</hi> <U+017F>ometimes groweth to the
height of a man before it be ripe and turned
Red, it <U+017F>eemeth of <U+017F>everal colours; for as
many Plants as I have <U+017F>een that were not
wholly petrified, were all of a Dusky, Green,
or <U+017F>uch colour as we <U+017F>ee in other Trees; and
tho<U+017F>e only begun to be Red, that had nothing
woody in them, as we <U+017F>ee that in Pears and
Apples, the Red colour is a <U+017F>ign of their ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
and maturity. When <hi>Coral</hi> is newly
taken out of the Sea, many impure things
<U+017F>tick to it outwardly, which being taken of,
the true colour <U+017F>heweth it <U+017F>elf. There are
<U+017F>everal <U+017F>orts of <hi>Coral</hi> in re<U+017F>pect of their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
for <U+017F>ome is <U+017F>oft, other hard, <U+017F>ome <U+017F>olid,
<U+017F>ome hollow, <U+017F>ome rough, <U+017F>ome poli<U+017F>hed,
<U+017F>ome porous.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Coral</hi> is taken out of the Sea, it is
for the mo<U+017F>t part rough, and then is made
<U+017F>mooth and poli<U+017F>hed by the Arti<U+017F>ts: There is
a Black <hi>Coral</hi> found in <hi>Gallicia,</hi> a Province
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30448:9"/>
of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <U+017F>uch another <U+017F>ort of cour<U+017F>e
one, called <hi>Savalia,</hi> is brought from <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany,</hi>
having the in<U+017F>ide woody, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ide
horny, and <U+017F>tony, of a Black, Yellow,
and Green colour. There is al<U+017F>o a <U+017F>ort of
White <hi>Coral</hi> found in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and called
by the <hi>Spaniards Polo:</hi> This hath no Bark,
and groweth in the bottom of the Sea, and
not upon Rocks, as the Red doth. The
be<U+017F>t <hi>Coral</hi> is now found upon the Coa<U+017F>ts of
<hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Tripoli. Theophra<U+017F>tus</hi> in his Book
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap> reckoneth <hi>Coral</hi> among the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Stones; and <hi>Orpheus</hi> in his Book <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>
<U+017F>peaketh very much of <hi>Coral.</hi> Before
I end this Chapter, and <U+017F>peak of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
of <hi>Coral,</hi> I will here, in favor of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
clear a doubt, and <U+017F>hew an error con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
its Nature that hath reigned a great
while (becau<U+017F>e <hi>Pliny</hi> writeth, that <hi>Coral</hi> while
it is in the Sea, is as <U+017F>oft as Wax, but a<U+017F><U+017F>oon
as it cometh to the Air it groweth hard) by
an Hi<U+017F>tory, taken out of. <hi>Beguinus</hi> own words
in his <hi>Tyrocinium Chymicum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this Controver<U+017F>ie, <hi>Iohn Bapti<U+017F>t</hi> of
<hi>Nicole,</hi> Squire of the City of <hi>Mar<U+017F>eilles,</hi> chief
Commander for the Fi<U+017F>hing of <hi>Coral</hi> in the
Kingdom of <hi>Tunis,</hi> hath a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me, That in
the year One thou<U+017F>and five hundred eighty
four, being upon the Sea of <hi>Bi<U+017F>erty,</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30448:10"/>
to the <U+017F>aid <hi>Tunis,</hi> where the <U+017F>aid Fi<U+017F>hing
of <hi>Coral</hi> was, and being curious to know
the Nature of <hi>Coral,</hi> and how it groweth in
the bottom of the Sea, cau<U+017F>ed a young Man
to dive into the Sea a hundred fathom deep,
being tied to a rope of a <U+017F>ufficient length,
with a weight of five and twenty pounds in
each hand, to go to the bottom, charging
him to bring <U+017F>ome <hi>Coral</hi> from the bottom,
and to ob<U+017F>erve, whether it was hard or <U+017F>oft.
Being come above Water, he brought a
Branch of <hi>Coral</hi> in each hand, affirming,
That it was as hard in the bottom of the Sea,
as out of it, and that being about eight or
nine fathoms near the bottom, he felt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ive
cold. The <U+017F>ame <hi>Nicole</hi> not contented
therewith, as the Nets were coming up, and
before they could be in the Air, ca<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf
into the Sea about one fathom deep, and took
<U+017F>ome <hi>Coral</hi> <U+017F>ticking to the Nets, which he
found as hard as when it is in the Air. The
<U+017F>ame hath been confirmed to be me by the
Lord of <hi>La Piotier,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Lion,</hi>
who within the<U+017F>e two years returned from
the <U+017F>aid Fi<U+017F>hing of <hi>Coral.</hi> Be<U+017F>ides this, the
<U+017F>aid Squire <hi>Nicole</hi> a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me, that in the
Spring when the <hi>Coral</hi> is plucked up, in the
breaking of it, there i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth out a liquor like
unto Milk, which falling upon any Stone,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30448:10"/>
Wood, Iron, or <U+017F>ome other matter, produceth
<hi>Coral;</hi> and that he had <U+017F>een in the Cabinet
of the great Duke at <hi>Pi<U+017F>a,</hi> the Skull of a dead
Man, upon which was grown in the Sea, a
great Branch of <hi>Coral;</hi> and an Anchor taken
out of the Sea, upon which were <U+017F>everal
Branches of <hi>Coral,</hi> produced by the Juyce of
<hi>Coral</hi> that fell upon it.</p>
            <p>Here we mu<U+017F>t rectifie a kind of <U+017F>eeming
contradiction, which is, when we have cited
<hi>Ovid</hi> and <hi>Mathiolus,</hi> and <U+017F>aid, That <hi>Coral</hi> was
<U+017F>oft under Water, and grew hard when it
came into the Air; and in another place,
That by the experiment of Squire <hi>Nicole,</hi> it
was found to be hard under Water; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
under<U+017F>tand this only to be <hi>Secundum
magis &amp; minus,</hi> as of tho<U+017F>e Stones which we
have <U+017F>aid to be as <U+017F>oft as Chee<U+017F>e in the Earth,
and then to harden in the Air when digged
up, for the Rea<U+017F>ons before alledged. For
though <hi>Coral</hi> may be hard in the bottom of
the Sea, yet it is nothing <U+017F>o hard as when it
hath been expo<U+017F>ed a while to the Air; and <U+017F>o
we perceive it to be in all kind of Trees which
dry and harden to the Air, when once wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and <U+017F>eparated from their natural <U+017F>ap or
moi<U+017F>ture, and growing place.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:30448:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the Nature, Faculties, and virtues
of <hi>Coral.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ACcording to the Famous <hi>Dio<U+017F>corides</hi> and
his Learned Commentator <hi>Mathiolus,
Coral</hi> in his manife<U+017F>t qualities is moderately
a<U+017F>tringent and cooling; but his <U+017F>pecifick qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
are <U+017F>o many and wonderful, that I
<U+017F>hould <U+017F>how my <U+017F>elf too prolix and tedious,
if I would treat of them one by one. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I <U+017F>hall content my <U+017F>elf to lay down the
chiefe<U+017F>t, and to back them with the Authority
of <U+017F>everal Learned and Famous Men, and
<U+017F>hall begin with <hi>An<U+017F>elmus de Booth,</hi> Phy<U+017F>ician
to the Emperor <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the Second, in his
Book <hi>De Gemmis &amp; Lapidibus,</hi> wherein he
<U+017F>aith, That the tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> <U+017F>toppeth the
immoderate Cour<U+017F>es of Women, both Red
and White; the Running of the Reins; the
Spitting of Blood; and cureth all Bloody
Fluxes, and Gripings of the Guts; expelleth
all kind of Gravel and Stones, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umeth
the over-growing of the Spleen. <hi>I
can te<U+017F>tifie of my <U+017F>elf</hi> (<U+017F>aith he) <hi>that being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<U+017F>ick of a Pe<U+017F>tilential Feaver, and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30448:11"/>
               <hi>every moment, and having been without
<U+017F>leep four days and four nights; in<U+017F>omuch, that
all tho<U+017F>e about me, de<U+017F>paired of my life, by
taking in a Spoon <U+017F>ix drops of the <U+017F>aid Tincture,
with the decoction of Violets, upon an in<U+017F>tant,
and as it were miraculou<U+017F>ly, I was cured. For
a<U+017F><U+017F>oon as I had taken two Spoonfuls of the <U+017F>aid
Tincture, I felt my Vital Spirits <U+017F>o refre<U+017F>hed,
and my Intrals <U+017F>o comforted by the gratefulne<U+017F>s
and efficacy of the <U+017F>aid Remedy; that as if the
Light had expelled Darkne<U+017F>s, I found manife<U+017F>tly
the <U+017F>trength of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e abated, and fell into a
critical Sweat (of which before there was no
<U+017F>ign.) So that Nature did thru<U+017F>t to the skin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
of Purple Spots, which pre<U+017F>ently being
obliterated and carried away by the Sweat, in
a little time I recovered my former health. That
Tincture</hi> (<U+017F>aith he) <hi>hath the faculty to bring the
Body to a right temper by a certain Cele<U+017F>tial
Power, and eradicateth all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es out of the
Internal Parts, by rea<U+017F>on of the Analogy it
hath with the Vital Spirits, and the natural
heat which it augmenteth and <U+017F>trenghtneth,
and therefore overcometh ea<U+017F>ily the contrary Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es.</hi>
It cureth the Falling Sickne<U+017F>s in few
weeks, though one hath had it from his
youth. It is commended above all again<U+017F>t
the immoderate Fluxes of Women, either
White or Red; for it doth <U+017F>tay them <U+017F>o, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30448:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30448:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30448:13"/>
the Women cannot fall into any inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency
by it. It doth al<U+017F>o <U+017F>top all Fluxes of
the Belly, and of the Blood from what<U+017F>oever
part it floweth. It al<U+017F>o <U+017F>toppeth the old Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
of the Reins. It is given in the Plague
with admirable <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s: Likewi<U+017F>e in the Flux
and Small Pox, chiefly when they do not come
out kindly. It is al<U+017F>o excellent again<U+017F>t Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy
and the Tympany. It appea<U+017F>eth the
Pains of the Eyes, <U+017F>tayeth the Rheum, and
taketh away the Spots that grow in the
Eyes.</p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Coral</hi> <U+017F>trengthneth the Heart,
and therefore is a <U+017F>overaign Remedy again<U+017F>t
the Plague, and all venemous, contagious,
and malignant Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. It is a certain Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote
in the Plague time, if one taketh of the
<U+017F>aid Tincture in a Morning fa<U+017F>ting, the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
of half a drachm. It hath the <U+017F>ame power
again<U+017F>t the poi<U+017F>on of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> which is analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal
to that of Feavers and Agues, cau<U+017F>ing
Gripings in the Stomach, and the Guts,
Vomiting, Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s, thickne<U+017F>s and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
of the Tongue, Short-breath, and other
dangerous Symptoms, which is confirmed
by <hi>Fore<U+017F>tus, Lib.</hi> 30. <hi>Ob<U+017F>ervat. Med. Ob<U+017F>erva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi>
7. <hi>in Scholio. Arnaldus Villanovanus</hi>
relateth, That if ten grains of the Tincture
of <hi>Coral</hi> be given to a Child newly born,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30448:13"/>
mixed with <U+017F>ome of the Mothers Milk, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Child hath taken any other Meat or
Drink, that the <U+017F>aid Child <U+017F>hall never be
troubled with the Falling-Sickne<U+017F>s; which is
al<U+017F>o affirmed by <hi>Camillus Leonardus, Lib.</hi> 2.
<hi>Speculi Lapidum, Litera, c.</hi> Thus far <hi>An<U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
de Booth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <U+017F>econd Author <U+017F>hall be <hi>Crollius,</hi> the
Prince of <hi>Chymi<U+017F>ts,</hi> who <U+017F>aith this. As <hi>Coral</hi>
doth wonderfully grow, <U+017F>o the Secrets that
are in it, are altogether admirable, and its
Faculties beyond expre<U+017F><U+017F>ion. The virtue of
its Tincture is <U+017F>uch, that it is able to clean<U+017F>e
and renew the Blood in <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ort, as to cure
all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es that comes from the corruption
thereof, and to re<U+017F>tore health, <U+017F>trength, and
alacrity. It <U+017F>toppeth all immoderate Fluxes
in Women, being taken in <hi>Plantain Water;</hi>
as al<U+017F>o all Lasks and Fluxes of the Belly, as
Bloody Fluxes, Dy<U+017F>enteries, Diarrhoea's, taken
in the decoction of the Roots of <hi>Tormentil;</hi>
all Haemorrhagies, Spitting of Blood, and
Haemorrhoides, taken in <hi>Plantain Water;</hi>
clean<U+017F>eth and reneweth the Blood, taken in
the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Fumitory</hi> or <hi>Cichory.</hi> Re<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth
Putrefaction, <U+017F>trengthneth the Heart, and the
Vital Spirits, and pre<U+017F>erveth them from Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on,
in <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Borrage</hi> or <hi>Buglo<U+017F><U+017F>e.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreth
and <U+017F>trengthneth the Stomach, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30448:14"/>
the Natural heat in <hi>Mint</hi> or <hi>Penniroyal Water.</hi>
Removeth all ob<U+017F>tructions, chiefly from the
Lungs, Liver, and Kidneys, in <hi>Water of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,
Gra<U+017F>s, Little Centaury, Spleenwort, Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort.</hi>
Di<U+017F><U+017F>olveth congealed Blood in <hi>Water
of Chervil</hi> or <hi>Dai<U+017F>ie.</hi> It cureth ab<U+017F>olutely the
Fits of the Mother, and the immoderate
Fluxes of Women, in the <hi>Water of Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort,
Balm, Penniroyal.</hi> It cureth the Drop<U+017F>ie,
Convul<U+017F>ion, Pal<U+017F>ie, Falling-Sickne<U+017F>s, in <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon
Water,</hi> continuing for a while. It
expelleth the Stone and Gravel in <hi>Saxifrage
Water,</hi> or that of <hi>Re<U+017F>t-Harrow.</hi> The do<U+017F>e is
from <U+017F>ix grains or ten, to a <U+017F>cruple or two,
according to the age of the Patient, and the
greatne<U+017F>s of the di<U+017F>temper. It cureth Ulcers
being applied to them, or mixed with Plai<U+017F>ters
proper for them.</p>
            <p>The third Author <U+017F>hall be <hi>Joannes Petrus
Faber,</hi> a famous Phy<U+017F>ician of <hi>Monpelier,</hi> who
in his Book called <hi>Myrothecium Spagiricum,</hi>
in the Chapter of <hi>Coral,</hi> <U+017F>peaketh thus. The
virtues and force of this Secret for the mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ying,
and purifying the Blood in all the
Body, is <U+017F>uch as it may be given in all <U+017F>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>
and di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which proceed from the
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> of the Blood, in <U+017F>o much that it
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> excellent in the Lepro<U+017F>ie. It <U+017F>tayeth
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="2 words">
                  <desc><<U+25CA><U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> Fluxes in Women being taken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30448:14"/>
in <hi>Plantain Water;</hi> as al<U+017F>o all kinds of Loo<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es,
and other Bloody Fluxes again<U+017F>t Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
It comforteth and <U+017F>trengthneth the
Heart wonderfully, as al<U+017F>o the Stomach. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>toreth
the Natural heat, by rea<U+017F>on of its radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
moi<U+017F>ture, which is almo<U+017F>t equal to ours.
It di<U+017F><U+017F>olveth all Congealed Blood and Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
Concretions, therefore al<U+017F>o mo<U+017F>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
to tho<U+017F>e that have the Stone and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel,
being drunk in the <hi>Water of Re<U+017F>t-Harrow.</hi>
It is wonderfully efficacious in all venemous
Ulcers, and others, if it be mixed with <U+017F>ome
proper <hi>Bal<U+017F>am,</hi> becau<U+017F>e it mundifieth the
Blood, and procureth Cicatrization.</p>
            <p>The fourth Author <U+017F>hall be our worthy
Countreyman, <hi>Roger Bacon,</hi> who in his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Treati<U+017F>e <hi>De Retardanda Senectute,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth
<hi>Coral</hi> in the<U+017F>e words. That Remedy
which lieth in the bottom of the Sea, is of a
wonderful virtue again<U+017F>t the infirmities of
old age, as experience teacheth us. It is hot
and dry in the <U+017F>econd degree, as <hi>I<U+017F>aac</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
It doth corroborate the Stomach, the
Sen<U+017F>es, and all the internal parts.</p>
            <p>The fifth Author <U+017F>hall be the mo<U+017F>t renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>Fernelius,</hi> who <U+017F>peaking of <hi>Coral,</hi> <U+017F>aith
thus; <hi>Coral</hi> being cold and dry in the <U+017F>econd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
by his A<U+017F>tringent quality <U+017F>trengthneth the
Stomach, and efficaciou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>toppeth all Bloody
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30448:15"/>
Fluxes, pre<U+017F>erveth the <U+017F>trength of the Heart,
and fenceth it again<U+017F>t all malignant and pe<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. Being taken inwardly, it <U+017F>tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the monethly Cour<U+017F>es of Women, and
<U+017F>trengthneth the Conception. It hindereth
Excre<U+017F>cences of Fle<U+017F>h, filleth up the cavity of
Ulcers, and weareth out the Scars in the Eyes.
It cooleth the heat of Choler, and <U+017F>tayeth the
eruptions of it, whether upward or down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.
It <U+017F>trengthneth the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the
Liver, let it never be <U+017F>o loo<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>I could in confirmation of the Premi<U+017F><U+017F>es,
bring the authority of all the be<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>icians
in all Ages that have made mention of <hi>Coral,</hi>
but that I am an Enemy to Prolixity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions.
The<U+017F>e will <U+017F>erve to <U+017F>atisfie any
rea<U+017F>onable per<U+017F>on, or el<U+017F>e nothing will.</p>
            <p>In a word, the Virtues of <hi>Coral</hi> are <U+017F>o great
and wonderful, that many grave and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
Authors did not <U+017F>tick to <U+017F>ay, That it was
an Amulet or Charm again<U+017F>t Fearfulne<U+017F>s, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witchings,
Sorceries, Poy<U+017F>ons, Falling-Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
A<U+017F><U+017F>aults of the Devil, Lightnings, Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>torms,
and other dangers what<U+017F>oever. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
in ancient time it was dedicated to <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
and <hi>Apollo.</hi> But of the<U+017F>e la<U+017F>t qualities, let
every one believe as much as he thinketh fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting:
Certain it is, by the te<U+017F>timony of <hi>Pliny,</hi>
and others, that anciently it was among the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30448:15"/>
               <hi>Indians</hi> almo<U+017F>t of an equal value with Pearls
of the <U+017F>ame bigne<U+017F>s. It is al<U+017F>o certain, that
Red <hi>Coral,</hi> if worn by a Man, hath, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erveth
its colour better than that which is
worn by a Woman; perhaps, becau<U+017F>e the
heat of a Man is greater than that of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
and the vapors that exhale out of his
Body are purer.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is an undoubted truth, That
Red <hi>Coral</hi> will grow pale, blewi<U+017F>h, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated
with <U+017F>everal <U+017F>pots<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> when it is worn
by one that is nigh death, or dangerou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>ick,
and will foretel Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es by the changing of
its colour. This I found true by a <U+017F>ad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
of my own; for having once a Girl
about Twelve Moneths old that wore a Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
of <hi>Coral,</hi> <U+017F>he fell into a Pe<U+017F>tilential Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:
So that when I came home and <U+017F>pied
the <hi>Coral</hi> quite altered, I began pre<U+017F>ently to
de<U+017F>pair of her recovery, which I would not
have done, if I had known then the Tincture
of <hi>Coral,</hi> as I do now. She lived but two days
in that ca<U+017F>e. After her death I would have
taken the Bracelet from her, and tried whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
I could have brought it to its former
colour again; but the Mother would never
<U+017F>uffer it, but would have it buried with her,
le<U+017F>t the <U+017F>ight of it <U+017F>hould bring her into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
of her lo<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>o deprived me
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30448:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30448:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:30448:17"/>
of <U+017F>o ju<U+017F>t a curio<U+017F>ity. Here by the By, Let us
con<U+017F>ider what affliction it is to Parents to <U+017F>ee
their young Children <U+017F>ick, without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,
and not able to expre<U+017F>s their own grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,
whereas now a <U+017F>poonful of this Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
which is plea<U+017F>ant to the ta<U+017F>te, and can
be no ways hurtful, may pre<U+017F>erve them alive
to the honor and glory of God, and the <U+017F>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
and joy of their Parents and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:30448:17"/>
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the Tincture of <hi>Coral;</hi> and what is
Tincture.</head>
            <p>TIncture is an Extract of the Colours ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering
to mixed Bodies, and of the
formal qualities thereof. Whence cometh it,
that Tinctures are <U+017F>ometimes called <hi>Oyls,</hi>
<U+017F>ometimes <hi>Spirits,</hi> and <U+017F>ometimes <hi>Quinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cence.</hi>
In the Extraction of Tinctures, the
Chymical Arti<U+017F>ts do chiefly labor, that they
may <U+017F>eparate the formal Virtue of the mixed
Bodies, in which lieth the faculty of curing
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es from its proper Matter or Feculent
Body, which is unprofitable, Terre<U+017F>trial or
Wateri<U+017F>h; for they draw by Extraction and
Means of a determinated <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> (for the
<U+017F>ame <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> is not fit to draw all kinds of
Tinctures) the Tincture or E<U+017F><U+017F>ence of it,
which is the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ecret and internal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance
that Nature had inclo<U+017F>ed and concealed in the
Intrals of it, to pre<U+017F>erve it from all external
injuries and accidents. And after that, they
draw or ab<U+017F>tract the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> from it; and
the Tincture or E<U+017F><U+017F>ence remaineth in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, in the con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of Honey
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30448:18"/>
or Pap, and then it is properly called <hi>Extract.</hi>
But if it be in a Liquid form joyned with its
<hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> and repre<U+017F>enting the colour out
of which it is drawn, then it is properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Tincture.</hi> Therefore ob<U+017F>erve that by the
word Tincture, the <hi>Chymi<U+017F>ts</hi> under<U+017F>tand the
colours <U+017F>ticking to the E<U+017F><U+017F>ence of the mixed
Bodies, and to the formal qualities drawn out
of them.</p>
            <p>Here we mu<U+017F>t make an exact di<U+017F>tinction,
between a Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution and an Extraction of
the Tincture; for in a true Tincture we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
only the formal Virtue of the <U+017F>ubject,
the ma<U+017F>s and lump of the Body remaining
whole; but in a di<U+017F><U+017F>olution, the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
is reduced into minute parts. Hence
cometh it, that the do<U+017F>e of the Tincture is
<U+017F>mall, but that of the di<U+017F><U+017F>olution mu<U+017F>t be in
a greater quantity, becau<U+017F>e it is not <U+017F>o effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>Ob<U+017F>erve al<U+017F>o, That there is no true Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
but that which remaineth of the <U+017F>ame
colour as the mixed Body was, after the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truum</hi>
is extracted from it. If by this rule
many Tinctures be examined, it will be ea<U+017F>ily
known that they are no true Tinctures, but
that their colour proceedeth from the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> with the Body di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:30448:18"/>
For example, Let any body take of the
Vulgar Tinctures of <hi>Coral,</hi> if you exhale or
di<U+017F>til the <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> from them, it will go
away pure and clear, and that which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<U+017F>hall not be Red, but <U+017F>hall look either
like Lime or Salt; whereas, if it were a true
Tincture, and a Red Sub<U+017F>tance extracted from
the Body, it <U+017F>hould remain <U+017F>o, though the
<hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> were ab<U+017F>tracted from it. But that
Tinctures are not always true, but vary accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to their <hi>Men<U+017F>truums,</hi> is evident in that
<U+017F>everal colours may be extracted out of one
and the <U+017F>ame thing by <U+017F>everal <hi>Men<U+017F>truums.</hi>
For example, if you put upon Silver calcined
with <hi>Mercury</hi> <U+017F>ublimate, the <hi>Spirit of Salt;</hi>
you <U+017F>hall have a Green colour like an Emerald,
but if you put upon it the <hi>Spirit of <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated
with the <hi>Salt of <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine,</hi> it will be
of a Blew colour. The<U+017F>e contradictions did
per<U+017F>wade once <hi>Crollius,</hi> an excellent Chymi<U+017F>t,
when he wrote his Book called <hi>Ba<U+017F>ilica Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica,</hi>
That the true Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> was
impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be had, or at lea<U+017F>t, that it was
not his fortune ever to <U+017F>ee any. But we <U+017F>hall
convince him <U+017F>ufficiently of the contrary, and
as many as <U+017F>hall be of his opinion.</p>
            <p>Here I cannot wonder enough at many
Chymi<U+017F>ts and Phy<U+017F>icians of good note, who
through ignorance, or by hear-<U+017F>ay, for the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30448:19"/>
obtaining the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> advi<U+017F>e to
calcine it, that the Tincture may be drawn
out of it, without con<U+017F>idering that in the
Calcination the fire burneth and con<U+017F>umeth
the Tincture, and that Calcination is good
for nothing but to Extract the Salt of it, which
al<U+017F>o hath <U+017F>everal Faculties in Phy<U+017F>ick of which
we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>peak in its proper place. For Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination
is the Reduction of a mixed Body
into a Calx or Lime made by fire, which
depriveth the <U+017F>aid mixed Body of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
or moi<U+017F>ture that united the parts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Now it is time to come to the true Tincture
of <hi>Coral.</hi> Take therefore (for an experiment)
half an ounce of the be<U+017F>t <hi>Coral</hi> in Powder,
put it in a Viol of about half a pint, pour
upon it <U+017F>ix ounces of our <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> and <U+017F>top
the Viol clo<U+017F>e with a Cork, you <U+017F>hall perceive,
that within four hours the <U+017F>aid <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi>
will be coloured Red, then pour it out, and
put new upon the <U+017F>ame <hi>Coral,</hi> and <U+017F>o do, <U+017F>o
often till you <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee the <hi>Coral</hi> white in the
bottom of the Gla<U+017F>s, then ab<U+017F>tract the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truum</hi>
in <hi>Balneo,</hi> in the bottom <U+017F>hall remain
the true Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> as Red as Blood,
and the Body <U+017F>hall remain in the Viol as white
as Snow: Edulcorate, that is, Wa<U+017F>h the <U+017F>aid
Tincture from its <hi>Men<U+017F>truum</hi> with <U+017F>ome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30448:19"/>
Water, which you <U+017F>hall afterwards Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tract
from the Tincture in <hi>Balneo,</hi> till it be
almo<U+017F>t dry, then <U+017F>halt thou have the true
Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> mo<U+017F>t efficacious for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, being given in <U+017F>ome
appropriated <hi>Vehiculum,</hi> and fit for the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper.
The do<U+017F>e is from ten drops to twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
or thirty, in two ounces of an appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Liquor.</p>
            <p>When you have Extracted the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> do not <U+017F>light or throw away the Body
of <hi>Coral</hi> which remaineth in the Viol, for
out of it may, by Chymical Art, be Extracted
the Salt of <hi>Coral;</hi> which in all re<U+017F>pects e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulateth
and cometh very near the Tincture,
except in the curing of malignant and pe<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p>I am here much <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed at the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory
opinion of <hi>Philibert Guibert,</hi> a famous
Phy<U+017F>ician of <hi>Paris,</hi> who in <U+017F>everal places of
his Book, called <hi>The Charitable Phy<U+017F>ician,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
highly commended the u<U+017F>e of <hi>Venice
Treacle</hi> again<U+017F>t the Plague, and other ven<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, according to the doctrine of
the be<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>icians, doth at la<U+017F>t in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>e
of the Plague, exclaim again<U+017F>t it as again<U+017F>t
an infamous Remedy, contrary to the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of the be<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>icians, and the con<U+017F>tant
experience of all Ages, as I have <U+017F>hewed in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30448:20"/>
my Treati<U+017F>e of the la<U+017F>t Plague <hi>Anno</hi> 1665.
and in<U+017F>tead of it, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tituteth two Antidotes
of his own, which are <U+017F>omething Comical.
The fir<U+017F>t is, The u<U+017F>e of good Wine; the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
is that which he calleth <hi>Electuarium de
tribus Adverbiis. Cito, longe, tarde.</hi> That is, to
be gone quickly out of the infected place, to
go far from it, and to come back as late as
one can, according to this old Di<U+017F>tich.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Haec tria tabificam pellunt Adverbia Pe<U+017F>tem,</l>
               <l>Mox, longe, tarde, cede, recede, redi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But as we do not deny that Wine is a noble
Aliment, and a great Cordial, <U+017F>o do we think
it too weak alone to cure the Plague, as is
<U+017F>een in many places where people drink no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but Wine, and that of the be<U+017F>t: No
more than his Antidote of the three Adverbs,
many having met with the Plague in the
Countrey, which they might have avoided,
if they had <U+017F>tayed in the City, as I did all the
while: For I do undertake (with the Grace
of God) to cure the fierce<U+017F>t Plague with
<hi>Venice Treacle,</hi> and my Tincture of <hi>Coral.</hi>
Add to this, that many people are not able to
go out of Town, either want of means or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
or being incumbred with a numerous
Fam<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:30448:20"/>
Before we fini<U+017F>h this Chapter, it will be
worth the curio<U+017F>ity of the Reader to know
how to Extract the Salt of <hi>Coral,</hi> which we
have <U+017F>aid to emulate the Virtues of the Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
except in the curing of the Plague, and
malignant Feavers.</p>
            <p>Take therefore that white Body of <hi>Coral</hi>
which remaineth in the Viol, after the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction
of the Tincture, wa<U+017F>h it very well
with fair water, dry it gently upon a <U+017F>oft fire,
and then pour upon it by degrees Vinegar,
that hath been di<U+017F>tilled three times, as much as
will cover it four Fingers above, then dige<U+017F>t
and di<U+017F><U+017F>olve that together, and after the <U+017F>olu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
Ab<U+017F>tract the Vinegar till the <hi>Coral</hi> be
dry; then wa<U+017F>h the <hi>Coral</hi> with di<U+017F>tilled water,
to take away the acrimony of the Vinegar;
after that, evaporate the Water till there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth
a Salt as white as Snow, and free
from all acrimony, which mu<U+017F>t be kept in a
Gla<U+017F>s clo<U+017F>e <U+017F>topt.</p>
            <p>Its virtues are mo<U+017F>t excellent, for it purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the Blood in all the Body, which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>toreth
to its former <U+017F>trength. It <U+017F>toppeth
all Fluxes of the Womb, of the Belly, and of
the Haemorrhoides. It <U+017F>trengthneth the Heart,
and the Stomach; it openeth all the ob<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of the internal parts; it di<U+017F><U+017F>olveth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed
Blood. It is mo<U+017F>t excellent in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30448:21"/>
Drop<U+017F>ie, Pal<U+017F>ie, Convul<U+017F>ion, the Stone,
Fits of the Mother. <hi>Crollius</hi> is of the <U+017F>ame
opinion; for he <U+017F>aith, That it purifieth the
Blood, and cureth in a <U+017F>hort time all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es
that proceed from the corruption of it, if it
be taken in <hi>Cichory</hi> or <hi>Fumitory Water.</hi> To
<U+017F>top all exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive Fluxes and lo<U+017F>s of Blood, as
well by Dy<U+017F>enteries and Haemorrhoides, and
<U+017F>uch like; as Hepatical Fluxes, Lienterical,
Men<U+017F>trual, Spermatical, Bleeding at the
No<U+017F>e, Spitting of Blood, being taken in
<hi>Plantain Water,</hi> or <U+017F>uch like; to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction,
to <U+017F>trengthen the Brains, the
Stomach, the Natural heat, and the Vital
Spirits, and to pre<U+017F>erve the Heart again<U+017F>t all
poy<U+017F>on; to remove all ob<U+017F>tructions from the
noble parts, to wit, The Lungs, the Liver,
and the Kidneys; to di<U+017F><U+017F>olve congealed
Blood, and to cure the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>tubborn Fits
of the Mother, and <U+017F>uperfluities of the
Monethly Cour<U+017F>es, being taken in the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of <hi>Motherwort, Balm,</hi> or <hi>Pennyroyal.</hi>
See <hi>Crollius</hi> in <hi>Ba<U+017F>ilica Chymica,</hi> and <hi>An<U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
de Booth, cap.</hi> 154. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Drop<U+017F>ie, Pal<U+017F>ie, Falling-Sickne<U+017F>s,
and Convul<U+017F>ion, this Salt is taken with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s in <hi>Cinnamon Water;</hi> and for
the Stone, in the Water of <hi>Re<U+017F>t-Harrow.</hi> It
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30448:21"/>
may al<U+017F>o be put in <hi>Lozenges,</hi> and be taken in
<U+017F>tead of common Salt in a boiled Egg, or in
Broth, or in White Wine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:30448:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <head type="sub">Why in the Curing of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, we chu<U+017F>e
rather to make u<U+017F>e of the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> then of the whole Body in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
however prepared.</head>
            <p>DI<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es never come upon mankind, but
by a Segregation and Heterogeneity of
humors; for while the Cra<U+017F>is or Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Humors, remaineth whole, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
con<U+017F>tantly performeth her Functions, the
Spirits play their part, and the oeconomy of
the Body remaineth intire; but a<U+017F><U+017F>oon as the
Humors begin to <U+017F>eparate them<U+017F>elves, and to
jar one again<U+017F>t another, the Spirits are <U+017F>cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered,
the Humors putrifie; and if there be
any malignity in the Air, it introduceth it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
immediately into that <hi>Chaos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the<U+017F>e Indications teach Phy<U+017F>icians,
fir<U+017F>t, to expel the malignity as the mo<U+017F>t pre<U+017F>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<U+017F>econdly, to <U+017F>ettle the Spirits; thirdly,
to unite again the Humors. Now the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
being aerial, cannot be expelled, but by
formal Qualities, neither can the Spirits be
<U+017F>ettled but by the <U+017F>ame; which both being
done, the third, which is the union of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30448:22"/>
Humors, will of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity follow; for the
Cau<U+017F>e being removed, the Effect in<U+017F>ueth. The<U+017F>e
things cannot ea<U+017F>ily be done by a Body in
Sub<U+017F>tance, (<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e <hi>Coral</hi> in Powder) for in
that Body the three Principles of Nature, to
wit, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> remain
united together, and <U+017F>o adhere one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other;
that although nature may dige<U+017F>t them,
yet will they not <U+017F>eparate them<U+017F>elves to do
the Body any determinate good, but will
either undige<U+017F>ted or dige<U+017F>ted, go all along and
keep company together; whereas, when they
are <U+017F>eparated one from the other, they work
determinately by the help of a proper <hi>Vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum,</hi>
upon the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e aimed at. For though
all the parts (for example of <hi>Coral</hi>) be friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to an Humane Body, yet are they more
friendly one to another, and will not <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
them<U+017F>elves to do a Body good, but will
rather <U+017F>tick clo<U+017F>e and peri<U+017F>h together, to the
illu<U+017F>ion of the Phy<U+017F>ician, and the delu<U+017F>ion of
the Patient. The <U+017F>econd Rea<U+017F>on is, That when
the Remedy is given in Sub<U+017F>tance, Nature is
put to the work and task of dige<U+017F>ting it, and
in the mean time the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e (chiefly if it be
aerial) getteth footing, the <U+017F>trength declineth,
and <U+017F>o many times the Scales weigh down;
whereas, if it be given <U+017F>eparate (<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e the
Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi>) Nature pre<U+017F>ently layeth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30448:23"/>
hold on it, cheareth up the heart with it,
who pre<U+017F>ently as the Sun of the Microco<U+017F>m
<U+017F>endeth it, by way of irradiation, to the part
affected, and <U+017F>o relieveth the Patient.</p>
            <p>Another inconveniency ari<U+017F>eth from giving
Remedies in Sub<U+017F>tance, which is, that when
the thinne<U+017F>t part of the Remedy, is di<U+017F><U+017F>olved
in the Body, the thicke<U+017F>t, which the <hi>Latins</hi>
call <hi>Faere</hi> or <hi>Cra<U+017F><U+017F>amentum,</hi> remains in the
way, and many times cau<U+017F>eth <U+017F>tubborn ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructions,
and other accidents, who<U+017F>e Cau<U+017F>es
being unknown to the Phy<U+017F>ician, becau<U+017F>e un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>u<U+017F>pected,
produce many times <U+017F>everal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents
wor<U+017F>e than the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
at fir<U+017F>t to be cured. This is to be daily
ob<U+017F>erved in tho<U+017F>e that u<U+017F>e gro<U+017F>s and f;aeculent
Means, and by the Rea<U+017F>on we have alledged
before, fall into <U+017F>toppages and ob<U+017F>tructions,
and con<U+017F>equently into divers Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es hard to
be cured.</p>
            <p>From this Rea<U+017F>on it is, that Spirits and
E<U+017F><U+017F>ences <U+017F>eparated and <U+017F>ublimated, work
more powerfully and efficaciou<U+017F>ly, than when
they are wrapt and involved in their whole
Bodies, <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="2 words">
                  <desc><<U+25CA><U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> whom they cannot ea<U+017F>ily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate
them<U+017F>elves, and <U+017F>hew forth their
power and virtue, as you may ob<U+017F>erve in
Spirit of Wine well rectified, one <U+017F>poonful
of which <U+017F>hall work more effect then a quart
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30448:23"/>
of the common one, out of which it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted.
The <U+017F>ame is of Vinegar, which, if
it be pure and good, <U+017F>hall in the quantity of
a <U+017F>poonful, in Sawces, Salets, or other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments,
do more effect than a quart of the
common one, and with le<U+017F>s charge and more
gratefulne<U+017F>s; becau<U+017F>e its efficacy and virtue
before was dulled, allayed, and made ineffica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
by the faeces, phlegm, and other impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities
that adhered to it. Upon this Rea<U+017F>on,
the Remedies that are to be admini<U+017F>tred to
Humane Bodies, are to be pure, rectified and
exalted: If you well con<U+017F>ider the effect you
expect from them, and the dignity of the
<U+017F>ubject with whom you have to do. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the be<U+017F>t Chymi<U+017F>ts in all Ages have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored
and labored to make their Remedies
as pure and defaecated as po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly they could,
that the effect aimed at, might follow, and
the Humane Bodies excellency <U+017F>hould not be
violated, as it is not, when in the preparation
of the Remedies, the pure is <U+017F>eparated from
the impure, the u<U+017F>eful from the unprofitable,
the <U+017F>piritual from the corporeal, and the
cordial from the poy<U+017F>on: And thus they do
not lie heavy upon the Stomach, they beget
no impurities, cau<U+017F>e no new ob<U+017F>tructions,
but immediately fight again<U+017F>t the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es,
and overcome them. Thus, Beer well <U+017F>ettled
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30448:24"/>
is whole<U+017F>omer than new; thus Wine <U+017F>epara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
from its Tartar, is better for the ta<U+017F>te, and
for the health, then when it is newly extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
from the Grape; thus the Meats we eat,
being <U+017F>eparated by Nature from their Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
after many light concoctions and <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations
of Excrements in the Liver, and
in the Veins, are at la<U+017F>t made fitter for the
nouri<U+017F>hment of the parts. Thus, <hi>Cinnamon
Water</hi> <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ooner and more efficaciou<U+017F>ly
comfort the Heart, than <hi>Cinnamon</hi> it <U+017F>elf in
Sub<U+017F>tance; thus, a few drops of <hi>Oyl of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>eed</hi>
<U+017F>hall work more effectually then many
Seeds, and thus of the re<U+017F>t. Whereby you
may <U+017F>ee that Remedies well prepared and
purified, are extraordinary efficacious for the
cure of the wor<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; as the Falling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s,
the Convul<U+017F>ion, the Drop<U+017F>ie, the
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uartan Ague, the Gout, and other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es
commonly deemed incurable; and that with
all <U+017F>afety diligence, and alacrity, imitating
Nature in this, which doth not <U+017F>end to the
parts for their nouri<U+017F>hment the Meats as they
are raw and whole, but altereth them in the
Stomach, dige<U+017F>teth and de<U+017F>troyeth them, and
in the Liver <U+017F>eparateth the pure<U+017F>t from the
Excrements.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the penetration of the
Virtue of the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote<U+017F>t
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30448:24"/>
parts, for the Curing of tho<U+017F>e de<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, we have mentioned, as Falling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s,
Convul<U+017F>ion, Gout, Pox, Bleeding
out of any part of the Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Con<U+017F>ider
how the Milk of a Nur<U+017F>e that hath taken
<hi>Rheubarb,</hi> is able to purge a Suckling-Infant,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:30448:25"/>
            <head type="sub">How the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> worketh upon
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</head>
            <p>BUt that we may make this obvious to the
meane<U+017F>t capacities, we will lay here open
the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ecret Foundations of Phy<U+017F>ick, to
wit, The Actinoboli<U+017F>m of Natural things,
which is no where el<U+017F>e <U+017F>o clearly to be <U+017F>een as
in Medicinal ones; and this is twofold, either
to life or to death. Which that you may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<U+017F>tand,
you mu<U+017F>t ob<U+017F>erve, That as all things
were created for Mans <U+017F>ake, even <U+017F>o there
was given to every one a particular virtue by
which Man might be pre<U+017F>erved: For he that
intendeth the End, intendeth al<U+017F>o the Means
to attain it, as are the Virtues of Natural
things. Seeing then that there is no Member
in an Humane Body, but hath its proper and
peculiar infirmities, the mo<U+017F>t High hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
Remedies again<U+017F>t all them; <U+017F>eeing al<U+017F>o
that there be Members hidden and concealed
in the mo<U+017F>t retired places of the Body, where
there was no acce<U+017F>s for Herbs and Plants to
come to. He hath given them like as it were
Beams of Light, <U+017F>preding them<U+017F>elves round
like tho<U+017F>e of the Sun, which pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing through
all the Body, do by their Actinoboli<U+017F>m or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30448:25"/>
Irradiation, penetrate to that Member which
is corre<U+017F>pondent to them, and hath need of
their Faculties and Virtues. Hence cometh,
that the Remedies having <U+017F>pred the Beams of
their Virtues, go directly to that Member
which is analogal and corre<U+017F>pondent with
them, and <U+017F>trengthen and comfort it. Thus
all Cordials by their Actinoboli<U+017F>m, do not
meddle with the Liver, Brains, or Spleen;
but with the Heart.</p>
            <p>The Hepatical Remedies by their Actino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli<U+017F>m,
do not comfort the Kidneys or the
Lungs, but the Liver: Thus, the Diureticks
meddle not with the Liver, Heart, or Brains,
but with the emulgent Veins, and the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.
Thus, the Actinoboli<U+017F>m of the Cathar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks
and Diaphoreticks, gather together into
the Intrals, all the Choler lurking in the Body,
and from thence carry it away as a <U+017F>uperfluous
and noxious thing.</p>
            <p>Hence it is manife<U+017F>t, by what Rea<U+017F>on the
compounded Medicines, indowed with divers
qualities, work upon the Body unconfu<U+017F>ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and are no hinderance one to another, no
more than the Suns Beams are among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves,
as it is demon<U+017F>trable in Mathematicks.
For <U+017F>eeing that the Specifick Virtues of each
Medicines which enter into the Compo<U+017F>ition,
remain in it after the lo<U+017F>s of their fir<U+017F>t qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30448:26"/>
when they are received in the Stomach,
as in a Natural place, every kind, without
mixing one with another, and confounding
their Beams, tends to that part to which it is
affected, and hath corre<U+017F>pondency with, and
with their Actinoboli<U+017F>m, do wonderfully
<U+017F>trengthen and comfort it. Whence cometh,
that all the Members being comforted, the
Natural heat mu<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity be <U+017F>trength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
and the more it is, the le<U+017F>s power will
the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e have; in<U+017F>omuch, that we may
imagine in Phy<U+017F>ick as many Centers of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
as there be Individuals that compound
it; and if there be many Cordials mixed
together, they all <U+017F>hall ca<U+017F>t their Beams upon
the Heart: Tho<U+017F>e Herbs that have relation to
the Lungs, <U+017F>hall work that way, and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patical
ones, <U+017F>hall all tend to comfort the
Liver. And thus by the Aggregation of <U+017F>o
many Virtues, the Body mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity
prevail again<U+017F>t the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e: So contrariwi<U+017F>e,
that Antipathetical Actinoboli<U+017F>m which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth
from poy<U+017F>ons, and poy<U+017F>onous things,
a<U+017F><U+017F>oon as it is got down into the Stomach,
doth fir<U+017F>t attack the Heart, as the fortre<U+017F>s of
the Body. Thus the Mineral Poy<U+017F>ons, as,
<hi>Ar<U+017F>enick, Orpine, Ochra,</hi> and the Poy<U+017F>ons of
Serpents, by their radiation, infect the next
Blood, and that the next, and <U+017F>o con<U+017F>equent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30448:26"/>
till it hath reached to the Heart. Whence
if it be not expelled by the Antactinoboli<U+017F>m
of <U+017F>ome counterpoy<U+017F>on it bringeth de<U+017F>tructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to the party: Be<U+017F>ides that, every Member
hath its peculiar Poy<U+017F>ons; for <U+017F>ome do not
attack the Heart immediately, but the Lungs.
As, that <hi>Zoophyte,</hi> called <hi>Pulmo Marinus,</hi>
which being eaten, ulcerateth the Lungs, and
bringeth the party into a <U+017F>low Con<U+017F>umption.
The <hi>Sardonian Smallage,</hi> as al<U+017F>o that In<U+017F>ect
called <hi>Tarantola,</hi> invading the S<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ats of the
Spirits, and the Arteries and Mu<U+017F>cles, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh
a Man to laughing and dancing. The
biting of the Serpent called <hi>Dyp<U+017F>as,</hi> as <U+017F>oon as
it beginneth to diffu<U+017F>e, doth by its Radiation
bring the Liver into Putrefraction. The
biting of a Mad-Dog giveth to a Man the
Dogs manners; for he continually barketh,
biteth, and feareth Water. The biting of a
Mad-Cat, imparteth the Cats manners. <hi>Sken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius</hi>
relateth of a Maid that had eaten of a
Cats Brains, and did perfectly imitate a Cats
manners, expre<U+017F><U+017F>ing its voice, and hunting
after Mice with her crooked Fingers and
Nails. The Poy<U+017F>on of an A<U+017F>p being an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
to the Nerves, doth by its Radiation cau<U+017F>e
a <U+017F>udden lack of Sen<U+017F>e in all the Limbs which
it corrupteth. The biting of the Serpent
(called for that rea<U+017F>on <hi>Haemorrhois</hi>) by its
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30448:27"/>
Radiation turneth all the Humors of the
Body into Blood, as <hi>Ge<U+017F>nerus</hi> witne<U+017F><U+017F>eth, <hi>Lib.</hi>
5. <hi>Hi<U+017F>t. Anim.</hi> Which is confirmed by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius</hi>
in his Ninth Book, by the<U+017F>e excellent
Ver<U+017F>es.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Impre<U+017F><U+017F>it dentes Haemorrhois a<U+017F>pera <hi>Tullo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Magnanimo juveni miratorique <hi>Catonis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>tque <U+017F>olet pariter totis <U+017F>e effundere venis</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corycii</hi> pre<U+017F><U+017F>ura croci: Sic omnia membra</l>
               <l>Emi<U+017F>ere <U+017F>imul rutilum pro <U+017F>anguine virus.</l>
               <l>Sanguis erant lachrymae: Quaecumque foramina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novit</l>
               <l>Humor, ab iis largus manat cruor: Ora redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</l>
               <l>Et patulae nares, <U+017F>udor rubet, omnia plenis,</l>
               <l>Membra fluunt venis: Totum e<U+017F>t pro vulnere cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We may <U+017F>ee by the<U+017F>e and <U+017F>everal other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments,
which I omit for brevities <U+017F>ake,
that the <U+017F>everal Members and Parts of the
Body have their <U+017F>everal Sub<U+017F>tances, which do
not work by their proper Poy<U+017F>ons, but by the
Diffu<U+017F>ion of their Radiant Virtues; which
cannot be remedied, but by the Radiation of
contrary Sub<U+017F>tances which de<U+017F>troy tho<U+017F>e ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous
qualities, even as the <U+017F>hadows and
darkne<U+017F><U+017F>es cannot be de<U+017F>troyed but by the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30448:27"/>
Radiation of Light. From all the<U+017F>e things it
is evident, that there is nothing in Nature
without that virtue of Radiation, in<U+017F>erted
by the Author of Nature, for tho<U+017F>e ends be<U+017F>t
known to him<U+017F>elf, and in imitation of the
Light, in<U+017F>omuch, that the Judicious Reader,
by this Doctrine of <hi>Actinoboli<U+017F>ms,</hi> and that of
<hi>Magneti<U+017F>ms,</hi> may as with two Wings <U+017F>oar to
the highe<U+017F>t knowledge of Natural things.
He that will be further <U+017F>atisfied in examples
of that nature, let him read <hi>Skenkius de
Venenis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the<U+017F>e mu<U+017F>t be added what we have
<U+017F>aid before, to wit, That the Specifick Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
of each Medicine that enters into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ition,
remain in it after the lo<U+017F>s of their
fir<U+017F>t qualities which may be proved by this
Experiment.</p>
            <p>Take <hi>Nettles,</hi> dry them, and burn them
to a<U+017F>hes, make Lees of tho<U+017F>e a<U+017F>hes; expo<U+017F>e
the Lees in the night to the Air, till it be
covered with an Icy thin Skin, and you <U+017F>hall
<U+017F>ee in that Skin the perfect figure of a <hi>Nettle,</hi>
with the <U+017F>tretching of its fibers and jagged
Leaves, as if it were a Natural one; and if
you look upon it with a Magnifying Gla<U+017F>s,
you <U+017F>hall perceive with admiration all the
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igure of the <hi>Nettle,</hi> grown out of <U+017F>mall and
<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lmo<U+017F>t infinite number of <U+017F>mall Cellules. Th
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30448:28"/>
<U+017F>ame will happen in any other Plant, to <U+017F>hew
that no Seed can be <U+017F>o exactly mixed with
other things, but it will retain and affect
<U+017F>till its own Nature. All this that we have
<U+017F>aid, tendeth to <U+017F>hew how <hi>Coral</hi> bringeth to
pa<U+017F>s all tho<U+017F>e wonderful Virtues we have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed
to it. Tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>hall de<U+017F>ire to be
better <U+017F>atisfied in this Doctrine of Actinobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<U+017F>m
and Radiation, let them <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
the Pla<U+017F>tical Virtue of all Seeds, in which,
being <U+017F>eated in the ab<U+017F>tru<U+017F>e<U+017F>t parts of the
Body, doth without any tools or noi<U+017F>e,
produce a work <U+017F>o wonderful in variety and
comline<U+017F>s of Parts, and that, out of a rough
and inform matter, in which there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tinction
of parts, nor variety that may be
ob<U+017F>erved by the Sen<U+017F>es. For we <U+017F>ee that in
the Seed, without any appearance lieth and
lurketh the whole Tree, with the Roots, the
Body, the Boughs, the Leaves, and the Fruits.
Out of one Corn of Wheat, proceedeth the
Root, the Stalk, the Ear, and the Corn. In
an Egg, which is the Seed of Birds, lurketh
the whole Bird, with all, and every one of its
Limbs, and all the differences of its colours.
In the Seed lieth the Body of the Animals
with all its Limbs, the Heart, the Brains, the
Lungs, the Liver, the Spleen, the Stomach,
the Kidneys, the Bladder, the Nerves, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30448:28"/>
Mu<U+017F>cles, Veins, Arteries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Every
one of which hath its proper and certain
figure, its colour, and proprieties. Who <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth
<U+017F>o many various things hidden in an
Homogeneal Body, who <U+017F>eparateth an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
Matter into Bones, Humors, Fle<U+017F>h,
Gri<U+017F>tles? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> None other certainly, but that
Pla<U+017F>tical Virtue which the Almighty hath
in<U+017F>erted into all things that were to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated
by Generation. This Virtue giveth
to every Limb its due <U+017F>cituation, colour, figure,
proportion, and quality: By its workman<U+017F>hip
the Body is hollowed into <U+017F>o many Pipes,
Chanels, Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, and Meanders. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
we <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, that the <U+017F>ame Pla<U+017F>tical Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
is diffu<U+017F>ed in all the parts of the Seed:
So that it is all in all, and all in every part of
the Seed.</p>
            <p>The rea<U+017F>on is, That the Productions are
<U+017F>ometimes but one, and <U+017F>ometimes many;
and that the Production that cometh from
one part of the Seed, is no le<U+017F>s perfect than
that which cometh from the whole: And
finally, that there is no confu<U+017F>ion nor inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination
of parts, which of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity <U+017F>hould
happen, if it were not uniform with the
Subject; for if one part of the Seed were
taken away, one part of the Production
<U+017F>hould al<U+017F>o be wanting. And thus <U+017F>hould
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30448:29"/>
happen a Confu<U+017F>ion in the Figure by the
tran<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of the parts: And although
the Seed, in order to the Sen<U+017F>es, <U+017F>eem to have
no di<U+017F>tinct and heterogeneal parts; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thele<U+017F>s,
being con<U+017F>idered in it <U+017F>elf, it hath:
Seeing that it is not a <U+017F>ingle, but a Body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
of many; for that part of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tick
Virtue which frameth the Brains, <U+017F>hall
not frame the Heart or the Liver; and that
part which hath framed the Bones, <U+017F>hall not
<U+017F>tretch the Membranes, or di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e the Guts
into a winding compa<U+017F>s. The only difficulty
is, Why that Pla<U+017F>tick Virtue, which is <U+017F>o
confu<U+017F>edly mixed, yet, worketh without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu<U+017F>ion,
and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>eth of all things with an
admirable order, and as the Greeks call it
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But this concerning not our Subject at
pre<U+017F>ent, we pa<U+017F>s it over, being contented to
have <U+017F>tirred up the curious Reader to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation
and Study of the <hi>Magneti<U+017F>ms</hi> and
<hi>Actinoboli<U+017F>ms,</hi> in which he <U+017F>hall find matter
enough to <U+017F>atisfie him<U+017F>elf in the proce<U+017F>s of
Nature, and in the admiration and love of
the Creator. But this digre<U+017F><U+017F>ion hath pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed
a little already the bounds of our Subject, let
us go back from whence we came.</p>
            <p>We conclude then, That the Tincture of
<hi>Coral</hi> being <U+017F>ep<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rated from the Body of it;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30448:29"/>
the pure from the impure; the formal from
the material; the Cele<U+017F>tial from the Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trial,
it worketh by its A<gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inoboli<U+017F>m or Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation,
and its Magneti<U+017F>m; by which it is
Analogal to the Heart, the Fountain of Life,
tho<U+017F>e wonderful Effects we have made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of, we will de<U+017F>cend to <U+017F>ome particular
In<U+017F>tances.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30448:30"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the Virtues of the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi>
in the Curing of all Malignant and
Pe<U+017F>tilential Feavers.</head>
            <p>WE give this in<U+017F>tance fir<U+017F>t, as the mo<U+017F>t
con<U+017F>iderable, and of greate<U+017F>t concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
The<U+017F>e Feavers under the notion and
name of a Cold, having de<U+017F>troyed <U+017F>o many of
late, that a Body cannot without grief, and a
certain horror, read the increa<U+017F>e of the Bill of
Mortality upon this particular point, while
the Patients flatter them<U+017F>elves that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but a Cold; and the Phy<U+017F>icians, either
by ignorance, wilfulne<U+017F>s, or mutual Envy,
pre<U+017F>cribe Bleeding, Purging, Bli<U+017F>tering, and
<U+017F>uch other dangerous and prepo<U+017F>terous
means; which though they may <U+017F>ometimes
be u<U+017F>ed in other Feavers, yet in this are they
Mortal.</p>
            <p>As fir<U+017F>t for Bleeding, it hath always been
condemned by the mo<U+017F>t judicious in Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
and Pe<U+017F>tilential Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, by rea<U+017F>on that
it weakneth Nature, by exhau<U+017F>ting the Blood
wherein the Life con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth, by dimini<U+017F>hing
the Spirits which are the tie of the Soul with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30448:30"/>
the Body, and by <U+017F>uffering the venemous
quality to rage the more by <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tracting that
<U+017F>weet and Natural Juyce, which was rather
to be incouraged for the taming and allaying
of it.</p>
            <p>Purging is neither to be admitted, unle<U+017F>s
there be an extraordinary fulne<U+017F>s of Humors,
it being <U+017F>ufficient to keep the Body <U+017F>oluble;
as al<U+017F>o, becau<U+017F>e in tho<U+017F>e Feavers there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
a perturbation of Humors, which Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
cannot <U+017F>egregate, till they be perfectly
concocted, and appear <U+017F>o by the Urines, and
the <U+017F>lacking of the bad Symptoms. <hi>Concocta
medicari oportet non cruda,</hi> <U+017F>aith <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As little <U+017F>ignificant as the<U+017F>e, is the new way
they go about by Bli<U+017F>tering; for whereas this
Pe<U+017F>tilential Feaver hath its <U+017F>eat in the Spirits,
what communion is there between their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity
and Bli<U+017F>ters, which do not reach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
the skin, <U+017F>et the whole frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
in torture and angui<U+017F>h, and cut the
troath of the Patient before the Wounds can
be cicratrized? This practice <U+017F>eeming only
invented to beget Apothecaries practi<U+017F>e and
Phy<U+017F>icians <U+017F>omewhat to <U+017F>ay, when they are at
their wits end.</p>
            <p>Now nothing remaineth to overcome <U+017F>o
powerful an enemy but <hi>Cordials,</hi> <U+017F>o called,
becau<U+017F>e, without doing any violence to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30448:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:30448:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:30448:32"/>
or weakening her <U+017F>trength, they directly
go to the Heart, chear it up, fight again<U+017F>t
the malignity; and as a Light di<U+017F>per<U+017F>eth
darkne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>o do the<U+017F>e, any thing that is ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
to Mans life. Which being done, that
whol<U+017F>ome temper, in which con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth Life
and Health, taketh place again, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
is re<U+017F>tored to his former <U+017F>tate.</p>
            <p>Under that name of <hi>Cordials,</hi> every one
almo<U+017F>t obtrudeth what his own fancy and
imagination thinketh, or hath heard to be <U+017F>o,
though it be but a <U+017F>imple Di<U+017F>tilled Water,
coloured with <U+017F>ome Sirrup; and thus trifle
away the mo<U+017F>t precious thing of the World,
which is time (as <hi>C<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<U+017F>iphon</hi> <U+017F>aith) while the
malignity gets footing, and never cea<U+017F>eth till
it hath de<U+017F>troyed the Patient.</p>
            <p>Now, as we do not deny that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
of tho<U+017F>e Remedies called <hi>Cordials,</hi>
in Nature; <U+017F>o we deny that it is every ones
Talent to know them, or the u<U+017F>e of them,
or the preparation of them. As for example,
What good can be expected from the Water
of a Plant Di<U+017F>tilled in a Mettallick Furnace,
having been fir<U+017F>t irrorated or <U+017F>teeped in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Water, that the greater quantity may
be drawn, as it is now commonly practi<U+017F>ed.
Be<U+017F>ides the inconveniency of the Metallick
quality of the Limbeck which communicateth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30448:32"/>
it <U+017F>elf to the Water, as it is evidently <U+017F>een,
and have often tried my <U+017F>elf: For having
occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>everal times to pre<U+017F>cribe Mineral
Waters, as that of <hi>Ep<U+017F>om, Tunbridge, &amp;c.</hi>
to <U+017F>everal Patients, and among them, to my
own Daughter. It fell out, that the Water
which was brought from the Wells in Bottles,
did agree very well with them, and wrought
effectually without any violence; but when,
by the want of that, I was forced to make u<U+017F>e
of that which they fell in Town, and keep
in Leaden Ci<U+017F>terns, I found a contrary effect;
for it wrought <U+017F>o untowardly, that it fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
me every time; which I could attribute
to nothing el<U+017F>e, but to the poy<U+017F>onous quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the Lead, of which the Ci<U+017F>terns were
made, and in which the Waters were kept.
By this we <U+017F>ee what a nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary thing it is, in
<U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>es, and many others, That a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ician
<U+017F>hould be his own Apothecary; and
this I <U+017F>peak meerly for the intere<U+017F>t of the
truth, being not ignorant how many inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed
per<U+017F>ons will contradict it.</p>
            <p>Having <U+017F>et down all the<U+017F>e Notions, it is
al<U+017F>o requi<U+017F>ite we <U+017F>hould <U+017F>et down the u<U+017F>e of
our Tincture of <hi>Coral;</hi> therefore a<U+017F><U+017F>oon as
one falleth into that Malignant or Pe<U+017F>tilential
Feaver, which is known chiefly by the <U+017F>mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
quickne<U+017F>s, and intermittency of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30448:33"/>
Pul<U+017F>e, let him go to Bed in a warm Room,
and being well covered to <U+017F>weat, let him
drink one do<U+017F>e of our Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi>
<U+017F>weating after, as long as he is a able; and let
him follow exactly the method we have <U+017F>et
down in our Book of the la<U+017F>t great Plague,
<hi>Anno</hi> 1665. The particulars of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
this, we <U+017F>hall repeat here, becau<U+017F>e
the Book is hard to be had, there having been
three Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed in <U+017F>ix weeks time,
and none to be had at pre<U+017F>ent, that I know:
Therefore I <U+017F>hall repeat to this purpo<U+017F>e, only
the XXX. XXXI. XXXII. XXXIII. XXXIV.
XXXV. XXXVI. <hi>Aphori<U+017F>mes mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="instructions">
                        <div n="30" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXX.</head>
                           <p>A<U+017F><U+017F>oon as any one findeth him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>tricken
with any of the<U+017F>e Symptoms, to wit, a Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake,
Vomiting, Faintne<U+017F>s, Loo<U+017F>ene<U+017F>s, and a
<U+017F>mall quick and intermitting Pul<U+017F>e, without
any prejacent or evident cau<U+017F>e, let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently
repair to a clean and warm Room,
and let a light fire of Wood be kindled in
the Chimney, to con<U+017F>ume and de<U+017F>troy all the
infectious vapors that proceed both from the
Air, and the infected party. Let the Patient
be pre<U+017F>ently put into a warm Bed him<U+017F>elf,
wrapped in a Sheet and Blanket, having
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30448:33"/>
fir<U+017F>t put off his Shirt, that when he cometh
to be dried, you may not be put to the trouble
of pulling off his wet Shirt, then give him
one do<U+017F>e of our Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
him with Cloaths very warm all over,
leaving only his re<U+017F>piration free, and putting
a warm Brick to the Soles of his Feet, and
another to his Knees; let him <U+017F>weat as long as
he is able, or at lea<U+017F>t, for the <U+017F>pace of three
or four hours, and be not afraid he <U+017F>hould
faint, if he hath breath enough.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="31" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXI.</head>
                           <p>If it <U+017F>hould happen, as it doth commonly
to tho<U+017F>e that are fir<U+017F>t taken with a vomiting,
that the Patient <U+017F>hould ca<U+017F>t up the <hi>Cordial,</hi>
you mu<U+017F>t give him another do<U+017F>e; and if he
<U+017F>hould ca<U+017F>t up this al<U+017F>o, give him a third,
and <U+017F>o continue <U+017F>till till he keepeth it once,
for he will never ca<U+017F>t it up afterwards; and
though he <U+017F>hould, yet by having taken it <U+017F>o
often, <U+017F>ome of the qualities of it will remain
behind, that will work their effect.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="32" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXII.</head>
                           <p>Children that cannot or will not take the
Remedy, mu<U+017F>t be compelled to it by pouring
it into their Throat with an In<U+017F>trument, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                              </gap>, which is a kind of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30448:34"/>
Spoon with a cover, having a <U+017F>pout to put
into the Mouth, and <U+017F>o to pour it down.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="33" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXIII.</head>
                           <p>The Patient having <U+017F>weated three or four
hours, the more the better, you mu<U+017F>t give
him a little more breath, and began to take
off the Cloaths by degrees; and when you
have dried him very well with warm Cloaths
(which all this while mu<U+017F>t hang by the fire
with his Shirt) then pull away the wet Sheet
and Blanket from under him, then give him
his Shirt, and after that, dry his Head, and
take heed, by all means, that any cold Air
<U+017F>hould come into the Room. After you have
dried his Head <U+017F>ufficiently, and that the party
beginneth to be cool, give him to drink lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urely,
two ounces of our <hi>Cordial</hi> Water, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribed
in the <U+017F>aid Book of the <hi>Plague,</hi> which
is of an admirable virtue in this ca<U+017F>e, and al<U+017F>o
in Faintne<U+017F><U+017F>es, Surfeittings, and Poy<U+017F>ons,
This will refre<U+017F>h him <U+017F>o <U+017F>peedily and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
that he will pre<U+017F>ently forget the tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>omne<U+017F>s
of his <U+017F>weating.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="34" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXIV.</head>
                           <p>When he is quite cold, give him to eat
any thing he hath a mind to; <U+017F>o that it be of
good Juyce, and ea<U+017F>ie dige<U+017F>tion: Let his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30448:34"/>
drink be <U+017F>trong Beer, lukewarm, or <U+017F>ome Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
Claret Wine; for, as we have <U+017F>aid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
this Feaver differeth from all others.
And whereas in others we <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tract Meat, and
<U+017F>trong Drink, as much as we can, we mu<U+017F>t in
this allow them, it being only a malignant
quality, in which, good Meat and Drink can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
hurt, but rather allay it, as al<U+017F>o becau<U+017F>e
the Patient would not be able to <U+017F>weat twice
a day in this manner (which of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity he
mu<U+017F>t do, if he will <U+017F>ave his life) unle<U+017F>s his
<U+017F>trength be repaired with good nutriment.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="35" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXV.</head>
                           <p>This cour<U+017F>e of Sweating twice a day, mu<U+017F>t
be continued for four days together or five at
the mo<U+017F>t, in which <U+017F>pace of time, all the
Malignity and Pe<U+017F>tilential Poy<U+017F>on will expire;
and, if this be carefully done, and attended,
there is no Malignant or Pe<U+017F>tilential Feaver
<U+017F>o <U+017F>tubborn of any kind what<U+017F>oever, but mu<U+017F>t
yield.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="36" type="instruction">
                           <head>XXXVI.</head>
                           <p>Although the danger be over in four days,
yet will it not be ami<U+017F>s to make u<U+017F>e <U+017F>till of
<hi>Cordials</hi> now and then; for it is not only
nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to dive away the Pe<U+017F>tilential Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but al<U+017F>o to <U+017F>trengthen the noble parts,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30448:35"/>
upon which it may have made an impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion,
the malignity of a thing being not only in the
Cau<U+017F>e, but al<U+017F>o in the parts to whom the
cau<U+017F>e did adhere.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Thus much have I tran<U+017F>cribed out of my
Book of the <hi>Plague,</hi> for the ea<U+017F>e and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency
of the Reader, and for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
the u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>o noble a Remedy, as the
Tincture of <hi>Coral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <U+017F>eeing that this Tincture is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini<U+017F>tred
with our admirable Water again<U+017F>t
the Plague, and Malignant Feavers, and
that the Sub<U+017F>tance of both is more formal then
material, not la<U+017F>ting long in the Body; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the do<U+017F>e is to be renewed every day, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
about three hours of Interval between
every do<U+017F>e, be<U+017F>ides one do<U+017F>e in the night, if
the Patient awakes. If this be carefully done,
there is no Malignant Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e but may be
cured.</p>
            <p>But as a Gardner that will carefully bring
up a Plant, taketh care to weed it often, le<U+017F>t
it <U+017F>hould be choaked or want nouri<U+017F>hment.
So that I may <U+017F>how the beauty of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,
I mu<U+017F>t extirpate <U+017F>everal Weeds that
have crept in of late into the Family of
Remedies, to the delu<U+017F>ion of the Patients, and
the irri<U+017F>ion of ignorant Phy<U+017F>icians.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:30448:35"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the dangerous and poy<U+017F>onous quality
and u<U+017F>e of Bli<U+017F>tering Play<U+017F>ters, and
that they ought to be exterminated
out of the Number and Family of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</head>
            <p>MAny times when a Phy<U+017F>ician is at his
wits end, and hath nothing to <U+017F>ay
more concerning the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e in hand, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribeth
Bli<U+017F>tering, not knowing nor di<U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>hing
whether it will be fitting or not.
And there is <U+017F>ome policy in that too; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides
the obligation, he layeth upon h<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Friend
the Apothecary, him<U+017F>elf is not without hope
of benefit, and of being <U+017F>ent for, the more
often whiles the wounds are green; but what
good this can do, or which way, chiefly in a
Malignant Feaver, you mu<U+017F>t not ask, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
cannot tell, but only, that it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
practice of the Town. Which, if it be
a <U+017F>atisfactory an<U+017F>wer, let every body judge.
If this abu<U+017F>e had been harmle<U+017F>s, I would
have pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed over it, as I do over many others
that I know, and do only range among the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30448:36"/>
Vulgar Errors. But <U+017F>eeing it tendeth to the
de<U+017F>truction of mankind, as I have <U+017F>een by
many <U+017F>ad and woful experiences, and <U+017F>hall
prove by many grave and Authentical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>in again<U+017F>t my Con<U+017F>cience,
Rea<U+017F>on, Knowledge, and Experience, if I
did not lay open the cheat thereof, in favor
of a gallant Nation, among which I live and
am <U+017F>o humanely protected.</p>
            <p>Be it known therefore, that there is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
now practi<U+017F>ed in Phy<U+017F>ick called by the
<hi>Greeks</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap> from the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>,
which in <hi>Latine</hi> <U+017F>ignifieth <hi>Attraho,</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<U+017F>h,
to draw</hi> or <hi>attract,</hi> which was invented
by the Ancients, chiefly to comfort the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
of tho<U+017F>e parts which come by cold, or
too much moi<U+017F>ture, whence it is evident, that
all tho<U+017F>e Remedies are exceeding hot, dry, and
<U+017F>harp. Of the<U+017F>e <U+017F>orts are <hi>Mu<U+017F>tard-Seed, Thap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ia,
Goats Dung, Cre<U+017F><U+017F>es-Seed, Eliampanes
Roots,</hi> the <hi>Sea Onion, Pigeons Dung, Mice
Dung, Lice-Bean, Cantharides,</hi> and <U+017F>uch
like; of which, at pre<U+017F>ent the Modern Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icians,
and namely the Di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>atory of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
have framed a Plai<U+017F>ter for that purpo<U+017F>e,
called <hi>Empla<U+017F>trum Epi<U+017F>pa<U+017F>ticon,</hi> of which, here
is the de<U+017F>cription.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:30448:36"/>
                        <head>Empla<U+017F>trum Epi<U+017F>pa<U+017F>ticum.</head>
                        <p>R. Sinapeas.</p>
                        <p>Eupborbii.</p>
                        <p>Piperis longi ana drachmam unam <U+017F>emis:</p>
                        <p>Staphi<U+017F>agriae.</p>
                        <p>Pyrethri, ana drachmas duas.</p>
                        <p>Gummi Ammoniaci.</p>
                        <p>Galbani.</p>
                        <p>Bdellii.</p>
                        <p>Sagapeni, ana drachmas tres.</p>
                        <p>Cantharidum integrarum drachmas quinque.</p>
                        <p>Picis navalis.</p>
                        <p>Re<U+017F>inae.</p>
                        <p>Cerae citrinae ana drachmas <U+017F>ex.</p>
                        <p>Terebinthinae, quantum <U+017F>ufficit, fiat Empla<U+017F>trum
u<U+017F>ui reponendum.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now, as I will not deny but that Plai<U+017F>ter
may be u<U+017F>eful in <U+017F>ome ca<U+017F>es, if it be judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ly
applied; <U+017F>o I affirm, that it is of a
dangerous efficacy, if it be mi<U+017F>applied, and
chiefly upon tender Bodies, extenuated by
Sickne<U+017F>s, Fa<U+017F>ting, Watching, and Pains;
the Rea<U+017F>on is, That the <hi>Cantharides</hi> or <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>h
Flies,</hi> which are the <hi>Ba<U+017F>is</hi> of it, are a
mo<U+017F>t deadly Poy<U+017F>on, and a particular enemy
to the Bladder and Genital Parts, which is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30448:37"/>
<U+017F>o much the more prevalent, in that <U+017F>ome
Apothecaries of their own accord to make the
Plai<U+017F>ter of a more quick working, have aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
the do<U+017F>e of the <hi>Cantharides.</hi> So that
when this Plai<U+017F>ter is applied to one <U+017F>ick of a
Malignant Feaver, and already extenuated
with the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e of Fa<U+017F>ting and Watching, he
hath good luck if he e<U+017F>cape with life. Tho<U+017F>e
that are for it, may chance to urge their own
experience, again<U+017F>t which I <U+017F>hall oppo<U+017F>e mine,
which is of forty years <U+017F>tanding; but becau<U+017F>e
neither they or I <U+017F>hould be believed, as being
Partial, I <U+017F>hall cite here <U+017F>ome memorable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervations
made by <U+017F>everal learned, hone<U+017F>t,
and famous Authors, to clear this point,
which is of <U+017F>o great a con<U+017F>equence.</p>
            <p>I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>peak here of the dangers and
cruel Symptoms that follow the taking of
<hi>Cantharides</hi> inwardly, becau<U+017F>e they are <U+017F>o
generally known, that no body can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
thereof, but tho<U+017F>e that are altogether
ignorant of Phy<U+017F>ick, I <U+017F>hall only mention
the pernicious effects, and <U+017F>ad con<U+017F>equences
they cau<U+017F>e, being applied outwardly. The
fir<U+017F>t Ob<U+017F>ervation <U+017F>hall be taken out of <hi>Guiliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
Fabricius Hildanus,</hi> a late Author, and
excellent Phy<U+017F>ician and Chirurgeon in <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland,</hi>
in his Ninety and eighth Ob<U+017F>erva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:30448:37"/>
A certain Gentleman of the Town of
<hi>Villeneuve,</hi> by the Lake of <hi>Geneva,</hi> having a
cold Tumor in one of his Knees, cau<U+017F>ed by a
cold, and tough Humor, did ask a Barbers
advice, who without taking notice of the
Antecedent Cau<U+017F>e, went about to cure him
only with Topical Remedies; therefore he
applied fir<U+017F>t Cupping Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, after that a
Cautery on the <U+017F>ide of the Kneepan, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to empty the Matter that was gathered.
When the<U+017F>e did not <U+017F>ucceed, he applied a
Pulte<U+017F>s made with <hi>Leaven</hi> and <hi>Cantharides,</hi>
and did exulcerate all the Knee, then follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
an exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive pain about the Knee, re<U+017F>tle<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
a Feaver, and <U+017F>everal other fearful
Symptoms; among which, was a grievous
pain of the Reins, and of all the Belly, and
pre<U+017F>ently after <U+017F>uch a heat in his Urine, that
he could not make one drop (for it came only
drop by drop, and that Bloody) without the
greate<U+017F>t torture imaginable. The Pulte<U+017F>s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
removed, he was <U+017F>omething the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e
it had drawn the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ubtle part of the
Humor: Which when the Barber <U+017F>aw, he
applied again the <U+017F>ame Pulte<U+017F>s of <hi>Cantharides,</hi>
upon which all the <U+017F>aid Symptoms became
wor<U+017F>e than before, and chiefly the heat of
Urine, which the Patient feeling would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
no more of the <U+017F>aid Pulte<U+017F>s, but di<U+017F>mi<U+017F>t
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30448:38"/>
his Barber, and after came to me to <hi>Lau<U+017F>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi>
where having prepared fir<U+017F>t his Body with
opening <hi>Apozemes,</hi> I purged him <U+017F>everal
times with the aggregative Pills, and tho<U+017F>e of
Her modacts; and after that, gave him the
decoction of <hi>Guaiacum, Sa<U+017F><U+017F>afra<U+017F>s,</hi> and <hi>China,</hi>
cau<U+017F>ing him to <U+017F>weat gently, that the Matter
about the Knee might melt and evaporate,
after that I applied this Pulte<U+017F>s of <hi>Vigo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                     <body>
                        <div type="recipe">
                           <head><U+211E>. Farinae Fabarum.</head>
                           <p>Farinae hordei, an. <U+2125> iv.</p>
                           <p>Furfuris bene triturati M. ij.</p>
                           <p>Stercoris Caprini triturati <abbr>lb</abbr>. <U+017F>s.</p>
                           <p>Meliloti an. m. 1. cum Lixivio &amp; Sapa <U+017F>ufficienti
de omnibus fiat Empla<U+017F>trum <U+017F>olidum addendo
olei Camomelini &amp; Anethini ana <U+2125> ij, appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur
calide bis in die.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <hi>When he had u<U+017F>ed this
Pulte<U+017F>s a whole moneth together, he recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
his health. You <U+017F>hall find the like exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in</hi> Joh. Langius, Lib. 1. Epi<U+017F>t. 47.</p>
            <p>The third Ob<U+017F>ervation <U+017F>hall be taken out of
<hi>Baccius,</hi> in <hi>Prolegomenis Venenorum &amp; Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotorum,</hi>
where he <U+017F>aith, <hi>We find by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
that</hi> Cantharides <hi>being mixed in Bli<U+017F>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Plai<U+017F>ters, and applied, do mo<U+017F>t violently
corrode the Stomach and the Belly; but above
all, to be by its property a peculiar enemy to the
Bladder, and to tear it in pieces with its
Bloody <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine, and <U+017F>o to kill the Patients. For</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:30448:38"/>
               <hi>we have ob<U+017F>erved many times, that when</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharides
<hi>have been applied to the Head in a
Lethargy, and to the Brawns of the Arms and
Legs; they have cau<U+017F>ed an extream pain, with
an inflammation and difficulty of Bloody <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine,
and <U+017F>o have killed the Patients. Which danger
de<U+017F>erves a <U+017F>erious con<U+017F>ideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Ob<U+017F>ervation is out of <hi>Bra<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volus,
Comm. ad Aphor.</hi> 17. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. who <U+017F>aith,
That one <hi>Vincentinus Grema,</hi> a famous Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon
in his time, took once a Medicine,
the Powders of which had been <U+017F>tamped in
a Morter, where <hi>Cantharides,</hi> had been <U+017F>tamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
before: Whereupon, though he did not
actually eat any <hi>Cantharides,</hi> yet was he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriated
from the Mouth to the Fundament,
and could not get his health again in le<U+017F>s then
eighteen Moneths <U+017F>pace; yet were there no
<hi>Cantharides</hi> in the ca<U+017F>e, but a kind of quality
proceeding from them that <U+017F>tuck about the
Morter.</p>
            <p>The fifth Ob<U+017F>ervation is out of <hi>Bartholomeus
Montagnana,</hi> a famous Phy<U+017F>ician of <hi>Italy,</hi> who
relateth, That one <hi>Francis Brac,</hi> a Citizen of
<hi>Padua,</hi> having applied <U+017F>ome <hi>Cantharides</hi> to
his Knee, did avoid by Urine above Five
pounds of Blood; and that the <U+017F>ame did
happen to one who applied them to his great
Toe, to take away the roughne<U+017F>s and uneven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30448:39"/>
of his Nails. <hi>Langius, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Epi<U+017F>t.</hi>
47.</p>
            <p>But what is more incredible then this is,
That a certain Chirurgeon of <hi>Milan,</hi> made
twice Bloody water, for carrying in his Pocket
a Ve<U+017F>icatory made of <hi>Cantharides.</hi> Thus
affirmeth, <hi>Joan. Michael Pa<U+017F>chalius, Method.
Curand. Morb. cap.</hi> 44.</p>
            <p>The <U+017F>ixth Ob<U+017F>ervation is of a certain Man
who carrying by chance <hi>Cantharides</hi> in his
Pocket, as the fa<U+017F>hion is of <U+017F>ome Chirurgeons,
did make Bloody Urine; and complaining to
me of it, I bid him he <U+017F>hould not meddle with
them, no not <U+017F>o much as to touch them, or
carry them in his Pocket. Such another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident,
I was told by <hi>Helidaeus de Paduinis,</hi>
a famous Phy<U+017F>ician of <hi>Bolonia,</hi> with whom
I u<U+017F>ed to vi<U+017F>it <U+017F>ick people, when I was at <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia.</hi>
The mo<U+017F>t famous Phy<U+017F>ician <hi>Adolphus
Occo</hi> in his <hi>Ob<U+017F>ervations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <U+017F>eventh Ob<U+017F>ervation is of a Noble Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
who having her Face full of red, burning,
and ugly Pimples, was <U+017F>o deformed therewith,
that every Body avoided her as a Leper, and
the Magi<U+017F>trates were ready to <U+017F>eque<U+017F>ter her
from the common <U+017F>ociety of Mankind. She
came to <hi>Paris,</hi> where having called for two
Doctors of Phy<U+017F>ick, to wit, <hi>Hollerius</hi> and
<hi>Grealmus,</hi> and two Chirurgeons Mr. <hi>Cabal,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:30448:39"/>
and my <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>he inquired with great care and
diligence, if there was no remedy again<U+017F>t
<U+017F>uch a deformity. Having con<U+017F>idered dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, we unanimou<U+017F>ly concluded
that it was no Lepro<U+017F>ie, but that it was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
that a Ve<U+017F>icatory made of <hi>Cantharides</hi>
<U+017F>hould be applied all the Face over, three or
four hours after her Bladder began to ake,
and to burn vehemently, and the Neck of the
Womb, to <U+017F>well with gripings, a continual
vomiting, and making of water, a raving
carriage of all her Limbs, and a Burning Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.
I called for the Phy<U+017F>icians again pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently;
the conclu<U+017F>ion was, That we <U+017F>hould
give her much Milk to drink, and inject <U+017F>ome
in the Guts by the Fundament, and into the
Womb and Bladder by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rethra;</hi> that <U+017F>he
<U+017F>hould go into a lukewarm Bath, wherein
<U+017F>hould have been boiled <hi>Lin<U+017F>eeds,</hi> the Roots
and Leaves of <hi>Mallows</hi> and <hi>Mar<U+017F>h-Mallows,</hi>
of <hi>Violets, Hemlock, Pur<U+017F>leine,</hi> and <hi>Lettice;</hi>
and <U+017F>o to continue, from time to time, till the
pain was quite cea<U+017F>ed. That the Reins and
Genital Parts <U+017F>hould be anointed with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum
Ro<U+017F>atum</hi> and <hi>Populeon,</hi> di<U+017F><U+017F>olved
and mixed with <hi>Oxycrat.</hi> By the<U+017F>e means all
the Symptomes vani<U+017F>hed away, in the mean
time the Face was full of Bli<U+017F>ters, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
broke, a great deal of Matter i<U+017F><U+017F>ued out,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30448:40"/>
and the deformity was cured, in<U+017F>omuch, that
a little while after <U+017F>he was married, and had
many Children. <hi>Ambro<U+017F>ius Paraeus, Lib.</hi> 5.
<hi>cap.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>For my own part I can certifie, that my
younge<U+017F>t Daughter <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> being about
thirteen or fourteen years old, and very <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
to <U+017F>ore eyes; after I had purged her, and
let her blood in the foot, I applied a Ve<U+017F>ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
of <hi>Cantharides,</hi> at the bottom of her
neck, thinking to make a diver<U+017F>ion of the
Humor, but within three or four hour after
<U+017F>he fell <U+017F>tark lame of her right hip, <U+017F>o that I
was forced pre<U+017F>ently to remove the Ve<U+017F>ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;
and for all that, the lamene<U+017F>s continued
three or four weeks after. By what I have
<U+017F>aid, it is apparent what a dangerous thing
<hi>Cantharides</hi> is, not only inwardly given, in
which ca<U+017F>e they are a deadly poy<U+017F>on, but al<U+017F>o
outwardly applied; as is <U+017F>een by the <U+017F>everal
Ob<U+017F>ervations I have made here, and many
more may be taken out of <hi>Fore<U+017F>tus, Cabrolius,
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could al<U+017F>o here relate <U+017F>ome fatal Ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
of my own, and of which, I have
been a <U+017F>ad eye-witne<U+017F>s; but that I do not
love to renew the grief of the living Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
nor to in<U+017F>ult on the mi<U+017F>carriage of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icians,
knowing that we are all faulty, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30448:40"/>
that again<U+017F>t death we have no power but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulne<U+017F>s.</p>
            <p>From the<U+017F>e things we may perceive the
truth of what <hi>Mathiolus</hi> <U+017F>aith upon the Sixth
Book of <hi>Dio<U+017F>corides,</hi> where he hath the<U+017F>e
words.</p>
            <p>Cantharides <hi>are hurtful chiefly to the Bladder,
and to all the parts that <U+017F>erve for the evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine, not only being taken inwardly,
but al<U+017F>o being applied outwardly where there is
occa<U+017F>ion to Bli<U+017F>ter, chiefly when they are mixed
with large Pulte<U+017F><U+017F>es, and are applied to places
near the Bladder, to wit, the Hips, the Privy
Parts, the Kidneys, or the Stones.</hi> Thus far
<hi>Mathiolus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore if any Body will make u<U+017F>e of
them, it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary he <U+017F>hould do it prudently
and circum<U+017F>pectly, chiefly let the young Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icians
take heed, lea<U+017F>t in pre<U+017F>cribing Remedies
which admit of <hi>Cantharides,</hi> they do not
err in quantity; for becau<U+017F>e <hi>Cantharides</hi> are
<U+017F>o light, that fifty of them weigh <U+017F>carce one
drachm, the Error is ea<U+017F>ie to be committed.
Nay, the mo<U+017F>t ingenuous of the Apothecaries
have confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed to me, that in the Di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of their <hi>Empla<U+017F>trum Epi<U+017F>pa<U+017F>ticon,</hi> they
double the do<U+017F>e of <hi>Cantharides</hi> to make it of
a quicker working. Who <U+017F>hall be <U+017F>o bold after
this, to make u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>o pernicious a Remedy,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30448:41"/>
and chiefly in Malignant Feavers, where the
Poy<U+017F>on is inward, the Vitals dejected, the
Natural <U+017F>trength abated, and no good can be
alledged to come out of this Remedy? All
the excu<U+017F>e being, that it is a common practice
about the Town, that is, a common and a
pernicious Vulgar Error. Away then with
tho<U+017F>e dangerous things, more pe<U+017F>tilent many
times then the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf; and let us turn
our practi<U+017F>e to a <U+017F>afer and nobler way, that is,
our Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> which without danger,
but rather with a great deal of plea<U+017F>ure, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth
in Malignant Feavers, and other di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es,
we have or <U+017F>hall mention, the three <U+017F>o
much required Indications, for the relief of
the Patient, and the honor of the Phy<U+017F>ician,
to wit, <hi>Cito, tuto, jucunde.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:30448:41"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the Virtue of the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi>
in all Feavers and Agues.</head>
            <p>I Have ranged the<U+017F>e two Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es under one
Head, becau<U+017F>e they are of the <U+017F>ame Nature,
except that Feavers are continual, and Agues
intermittent, but both to be cured the <U+017F>ame
way.</p>
            <p>I am not here to expre<U+017F>s the Nature of all
Feavers, which belongeth to the general
knowledge of Phy<U+017F>ick, and would <U+017F>well
this little Treati<U+017F>e into a Volume, but to
touch as much of them as will <U+017F>erve our own
intention, and to <U+017F>hew how the Tincture of
<hi>Coral</hi> is, and may be a Sovereign Remedy for
them: Therefore leaving a<U+017F>ides their <U+017F>everal
Definitions, Divi<U+017F>ions, and Controver<U+017F>ies,
we <U+017F>hall only mark the chief Grounds of their
Nature, and the Analogy that is between it
and their Remedy, to wit, The Tincture of
<hi>Coral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fir<U+017F>t then let it be e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>hed, that a Feaver
is a hot intempery proceeding from a Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
heat kindled in the Heart; and from
thence di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed into all the Body, by the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30448:42"/>
means of the Veins and Arteries, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Natural Actions. The chief Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
for the curing of them, is to take away
that Preternatural heat, and to reduce the
Body into its former temper, as we <U+017F>ee, that
all things after they have left their boiling and
fermenting, and are cooled, become purer
then they were before. Wherein it is to be
ob<U+017F>erved, that the Natural heat, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural,
differ chiefly in this, That the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
heat is a Sub<U+017F>tance, and the Preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
only a Quality. The ignorance of this
difference is the cau<U+017F>e, that <U+017F>o many mi<U+017F>carry
in Feavers; for when Phy<U+017F>icians go about
that Preternatural heat (<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e by Bleeding)
they altogether quench the Natural one,
which by all means ought to be pre<U+017F>erved, and
<U+017F>o ha<U+017F>ten the Di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of the Patient, by
taking away the <hi>Ba<U+017F>is,</hi> upon which, Life is
founded: For what need is it, if one de<U+017F>ireth
to take away the Preternatural heat, and <U+017F>o
to cure a Feaver, that he <U+017F>hould al<U+017F>o take
with it the Natural one, in which con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth a
Mans life; for the Preternatural heat being
once removed, the other remaineth free for
the exerci<U+017F>ing harmonically the Functions of
the Body. The only ea<U+017F>ie, and <U+017F>ure way
therefore to cure Feavers, is to extingui<U+017F>h the
Preternatural heat, without doing prejudice
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30448:42"/>
to the Natural one, but rather comforting and
<U+017F>trengthning it.</p>
            <p>Now I affirm, that this cannot be done
<U+017F>afely but by <U+017F>eparating the Preternatural heat
from the Natural; and <U+017F>o expelling the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural,
while the Natural remaineth in
liberty, to perform the Functions of Nature;
which being helped by noble and harmle<U+017F>s
Remedies, will quickly and <U+017F>afely disburden
her <U+017F>elf of what is noxious and <U+017F>purious, as
we have <U+017F>hewed before in the example of
<hi>An<U+017F>elmus de Booth:</hi> And this by an Univer<U+017F>al
Evacuation thorough the Pores, becau<U+017F>e the
di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is univer<U+017F>ally di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed thorough the
whole Body; which by this means is not only
lightned of its burden, but comforted and
<U+017F>trengthned by the virtue and efficacy of this
noble Remedy.</p>
            <p>It is al<U+017F>o to be ob<U+017F>erved, That the Natural
heat is Cele<U+017F>tial, as flowing from the Sun, <hi>Sol
&amp; homo generant hominem,</hi> and the Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural,
is Elementary; and therefore ea<U+017F>ily
<U+017F>eparable from the other: But <U+017F>ome Body
will object perhaps, that be<U+017F>ides the Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
heat which makes a Feaver, there may
be mixed with it a Latent Malignity, and ask
what <U+017F>hall become of it? I an<U+017F>wer, That the
Preternatural heat, and the Malignity go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
together in the Evacuation; for the way
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30448:43"/>
way through the Pores, being free and open,
and this Remedy being one of the mo<U+017F>t power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Cordials in the World, driveth away from
the Heart, that is, from the Center to the
Circumference, what<U+017F>oever is an Enemy to
the Humane Body, and that with a great deal
of ea<U+017F>e and <U+017F>ecurity.</p>
            <p>Now concerning tho<U+017F>e Feavers called <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent,</hi>
or as the vulgar termeth them, <hi>Agues,</hi>
the Method and Remedy is the <U+017F>ame, except
that the <hi>Salt of Coral</hi> mu<U+017F>t be mixed with
the Tincture, becau<U+017F>e the<U+017F>e Agues have their
foundation in a toughter matter then the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
to wit, in the Humors; as the Tertian
in Choler, the Quotidian in Phlegm, the
Quartan in Melancholy, wherein they harbor,
as in their proper Ferment, which they will
hardly for<U+017F>ake till it be de<U+017F>troyed. Now the
<hi>Tincture of Coral</hi> alone, being too Formal
and Spiritual to de<U+017F>troy and di<U+017F>per<U+017F>e tho<U+017F>e
earthly dro<U+017F><U+017F>es, we in this ca<U+017F>e joyn with it
the <hi>Salt,</hi> which cutteth and inci<U+017F>eth the tough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
of the matter and den<U+017F>ity, and prepareth
it to expul<U+017F>ion, when the <hi>Tincture</hi> cometh to
radiate upon it.</p>
            <p>I have thus a little inlarged my <U+017F>elf upon
this <U+017F>ubject of Feavers, becau<U+017F>e there is no
di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e more vulgar and frequent; for <U+017F>eeing
that mo<U+017F>t of other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es do not <U+017F>ei<U+017F>e upon
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30448:43"/>
Humane Bodies equally, but are more or le<U+017F>s
familiar to <U+017F>ome Ages, Regions, and Con<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions
of Bodies then others; there is no
Age, Region, and Con<U+017F>titution of Body, that
can promi<U+017F>e to it <U+017F>elf a freedom from Feaver;
and, as it is a frequent di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, <U+017F>o is it mo<U+017F>t
dangerous, and not without cau<U+017F>e: For it
occupieth the Storehou<U+017F>e of the Natural and
Vivifying heat, wa<U+017F>teth and de<U+017F>troyeth it, and
unle<U+017F>s that Fiery and Preternatural heat be
timely prevented, it <U+017F>cattereth and devoureth
the Natural one; which being the Trea<U+017F>ure
of Life, Death is pre<U+017F>ently at the door, in<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,
that mo<U+017F>t people die of that di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e;
or rather, as <hi>Galen</hi> <U+017F>aith, <hi>Nemo <U+017F>ine febre mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur,</hi>
No Body dies without a Feaver; which
is the rea<U+017F>on, that the Ancient <hi>Romans</hi> having
a mind to court it, and to render it propitious
unto them<U+017F>elves, did build it a Temple and
Wor<U+017F>hipped it <U+017F>uper<U+017F>titiou<U+017F>ly as a Godde<U+017F>s;
as <hi>Plinius</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Augu<U+017F>t. de
Civit. Dei, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. And <hi>Val. Max. Lib.</hi>
2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30448:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:30448:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:30448:45"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <head type="sub">How the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> worketh upon
all tho<U+017F>e other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, we have <U+017F>aid it
was fit for.</head>
            <p>WE have here and there mentioned <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; in which we affirm the
<hi>Tincture of Coral</hi> to be a mo<U+017F>t Sovereign Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy;
and that not only out of our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
but out of the Authority of famous
and learned Men in all Ages, as
<list>
                  <item>Dio<U+017F>corides.</item>
                  <item>Mathiolus.</item>
                  <item>An<U+017F>elmus de Booth.</item>
                  <item>O<U+017F>waldus Crollius.</item>
                  <item>Joannes Petrus Faber.</item>
                  <item>Arnoldus Villanovanus.</item>
                  <item>Forre<U+017F>tus.</item>
                  <item>Fernelius.</item>
                  <item>Cardanus.</item>
                  <item>Rogerius Baco.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And as many others as have written of the
Nature and Virtues of <hi>Coral,</hi> who agree all in
one, and by that means have made it an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable
truth. It will not be ami<U+017F>s now by
way of Recapitulation to mention all tho<U+017F>e
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30448:45"/>
Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es again, and to illu<U+017F>trate as much as in
us lieth, the way and manner how the <hi>Tincture
of Coral</hi> worketh upon them.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es again<U+017F>t which the Tincture of
<hi>Coral</hi> is a Sovereign Remedy.</head>
               <item>The Plague.</item>
               <item>All <U+017F>orts of Feavers.</item>
               <item>All <U+017F>orts of Agues.</item>
               <item>Flux, Small Pox, Mea<U+017F>les.</item>
               <item>All immoderate Fluxes in Women, whether
Red or White.</item>
               <item>All Bloody Fluxes, Gripings, and Lasks.</item>
               <item>Spitting of Blood, and the Piles.</item>
               <item>Fits of the Mother.</item>
               <item>Drop<U+017F>ies.</item>
               <item>Convul<U+017F>ion.</item>
               <item>Pal<U+017F>ie.</item>
               <item>Falling Sickne<U+017F>s.</item>
               <item>The Stone and Gravel.</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers.</item>
               <item>Pleuri<U+017F>ie.</item>
               <item>Barrenne<U+017F>s in Women.</item>
               <item>Running of the Reins.</item>
               <item>Intemperies of the Liver, Spleen, and Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys.</item>
               <item>Venereal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</item>
               <item>Faintings.</item>
               <item>Surfeitings.</item>
               <item>Vomitings.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="disease">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:30448:46"/>
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Plague.</head>
               <p>It worketh both by its Elementary and
Specifick qualiies; for while by its excellent
temper it bringeth all the Humors into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<hi>Cra<U+017F>is,</hi> and union, and quelleth all the
Jars that are among them; the Formal part of
it, in which lies the Specifick quality doth by
its Actinoboli<U+017F>m or Irradiation, expel all the
Malignancy and Poy<U+017F>on of the Air thorough
the Pores, by ca<U+017F>ting the Patient into a gentle
and moderate <U+017F>weat, and <U+017F>trengthning the
noble Parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Feavers and Agues.</head>
               <p>It worketh the <U+017F>ame way, and be<U+017F>ides it
de<U+017F>troyeth and <U+017F>cattereth the Ferment, in
which lieth the form of the Feaver, and the
type of the Ague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Flux, Small Pox, and Mea<U+017F>les.</head>
               <p>The<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es being naturally rooted in
the Body, as a part and portion of the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of the Men<U+017F>trual Blood, which is the
rea<U+017F>on that all mankind is liable to it once in
its life, <U+017F>ooner or later, and may be called <hi>The
original <U+017F><gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of the Body,</hi> or as <hi>Avicenna</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
it, <hi>Morbus Men<U+017F>trui.</hi> This noble Remedy
clean<U+017F>eth all tho<U+017F>e Impurities by <U+017F>eparating the
pure from the impure, which it thru<U+017F>teth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
from the Center to the Circumference
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30448:46"/>
thorough the Pores; and <U+017F>o comforteth the
noble Parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t all immoderate Fluxes in Women.</head>
               <p>It worketh by its Specifick quality of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborating
the Liver and Spleen, the Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
of which is the Antecedent and chief
au <U+017F>e of all the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>orders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t all Bloody<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Fluxes, Gripings,
and Lasks.</head>
               <p>There being <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>ympathy between Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
Blood, and the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> it is
not hard to gue<U+017F>s, that in this ca<U+017F>e it worketh
by the amity and friend<U+017F>hip they have toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
by which the Blood is cheered up, and,
as it were, courted to remain in its Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
and Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els; by which means, and the
<U+017F>trengthning of the Vitals, all the Preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<U+017F>ymptoms cea<U+017F>e.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Spitting of Blood, and the Piles.</head>
               <p>All the<U+017F>e kinds of Haemorrhagies proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
from a Vein that is either broken, corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
or gaping, it is apparent, that no better
Remedy can be given then the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> given in a proper <hi>Vehioulum,</hi> having
manife<U+017F>t Qualities for the healing of the
Veins, and Specifick ones for the <U+017F>tanching of
the Blood; and it is agreed by all Authors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Fits of the Mother.</head>
               <p>Seeing that this Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e called by the <hi>Latins
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30448:47"/>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>teri Suffocatio,</hi> hath more <U+017F>everal Cau<U+017F>es then
can at this time be ea<U+017F>ily expre<U+017F><U+017F>ed. We <U+017F>hall
only <U+017F>ay, That the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> being
mini<U+017F>tred in a proper Vehicle, <U+017F>cattereth all
tho<U+017F>e noxious fumes; and by its Radiation,
penetrates as far as to the <U+017F>eat of the di<U+017F>temper,
and <U+017F>trengthneth all the Vitals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Drop<U+017F>ies.</head>
               <p>It is known to every Body that mo<U+017F>t Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ies
come by an Intempery of the Liver or
Spleen; which is vi<U+017F>ibly and palpably recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
by this noble Remedy, having fir<U+017F>t purged
and emptied the <U+017F>uperfluous Matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Convul<U+017F>ion.</head>
               <p>This Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e being mo<U+017F>t frequent among
Children, and proceeding from the Malignant
Vapors of the Body, which vellicate and
pluck the Nerves, is cured by the Irradiation
and Specifick quality of this Remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Pal<U+017F>ie.</head>
               <p>The Pal<U+017F>ie being an aboli<U+017F>hing of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and <U+017F>ometime of the Sen<U+017F>e, cau<U+017F>ed by
the want of the Animal Spirits, which are
nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for the free motion of the Body, is
helped by this Remedy; which openeth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructions,
dilateth the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages, quickneth the
Animal Spirits, and makes them fit for Radia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:30448:47"/>
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Falling Sickne<U+017F>s.</head>
               <p>The Epilep<U+017F>ie or Falling Sickne<U+017F>s, is an
often <U+017F>tretching of the Body, or a <U+017F>hort Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vul<U+017F>ion,
by which a Man falleth down on a
<U+017F>udden, without Sen<U+017F>e or Motion; <U+017F>o that he
neither heareth nor <U+017F>eeth, nor remembreth
any thing that is pa<U+017F>t in the Fit, when he is
out of it. In the agitation they foam at the
Mouth, and the Mu<U+017F>cles being loo<U+017F>e, either
the Urine, or Dung, or Seed. cometh out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntarily.
This being cau<U+017F>ed by a Malignant
Vapor which proceedeth from either the
Brains, the Stomach, or <U+017F>ome particular part
of the Body, is cured by the Tincture of
<hi>Coral,</hi> given in <hi>Paeony Water,</hi> after the nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ary
Evacuations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Stone and Gravel.</head>
               <p>In this di<U+017F>temper we give both the Tincture
and the Salt; that while the Tincture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth
the noble Parts, the Salt by its open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and diuretick faculty may wa<U+017F>te and break
to pieces what<U+017F>oever is of Stone or Gravel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers.</head>
               <p>Ulcers being either inward or outward, the
inward ones are cured by the taking of the
<U+017F>aid Tincture in a proper Vehicle; and the
outward ones, be they never <U+017F>o malignant, are
cured by the outward application of it; for it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30448:48"/>
correcteth all malignity, and cicatrizeth them,
even to admiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Pleuri<U+017F>ie.</head>
               <p>It hath been a general opinion, that a Pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<U+017F>ie
cannot be cured without Blood-letting<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
but give me leave to tell you, That in my forty
years experience and practice, I have <U+017F>een more
mi<U+017F>earry by that way, then <U+017F>aved; unle<U+017F>s the
Body be extraordinarily Plethorical, and the
Pleuri<U+017F>ie exceeding violent<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the rea<U+017F>on is,
that <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tracting the Blood, you exhau<U+017F>t the
Trea<U+017F>ure of Life. So that many times, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
cannot la<U+017F>t till Suppuration, for want of
<U+017F>trength and <U+017F>o drops by the way before he can
reach home. Add to this, that the Feaver
which is an in<U+017F>eparable companion of the
Pleuri<U+017F>ie, is not <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon extingui<U+017F>hed this way
as it is <U+017F>cattered into <U+017F>everal Particles, by this
noble Remedy, while the Fomentations di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<U+017F>s
the <U+017F>eat of the di<U+017F>temper, and a<U+017F><U+017F>wage
the pain and other <U+017F>ymptoms, and proper
Pulte<U+017F><U+017F>es utterly di<U+017F><U+017F>ipate the Impo<U+017F>thume.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Barrenne<U+017F>s in Women.</head>
               <p>There being divers and almo<U+017F>t innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Cau<U+017F>es of Barrenne<U+017F>s, we do not pretend
here to <U+017F>hooe every foot by the <U+017F>ame La<U+017F>t; we
know that <U+017F>ome of the Cau<U+017F>es may belong
to Chirurgery, as well as to Phy<U+017F>ick. The judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Phy<U+017F>ician that <U+017F>hall be near at hand, will
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30448:48"/>
ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h them, and pre<U+017F>cribe Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
proper for them. We do only pretend
that when<U+017F>oever the Cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>hall lie in any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempery
of the noble parts, no Remedy <U+017F>hall
go beyond this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Running of the Reins.</head>
               <p>The Body being duly purged, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity
<U+017F>wept away, our Tincture is a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
Remedy to <U+017F>top it, by comforting the
parts, and to prevent any lachrymation or
weakne<U+017F>s, which u<U+017F>e to follow that di<U+017F>temper,
and many times put the Patients to a great
deal of impatiency, and the Phy<U+017F>ician to his
<hi>nonplus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Intemperies of the Liver,
Spleen, and Kidneys.</head>
               <p>This Tincture being given in a proper Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle,
will rectifie them, as well by its Anati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
temper, as by its Actinoboli<U+017F>m and Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick
qualities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t the Venereal Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, vulgarly
called the Great Pox.</head>
               <p>This Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e having its chief foundation in
the Liver, which by the Malignant quality
of this di<U+017F>temper, hath lo<U+017F>t his Tone, and di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<U+017F>ed
the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e thorough the whole Body.
By the u<U+017F>e of this Tincture is brought to its
right temper again; and all the malign<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30448:49"/>
the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e expelled, by the Alexipharmacal
and Specifick quality of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Faintings.</head>
               <p>Fainting is a <U+017F>udden failing of the <U+017F>trength,
that is, a <U+017F>udden diminution of the Vital, and
con<U+017F>equently of the Animal Actions. The
Cau<U+017F>e is a <U+017F>udden want of the Vital Spirits,
which by the Virtue of this Tincture, and of
our admirable Water mixed together, are on
a <U+017F>udden repaired, and the Patient kept in the
Land of the Living, as I have <U+017F>ufficiently
proved upon divers per<U+017F>ons that are alive to
this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Surfeitings.</head>
               <p>There are two kinds of Surfeits, one in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,
the other in quality, but both many
times mortal. The Surfeit in quantity is, when
one eateth or drinketh more then his appetite
de<U+017F>ireth, and his <U+017F>trength can bear. The Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
in quality is, when one eateth or drinketh
never <U+017F>o little of a thing that he hath a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
again<U+017F>t; both are immediately cured by
the Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> mixed with our <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial
Water;</hi> not as the former Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es we
have made mention of, either by Specifick
qualities or Actinoboli<U+017F>ms, but by their grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulne<U+017F>s
and friendline<U+017F>s to our nature, which
when it lieth under the burden of a Surfeit,
and findeth the gratefulne<U+017F>s of this Remedy
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30448:49"/>
it gra<U+017F>peth upon it, and lets fall the Matter of
the Surfeit, which being loo<U+017F>ed it expelleth
by Vomiting, without leaving any Particle of
it behind, and <U+017F>o is immediately well, as I
have tried many times, even to the admiration
of the beholders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>Again<U+017F>t Vomitings.</head>
               <p>This is a pernicious Symptom which is
much in reign, when a Patient can retain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in his Stomach, but immediately bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
it up all again, whether Meat, Drink, or
Phy<U+017F>ick. But this Tincture, and its Vehicle
are <U+017F>o friendly to Nature, and of <U+017F>o admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
a Virtue, that it will immediately <U+017F>tay
the Vomiting; And if there be any Cau<U+017F>e of
it, will bring it up, or if the Remedy <U+017F>tayeth
with the Cau<U+017F>e of the Vomiting in the Body,
it will certainly conquer and de<U+017F>troy it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Many more other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es could I mention,
in which the Tincture of <hi>Coral</hi> would effect
wonderful things. But I think the<U+017F>e will be
<U+017F>ufficient for any rea<U+017F>onable and ingenuous
per<U+017F>on: Tho<U+017F>e that will know more, may
advi<U+017F>e with the Author, who <U+017F>hall ingenuou<U+017F>ly
tell them if it be fit for their di<U+017F>temper or not,
and in what Vehicle it mu<U+017F>t be taken; advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
them <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly, That if they receive no
benefit by this Remedy in tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30448:50"/>
which it is properly admini<U+017F>tred, they can
hardly expect it from any other. The Author
having al<U+017F>o a peculiar Talent to judge of Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es,
and the Remedies thereof, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pection
of Urines, de<U+017F>ireth tho<U+017F>e that will
<U+017F>ave charges or lives, afar of, to <U+017F>end their
Water; by the examination of which, they
<U+017F>hall receive all rea<U+017F>onable <U+017F>atisfaction: And
for the<U+017F>e purpo<U+017F>es and others, he <U+017F>hall give
his con<U+017F>tant attendance at his own Hou<U+017F>e, from
eight of the clock in the Morning, till eleven;
and from three in the Afternoon, till five.
The re<U+017F>t of the time, it will be known where
he is, and when he will be at home again.</p>
               <p>Tho<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o that <U+017F>hall doubt of the reality
and extraction of the <U+017F>aid Tincture, may
have from him <U+017F>ome of his <hi>Men<U+017F>truum,</hi> with
which he extracteth it, and with that and
their own <hi>Coral,</hi> make the experiment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:30448:50"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <head type="sub">How and in what Vehicles the Tincture
of <hi>Coral</hi> is to be administred.</head>
            <p>THis Tincture being <U+017F>o noble and <U+017F>o pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,
and working <U+017F>o powerfully in <U+017F>o
little a quantity, is to be u<U+017F>ed with all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pection
imaginable, that there be no wa<U+017F>te
in the quantity, nor impediment in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
There would be a great wa<U+017F>te in the
quantity, if it were taken alone, and by it
<U+017F>elf, con<U+017F>idering, That one pound of <hi>Coral</hi>
will <U+017F>carce yield above one drachm of Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture;
therefore we give it in a little quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
(<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e of about twenty drops) in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Vehicle, <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e of two or three ounces;
that by its diffu<U+017F>ion in it, it may go and enter
over all the noble parts of the Body; as you
<U+017F>ee that a grain of <hi>Cochenille</hi> will die a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>and
times of its weight of Water; and that
<hi>Saffron</hi> will diffu<U+017F>e its Tincture in a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
quantity of liquor. There would al<U+017F>o
be a wa<U+017F>te in the quantity, if the Tincture
were given alone, and by it <U+017F>elf; for the
Natural heat would con<U+017F>ume it, before it could
diffu<U+017F>e its virtue, and radiate thorough the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30448:51"/>
whole Body. Add al<U+017F>o, that a Specifick Vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
will make it work more effectually and
determinately upon the part aimed at. There
would be al<U+017F>o an impediment in the quality,
if it were not given in a Vehicle that were
unfit, or contrary to the di<U+017F>temper that it is
given for; as if of two Hor<U+017F>es, the one <U+017F>hould
draw before, and the other back, they could
hardly reach home in a convenient time; or,
if it were given among<U+017F>t Meat, or upon a full
Stomach, it is evident, that its virtue <U+017F>hould
be drowned, and its Radiation hindered: As
when a thick cloud is interpo<U+017F>ed between the
Sun, and us. For the illu<U+017F>tration of what we
have <U+017F>aid, it is vi<U+017F>ible, and in a manner palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
That if the <U+017F>aid Tincture were given
again<U+017F>t the Plague and Malignant Feavers in
<hi>Plantain Water,</hi> it would hardly work the
de<U+017F>ired effect, becau<U+017F>e <hi>Plantain Water</hi> is cool
and a<U+017F>tringent; and our intention in this, is
to expel the malignity of the Plague and Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
by a moderate <U+017F>weat, which cannot be
conveniently procured, but by a hot Vehicle,
<U+017F>uch as is our Cordial Water, or that of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus,</hi>
and <U+017F>uch other-like. Contrariwi<U+017F>e, if
in immoderate Fluxes of Women and Haemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhagies,
it be admini<U+017F>tred in hot Vehicles,
and not in cool and A<U+017F>tringent ones, <U+017F>uch as
<hi>Plantain Water</hi> is, little good can be expected
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30448:51"/>
of it, by rea<U+017F>on of the contrariety and di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion
that is between the Agent and the
Patient, that is, the Remedy and the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.
Let it therefore be concluded, That it mu<U+017F>t
be given in a proper Vehicle, that is, <U+017F>uch
a one, as is proper for the di<U+017F>temper,
and will forward the effect of the <U+017F>aid Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
and hath a peculiar analogy and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<U+017F>pondence
with the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e aimed at. As
for example, For the <U+017F>topping of all immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
Fluxes in Men and Women, it ought
to be given in <hi>Plantain Water,</hi> or the decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Roots of <hi>Tormentil.</hi> For the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
or renewing of the Blood, in <hi>Fumitory</hi>
or <hi>Cichory Water.</hi> For <U+017F>trengthning the Heart
and the Vital Spirits, in <hi>Buglo<U+017F>s,</hi> or <hi>Borrage
Water.</hi> For comforting and <U+017F>trengthning the
Stomach, in <hi>Mint</hi> or <hi>Penniroyal Water.</hi> For
removing of ob<U+017F>tructions in <hi>Sorrel Water,
Little Centaury, Spleenwort, Liverwort.</hi> For
di<U+017F><U+017F>olving congealed Blood, in Water of <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
or <hi>Dai<U+017F>ie.</hi> For the Fits of the Mother, in
the Water of <hi>Motherwort, Balm, Penniroyal.</hi>
For the Drop<U+017F>ie, Convul<U+017F>ion, Pal<U+017F>ie, Falling-Sickne<U+017F>s,
in <hi>Cinnamon Water,</hi> continuing for
a while, becau<U+017F>e tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are <U+017F>tubborn.
For the Stone and Gravel, in <hi>Saxifrage</hi> or
<hi>Re<U+017F>tharrow Water.</hi> The do<U+017F>e is from <U+017F>ix grains
or ten, to a <U+017F>cruple or two, according to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30448:52"/>
age and <U+017F>trength of the Patient, and the
greatne<U+017F>s of the di<U+017F>temper: And <U+017F>o it may
be <U+017F>aid of all the re<U+017F>t of the di<U+017F>tempers which
it is proper for. Upon which, the Author
will give his advice to tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>hall de<U+017F>ire
it; and for that purpo<U+017F>e, <U+017F>hall give his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tant
attendance at his own Hou<U+017F>e, from eight
of the clock in the Morning, till eleven; and
from three in the Afternoon, till five. The
<U+017F>ame Author having al<U+017F>o a <U+017F>pecial Talent to
judge of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and the Remedies thereof,
by the In<U+017F>pection of Urines, may be advi<U+017F>ed
with at the <U+017F>aid time; therefore tho<U+017F>e that
<U+017F>hall be minded to <U+017F>ave the charges of Fees,
may at the <U+017F>aid time bring or <U+017F>end their Urine,
upon <U+017F>ight whereof, they <U+017F>hall receive all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onable
<U+017F>atisfaction.</p>
            <p>As for the <U+017F>aid Tincture of <hi>Coral,</hi> with the
Vehicles proper for it, they are only to be had
and mini<U+017F>tred by him, to prevent all <U+017F>uppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ition,
fal<U+017F>ification, or mi<U+017F>takes, the World,
at pre<U+017F>ent, being <U+017F>o full of Envy, Backbiting,
and Deceitfulne<U+017F>s, that he dares tru<U+017F>t no Body
with it; but is re<U+017F>olved, as he is the <U+017F>ole
Author of it, <U+017F>o to have all the prai<U+017F>e of it,
and bear all the blame alone, if any be. He
al<U+017F>o carrieth always <U+017F>ome of the <U+017F>aid Tincture
about him, ready to be admini<U+017F>tred, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>oever
occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>hall require, that no time
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30448:52"/>
may be lo<U+017F>t, as mo<U+017F>t commonly it is, in acute
and exceeding ha<U+017F>ty Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. That <U+017F>hall not
hinder, but if any Body be <U+017F>atisfied with the
Virtues and Effects of the <U+017F>aid Tincture, he
may have of him what quantity he plea<U+017F>eth
to lie by him, again<U+017F>t the time of need; and
this he doth to make good his Motto, which
al<U+017F>o was that of <hi>Cardan. Io <U+017F>uon Medico non di
parole ma d'effetto.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Hou<U+017F>e in
Clarkenwel Clo<U+017F>e, the
Second on the Left<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand.</dateline>
               <signed>Garencieres.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

