<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aero-chalinos, or, A register for the air for the better preservation of health and cure of diseases, after a new method / by Nathaniel Henshaw.</title>
            <author>Henshaw, Nathaniel, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08712070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08712070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A43353)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1261:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aero-chalinos, or, A register for the air for the better preservation of health and cure of diseases, after a new method / by Nathaniel Henshaw.</title>
                  <author>Henshaw, Nathaniel, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 98 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Dancer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"In five chapters, 1. Of fermentation, 2. Of chylification, 3. Of respiration, 4. Of sanguification, 5. That often changing the air is a friend to health. Also a discovery of a new method of doing it, without removing from one place to another, by means of a domicil or air-chamber fitted to that purpose."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Air.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AE<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OCHALINOS: OR, A Regi<U+017F>ter for the Air; IN FIVE CHAPTERS.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Of Fermentation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Of Chylification.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Of Re<U+017F>piration.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Of Sanguification.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That often changing the Air, is a friend to health. Al<U+017F>o a di<U+017F>covery of a new method of doing it, without removing from one place to another, by means of a Domicil, or Air-Chamber, fitted to that purpo<U+017F>e.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the better pre<U+017F>ervation of Health, and cure of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, after a new Method.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANIEL HENSHAW,</hi> M. D. a Member of the Royal Society at GRESHAM-COLLEDGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Dancer,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eller in <hi>Ca<U+017F>tle-<U+017F>treet,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>O<U+017F><U+017F>ory,</hi> Lord Deputy General of IRELAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat the happy Indu<U+017F>try of former A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (whereby we enjoy the benefit of <U+017F>o many u<U+017F>eful inventions) hath <U+017F>till left mater enough, for the contrivance and di<U+017F>covery of <U+017F>ucceeding times, cannot be better made appear, than by calling to mind, tho<U+017F>e many worthy improvements, which almo<U+017F>t all the more Liberal Arts, have received within the compa<U+017F>s of this la<U+017F>t Century, e<U+017F>pecially Phy<U+017F>ick, wherein Anatomy alone (I may truly <U+017F>ay) hath been inriched, by a full third part at lea<U+017F>t. And herein our own Countrymen, have been as <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sfully inqui<U+017F>itive, as any other their Contemporaries what<U+017F>oever. No wonder then if in <U+017F>uch an Age, I, imitating their example, have thought fit, to give this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of my lei<U+017F>ure, to the world; but
<pb facs="tcp:41619:3"/>
that I offer it to the protection of <U+017F>o great a Patron; the rea<U+017F>ons, perhaps, are not <U+017F>o ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nife<U+017F>t, as nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary. For as the Novelty of <U+017F>o unexpected a method, as I here propo<U+017F>e, will undoubtedly expo<U+017F>e it to the calumny of <U+017F>uch, who (rather than give them<U+017F>elves the trouble of examining the truth of it, being betimes per<U+017F>waded, that they already know as much as is to be learnt) will <U+017F>oon condemn it, both of folly and innovation. So it <U+017F>eems of ab<U+017F>olute nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, that it bear with it the <U+017F>plendid name of <U+017F>ome great Per<U+017F>onage, the better to be<U+017F>peak the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Readers charitable Cen<U+017F>ure. Who<U+017F>e name then could I more hopefully have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, than that of your Lord<U+017F>hips, a per<U+017F>on <U+017F>o Noble by de<U+017F>cent, <U+017F>o Eminent by your Great and Honorable Imployments, and <U+017F>o de<U+017F>ervedly beloved and admired of all for that excellent compo<U+017F>ure of Greatne<U+017F>s and Goodne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>o remarkable in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hip; which attempt of mine, if it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a favourable Interpretation, I <U+017F>hall be obliged to continue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors in all <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>N. H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 1. 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Hold it not un<U+017F>uitable to our de<U+017F>ign in this Treati<U+017F>e (where I have <U+017F>o often occa<U+017F>ion to make mention of it) that <U+017F>omething be <U+017F>aid by way of Preface, concerning the Air. Not that I intend to treat of it's fir<U+017F>t or <U+017F>econd qualities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which I leave to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philo<U+017F>ophers con<U+017F>ideration, much le<U+017F>s of the Ela<U+017F>tic power of it, in Pneumatick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines; already <U+017F>o well performed by others, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pecially by the Honorable <hi>Robert Boyl,</hi> in his mo<U+017F>t accurate Treati<U+017F>e on that Subject: my purpo<U+017F>e here being only to pre<U+017F>ent my Reader, with <U+017F>ome few ob<U+017F>ervables concerning Air, the better to confirm and illu<U+017F>trate, what follows in the Treati<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf: e<U+017F>pecially in the Chapter of Fermentation. Fir<U+017F>t there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the Air is of <U+017F>ome very general u<U+017F>e, may well appear from its being <U+017F>o great in <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>biquitarian, as it is. No place almo<U+017F>t without it, no body (perhaps) but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating, more or le<U+017F>s, of it; in<U+017F>omuch, that
<pb facs="tcp:41619:4"/>
even in metals them<U+017F>elves, the <U+017F>ound of them, it reckoned an affection of the Air included in them. And if the tran<U+017F>parency of Bodies be to be imputed to their porou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, or rather to the <U+017F>treightne<U+017F>s or rectitude of their pores, (as its almo<U+017F>t generally agreed on by Modern Writers) it will follow, that there is a great proportion of Air in the harde<U+017F>t Gemmes. Which is yet more manifest in <U+017F>ofter <U+017F>tones, and becomes the cau<U+017F>e of their moldring and cracking (after they are taken out of the Quarrey, and expo<U+017F>ed to the weather) which <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ort of <U+017F>tones are very <U+017F>ubject to: For the impri<U+017F>oned Air, that while it was in the cold bowels of the Earth, lay very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<U+017F>ed or compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, afterward <U+017F>ymbolizing with the Air of a thinner Medium, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully dilates its <U+017F>elf, and after <U+017F>ome time <U+017F>o weakens the continuity of parts, that at la<U+017F>t becoming too <U+017F>trong for it, the <U+017F>tone breaks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many pieces, which will <U+017F>ooner happen if the <U+017F>ame be thrown into the fire: the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Air, in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e, with much more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence dilating its <U+017F>elf, than in the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. Plants <U+017F>eem to owe their very life and being to this included Air: for not ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving hearts, or other principal of motion in
<pb facs="tcp:41619:4"/>
them, (that we know of) for the di<U+017F>tributing of the Sap: the included Air <U+017F>eems to <U+017F>upply that defect, after this manner. In the day time, in hot weather, and generally as often as the Air of the Medium, is dilated or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: the Air included, in the body of every Vegetable, <U+017F>uffers after the <U+017F>ame manner, and has its dimen<U+017F>ions and tone varied. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<U+017F>e two con<U+017F>iderable effects follow, to wit, that upon the dilatation of the internal or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Air, the parts of the Vegetable are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tended (<U+017F>omewhat) according to their trinal dimen<U+017F>ion, whereby the Plant grows bigger and taller. And again, upon the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the internal Air, room is made for the water or <U+017F>ap, to ri<U+017F>e up, through the pores of the Plant, exactly after the manner of the Weather-gla<U+017F>s: where the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the Air becomes the cau<U+017F>e of the a<U+017F>cent of the water. And thus according to the<U+017F>e periods of heat and cold, and the con<U+017F>equent rarity and den<U+017F>ity of the included Air, and that of the Medium; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Plant makes, as it were, <U+017F>o many meals, or is <U+017F>o often refre<U+017F>hed, by the a<U+017F>cending Sap, which a<U+017F>cent is al<U+017F>o not a little promoted, by tho<U+017F>e gentle Vibrations from the winds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the parts of Vegetables (and con<U+017F>equently
<pb facs="tcp:41619:5"/>
the included Air) are moderately compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed and dilated reciprocally; wherrupon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aid effects follow, even after the <U+017F>ame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as is <U+017F>aid of the Swing, and in the la<U+017F>t Chapter of this Treati<U+017F>e. The included Air <U+017F>erves likewi<U+017F>e in Vegetables (as in all other bodies) for the maturing and fermenting the juices in them, in <U+017F>uch manner as is hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expre<U+017F><U+017F>ed. A farther confirmation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be hence had, that the mo<U+017F>t vegetous plants, and <U+017F>uch as we call <hi>Ever-Greens,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound most with Air in them: as appears when they are thrown into the fire, by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent eruption of it. And there is, I think, no vegetable that has not one great pore or Pipe running from the root to the very top of it. Farther, in the Sea wrack, or <hi>Quercus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina,</hi> 'tis obvious for every one to ob<U+017F>erve a very particular and curious contrivance of Nature, for the nouri<U+017F>hment of that plant, by the help of Air after this <U+017F>ort. The plant as always fa<U+017F>tened to <U+017F>ome <U+017F>tone; and as it branches out, with jagged leafs, <U+017F>omewhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>embling tho<U+017F>e of the Oak: it hath <U+017F>everal little Bli<U+017F>ters or Bladders on it (<U+017F>ome where of I have <U+017F>een as big as a <U+017F>mall Pullets Egg.) Now upon the coming in of the Tide, the water
<pb facs="tcp:41619:5"/>
ri<U+017F>ing this weed by means of the <U+017F>aid Bladders floats; and if the Stone be not too heavy Boys it up. (and hangs in the water like a Net that hath Corks and Leads to it) whereupon the Plant is con<U+017F>iderably <U+017F>tretched; and again, upon the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>iding of the water, receives its nouri<U+017F>hment, as in the former in<U+017F>tance of other vegetables, though perhaps not from the root, being fa<U+017F>tened to a <U+017F>tone, but by the poro<U+017F>e <U+017F>urface of its body. And la<U+017F>tly, that there is much Air di<U+017F><U+017F>eminated through the bodies of Animals, is manife<U+017F>t from their food: herbs and water, both which participate of it in good quantity. A notable argument whereof in water, may be, that it doth upon <U+017F>uch ea<U+017F>ie terms ri<U+017F>e up in a vapour, and mingle its mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute and in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible parts with the Air. For as the water grows warm, either by the heat of the Sun or fire, the <U+017F>mall parts of Air di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating, make ha<U+017F>te to the top of the water, where they frame them<U+017F>elves, with <U+017F>ome of the water, into little bubbles; and are carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the motion of the Air or Medium, like tho<U+017F>e bubbles made by Children, with Soap and water. And this perhaps may be one rea<U+017F>on, why Rain water is better for plants, then other water, becau<U+017F>e it has more air in it; a te<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:41619:6"/>
whereof the Scale may afford us. And this is manifest in wine even to <U+017F>en<U+017F>e: from which (if it be brisk and fre<U+017F>h, and poured from on high, into a gla<U+017F>s) you <U+017F>hall fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ee a great number of little bubbles, or floating parcels of Air ri<U+017F>e up, with <U+017F>uch force, as to mount neer a foot, above the <U+017F>urface of the wine. But it is not enough for us to have proved great quantities of Air in all mixed bodies, unle<U+017F>s it be at the <U+017F>ame time allowed us, that the Air be actually and formally there as in the Medium or open Air, <U+017F>uffering no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing el<U+017F>e but barely an impri<U+017F>onment, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement only, which is already <U+017F>ufficiently made out by the u<U+017F>es lately a<U+017F><U+017F>igned it in vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, (unle<U+017F>s they may be otherways more commodiou<U+017F>ly explained) be<U+017F>ides, that the po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of converting one <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, was yet never <U+017F>o clearly taught, as to become intelligible, and has at this day but few A<U+017F><U+017F>erters of it.</p>
            <p>In contemplation of all which particulars and that the Air alone, of all Simple Bodies is capable of dilatation and constriction (or call it rarity and den<U+017F>ity) yet, not by any power to move it has of its <U+017F>elf, but as it is moved more or le<U+017F>s, by the pre<U+017F>ence or ab<U+017F>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:41619:6"/>
the neerne<U+017F>s or remotene<U+017F>s of the Sun (the heart and Center of this worldly Sy<U+017F>tem in which we live) I thought it a matter worth my pains (though perhaps exceeding my abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) to a<U+017F><U+017F>ay whether all fermentation, were not reducible to this <U+017F>imple motion of the Air, and did not depend on it, as on a general and more univer<U+017F>al cau<U+017F>e; which if I fail not in, it will be no very difficult matter, to reduce all other motions in the world, to that of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and probably to re<U+017F>olve many hard que<U+017F>tions, not as yet <U+017F>o rightly determined. But becau<U+017F>e contemplations of this kind, are, in their own Nature, very unprofitable, if not reducible to practi<U+017F>e: I have, as well as I could, applied the <U+017F>ame to the cure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of mo<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es: as will <U+017F>omewhat more at large appear by the en<U+017F>uing Treati<U+017F>e. Which I have <U+017F>uffered to undergo the publick view, with this a<U+017F><U+017F>urance, that if the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion I build on, fail me not, I need not at all <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bt the Super<U+017F>tructure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:7"/>
            <p>CLari<U+017F><U+017F>imi viri <hi>Nathan. Hen<U+017F>haw,</hi> M. D. opus hoc mole quidem Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iguum, <U+017F>ed acumine, eruditione cùm variâ &amp; jucundà, tum utili &amp; novà, <U+017F>uccóque, plenum relegimus; idque cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis tam Medicinae non-vulgaris quàm Secretioris &amp; Solidioris Philo<U+017F>ophiae Studio<U+017F>is <U+017F>ummoperè commendamus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JOHANNES STEARNE.</hi> M. &amp; J.<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>.D. &amp; M. Profe<U+017F><U+017F>or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus in Academiâ Dublinien<U+017F>i.</signed>
               <dateline>Dat. è Collegio S. &amp; Individ. Trin. propter Dubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Calend. <date>
                     <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii 1664.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41619:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Fermentation in General.</head>
            <p n="1">1. BY Fermentation, I under<U+017F>tand that motion ob<U+017F>ervable in all compound or mixed bodies whereby the order and <U+017F>itu<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of all the minute parts of the <U+017F>ame, are continually changed, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pect of them<U+017F>elves, as of the whole Ma<U+017F>s whereof they are parts: and that, chiefly from an internal cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>o moving or di<U+017F>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing them, (without the local motion of the whole) whether the <U+017F>ame be accompanied with any <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible heat, in the Ma<U+017F>s <U+017F>o fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, or not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <U+017F>uch a motion or fermentation <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> every where ob<U+017F>ervable, we need not go <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> to prove, if we con<U+017F>ider, that there is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41619:8"/>
<U+017F>carce any thing <U+017F>ublunary, which is <U+017F>ubject to our ob<U+017F>ervation, that continues the lea<U+017F>t moment of time in the <U+017F>ame tenour without alteration, which, if not ob<U+017F>ervable to <U+017F>ence is yet found to be <U+017F>o, with as little rea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as that the <U+017F>hadow upon the Dyal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually moves on, though our eye deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine not, till after <U+017F>ome minutes, perhaps, of time, it becomes apparent, that the <U+017F>hadow has moved and then we <U+017F>traight conclude it moved all the while: and that the proportional parts of <U+017F>pace, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<U+017F>urate to the re<U+017F>pective moments, in which the <U+017F>hadow pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed from one term to the other: if therefore all bodies are thus moved or fermented at all times, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ows that the Doctrine of Fermentation (according to our acception of the word) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> manner as far extended as that of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> it<U+017F>elf. I <U+017F>hall only con<U+017F>ider it <U+017F>o <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> as it <U+017F>eems conducible and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>ervient to tho<U+017F>e noble ends I have propo<U+017F>ed my <U+017F>elf in this Treati<U+017F>e, viz. the continuation of health, the cure of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and the retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of old Age (to <U+017F>ay no more, and not <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o promi<U+017F>e too much) by a new and hitherto unheard of method.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41619:8"/>3 The mo<U+017F>t general properties of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation are the<U+017F>e: that the Ma<U+017F>s <U+017F>o fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented <U+017F>uffers an eminent alteration in all its u<U+017F>ual wayes of affecting our <U+017F>en<U+017F>es, as well in its fir<U+017F>t as <U+017F>econd qualities: they are either exalted or depre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, they are <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times changed for their contrary, and in a word, relation being had to our e<U+017F>teem of things thus fermented, all fermentation may be <U+017F>aid to be either perfective or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructive, though in it <U+017F>elf it be but one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued flux: as for in<U+017F>tance in an apple, or the like, that from a green au<U+017F>tere bud, fir<U+017F>t acquires its due perfection, and after by a continuation of that fermentation, that ripened it, at la<U+017F>t arrives at corruption, and <U+017F>o changes both its name and nature together.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Another eminent property of fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is that for the mo<U+017F>t part the Body fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented doth occupy more <U+017F>pace than the <U+017F>ame did before, which is very evident in the drowned bodies of men or other ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, which though at fir<U+017F>t they go to the bottom, yet after a certain time do <U+017F>lowly boye them<U+017F>elves up again to the top of the water, not for that the breaking of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41619:9"/>
Gall becomes the cau<U+017F>e of their a<U+017F>cending: (as <U+017F>ome even knowing men have <U+017F>uffered them<U+017F>elves to be per<U+017F>waded) but becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch bodies formerly heavier than water, quantity for quantity, and con<U+017F>equently apt to <U+017F>ink, have now acquired a larger dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion, while they however increa<U+017F>e not their weight, and <U+017F>o becoming lighter than the water contained in the like <U+017F>pace are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded by it to the top where they by degrees <U+017F>well yet bigger<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> <U+017F>o that <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I have <U+017F>een a dog lye with more than one halfe of his body above the <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the water, and it is no more than happens in a pound of Gla<U+017F>s, metal or other heavy material, which in a <U+017F>olid Ma<U+017F>s <U+017F>inks to the bottom, but if blown or wrought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a bottle, it keeps the top of the water: all which together with the rea<U+017F>on is well enough known to <U+017F>uch as have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ant in <U+017F>tatick Experiments.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Another very u<U+017F>eful property of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation is, that while it <U+017F>eparates all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous parts, it leaves the Ba<U+017F>is as it were, or main ingredient of the Ma<U+017F>s clear and limpid, if not hindred by the den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity of the body, and throws off two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41619:9"/>
or <U+017F>uperfluities, one a heavier de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>cending to the bottom, the other of a lighter more frothy <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, which takes its place at the top of the liquor: as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t in Wine, Sider and the juices of other fruits: in Beer made with Barly, and the decoctions of other grains, fir<U+017F>t, maulted and grown'd. This happens not in Bread becau<U+017F>e the greate<U+017F>t part of the Ma<U+017F>s be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the more <U+017F>olid, the le<U+017F>s or watry par<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> takes its flight on all <U+017F>ides to the circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference, though <U+017F>omewhat more <U+017F>lowly and there coagulates into a blew mould.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another noble property of Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, is, that it exalts the body fermented to what perfection it is capable of, but then it is requi<U+017F>ite that the body fermented be of <U+017F>uch a con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, as may not be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented too fa<U+017F>t, as in fruits, upon trees: or if thin, that it be clo<U+017F>e <U+017F>top't in <U+017F>ome full Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, as all kind of drinks: or if o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> middle con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, that it be often <U+017F>tirred<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> which is ob<U+017F>erved by Apothecaries in the making of Treacle, and other <U+017F>uch Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>po<U+017F>itions, which afterward will keep a very long time. For thus it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, that that <U+017F>pirit (as we will call it for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41619:10"/>
which ferments the Ma<U+017F>s, be for a while detained either by the tone of the body, by <U+017F>ome <U+017F>trong ve<U+017F><U+017F>el; or that it be often re-effu<U+017F>ed, as it were, upon its body, that <U+017F>o by its long, difficult and reiterated working, it may at la<U+017F>t find out <U+017F>ome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity among<U+017F>t the le<U+017F>s Heterogeneous parts, and cau<U+017F>e a kind of complanation of the whole Ma<U+017F>s, and it <U+017F>elf with le<U+017F>s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy, be detained in the Body or Ma<U+017F>s.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Another very General property of Fermentation is, that all bodies, almo<U+017F>t by it, at la<U+017F>t become acide: as is manife<U+017F>t in all liquors, decoctions of fle<U+017F>h, or herbs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuaries, <U+017F>irups, &amp;c. by which acidity I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<U+017F>tand not that <U+017F>owre ta<U+017F>te, ob<U+017F>ervable in mo<U+017F>t green fruits, which is rather to be termed acerbity, and differs as much from what we here <U+017F>peak of, as Agre<U+017F>ta (the juyce of green grapes expre<U+017F>t) doth from Vinegar.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In the next place, let us briefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider the cau<U+017F>es of Fermentation, the mo<U+017F>t immediate of which, <U+017F>eems to be the Air, contained in every mixt body: for as I noted before, all bodies fermented, do occupy a larger room, than they did before
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41619:10"/>
fermentation: which cannot be duely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribed, to any other ingredient in mixt bodies, than to the air, for that it hath not yet been found, by <U+017F>ufficient experiment, that any body what<U+017F>oever is capable of rarifaction and conden<U+017F>ation; or dilation and con<U+017F>truction be<U+017F>ides air: as for Leaf Gold, what it got in one dimen<U+017F>ion, it lo<U+017F>t in the other, and all the parts of Gold calcined, do but equal the Ma<U+017F>s they were made of, no more than if the <U+017F>ame had been redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to an impalpable powder by means of a very fine file. The <U+017F>ame is to be under<U+017F>tood of water evaporated by heat: which is only a comminution of it, into exceeding <U+017F>mall parts, and no way a conver<U+017F>ion of it into air (as hath been formerly received) which is from hence evidenced, that <U+017F>uch vapours by the Alembic, are again reduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <U+017F>ame liquors from whence they were fir<U+017F>t rai<U+017F>ed, viz. into Ro<U+017F>ewater or <U+017F>pirit of Wine, which were no more po<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if they had been really converted into air, then out of common air to draw Ro<U+017F>e-water or <U+017F>pirit of Wine, and if water, or milke or other liquor take up more room when boyling on the fire, then they did
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41619:11"/>
cold, 'tis by rea<U+017F>on that the particles of air, formerly not vi<U+017F>ible are now con<U+017F>iderably dilated, <U+017F>o as to become ob<U+017F>ervable to the eye.</p>
            <p n="9">9. As the Air contained in mixt bodies, is the mo<U+017F>t immediat efficient cau<U+017F>e of Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: <U+017F>o it needs, exciting and actuating, for the mo<U+017F>t part, as well by the temper and tone of the <hi>Medium,</hi> as from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, of this or that particular Ferment as of leven yea<U+017F>t, Renet, or the like: of which perhaps we <U+017F>hall have farther occa<U+017F>ion to <U+017F>peak more, hereafter, and at pre<U+017F>ent only con<U+017F>ider how the <hi>Medium</hi> e<U+017F>pecially the Ambient Air, excites the internal air in the work of Fermentation.</p>
            <p n="10">10. By the Tone of the Air, I under<U+017F>tand the mea<U+017F>ure of its rarity and den<U+017F>ity and e<U+017F>pecially its reciprocations or frequent acce<U+017F>s and rece<U+017F>s to this or that degree of rarity and den<U+017F>ity. Now, that one Air is rarer than another as that of hills, then that of the valleys, that of <U+017F>outhern Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, then that of the more Northern: is I think an undoubted truth: al<U+017F>o that the Air of every particular place is <U+017F>ometimes rarer <U+017F>ometimes den<U+017F>er according to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41619:11"/>
<U+017F>everal <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons of the year, times of the day and night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> needs no other proof then that of the Weather-gla<U+017F>s. By the temperature of the Air, I mean its degree and difference of heat and cold, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of the <U+017F>ame con<U+017F>iderations of place and time as before, and is not only proved by the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, but even by <U+017F>en<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The manner how the Ambient works upon the internal air in mixed bodies, is the <U+017F>ame with that of the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, where the inclo<U+017F>ed air is rarified, and conden<U+017F>ed, heated and cooled accordingly, as the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium is affected: So in bodies fermented, e<U+017F>pecially liquors, the imperceptible parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of air being gently and by degrees di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, become the cau<U+017F>e that the whole Ma<U+017F>s doth occupy more and more room, or encrea<U+017F>es its dimen<U+017F>ions under the <U+017F>ame weight, whereupon this effect immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows, that <U+017F>everal Heterogeneous Particles, which before floated in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and were (as I may <U+017F>ay) equilibrous with the <U+017F>ame, do now gently de<U+017F>cend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the bottom, in order, according to their weight: The <U+017F>mall Particles of air in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41619:12"/>
the mean while being more and more dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted do, together with the more vi<U+017F>cous parts of the liquor (of which they form them<U+017F>elves Coats or Integuments) gently a<U+017F>cend to the top of the Ma<U+017F>s, where they make that frothy head or <U+017F>cum ob<U+017F>ervable in Sider, Wine, Beer, and other liquors; and this I take to be the natural method of all ferment<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion when not checked, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e determined by <U+017F>ome outward circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance: And this al<U+017F>o <U+017F>eems a genuine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on of the depuration, and of the ca<U+017F>ting off the heavier and lighter recrement men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before (N. 5.) to happen in ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed liquors.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That Bodies are ripened and acquire their due perfection by fermentation, is a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erted N. 6. but in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, that this fermentation be checked or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded in <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ort as is there mentioned, both in natural and more artificial fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: But the mo<U+017F>t univer<U+017F>al Moderator of this motion, is what was lately call'd the tone of Air, as well as its temperature, which daily and hourly changing, doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerate, retard, check and put backward this motion, and then re<U+017F>tores it again; by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41619:12"/>
which various, and oft repeated cour<U+017F>e, the parts are comminuted, their roughne<U+017F>s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunded and mitigated, and they <U+017F>o di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed of, after an inexplicable manner, as condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces mo<U+017F>t to the beauty and perfection of the Body fermented.</p>
            <p n="13">13. This dilatation and con<U+017F>triction in Bodies fermented, cau<U+017F>ed by the like acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the Ambient Air, may not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly be compared with the pul<U+017F>e in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals having its <hi>Sy<U+017F>tole</hi> and <hi>Dia<U+017F>tole,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as they have, though by longer peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods, as of day and night, warm weather and cold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and from hence perhaps is the true cau<U+017F>e of pul<U+017F>es in Animals to be lookt for, which yet as forreign to our pre<U+017F>ent <U+017F>cope we here enquire not farther after; but it will not be improper to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve (with common experience) that Malt is be<U+017F>t made in windy weather, and that the be<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t la<U+017F>ting Beer is brewed in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> (windy moneths, and of an unequal temper) Now 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that all winds are moved by gu<U+017F>ts rather then equal fluxes (from whence probably it is that the Sea is lifted into Waves, as it were numbring to us the <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41619:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
impetuous <U+017F>troaks it received from the winds.) Thus the motion of all Animals <U+017F>eems to be performed by <U+017F>natches and jerks; and it is indeed a great que<U+017F>tion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong School-Philo<U+017F>ophers, whether any local motion be (<U+017F>trictly <U+017F>peaking) continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and not rather con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting, of <U+017F>hort moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and frequent re<U+017F>ts, as it were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded together. This Pul<U+017F>e, or frequent change in the tone of the Air, however it may <U+017F>eem at fir<U+017F>t view an idle or over-<U+017F>ubtil contemplation, will upon due con<U+017F>iderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be found not only true, and the cau<U+017F>e of tho<U+017F>e effects a<U+017F><U+017F>igned to it in the foregoing Paragraph, but that it may al<U+017F>o with good effect be made u<U+017F>e of in Phy<U+017F>ick, as a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in<U+017F>trument for pre<U+017F>ervation of health, and the cure of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. I <U+017F>hall hereafter endeavour to prove in the en<U+017F>uing di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e. That mo<U+017F>t liquors fermented, e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the beginning, conceive heat, and become warm, even to <U+017F>en<U+017F>e the rea<U+017F>on, may be partly gathered out of what has been already <U+017F>aid; namely, that the <U+017F>mall particles of Air in <U+017F>uch liquor become di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, which dilatation is always accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with an encrea<U+017F>e of heat, they mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41619:13"/>
making way for, and introducing one the other (in the Air and bodies participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Air) if not hindred from without; to which may be added, that all motion is apt to beget heat in the Body moved, which is true not only of <U+017F>olid Bodies, though more eminently in them, but al<U+017F>o of liquid Bodies them<U+017F>elves. Thus 'tis <U+017F>aid in making Butter, you mu<U+017F>t neither make too much at once, nor yet mu<U+017F>t it be too violently beaten or <U+017F>haken, for in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e there will be great hazard of over-heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Butter, which as you <U+017F>ee is the meer effect of motion in a liquid Body only<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Be<U+017F>ides mo<U+017F>t liquors fermented, abou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a kind of Tartar (which afterw<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>ub<U+017F>ideth when the Ma<U+017F>s begins to co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the colli<U+017F>ion of who<U+017F>e rough particles <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> again<U+017F>t the other, may perhaps <U+017F>omew<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> contribute to the production of this he<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> though I for my part impute le<U+017F>s to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> then the cau<U+017F>es before a<U+017F><U+017F>igned, though <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> remarkable heat ari<U+017F>ing in <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>ed upon filings of Iron or Silver, is perh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be<U+017F>t made out by the colli<U+017F>ion of its a<U+017F>pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> parts again<U+017F>t tho<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>aid Metals.</p>
            <p n="14">14. As concerning particular ferments, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41619:14"/>
<U+017F>hall only ob<U+017F>erve, that congenerous Bodies <U+017F>uffer mo<U+017F>t, and are be<U+017F>t fermented by their own proper ferments, namely Ale by yea<U+017F>t, Dough by Leven, Milk by Renet. Thus Apples, Pears and Grapes, and generally all fruit, once corrupted or rotten, do more ea<U+017F>ily affect and putrifie tho<U+017F>e of their own kind then of any other; I <U+017F>ay more ea<U+017F>ily, for they will, though with more difficulty, and after a longer time, corrupt fruits of a divers kind al<U+017F>o; and tho<U+017F>e particular Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens before-mentioned, will in like manner (though probably not <U+017F>o naturally) ferment <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Bodies of who<U+017F>e kind they are not: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s Ye<U+017F>t will ferment Dough (which yet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>omething congenerous to it, as pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng it <U+017F>elf originally from Corn or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap>;) and whites of Eggs bea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> up <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>nowy froth, will indifferently <U+017F>upply <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ant of Ye<U+017F>t, in either Wort or Dough; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>am verily per<U+017F>waded, that the Ye<U+017F>ty <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> which may be taken off the top of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> running Drills of water, would effect <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>me mingled with Dough, unle<U+017F>s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it be not vi<U+017F>cous enough, wherein it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ms only to differ from the whites of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggs beaten as is <U+017F>aid; and it were worth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41619:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the trying to under<U+017F>tand, whether a Ma<U+017F>s of Dough made with flower and <U+017F>now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, would need any other rai<U+017F>ing or Leven. I have read, that in the Countryes about <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Piacenza,</hi> whence tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>o much valued Parmi<U+017F>an Chee<U+017F>es come, the people make u<U+017F>e of Snow in<U+017F>tead of Renet. This in<U+017F>tance however of the white of an Egg beaten, may <U+017F>erve very well to illu<U+017F>trate our Po<U+017F>ition concerning the fermentation of Bodies by the dilatation and con<U+017F>triction of its aereous Particles: as al<U+017F>o the kneding of Dough, and <U+017F>haking of liquors (which is a kind of kneding too) the better to make them ri<U+017F>e and work, will notably confirm what we <U+017F>aid of the Tone of the Air, its frequent alterations, and of windy weather, how much they conduce to the better fermentation of mo<U+017F>t Bodies.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Note, that the rea<U+017F>on why the juices of mo<U+017F>t fruits do <U+017F>oon after expre<U+017F><U+017F>ion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a <U+017F>trong fermentation, <U+017F>eems to be this, that not only the liquor is now more at liberty, then when mixed with the fle<U+017F>hy parts of the fruit, but likewi<U+017F>e that the Airy Particles lay very much compre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed in the fruit, every particular Grape,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41619:15"/>
Cherry and Apple, being in the nature of a little Bottle, which as we <U+017F>ee, if well <U+017F>topt, hinders the working of Ale or Wine, but once opened, the liquors <U+017F>traightway fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <U+017F>well very impetuou<U+017F>ly, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Air forcibly dilating it <U+017F>elf; and this is the rea<U+017F>on that fruit a little eaten by the Birds or Snails, will ripen much fa<U+017F>ter than if they had not been entered upon, (but then the ta<U+017F>te will not be altogether <U+017F>o generous and <U+017F>prightly.) Thus Apples and Pears gather'd green and hoarded, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <U+017F>ooner far, than if they had continued hanging on the Trees, for that they now receive <U+017F>ome vent at their <U+017F>talks; and I find the Ancients were wont to plant the <hi>Caprificus</hi> (or wild Fig-tree) neer their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dome<U+017F>tick Fig-trees, that <U+017F>o the Flees which in great quantities are bred out of the fruit of the <hi>Caprificus,</hi> may <U+017F>eize and pierce the Figs of the other trees, as they do in <U+017F>everal places, thereby not only acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating their time of maturity, but al<U+017F>o (which perhaps is particular to this kind of fruit) rendring them much more tender and delightful than otherwi<U+017F>e they would have been, had no <U+017F>uch Artifice been made
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41619:15"/>
u<U+017F>e of. Now as we have <U+017F>aid, this kind of fermentation whereby fruits attain their maturity, bears a very due proportion with that ob<U+017F>erved in botled drinks, which if well <U+017F>topt are <U+017F>lower in ripening (but of better ta<U+017F>te) than in open ve<U+017F><U+017F>els: as al<U+017F>o if placed in cold well-vaulted Cellars, then if expo<U+017F>ed to the Air: and that for this rea<U+017F>on, that the difference of heat and cold (e<U+017F>pecially in Summer) is by many degrees more in the open Air, than in <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ubterraneous Vaults, and con<U+017F>equently the Aerous Particles, contained in <U+017F>uch ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed liquors, are more dilated and con<U+017F>tricted (reciprocally) when expo<U+017F>ed to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than if laid up in Cellars, or buried in the ground. Which reciprocation of the tone of Air, we have already a<U+017F><U+017F>erted to be the principal, if not the only cau<U+017F>e of all fermentation. And it may be farther illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trated, by a common practi<U+017F>e of botling up Wine, or other drink, with a lump of Loaf-<U+017F>ugar in it, which will make it much more brisk and lively. And this it d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, not by its <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s <U+017F>ure, for that were apter to clog and tame it, as is found by practi<U+017F>e; or if it did, then Syrup of Sugar, or a <U+017F>mall quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:41619:16"/>
of powder Sugar, might indifferently produce the <U+017F>ame effect: which yet is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradicted by experience. Nay, I dare confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirm, that the like quantity of the fame Loaf-<U+017F>ugar, fir<U+017F>t done into very fine powder, will not <U+017F>erve the turn. So that I cannot imagine other rea<U+017F>on, why the lump of Loaf-<U+017F>ugar is of that u<U+017F>e, put into bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than that being very porous, it conveys with it <U+017F>elf, a great quantity of air into the liquor: and does in effect no more, than what has been already <U+017F>aid of the whites of Eggs beaten up together into a froth. So it is not the Sugar, but the air contained in the <U+017F>ugar, which mends the fermentation of the drink, and whereby the Sugar <U+017F>upplies the place of an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal ferment, the better to excite the working of the liquor.</p>
            <p n="16">16. And la<U+017F>tly, methinks it might alone <U+017F>erve turn, to convince us of the great effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy the air hath, and the power it exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<U+017F>eth on all or mo<U+017F>t mixed Bodies: what we finde to manife<U+017F>t by experience in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erving of fle<U+017F>h, fruits, the Bodies of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ects, and other the like, whether for ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or curio<U+017F>ity only, and that with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41619:16"/>
other preparation many times, than by barely immer<U+017F>ing them in wax, oyl, butter, <U+017F>ewet, <U+017F>ome Gum or Ro<U+017F>ine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward carefully putting them up into Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els well <U+017F>topped. By which practi<U+017F>e we <U+017F>eem to obtain little el<U+017F>e, than that we do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as it were, conceal tho<U+017F>e Bodies, thus pre<U+017F>erved, from the air, which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwi<U+017F>e, in a <U+017F>hort time, have totally cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted them: their long continuance and pre<U+017F>ervation <U+017F>eeming to follow, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equence of that artificial exclu<U+017F>ion of the air, whereby the Bodies (or rather the air in them) are no longer apt to be affected, according to the various di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions of the Medium.</p>
            <p>Farther, it is well worth our Ob<U+017F>ervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Chyle, Milk, Cream, the <U+017F>eeds of all Vegetables, and even that of Animals it <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>eem to owe their whitene<U+017F>s, to the inter<U+017F>per<U+017F>ion or di<U+017F><U+017F>emination of air only: even after the <U+017F>ame manner, as is already ob<U+017F>erved in Snow, and <U+017F>ome other Bodies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41619:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That Chylification is a <U+017F>ort of Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and how di<U+017F>tribution is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe Stomack or Ventricle in animals, de<U+017F>igned by Nature for the Office of Chylification, commonly called the fir<U+017F>t Concoction (and which is, as it were, the root of all Vegetation or nutrition in them) <U+017F>eems at fir<U+017F>t birth but ill fitted for <U+017F>uch a work, till the Coats or Membrances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, have been well <U+017F>tained or <U+017F>ea<U+017F>oned by the receipt of an aliment <U+017F>o prepared, that it want little more than warmth, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of that operation upon it, which is expected from the Stomack. And thus, for all animals that <U+017F>uck, Nature has provided for their fir<U+017F>t food, a kind of corrupted Milk, u<U+017F>ually called Bea<U+017F>tings, which gives, as it were, the fir<U+017F>t tincture to their tender Stomacks, and whereby they <U+017F>eem enabled to concoct more perfect Milk,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41619:17"/>
which they begin to draw after a day or two. Which Milk al<U+017F>o by degrees becomes more thick and harder of concoction, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to the encrea<U+017F>e of <U+017F>trength, in the <U+017F>tomack it <U+017F>elf, till by little and little, they begin to alter their diet, and for<U+017F>ake the Teat, for <U+017F>uch other food as is mo<U+017F>t proportionable to their re<U+017F>pective Natures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Tincture, thus imprinted on the Stomack, may very properly be termed a ferment, and <U+017F>eems to bear a ju<U+017F>t proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Leven, which is a <U+017F>mall part of the Ma<U+017F>s of Dough, <U+017F>uffered to grow <U+017F>owre, while the re<U+017F>t is converted into bread, which if not hindred, would have all turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into leven likewi<U+017F>e. Thus after the Chyle is conveyed from the Stomack into the Guts, from thence to be di<U+017F>tributed through the whole Body: <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall part that remains <U+017F>ticking to the coats of the Stomack, <U+017F>oon after acquires that acidity, due to all fermentation not interrupted: which after <U+017F>ome time begins to grieve and afflict the Stomack with its <U+017F>harpne<U+017F>s: the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e whereof, we u<U+017F>ually call hunger: which <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of pain (or hunger) continues to grow more and more, (that which cau<U+017F>ed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41619:18"/>
it becoming <U+017F>till <U+017F>harper and <U+017F>harper) till by the reception of new aliment, the acidi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of the <U+017F>aid Tincture or Leven, be <U+017F>o mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated and allayed, that the Stomack be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it were, healed by application of the<U+017F>e new, benigne, and uncorrupted juices, is no longer <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of any pain or mole<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which then puts an end to the de<U+017F>ire of eating. But if food be forborn, or withheld, the pain <U+017F>o long encrea<U+017F>es, till it at la<U+017F>t de<U+017F>troys the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of the part, and introduces a <U+017F>phalelus, Gangrene or Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the Stomack: which is afterward <U+017F>oon conveyed to the heart and brain, by its communion of Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and <U+017F>o at length becomes the death of the Animal. Which <U+017F>eems rather to be the cau<U+017F>e of death, in <U+017F>uch as peri<U+017F>h by hunger, than the empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s or inanition of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, which, though much exhau<U+017F>ted, are yet found in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>es, with a con<U+017F>iderable quantity of blood in them. Nay, 'tis a frequent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<U+017F>e in the De<U+017F>arts of <hi>Arabia</hi> (as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by <U+017F>ome that have travelled in the Levant) to let their Camels blood after <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral days fa<U+017F>ting, and to give them their own blood to drink, as the la<U+017F>t means left
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41619:18"/>
to pre<U+017F>erve their lives. Which practi<U+017F>e, as it cannot repleni<U+017F>h the veins, to that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure it already emptied them: <U+017F>o it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently concludes, that emptine<U+017F>s of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, is not the true cau<U+017F>e, of peri<U+017F>hing for want of food. Much le<U+017F>s can the continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Suction, from the exhau<U+017F>ted Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to the Stomack, be the cau<U+017F>e of hunger. For fir<U+017F>t, <U+017F>uch hunger could not be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately appea<U+017F>ed after eating, the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els receiving no part thereof, till a con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time after, when di<U+017F>tribution begins to <U+017F>ucceed concoction, as is well known and confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed. Secondly, 'twill appear to <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>hall duly con<U+017F>ider it, that the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els or Veins are then fulle<U+017F>t, when the Stomack is emptie<U+017F>t <hi>(&amp; è contra)</hi> the emptying of the Stomack, beginning with the filling of the Guts, and Veins. Nor <U+017F>hall we need o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arguments, again<U+017F>t this Suction (though it were ea<U+017F>ie to charge it with more difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) than that the owners of it, will be forced to prove, there is <U+017F>ome <U+017F>uch power of moving by attraction, drawing or Sucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which will be a harder matter than it appears at fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight. Though as not making to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, I <U+017F>hall not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ought, concerning it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41619:19"/>3. In confirmation of this our A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> That the concoction of the <U+017F>tomack is a kind of fermentation, it will not b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>s to <U+017F>hew the rea<U+017F>on of <U+017F>ome circum<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it. And fir<U+017F>t, concerning that prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration, which meat receives in the mouth, by chewing or jawing of it, which is rather a brui<U+017F>ing than mincing: and it is a common ob<U+017F>ervation, that fle<U+017F>h minced very <U+017F>mall, is of much harder concoction, than if eaten by bigger pieces; and a <U+017F>ufficient rea<U+017F>on is withall a<U+017F><U+017F>igned, that meat minced, <U+017F>lips down into the <U+017F>tomack, before it be duly ma<U+017F>ticated or chewed, which is <U+017F>o nece<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an antecedent of concoction, that the Arabian Phy<U+017F>itians are wont to <U+017F>ay, <hi>That he that chaws not his meat well, hates his own Soul.</hi> Now that any thing brui<U+017F>ed will <U+017F>oon after corrupt, is evident in all fruits: which will <U+017F>ooner putri<U+017F>ie, after brui<U+017F>ing, than if they were cut with a <U+017F>harp knife in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many pieces. Thus a fle<U+017F>h-wound, made without brui<U+017F>ing, will commonly heal again with little or no corruption, but not if the part were brui<U+017F>ed at the <U+017F>ame time. Thus the common practi<U+017F>e is to brui<U+017F>e Whitloes, to ripen and break them the <U+017F>ooner. And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41619:19"/>
thus to conclude, our meat by being brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, becomes of much ea<U+017F>ier and <U+017F>peedier concoction, which <U+017F>eems to be the rea<U+017F>on why Nature has given to mo<U+017F>t Creatures, namely, Dogs, Wolfes, Swine, Foxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> three <U+017F>orts of teeth; to wit, Tusks to kill their prey with, <U+017F>harp fore-teeth or cutters, wherewith they tear it into <U+017F>maller pieces: And la<U+017F>tly, Grinders to chew and brui<U+017F>e it, the better to prepare it for the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</p>
            <p>Birds <U+017F>eem to grinde their meat in their Gizards, after it is fir<U+017F>t well <U+017F>oak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their craps, for which purpo<U+017F>e they pick up <U+017F>harp <U+017F>tones, and their <U+017F>tomacks are made of two large Mu<U+017F>cles; one, on either <U+017F>ide: the chief in<U+017F>truments in this work of Moliture, or grinding. The Locu<U+017F>ta or Lob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ters has his teeth placed in his <U+017F>tomack, and <U+017F>o have the re<U+017F>t of that kind, which they imploy for the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our next ob<U+017F>ervation <U+017F>hall be upon two Rules of Diet, commonly given by Phy<U+017F>itians: the one is, that we <U+017F>hould not put new meat into our <U+017F>tomack, till after a perfect dige<U+017F>tion of what was eaten the meal before: the rea<U+017F>on of which Rule,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41619:20"/>
<U+017F>eems to be this; That it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>tomack, <U+017F>hould continue <U+017F>ome time empty, that <U+017F>o the Fracid Tincture, or <U+017F>mall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted remaining portion, of the former meat, may have acquired its due acidity: whereby it may the better help the <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fermentation or concoction. And it is no more than if you <U+017F>hould advi<U+017F>e the Hou<U+017F>e-wife, not to make any new Bread till the Leven be grown ripe, or <U+017F>owre enough to leven and ferment the Ma<U+017F>s of Dough. The <U+017F>econd Rule is, that we <U+017F>hould leave eating, with <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall appetite to eat on; or that we <U+017F>hould ri<U+017F>e from Table with an appetite: the rea<U+017F>on is almo<U+017F>t the <U+017F>ame with the former, and may well be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<U+017F>trated by the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tance, which is, that it is requi<U+017F>ite, the Leven <U+017F>hould bear <U+017F>ome ju<U+017F>t proportion, to the Ma<U+017F>s it is to ferment. Thus if we ri<U+017F>e with an appetite, it will appear that we have not over-char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this ferment of our <U+017F>tomacks, for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite being, as is <U+017F>aid, a <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of pain cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed by the <U+017F>harpne<U+017F>s of this acid ferment; it follows, that this acidity is not yet quite ob<U+017F>cured by the late mixture of good, and con<U+017F>equently the <U+017F>tomack, not charged with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41619:20"/>
more, than may be well dige<U+017F>ted, at once by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap>. And the<U+017F>e are Rules, very fit to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved, as well by tho<U+017F>e which are of a more robu<U+017F>t nature, as of them (e<U+017F>pecially) who have weak <U+017F>tomacks, and find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed after eating.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis further advi<U+017F>ed by <U+017F>ome Phy<U+017F>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that <U+017F>uch as have weak <U+017F>tomacks, <U+017F>hould forbear drinking, till they have neer dined: and we commonly ob<U+017F>erve, that drinking ju<U+017F>t before dinner, <U+017F>poils our eating, which it does, by diluting this ferment of the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, whereupon the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of pain, and con<U+017F>equently hunger, abates very much, or quite cea<U+017F>es for a time. And 'tis u<U+017F>ually <U+017F>een, that they who are great Drinkers, are bad Trencher-men: and that as well, for that much drinking relaxes the tone, and extenuates the coats of the <U+017F>tomack, as more e<U+017F>pecially, for that it wa<U+017F>hes away by little and little, all this fracid tincture, or <U+017F>owre ferment, of the membranes thereof, which is as well the cau<U+017F>e of concoction, as of appetite or hunger.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Bulls Blood drunk, was found a pre<U+017F>ent poy<U+017F>on by the Ancients, and Milk taken plentifully, and after curdling on the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41619:21"/>
has often been the cau<U+017F>e of great and mortal Surfeits: the rea<U+017F>on of both is the <U+017F>ame; for that, both blood and milk being curdled, and brought into one hard lump, becomes in<U+017F>uperable to the <U+017F>tomack. Whereas, if the <U+017F>ame be <U+017F>uffered to coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late (before they be eaten) and broken into <U+017F>mall parts, they will have no <U+017F>uch effect, and in<U+017F>tead of poy<U+017F>oning, will afford an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different good nouri<U+017F>hment to the body: So far <U+017F>eems <hi>Helmont</hi> to have mi<U+017F><U+017F>ed the mark, when he <U+017F>ays, <hi>The cau<U+017F>e of this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on is, Imago Irae, in Sanguine Taurino.</hi> And I doubt not but a lump of Beef, or a piece of Chee<U+017F>e, of the <U+017F>ame bigne<U+017F>s, whole in the <U+017F>tomack, would as <U+017F>urely poy<U+017F>on, if not more effectually. And this may farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, what is <U+017F>aid in the third paragraph, of preparing our Food, by chawing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The inward membranes, or skins of the Gizards of mo<U+017F>t Birds (e<U+017F>pecially <U+017F>uch as feed on corn) prepared, by drying and powdring them, are held a great help to concoction. Now the acidity of them is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manife<U+017F>t, and no doubt they do no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e comfort our <U+017F>tomacks, than by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>ing and corroborating that ferment <U+017F>o
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41619:21"/>
often mentioned. Thus, the dung of <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Animals prepared, namely of Wolves, Dogs, Peacocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have been approved of in divers di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, or di<U+017F>tempers of the <U+017F>tomack and guts, for the <U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>e. Nay, I have heard that <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us,</hi> his Occidental Civet prepared, will make an excellent Peptick, for them that can di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e with <U+017F>uch homely remedies.</p>
            <p n="8">8. It is a famous Que<U+017F>tion among Phy<U+017F>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Whether it be better to make a meal of one only di<U+017F>h of meat, or to eat of <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral meats at the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>etting? and it is commonly determined, in favour of the <U+017F>impler diet. But it <U+017F>eems more con<U+017F>onant to our Opinion, to allow rather of <U+017F>everal di<U+017F>hes; for that which is ea<U+017F>ie of concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will help to concoct that which is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Thus good Sauces to meats make them <U+017F>et ea<U+017F>ie, and light, upon the <U+017F>tomack: the Sauces (being ea<U+017F>ie of concoction) helping the di<U+017F><U+017F>olution of the meats. And we may <U+017F>urely expect, a heartier nouri<U+017F>hment from them, than <U+017F>ingle di<U+017F>hes; as we find by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, better broth to be made of <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <U+017F>orts of fle<U+017F>h, than of any one; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the more variety, the more perfect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41619:22"/>
is the pottage. And its well known, we are nouri<U+017F>hed by juices only, and not by the <U+017F>olid part of our food.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Where this ferment of the <U+017F>tomack is more acid than is requi<U+017F>ite (as it is in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochondriacal per<U+017F>ons, and <U+017F>uch as are troubled with <U+017F>owre belches) 'tis found by experience, that to make two, three, or four meals in a day, is better than one: and that fa<U+017F>ting encrea<U+017F>es much the acidity. Tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hard meats, as dry bread, Bi<U+017F>cuits, and tho<U+017F>e that are le<U+017F>s ea<U+017F>ie concoction, are more u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than Broths (and other light meats:) which will <U+017F>ometimes (e<U+017F>pecially taken in a morning, the ferment after long emptine<U+017F>s becoming extraordinary <U+017F>owre) work <U+017F>o vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently, that they will flow up into the mouth, and with their eagerne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>et the teeth an edge, and ferment the very ground. But both in this, and the former rule, 'twill be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to take <U+017F>ome care, that we do not eat much more of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny di<U+017F>hes, than we <U+017F>hould have eat of one, and that the quantity of our meat, at many meals, but equals, or not much exceeds, what we <U+017F>hould have eaten at once or twice.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41619:22"/>10. 'Tis ob<U+017F>erved, that <U+017F>udden change of diet has <U+017F>ometimes proved very fatal, and been often the occa<U+017F>ion of dangerous di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es. The rea<U+017F>on may well be, that the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, having received its tincture or ferment from food of another nature, is but ill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the concoction of tho<U+017F>e meats, to which it hath not been accu<U+017F>tomed, and from which it has as yet received no <U+017F>tain or impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion. Such changes therefore mu<U+017F>t be made by degrees; and thus I have heard, that hor<U+017F>es have been brought to live upon fle<U+017F>h: and <U+017F>ome men, have indifferently well <U+017F>upported life, with bread and herbs only.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Wolves are <U+017F>aid, when pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with extremity of hunger, <U+017F>ometimes to tear the ground, and fill their panches with meer earth: which <U+017F>urely affords them lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no nouri<U+017F>hment. But it <U+017F>erves for the pre<U+017F>ent, to abate the edge of their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, till they meet with <U+017F>ome prey, at which time, they ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>charge their <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks of the earth, and fall to better meat. This in<U+017F>tance may indifferently well <U+017F>upport our A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion, that hunger is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of pain from the acid ferment
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41619:23"/>
of the <U+017F>tomack, than of emptine<U+017F>s from the Suction of the veins.</p>
            <p n="12">12. As concoction <U+017F>ucceeds be<U+017F>t with re<U+017F>t, <U+017F>o motion is <U+017F>aid to help di<U+017F>tribution<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Now by di<U+017F>tribution, we are to under<U+017F>tand the di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ing, of the thinner parts of the Chyle into the milky veins, from thence into the Subclavials, thence into the right Ventricle of the heart, where the Chyle already is pretty well <U+017F>tained, or imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mingled with blood: from whence it takes its cour<U+017F>e to the lungs, where by the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procations of that part, it is yet more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, mixed with the blood. From the lungs, it de<U+017F>cends into the hearts left Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle: from whence, it is thrown into the Arteries: where by degrees it receives the form and name of blood: and by them is conveyed into all parts of the body. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the milky veins, have no attractive power, whereby the Chyle might be <U+017F>uckt into them (as far as could yet be fairly made appear) nor has the Chyle (much le<U+017F>s) any <U+017F>uch inclination or power of moving it <U+017F>elf that way; it remains, that this di<U+017F>tribution of the Chyle, is performed by the motion of the body. And thus we find moderate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41619:23"/>
exerci<U+017F>e, <U+017F>oon cau<U+017F>es an emptine<U+017F>s in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ir<U+017F>t ways, and begets an appetite. And yet we may likewi<U+017F>e ob<U+017F>erve, that while we <U+017F>it <U+017F>till, or <U+017F>leep, this di<U+017F>tribution is performed, though not <U+017F>o <U+017F>peedily. Now while we re<U+017F>t, there is no other motion ob<U+017F>erveable, be<U+017F>ide that of breathing, which <U+017F>eems to be the true cau<U+017F>e of this di<U+017F>tribution of the Chyle, till it comes into the Subclavials: for when we draw in our breaths, the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragme or Midriff compre<U+017F><U+017F>eth the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, and gently forceth the Chyle thence into the guts. And again, when we breath out, the Mu<U+017F>cles of the belly <U+017F>traight <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ide, and <U+017F>trongly compre<U+017F>s the guts; whereupon the thinner part of the Chyle in<U+017F>inuates it <U+017F>elf into the mouths of the milky veins, and by the <U+017F>ucceeding parts of the Chyle, is protruded into the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavials, where afterward it is moved with the motion of the blood. I do not deny the Peri<U+017F>taltick motion of the Inte<U+017F>tines, (whereby the guts di<U+017F>tended with Chyle beyond their due tone, do again by their tran<U+017F>ver<U+017F>e fibres contract them<U+017F>elves) for this is al<U+017F>o a partial cau<U+017F>e of di<U+017F>tribution (as appears in the di<U+017F><U+017F>ection of live Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41619:24"/>
where this motion of the Chyle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues after the Abdomen or belly is laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from one end to the other) but is much <U+017F>trengthened, no doubt, by the Mu<U+017F>cles of the belly; be<U+017F>ides this Peri<U+017F>taltick motion of the guts, <U+017F>hews indeed in part how they are emptied, but not how they are fitted with Chyle, which is the fir<U+017F>t part of di<U+017F>tribution.</p>
            <p n="13">13. 'Tis worthy ob<U+017F>ervation, that Butter melted, and very well beaten (or drawn) the while, becomes a much plea<U+017F>anter cau<U+017F>e, and ea<U+017F>ier of dige<U+017F>tion, than if it be not beaten; and yet all the difference is, that by beating a great quantity of Air, is every where mingled with it, whereby it very much helps the fermentation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of our meat in our <U+017F>tomacks, after the <U+017F>ame manner as is already <U+017F>aid of whites of Eggs, in the former Chapter; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all <U+017F>au<U+017F>es are a kind of additional fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. That there is great quantity of air in Butter thus beaten, may not only be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from hence, that after beating, it takes up more room than it did before, or otherwi<U+017F>e would do, if not beaten; but the <U+017F>ame particles of air are even manife<U+017F>t to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41619:24"/>
<U+017F>en<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf, and the whole Ma<U+017F>s of Butter appears, beaten up, into a froth, <U+017F>o far is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t from being made thicker thereby, (as we commonly expre<U+017F>s our Opinions of it) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat indeed it becomes much thinner and lighter, if compared quantity with quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as is manife<U+017F>t.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Re<U+017F>piration.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="inter">N. 1.</note>THat Animals breath not at all, while in the womb, is mo<U+017F>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that all viperous creatures, after the birth, cannot live long without breath, is mo<U+017F>t certain; yet I do not find the u<U+017F>es of Re<U+017F>piration <U+017F>o clearly determined, but that it may afford us matter for farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. The common received Opinion is, that Re<U+017F>piration <U+017F>erves chiefly for cooling the heart, next that, it yields matter for production of new vital <U+017F>pirits; and la<U+017F>tly, that it di<U+017F>charges the lungs of a fuliginous
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41619:25"/>
excrement, which <U+017F>eems to tran<U+017F><U+017F>ude from the Ma<U+017F>s of blood into the branches of the rough Artery: that the heart is cooled by breathing, is very probable, but not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately; for the air going no farther than the lungs, fir<U+017F>t cools them, next the blood in them, and con<U+017F>equently the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes le<U+017F>s hot, than otherwi<U+017F>e it would be; but this is, in effect, no more than is obtained by bathing the limbs in cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which does a together (if n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t more effectually) cool the Ma<U+017F>s of blood, as much as the air in breathing can be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to do it, and yet bathing will in no wi<U+017F>e become a Sub<U+017F>titute to breathing. Nor does the generation of vital <U+017F>pirits <U+017F>eem to be the chief u<U+017F>e of the air in breathing, in regard it is not ea<U+017F>ie to conceive any <U+017F>uch contrivance in the lungs, that may <U+017F>erve for the letting in of air, into the veins and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, which contain the blood, without endangering, contrariwi<U+017F>e, the effu<U+017F>ion of that precious juice, much le<U+017F>s has Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as yet, di<U+017F>covered any <U+017F>uch pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages unto us. La<U+017F>tly, as I <U+017F>hall not deny, but that the lungs do di<U+017F>charge them<U+017F>elves of a fuliginous excrement by breathing; <U+017F>o I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41619:25"/>
think it as true, that this is none of the principal u<U+017F>es of Re<U+017F>piration. Nor is it at all likely, that either the heart <U+017F>hould grow <U+017F>o hot, or that the vital <U+017F>pirits <U+017F>hould vani<U+017F>h <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t, or the fuliginous excrement be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated in that quantity, upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of breathing for a <U+017F>hort time only, as to indanger our lives beyond recovery, as the ab<U+017F>olute nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of Re<U+017F>piration would <U+017F>eem to inforce. Before I come to deliver my own Opinion, I <U+017F>hall make a <U+017F>light digre<U+017F><U+017F>ion concerning the circulation of the blood, which will not a little illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trate what we are about to <U+017F>ay concerning this Subject.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis manife<U+017F>t in the circulation of the blood in Animals, that the blood is moved from the left Ventricle of the heart, through the great Artery, into all its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, from whence it is brought back by the <U+017F>maller veins, which di<U+017F>charge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves into the Vena Cava, from whence it is returned into the right Ventricle of the heart, from whence it is <U+017F>ent by the Vena Arterio<U+017F>a into the lungs, and <U+017F>o brought back again into the left Ventricle of the heart by the Arteria Veno<U+017F>a: And in this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41619:26"/>
circular motion of the blood, life chiefly con<U+017F>i<U+017F>teth: and if the <U+017F>ame by any chance <U+017F>hould cea<U+017F>e or intermit, though but for a very <U+017F>mall time (le<U+017F>s than a minute) death would unavoidably follow. In this motion of the blood, it is ob<U+017F>ervable fir<U+017F>t, that as the pul<U+017F>ation of the heart <U+017F>endeth it through the Arteries, into the whole habit of the body, <U+017F>o the return of it by the veins, <U+017F>eems to depend chiefly upon the tonical motion of the body; for the parts being extended by the flowing in of the blood, <U+017F>omewhat beyond their tone, do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain gently <U+017F>ub<U+017F>ide, and thereby continue the intended cour<U+017F>e of the blood toward the heart again. An argument hereof is, that all Paralytick parts grow immediately cold, and that for no other rea<U+017F>on, than that the tonical motion, together with the power Locomotive, cea<U+017F>ing, the circulation is either very weakly, or not at all perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through that part, which then grows cold, for want of that con<U+017F>tant fre<U+017F>h <U+017F>upply of blood, which formerly kept it warm. But herein the tonical motion is not a little helped by exerci<U+017F>e and labour, which we find, by experience, to cau<U+017F>e the heart to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41619:26"/>
beat quicker and oftner, as al<U+017F>o to induce a nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of breathing more frequently; and this it doth no otherwi<U+017F>e, than by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerating this circular motion of the blood, which then enforceth the heart and lungs to double duty. Our <U+017F>econd ob<U+017F>ervable in this circular motion of the blood is, that there pa<U+017F><U+017F>es as much blood from the right Ventricle of the heart into the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very pul<U+017F>e (taking one time with another) as is <U+017F>ent from the left Ventricle into all the parts of the body be<U+017F>ide. Nor can it be otherwi<U+017F>e, the left Ventricle being <U+017F>upplied from the lungs only; and the lungs recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, not el<U+017F>ewhere than from the right Ventricle of the heart. So, that to continue this circular motion of the blood, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary, the <U+017F>upply neither exceed, nor come <U+017F>hort of that quantity, di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ed from the left Ventricle of the heart, into the whole body (the Lungs excepted.) From hence it follows, that there flows a greater quantity of blood, by many degrees, into the lungs, than what is <U+017F>ufficient for its own private u<U+017F>e. As al<U+017F>o, that the blood in the lungs, mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, move very much fa<U+017F>ter, than it does in any part of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41619:27"/>
body: though we take for example, the great vein or artery them<U+017F>elves: and that, in the <U+017F>ame proportion, as the <hi>Vena Arterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a,</hi> and <hi>Arteria Veno<U+017F>a,</hi> are <U+017F>maller than the trunks of the fore<U+017F>aid great ve<U+017F><U+017F>els. For, let the <U+017F>ame quantity of liquor be conveyed through a pipe, who<U+017F>e capacity is but one fourth, or one tenth, <U+017F>o big as another pipe, through which the like quantity mu<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>s in the <U+017F>ame time: and it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the liquor mu<U+017F>t run four times, or ten times as fa<U+017F>t, through the <U+017F>maller pipe, as it does through the greater. And thus, it appears, that a very con<U+017F>iderable part of the Ma<U+017F>s of blood, is continually running through the Parenchyma of the lungs; and that, at a much <U+017F>wifter rate, than it doth, through any part of the whole body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ide.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Farther, before we proceed to treat of the u<U+017F>e of Re<U+017F>piration, it will not be ami<U+017F>s to con<U+017F>ider, what kind of motion that is which the lungs are exerci<U+017F>ed with, in breathing. Nor is it any other, than a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of dilatation and con<U+017F>triction; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the lungs are reciprocally opened and <U+017F>hut, <U+017F>omewhat after the manner, of a pair
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41619:27"/>
of Organ-Bellows: the air entring into them, when dilated or opened, and rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding again, upon their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>iding. And this is what we call Re<U+017F>piration. Nor yet, does this reciprocation of the lungs, proceed from any power to move, they are endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with of them<U+017F>elves. For, if we con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the frame and <U+017F>tructure of them, they will appear of a Parenchymous kind of <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, not much unlike the liver, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together void of Mu<U+017F>cles; without which, no local motion can be performed. We may conclude therefore, that the lungs are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by con<U+017F>ent, and that chiefly of the Diaphragme or Midriff, in a free and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary breathing. But, in any difficulty of breathing, as in the A<U+017F>thma, Tabes, violent exerci<U+017F>e, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not only the Midriff, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t all the Mu<U+017F>cles of the trunk of the body, namely, tho<U+017F>e of the Belly, Che<U+017F>t and Shoulders, <U+017F>eem to afford their a<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance, in this great work of Re<U+017F>piration. The motion of the Midriff is fir<U+017F>t down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; whereupon the lungs follow, and the air is admitted, and again upwards; whereby the lungs are compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, and the air excluded. Thus you <U+017F>ee, that as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truction
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41619:28"/>
of the Midriff, <U+017F>o is its motion, <U+017F>omewhat different from that of other Mu<U+017F>cles: which, as being well known, we <U+017F>hall not need to <U+017F>pend longer time about, but come to the publick u<U+017F>e of the lungs, in the Oeconomy of our bodies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the circulation of the blood, we a<U+017F>cribed the reduction of it again into the right ventricle of the heart, to the Tonical motion of the body: where yet, as we have <U+017F>aid, the blood moves but very <U+017F>lowly, if compared, with that <U+017F>wift, and rapid moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is carried on with, through the lungs; where it moves, perhaps, ten times as fa<U+017F>t, as in any other part of the body; as has been already proved. Which notwith<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we <U+017F>hall not be able, upon peru<U+017F>al of the <U+017F>tructure of the lungs, to conclude, that they are endowed with any con<U+017F>iderable tonical motion, as may be gathered, as well from their want of Mu<U+017F>cles, as for that their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, is very <U+017F>pongey and flaccid: and their common integument is but one thin membrane. Nor was it without a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and that a mo<U+017F>t excellent de<U+017F>ign: that Nature thus contrived the lungs with little or no tonical motion in them. For fir<U+017F>t, had this Tone been equivalent to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41619:28"/>
Ma<U+017F>s of blood, to be returned by it; it would much have retarded the influx of the blood, into the lungs: and con<U+017F>equently, have hindered a great work of Nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it there, as <U+017F>hall be <U+017F>hewed hereafter. But chiefly, for that it has largely <U+017F>upplied <U+017F>uch defect, by the a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragme<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> which becomes the cau<U+017F>e, both of dilating, and contracting the lungs; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the occa<U+017F>ion, and at the will and plea<U+017F>ure of the Animal. And this is, indeed, the fir<U+017F>t and principal Office of the lungs; as to what concerns their reciprocal moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Namely, that upon the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>iding of them, in Re<U+017F>piration, the blood may be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>queezed out of them, through the <hi>Arteria Veno<U+017F>a,</hi> into the hearts left Ventricle. And becau<U+017F>e, the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the lungs is very tender; Nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives, that not the Diaphragme immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the air inclo<U+017F>ed in the cavity of the bre<U+017F>t (for this very purpo<U+017F>e only) being fir<U+017F>t, <U+017F>treightened and crowded, as it were, together, by the motion of the Diaphragm upward, <U+017F>hould cau<U+017F>e this compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion upon the lungs; while by its Ela<U+017F>tic pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, it endeavours to dilate it <U+017F>elf again, to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41619:29"/>
its u<U+017F>ual dimen<U+017F>ions. Nor could any way of compre<U+017F><U+017F>ing the lungs, (thereby to di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them of the <U+017F>uperfluous blood) have been contrived more equal: for this pent air, is as apt to pre<U+017F>s upon one part, as on another. Nor yet more gentle, and <U+017F>ecure: for what contact could have been more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate, or le<U+017F>s apt, to wound the tender membrane of the lungs, than the air in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clo<U+017F>ed in the bre<U+017F>t about them? Nor need any doubt, but that the air, thus compre<U+017F>t and <U+017F>treightned, is of <U+017F>trength <U+017F>ufficient for this <U+017F>ervice: and that there is <U+017F>uch a Spring in the air; who, <U+017F>hall but con<U+017F>ider with what force, the air breaks forth of the Wind-gun, and other Pneumatic Engines. A farther confirmation hereof, may be had from hence: that <U+017F>uch wounds, as perfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the bre<U+017F>t, if left open, but for a little time, do quickly cau<U+017F>e a difficulty of breathing<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and I do not much que<U+017F>tion, but if both <U+017F>ides of the bre<U+017F>t were perforated, it would as certainly di<U+017F>patch a man, as hanging; and that, almo<U+017F>t, in as <U+017F>hort a time. Farther, in the di<U+017F><U+017F>ection of live Animals, Re<U+017F>piration continues, long after the Abdomen or belly is laid open; but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41619:29"/>
immediately cea<U+017F>es, upon dividing the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragme or Midriff.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether the air, that enters into the lungs, by the Wind-pipe, have a <U+017F>hare in this compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of them, for the di<U+017F>char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the blood, or not, I am as yet not well <U+017F>atisfied. At fir<U+017F>t view, this compre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion <U+017F>hould <U+017F>eem, to be be<U+017F>t made upon drawing in our breath; between the air implanted in the cavity of the bre<U+017F>t, and the air, in the rough Arteries: (or bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Wind-pipe) but at <U+017F>uch time, the implanted air, is but little or not at all contracted: and therefore we mu<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that either the air taken in, bears no part in this compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion: or which is mo<U+017F>t probable, that the <U+017F>anguine Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the lungs, are not only <U+017F>trongly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, upon expirations; but al<U+017F>o upon in<U+017F>piration; that is, <U+017F>o often, as the lungs are removed from their natural, middle, or indifferent <U+017F>cituation: whether expanded or contracted. Viz. <hi>Tàm in quiete externâ, quàm internâ.</hi> We mu<U+017F>t likewi<U+017F>e allow the air to cool the lungs very con<U+017F>iderably, and that it di<U+017F>charges them of a fuliginous, or rather vaporous excrement. But the<U+017F>e are,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41619:30"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s we have <U+017F>aid, the le<U+017F>s principal u<U+017F>es of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>piration. As for the airs becoming the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Vital Spirits in Re<U+017F>piration, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ay no more, than that I neither find any need of it, nor any may for the mingling of it, with the Ma<U+017F>s of blood.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Allowing what has been <U+017F>aid, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he u<U+017F>e of re<U+017F>piration: we may, perhaps, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd out a more commodious rea<U+017F>on of <U+017F>igh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than has been yet a<U+017F><U+017F>igned. For, if a man <U+017F>hall for a while, either wholly forbear breathing: or, at lea<U+017F>t, breath <U+017F>eldomer, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd lower, than is his u<U+017F>ual cu<U+017F>tom: the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unges, in the mean time, <U+017F>well and fill <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem<U+017F>elves with blood, (for want, of that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>requent and <U+017F>trenuous compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly equal to the influx of the blood,) while the pul<U+017F>e is not <U+017F>o full as ordinarily: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he hearts left Ventricle not receiving its <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue <U+017F>upply from the lungs, which in this <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<U+017F>e receive more than they deliver: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon a man is nece<U+017F><U+017F>itated, (for avoiding <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uffocation) to fetch a great breath, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gh, which may more <U+017F>trongly, than u<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly, compre<U+017F>s the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the lungs, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd reduce them to their former e<U+017F>tate. And thus, great attention, any deep con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41619:30"/>
<U+017F>ad thoughts, and a melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick con<U+017F>titution; do often become the cau<U+017F>e of frequent <U+017F>ighing: As al<U+017F>o, a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <U+017F>loth, or le<U+017F>s aptne<U+017F>s in the lungs them<U+017F>elves, or Diaphragme, to motion: will <U+017F>ometimes make this pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion cu<U+017F>tomary, and habitual. And it is ob<U+017F>ervable, that the pul<U+017F>e ri<U+017F>es very much upon <U+017F>ighing; for the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>troak, or two, at lea<U+017F>t: the blood coming to the Artery again, in that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that a man may feel the tingling of it, at his very fingers ends.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Furthermore, it may not a little <U+017F>trengthen our A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion, that in all great difficulties of breathing: and where there is mo<U+017F>t imminent danger of <U+017F>uffocation, to let blood in good quantity, is commonly pre<U+017F>cribed, as the la<U+017F>t remedy: and which <U+017F>eldome fails, of giving, at lea<U+017F>t, a pre<U+017F>ent relief, let the cau<U+017F>e be what it may be. And this it <U+017F>eems to do, by diverting the cour<U+017F>e of blood from the lungs; while they gently again di<U+017F>charge them<U+017F>elves of their burden. And in ca<U+017F>e of hanging, or <U+017F>trang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, letting of blood in great quantity, has <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>aved mens lives that have been executed; and this by no other ways, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41619:31"/>
I can think of, than by helping to di<U+017F>charge the lungs of their oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, as has been already <U+017F>aid.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And thus we have, if our Opinion fail us not, di<U+017F>covered the true u<U+017F>e of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>piration. We have, al<U+017F>o of con<U+017F>equence, freed the heart, of almo<U+017F>t one half of the task impo<U+017F>ed on it, by the modern Phy<U+017F>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. For <U+017F>ince the circulation of the blood con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts of two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Fir<U+017F>t, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying it from the heart, or center, to the re<U+017F>t of the body, as to a kind of natural circumference. And <U+017F>econdly, the return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or bringing back of the blood again, to the heart. The fir<U+017F>t part, we conceive to be the Office of the heart. The <U+017F>econd part, <U+017F>eems to be the work of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular member, to di<U+017F>charge it <U+017F>elf of its own <U+017F>uperfluities: For which purpo<U+017F>e, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath endued them with a tone, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical motion, <U+017F>ufficient for that <U+017F>ervice, the lungs only excepted, wherein Nature hath worthily imployed her indu<U+017F>try, by the additional contrivance of Re<U+017F>piration, through the a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the Diaphragme: which labour of the lungs, in Re<U+017F>piration, for the returning of the blood to the left
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41619:31"/>
Ventricle of the heart; <U+017F>eems to equal that of the tone, or tonical motion, of all the other parts of the body; for the lungs convey the <U+017F>ame quantity, with all the re<U+017F>t: that is to <U+017F>ay, the whole Ma<U+017F>s of blood, through them; and that in as little time, as the <U+017F>ame pa<U+017F><U+017F>es through the re<U+017F>t of the body. And, if it carries it not <U+017F>o far, it moves <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <U+017F>o much the fa<U+017F>ter. And <U+017F>o, we <U+017F>hall have entitled the lungs, to one full quarter part, of this work of the circulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood, leaving an other quarter to the tonical motion of the body: And the fir<U+017F>t, and worthier half, of di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ing blood and life through the whole body, to the heart, as its proper office and duty. What part, the lungs may ju<U+017F>tly claim to them<U+017F>elves, in the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s of Sanguificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we <U+017F>hall more conveniently find place to con<U+017F>ider of, in the following Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41619:32"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Sanguification.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="inter">N. 1.</note>THe Chyle, when <U+017F>eparated from the remaining unprofitable parts of our Aliment is, by proper ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of its own (the di<U+017F>covery of modern Anatomi<U+017F>ts) conveyed directly into the Subclavial veins, and from thence into the right Ventricle of the heart, where it is mingled with a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger quantity of blood, returning home by the great vein, together with which it is immediately tran<U+017F>mitted to the lungs, where (though it make great ha<U+017F>t through, and moves very impetuou<U+017F>ly, as has been <U+017F>aid, yet) by rea<U+017F>on of the length of the way, it continues a con<U+017F>iderable time, and is more perfectly mingled with the blood, and wrought up together with it, into one Ma<U+017F>s, and at the <U+017F>ame time, acquires both the name and form of blood (as Phy<U+017F>itians term it) and <U+017F>o is fitted for the heart, from thence to be di<U+017F>tributed to the re<U+017F>t of the body: where after what manner it is cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41619:32"/>
we <U+017F>ay not, as a thing already <U+017F>uffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently known, and whereof we have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered our <U+017F>en<U+017F>e already.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Chyle is very ea<U+017F>ily mixt with blood, is evident, for that it is the matter whereof all blood is made, by a farther continuation, of that fermentation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, begun on it in the <U+017F>tomack. Nor yet is the proportion <U+017F>o great between them, but that upon mingling; the di<U+017F><U+017F>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of parts, becomes immediately the cau<U+017F>e of an extraordinary ebullition: which is very much encrea<U+017F>ed by the reciprocal motion of the lungs, whereby the blood is wrought almo<U+017F>t all into a froth or foam, by that time it gets into the left Ventricle of the heart. Which <U+017F>udden exce<U+017F>s of heat, is not unlike what happens upon the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling <U+017F>everal Chymical liquors together, as Spirit of Wine, and Spirit of Turpentine, and other <U+017F>uch like, where the heat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <U+017F>o great, that it often endangers the ve<U+017F><U+017F>el they are contained in. And this is the cau<U+017F>e of that heat a while after meals di<U+017F>cernable in Hectical per<U+017F>ons, and others, otherwi<U+017F>e affected: and which in many ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, by flu<U+017F>hings in the face. Now that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41619:33"/>
the blood is wrought up to that froth, we <U+017F>peak of, during its pa<U+017F><U+017F>age through the lungs, is not only <U+017F>uitable to rea<U+017F>on, but appears mo<U+017F>t evidently, in tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>anguine excretions from the lungs, which happen in con<U+017F>umptive per<U+017F>ons: nor does that frothi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, then ob<U+017F>ervable, proceed from the mingling with it the air we breath, for that at one breathing out (or expiration) could not be <U+017F>ufficiently performed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The blood, by <U+017F>everal very learned men, has not unaptly been compared to wine; and in my Opinion, the Chyle may as properly be likened to the juice, newly pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed out of the Grapes: which if it were by certain intervals, in a due proportion, poured gently into new wine, or mu<U+017F>t, as it begins to cool, would again renew its e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullition, and continue the warmth of it, to what degree is requi<U+017F>ite, and that <U+017F>o long as this practi<U+017F>e <U+017F>hall be continued. And from this Illu<U+017F>tration<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> may be clearly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd; the nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity and u<U+017F>e of eating, at lea<U+017F>t within certain periods, or intervals: to wit, that by the frequent affu<U+017F>ion of Chyle, the blood may again recover its motion, warmth and vigour, without which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41619:33"/>
<U+017F>upply, it would <U+017F>oon langui<U+017F>h, cool and congeal, and con<U+017F>equently, death en<U+017F>ue. Now that the lungs are indeed the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal <hi>Officina Sanguinis,</hi> may be farther colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from Con<U+017F>umptions of the lungs, wherein all parts of the body are <U+017F>o <U+017F>udden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extenuated, by the affection of the part.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis probable, that the blood during its <U+017F>tay in the lungs, does not actually dilate it <U+017F>elf, and ri<U+017F>e into froth, but only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an aptne<U+017F>s <U+017F>o to do, as <U+017F>oon as it is at a little more liberty, as appears in blood <U+017F>pit out of them; and con<U+017F>equently; when it falls into the left Ventricle of the heart, it immediately dilates it <U+017F>elf with great force, in the manner of botled Beer; and in this manner does, for ought I know, in great part, become the cau<U+017F>e of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tole, or expan<U+017F>ion of the heart, which being extended, beyond its due and natural <U+017F>cituation, does again violently contract it <U+017F>elf, by a power almo<U+017F>t all bodies have of re<U+017F>toring them<U+017F>elves, and which we call the tone, or tonical motion. And as we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve in a Switch bowed down, or in a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulum removed out of its place, that they return beyond the perpendicular; <U+017F>o it
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41619:34"/>
fares in this motion of the heart, whereby it is again more contracted, than is natural to it, and <U+017F>o of it <U+017F>elf returns again to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pand it <U+017F>elf, and is again violently di<U+017F>tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as before, by the influx of more <U+017F>pumy blood from the lungs. Now though it may be objected, that the pul<U+017F>e in the heart continues, many times, a long while, after it is taken out of the body; and when there is no longer any <U+017F>uch influx to be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the cau<U+017F>e of it. To this I an<U+017F>wer, that <U+017F>uch pul<U+017F>e, is what the Phy<U+017F>itians call the <hi>Myurus,</hi> or Mou<U+017F>e-tail, for that its Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromes, or differences, between greate<U+017F>t and lea<U+017F>t expan<U+017F>ion, do continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come le<U+017F>s and le<U+017F>s, even as it happens in <hi>Pendulums,</hi> once removed from the perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular, which continue their motion for a long time, after the hand is from them that fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>et them awork. At lea<U+017F>t this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullition of the blood in the heart, <U+017F>eems not a little to contribute to the continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <U+017F>trengthening of this pul<U+017F>ive moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In contemplation of this <hi>Orga<U+017F>mus,</hi> or fury, as I may call it, in the blood i<U+017F><U+017F>uing out of the lungs, and now to be di<U+017F>tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into all parts of the body Nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41619:34"/>
the Arteries with thick and double coats, the better to contain it: whereas the veins de<U+017F>igned for the carrying it back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the heart, at what time the blood is very much cooled and tamed, are only made of <U+017F>ingle membranes, as being <U+017F>uffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient now to hold it. And this is all the difference between Arterial and Venal blood.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It <U+017F>eems of all other Opinions the mo<U+017F>t probable, that the blood, when arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the extremities of the <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, is there <U+017F>hed upon the habit of the body, in the belly, or fle<U+017F>hy part of every Mu<U+017F>cle; each Mu<U+017F>cle having the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or likene<U+017F>s, of one of the quarters, or Acetabula in an Orange, or a Lemon; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of which, either by local or tonical motion, it is not hard to conceive, how the blood is again forced into the mouths of the veins; and after the <U+017F>ame manner has every Mu<U+017F>cle its parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular membrane. And thus we find that blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ues forth, upon pricking the fle<U+017F>h, in any place; although it cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we <U+017F>hould always prick a vein or Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: or we mu<U+017F>t conclude, there is nothing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41619:35"/>
el<U+017F>e in fle<U+017F>h, but a multitude of capillar veins and arteries, which were ab<U+017F>urd to be a<U+017F><U+017F>erted.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To make <U+017F>hort: Life it <U+017F>elf is but a continuation of this vigorous fermentation of the blood, which is <U+017F>o long maintained, as the Ma<U+017F>s of blood is kept hot, and circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating through the veins and arteries; and if done by tho<U+017F>e means, and in that manner, which is <U+017F>uitable to Nature, <U+017F>o long the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is in perfect health. If it be too violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fermented, or moved, it does, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, become the cau<U+017F>e of Fevers, and other acute di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es: as contrariwi<U+017F>e, if the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation be too weak, from thence all chronical di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es take their original: and that particularly, according to the <U+017F>everal irregularities that may happen, either in exce<U+017F>s, or defect, in this fermentation and circular motion of the blood. We de<U+017F>cend not now to particulars, the mo<U+017F>t we aim at in this Treati<U+017F>e, being but a general me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, either of preventing or curing di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, after a way not yet treated of.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Since the di<U+017F>covery of the circulation of the blood, it has been the Opinion of many great A<U+017F><U+017F>ertous of it, that where the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41619:35"/>
indication is of letting blood, it matters not out of what vein it be taken, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <U+017F>o many ounces be let out, as the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e requires. And this their A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion is made probable, by many arguments alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them for that purpo<U+017F>e; and but for the tonical motion of the habit of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, would be as great a truth, as any is in Phy<U+017F>ick. But the tonical motion of the parts once admitted, We mu<U+017F>t likewi<U+017F>e grant, that tho<U+017F>e parts will empty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves fir<U+017F>t, that lie neare<U+017F>t to the inci<U+017F>ion; as well, for that there is le<U+017F>s <U+017F>trength re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to force any liquor to a <U+017F>horter than a longer di<U+017F>tance: as al<U+017F>o, becau<U+017F>e the more remote parts, or Mu<U+017F>cles, do exerci<U+017F>e a kind of Antipraxia, or Contranitency, and <U+017F>o become of mutual impediment one to the other: whereas the nearer parts, do almo<U+017F>t immediately di<U+017F>charge them<U+017F>elves upon the Orifice, or inci<U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p n="8">8. From this tonical motion of the whole body, it happens, that any particular part is <U+017F>ometimes preternaturally <U+017F>welled, either from a <U+017F>troak, the application of cupping-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, or generally any other cau<U+017F>e, which may weaken the tone of the part; for in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41619:36"/>
<U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e, the heart continuing its motion, for the di<U+017F>tribution of the Ma<U+017F>s of humors, it is very ea<U+017F>ie to conceive, that more of them will pa<U+017F>s into that part, where lea<U+017F>t re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance is made, than otherwi<U+017F>e would have happened, had the part continued in its natural tone and vigour.</p>
            <p n="9">9. From hence likewi<U+017F>e the rea<U+017F>on is to be <U+017F>ought, how it happens in letting blood, that <U+017F>o large a quantity <U+017F>hould in <U+017F>o <U+017F>mall a time, i<U+017F><U+017F>ue out at the inci<U+017F>ion made in one vein, and that perhaps none of the large<U+017F>t. For if we duly con<U+017F>ider, how quickly a man may bleed to death, by the opening (for in<U+017F>tance) of a vein in his arm; we mu<U+017F>t conclude, that the blood pa<U+017F><U+017F>es not much fa<U+017F>ter through the heart, than it does at the <U+017F>ame time out at the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifice in his arm; and that con<U+017F>equently, there is but little blood received, during this evacuation, into the re<U+017F>t of the body, which doth then by its tone di<U+017F>charge it <U+017F>elf (into the great vein) of its Plethora, or <U+017F>uperfluous blood<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> which returning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the heart, toward the habit, the greate<U+017F>t part takes its way to the part, where the inci<U+017F>ion was made, it finding
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41619:36"/>
there no other oppo<U+017F>ition, than what it has while it is trava<U+017F>ated from the arteries into the veins, through the <U+017F>mallne<U+017F>s of their mouths, which yet is in part recompenced by the multitude of them. Now if it be agreed on, that in half an hour a man may bleed to death, or thereabout, if a vein in the arm be kept open: and that there will, in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e, be about one half of his blood let out, computing what is likewi<U+017F>e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the capillar ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the habit of the body, it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, either that the whole Ma<U+017F>s is compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly circulated twenty four times in twenty four hours, or a natural day. Which <U+017F>eems a little too often, or that the blood circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates much fa<U+017F>ter, while a vein is breathing, than at other times, which is not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; or that a man may continue bleeding longer than half an hour, which is not <U+017F>o likely: or that there is not in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e of bleeding to death, one full half of the Ma<U+017F>s let out: All which may de<U+017F>erve a more exact <U+017F>crutiny, but mu<U+017F>t now be left to be decided by the experiments of <U+017F>uch, as are conver<U+017F>ant in the di<U+017F><U+017F>ection of live Animals.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41619:37"/>10. It is frequently <U+017F>een in hor<U+017F>es, that upon long and much labour, they lo<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ight of their eyes; nay, I have known <U+017F>ome hor<U+017F>es that have lo<U+017F>t one or both eyes, with one days over-<U+017F>training, either by draught, or cour<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>o became blinde of a <U+017F>udden. And then we commonly <U+017F>ay, they have drawn their eyes out: But how the eyes <U+017F>hould <U+017F>uffer, or what part they take in the labour, or violent exerci<U+017F>e of the body, is not <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>ily made out, unle<U+017F>s by this tonical motion of the body, which now becomes much <U+017F>trengthened by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent local motion, either in drawing, or running, whereby the Mu<U+017F>cles of the whole body are much more compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, than in their natural <U+017F>tate of re<U+017F>t, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently, do not only not admit of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ual quantity of blood and humours, due to them by circulation; but by their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and frequent contraction, do return them back in much a larger proportion, than they now receive them; whereupon the lungs become over-charged, which cau<U+017F>es frequent breathing, and makes the pul<U+017F>e quicker and <U+017F>tronger than formerly, di<U+017F>tends the great vein and artery, with a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41619:37"/>
greater quantity of blood, than is u<U+017F>uall: Whereupon the Artery, by its pul<U+017F>e, and tone endeavours to di<U+017F>charge it <U+017F>elf upon the habit of the body, which not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in its due and accu<U+017F>tomed proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the blood does in a more than a u<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al manner, fill the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the eyes (and other weak parts) and either by di<U+017F><U+017F>enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, or extrava<U+017F>ation of blood, or other humor, the order and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of the parts of the eyes becomes <U+017F>o confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed and di<U+017F>turbed, that no wonder if blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s immediately, or <U+017F>oon after, do en<U+017F>ue. Now 'tis manife<U+017F>t from hence, that where the body of an hor<U+017F>e is clean, that is to <U+017F>ay, not <U+017F>o full of humors; and where blood abounds not over-much, this accident <U+017F>hall not ea<U+017F>ily happen. And here we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve, that though the native tone of the eye do rather exceed that of the other parts, than come <U+017F>hort of it, yet it is not <U+017F>ufficient to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t this influx, when the tone of the other parts is <U+017F>o much <U+017F>treng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by the violent local motions of the body.</p>
            <p n="11">11. If we a little reflect upon the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Circulation of the Blood, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41619:38"/>
how by very modern di<U+017F>covery, the Chyle is fir<U+017F>t mingled with the blood, in the axil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary or <U+017F>ubclavial veins, from whence it pa<U+017F><U+017F>es by the right Ventricle of the heart, through the lungs, into the left Ventricle; from thence to be di<U+017F>tributed into the whole body: One thing very remarkable will ari<U+017F>e to our ob<U+017F>ervation; namely, that what part of the blood is <U+017F>ent toward the head by the carotides or arteries of the neck, flows thither very crude, and accompanied with all its excrements, it having not yet received or <U+017F>uffered any depuration, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, from the Reins or Spleen, like that which pa<U+017F><U+017F>es into almo<U+017F>t all other, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pecially the lower parts of the body (though indeed it <U+017F>eems not to be clean<U+017F>ed of the gall, till it returns home again through the liver.) Now though Natures purpo<U+017F>e herein be very ob<U+017F>cure, that the blood thus impure, <U+017F>hould be de<U+017F>igned for the <U+017F>ervice of the mo<U+017F>t Noble part, yet, that <U+017F>o it is, will farther appear, by the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Emunctories (or <U+017F>inks) wherewith the head is in a particular manner provided, as the ears, eyes, no<U+017F>e, palat; every of which, di<U+017F>charge the brain of a <U+017F>everal excrement,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41619:38"/>
and that no longer u<U+017F>eful to the body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what is <U+017F>ecerned by the palat, which is for the mo<U+017F>t part again returned to the <U+017F>tomack: for the better <U+017F>eparating of which, Nature has indu<U+017F>triou<U+017F>ly placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the head, <U+017F>o many of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>erous ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, called the <hi>Ductus Salivares,</hi> which <U+017F>eem here to perform the <U+017F>ame Office, to that part of the blood <U+017F>ent to the head, which the Reins do execute, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Ma<U+017F>s. Hence no wonder it is; if exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drinking do <U+017F>o much weaken the brain, cau<U+017F>e Catarrhs (which is nothing but an over-flowing of the <hi>Ductus Salivares</hi>) weaken all the faculties of the Soul and <U+017F>en<U+017F>es, and at length, enervate the whole body, although, at the <U+017F>ame time, the Reins do their duty indifferently well; and this e<U+017F>pecially, if the native tone of the brain be weak, it being then <U+017F>o much the le<U+017F>s able to di<U+017F>charge it <U+017F>elf of <U+017F>uch <U+017F>uper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous excrements. This may be <U+017F>aid in general, that the blood is thus <U+017F>ent to the brain, before depuration, in regard of its publick Office, that the <U+017F>ame may there be farther elaborated, as <U+017F>hall be<U+017F>t <U+017F>uit with its <U+017F>ervice in that Noble part. Thus
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41619:39"/>
much, by way of an u<U+017F>eful digre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, may <U+017F>uffice, concerning tonical motion, and <U+017F>ome con<U+017F>iderable circum<U+017F>tances of it; which as well for the a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance it gives the heart, in the circulation of the blood, as for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny u<U+017F>eful indications from thence ari<U+017F>ing, in the Doctrine of Phlebotomy, was mo<U+017F>t properly to be handled in this Chapter of Sanguification.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And now I do not much doubt, but whoever <U+017F>hall have carefully peru<U+017F>ed what has been lately <U+017F>aid concerning Sanguifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the u<U+017F>e of the lungs; will as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily conclude with me, that the lungs do bear a very principal part in the work of Sanguification, for in them the Chyle is perfectly mingled with the blood; in them one half part of the circulation is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and in them the blood <U+017F>eems to free it <U+017F>elf, fir<U+017F>t of all, from any excrement: to wit, a fuliginous, or rather a vaporous wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <U+017F>uperfluity (which pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth out together with our breath.) And this <U+017F>eems the fir<U+017F>t and chiefe<U+017F>t part of Sanguification. The <U+017F>econd, is a farther elaborating the Ma<U+017F>s of blood in the arteries, which is performed by the pul<U+017F>ive motion of the heart. The
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41619:39"/>
third and la<U+017F>t part, is the depuration of the blood, whereby its <U+017F>uperfluous excrements are <U+017F>eparated from it: and this is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the re<U+017F>t of the bowels thus: by pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing through the Reins, it is dreined of its <U+017F>erous parts: Another excrement it <U+017F>eems to leave behind it in the Spleen, though of what kind, is not yet well determined among the modern Phy<U+017F>itians: But on all <U+017F>ides it is concluded, that while it pa<U+017F><U+017F>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through the liver, as through a Streiner, i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is there purged of choler, which in mo<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Animals is collected in a little bladder, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ci<U+017F>tis; from whence it is tran<U+017F>mitted to th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Inte<U+017F>tines, where it becomes a kind of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cly<U+017F>ter, and provokes to the excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the excrements of the fir<U+017F>t ways, as they u<U+017F>e to term them. And this is what lay in our way, to <U+017F>ay at pre<U+017F>ent, concerning Sanguification.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41619:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That often changing the Air, is a friend to health: Al<U+017F>o a di<U+017F>covery of a new method of doing it, without remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from one place to another, by means of a Domicil, or Air-Chamber, fitted to that purpo<U+017F>e.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="inter">N. 1.</note>HAving hitherto <U+017F>hewed what part the air acts in all fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that in re<U+017F>pect of its tone and temper: <hi>Viz.</hi> its difference of rarity, and den<U+017F>ity, and of heat and cold; and that in general only: not con<U+017F>idering what other di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions of the Air may make it apt to promote or retard the motion of fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whereby it may al<U+017F>o powerfully ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, to the continuation or de<U+017F>truction of mixt bodies: as not <U+017F>o directly <U+017F>erving for the illu<U+017F>tration of the Subject, we princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally intend in this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. Having far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made it probable, that the work of our <U+017F>tomacks, upon our Aliments, as al<U+017F>o,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41619:40"/>
that Sanguification it <U+017F>elf, is a kind of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. And la<U+017F>tly, having a<U+017F><U+017F>erted the publick Office of the lungs, together with the u<U+017F>e of breathing, as well in promoting the circulation, as elaborating of the blood. And having likewi<U+017F>e <U+017F>aid <U+017F>omething of the tonical motion of the body; and all this, after a manner, <U+017F>omewhat different from what has been hitherto received, and taught in the Schools. It remains, that from the<U+017F>e Phy<U+017F>iological <U+017F>peculations, we proceed to rai<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome medicinal conclu<U+017F>ions and contrivances, very u<U+017F>eful for the cure, as well as prevention of <U+017F>undry di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But fir<U+017F>t it will be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, to premi<U+017F>e, that the Atmo<U+017F>phere, wherein we breath and live, is heavy or ponderous, and pre<U+017F><U+017F>es more or le<U+017F>s, upon all bodies in it; and upon all <U+017F>ides expo<U+017F>ed to it; and that e<U+017F>pecially, according to its difference of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and den<U+017F>ity. So that upon the tops of very high hills, and in bright weather, the Atmo<U+017F>phere will lie lighter upon us; and all other bodies than the <U+017F>ame, will in thick weather, and in deep valleys; and con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that we move with more difficulty when the air is thick, and with more ea<U+017F>e
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41619:41"/>
when the <U+017F>ame is thinner; which is as much as to <U+017F>ay, that the re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the Medium is proportionable to its mea<U+017F>ure of rarity and den<U+017F>ity. All which we now take for granted, and <U+017F>hall <U+017F>pare our <U+017F>elves the pains of proving, as what has been already <U+017F>ufficiently made out by <U+017F>everal learned men in this our Age: from who<U+017F>e writings <U+017F>uch as doubt, may receive very ample <U+017F>atisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And we <U+017F>hall only conclude, that if all motion, be ea<U+017F>ie<U+017F>t performed in the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>t air, then in <U+017F>uch an air, we <U+017F>hall breath freer, dige<U+017F>t our meat better, and be le<U+017F>s tired with wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king, or working, than in a thicker air: and con<U+017F>equently, perform all the functions of life better, as is indeed manife<U+017F>t, even to experience it <U+017F>elf. (which yet is wont, for the mo<U+017F>t part, to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice but of the more gro<U+017F>s ob<U+017F>ervables) for who almo<U+017F>t is there, of <U+017F>o happy a con<U+017F>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that during health it <U+017F>elf, and in the prime of his years, is not in <U+017F>ome mea<U+017F>ure affected by the alteration of the weather, and by the change of the air? for, as for <U+017F>uch as are <U+017F>ick, the very moments of life and death, do <U+017F>eem to depend upon this change: and <U+017F>uch as are Valetudinary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41619:41"/>
commonly find, to their great grief, that their own bodies, may indifferently well <U+017F>upply the want of a weather-gla<U+017F>s, in admoni<U+017F>hing them, not only of the changes of the weather, but of the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons of the year al<U+017F>o. So very con<U+017F>iderable is this alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the air to all mixed bodies, e<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Animals, and among them, to men more particularly, as being le<U+017F>s armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t the injuries of the air, and among men mo<U+017F>t of all, to <U+017F>uch as are infirm; as hath been <U+017F>aid.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now if the Natural and Vital Functions are better and ea<U+017F>ier performed in a purer air, than in a cour<U+017F>er; no wonder, if upon changing the wor<U+017F>e for the better air, many (e<U+017F>pecially Chronical) di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, do by degrees from thence, receive a cure: which were before invincible, by other remedies: or mu<U+017F>t have been patiently endured, till the alteration of the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on of the year, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that change in the air, (as to its tone and temper) which is <U+017F>ufficient <U+017F>o to rectifie the motion of the humours in our bodies, as at length to overcome the di<U+017F>temper. Which might po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly have <U+017F>ooner been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, by a <U+017F>ea<U+017F>onable removal into a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>omer,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41619:42"/>
warmer, or drier Region. But it is much more remarkable, that not only the changing a bad air for a better, is available in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>es; but much more the often changing of the air, though <U+017F>ometime for a wor<U+017F>e, which is not only confirmed by experience, but likewi<U+017F>e by the Authority of <hi>C. Cel<U+017F>us,</hi> who <U+017F>trictly injoyns it, and adds this as a rea<U+017F>on, that if a man re<U+017F>ide in <U+017F>o good an air, that he knows not where to remove to a better, yet it will be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to remove, and that often; for in ca<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, that may ju<U+017F>tly be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teemed the wor<U+017F>t air, as to the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Patient, in which the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e took its beginning. The rea<U+017F>on (in gro<U+017F>s) why changing the air at all, <U+017F>hould cure di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es, may be this; that the body of man is capable of enduring a greater latitude, either in the tone or temper of the air, than what the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e thus curable can con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t with; and perhaps no other Animal is able to endure that variety of Climes, that a man may indifferently enjoy him<U+017F>elf in. And thus men are found to inhabit in all parts almo<U+017F>t of the Inhabitable World, whereas other Animals are proper to this or that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41619:42"/>
particular Region, and will either die, if tran<U+017F>ported into other places, or at lea<U+017F>t lo<U+017F>e much of their vigour, and not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. The <U+017F>ame is al<U+017F>o ob<U+017F>ervable in plants. 'Tis <U+017F>aid, that Lice bred on this <U+017F>ide the Line, (or Aequator) will immediately all die on the other <U+017F>ide the Line: So that it follows, the Pthera<U+017F>is, or Low<U+017F>ie di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, will be <U+017F>peedily cured by <U+017F>uch a change of the air or Clime: and all, or mo<U+017F>t other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, do <U+017F>eem to bear <U+017F>ome Analogy in their exi<U+017F>tence, to the life of that de<U+017F>pica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble little Animal. But that the often chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the air, is <U+017F>o much a Nobler Remedy, than that of removing once for all into the be<U+017F>t air: The rea<U+017F>on is <U+017F>urely this, that fir<U+017F>t, in the finer air, the motion of Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the humors, and juices of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, is better performed, and <U+017F>omewhat accelerated; and again, a little retarded, by a <U+017F>peedy remove into a gro<U+017F><U+017F>er air, whereby the humors are, as it were, knead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or carded; and the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e at every <U+017F>uch change, receives a notable <U+017F>hake, which <U+017F>eems to be much more <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible (if I may <U+017F>o <U+017F>ay) of every <U+017F>uch impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, than our bodies are. And this often changing the air,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41619:43"/>
does well re<U+017F>emble the many <U+017F>troaks, which are nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to fall the <U+017F>turdier Oak, while one or two, though very con<U+017F>iderable ones, are not <U+017F>ufficient to bring him to the ground. I <U+017F>hould therefore from hence conclude, that if once changing the air, do not in <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>onable time give a<U+017F><U+017F>urance of a cure, that then we doubt not, with the Judicious <hi>Cel<U+017F>us,</hi> to change, as often as <U+017F>hall <U+017F>eem convenient, which <U+017F>urely will, (other helps not neglected) at length (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e be curable) put an end to, and wholly eradicate the di<U+017F>temper, be it almo<U+017F>t what it may be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But it will not be ami<U+017F>s, to be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more particular, in <U+017F>hewing, after what manner the air works upon our bodies, and affects it with its <U+017F>everal alterations, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of rarity or den<U+017F>ity. And fir<U+017F>t, I think it wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be granted by mo<U+017F>t men, and might be clearly proved by <U+017F>everal experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that there is a certain quantity of air in all liquors, in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed in very minute parts, through the whole Ma<U+017F>s of them, which <U+017F>mall particles do actually <U+017F>ymbolize with the Medium; and will, by contracting or dilating them<U+017F>elves, cau<U+017F>e
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41619:43"/>
the liquor wherein they re<U+017F>ide, to take up <U+017F>ometimes more, and <U+017F>ometimes le<U+017F>s room: as will be manife<U+017F>t to him, that <U+017F>hall fill a large gla<U+017F>s bottle, of about a pottle or more, with water, till it ri<U+017F>e two or three inches in the neck, which will need to be very <U+017F>lender, and <U+017F>omewhat long, and it will <U+017F>oon appear, that the water <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ometimes ri<U+017F>e, and at other times fall, almo<U+017F>t after the manner of ordinary Weather-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es: as will be much more manife<U+017F>t, if it be for a while <U+017F>et neer the fire, <U+017F>o as to be a little warmed by it. Now the humors and jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our bodies, have likewi<U+017F>e the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain proportion of air in them, and that in a far greater mea<U+017F>ure, than common wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which <U+017F>eems of all other liquors to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the lea<U+017F>t (as is probable from the <U+017F>mall inclination it has to be fermented) and therefore it <U+017F>eems to follow, that upon all changes in the Air, or Medium, the juices of our bodies are affected: (even after the <U+017F>ame manner, as has been <U+017F>aid of common water) and that according to the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Weather, of day and night, and of the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons of the year. Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, or changes, in any one particular
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41619:44"/>
place, have a kind of orderly method of <U+017F>ucceeding one another, but much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of another place or Region, which, though it have the like alterations of Weather, Sea<U+017F>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the order or method of this variety, is as it were, of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Scale from that of the former. And the differences of heat and cold, den<U+017F>ity and rarity in the Medium, are either greater or <U+017F>maller, than tho<U+017F>e of the former: whereby the body removed from the place of its former aboad, to another, is affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the varieties afore<U+017F>aid, after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner than what was u<U+017F>ual to it. Whereby the face (if I may <U+017F>o <U+017F>ay) or complexion of the humors and juices in the body, will be much altered and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from what it lately was: and con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the Morbo<U+017F>e Character very much defaced, if not wholly obliterated. Which effect will in all probability more certainly <U+017F>ucceed upon often, than upon once change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the air, as has been already <U+017F>ufficiently evinced, both from rea<U+017F>on and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of all changes of the air, that is commonly ob<U+017F>erved to be mo<U+017F>t effectual, for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41619:44"/>
the cure of any di<U+017F>temper gotten abroad; which is made by removal from a forreign Country, to a mans own Native Soil, or the place of his birth, and fir<U+017F>t abode: which <U+017F>eems to be true <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> from hence, that the Aerious Particles, which originally go, as one principal ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the making up of the body, were at fir<U+017F>t of the <U+017F>ame tone exactly with that of the Medium: and it cannot be imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that upon any con<U+017F>iderable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval, the<U+017F>e Aery Particles mu<U+017F>t be more or le<U+017F>s dilated, or contracted, than they formerly were, whereby the body will be preternaturally affected. Which though during the <U+017F>tate of health, it be not cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ufficient, perhaps, to manife<U+017F>tly hinder any action of the body; yet in ca<U+017F>e of a di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, it <U+017F>eems to be a notable relief to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be re<U+017F>tored again to its Native con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>titution (as far as is po<U+017F><U+017F>ible) which is a kind of renewing, and no <U+017F>mall refre<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the body: from whence a Patient <U+017F>eldome fails of a relief, and very often finds a perfect cure, in <U+017F>everal contumacious di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I would not be <U+017F>o far mi<U+017F>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tood:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41619:45"/>
as if I a<U+017F><U+017F>erted the alterations our bodies <U+017F>uffer from the Medium, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly the <U+017F>ame, in degree, with tho<U+017F>e of the Weather-gla<U+017F>s; for that I think were hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with perfect health, as we find the<U+017F>e alterations in mo<U+017F>t per<U+017F>ons are: though in infirm bodies they are very mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t. But I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, by this time, it may be expected from me, that I give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this difference, and <U+017F>ay how it comes to pa<U+017F>s, that the air in our bodies is not affected by the Medium exactly, after the manner of the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, but in a le<U+017F>s degree, where for the only rea<U+017F>on I can think of, I <U+017F>hall a<U+017F><U+017F>ign the tone or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical motion of every body <U+017F>o often menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; which being compre<U+017F><U+017F>ive of all the parts of our bodies, it very con<U+017F>iderably checks and hinders that dilation of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, by means of the rarified air, which would otherwi<U+017F>e en<U+017F>ue upon the like affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Medium: which compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, or re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the tone, or tonical motion of the body, may be very well illu<U+017F>trated from a bottle full of (nothing but) air, well <U+017F>topt, and afterward expo<U+017F>ed to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of heat and cold. In which ca<U+017F>e, it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41619:45"/>
cannot be imagined, that the included air, is at all either dilated, or contracted: not the fir<U+017F>t, becau<U+017F>e there is no room for it to expand it <U+017F>elf upon, nor yet the la<U+017F>t, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ides of the Bottle are not apt to <U+017F>ub<U+017F>ide, without which, no <U+017F>ufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on can be given, why the air, upon exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal cold, <U+017F>hould quit any part of the place it formerly repleni<U+017F>hed. And yet in <U+017F>ome ca<U+017F>es, the differences of heat and cold may be <U+017F>o great, as to prevail over the <U+017F>trength of an ordinary bottle, and break it, as has been often found by experience. But here we mu<U+017F>t ob<U+017F>erve, that though the <U+017F>ides of the bottle give no way at all to the air included, yet the tonical power of the body doth <U+017F>omewhat yield to <U+017F>uch alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the humors; and that more or le<U+017F>s, according to its different <U+017F>trength in the body, of this or that individual. Nor doth this experiment of the Bottle <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently conclude, but that, at lea<U+017F>t, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the air in our bodies, ought to an<U+017F>wer that of the Medium: and indeed, that it doth not, <U+017F>eems to proceed from the internal heat in the humors of Animals, (maintained, as is <U+017F>aid in the Chapter of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41619:46"/>
Sanguification) which is of power <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, not only to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the tone, or tonical motion of the habit of the body, but that of the medium al<U+017F>o. And <U+017F>hould the contrary happen, death would inevitably en<U+017F>ue.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It may be farther noted, that all bodies (whether men, or other Animals) are not equally affected with the <U+017F>ame change or alteration in the Medium; but, as hath been <U+017F>aid, proportionably to the <U+017F>trength of the tonical power of each bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And thus it happens, that a per<U+017F>on of a Robu<U+017F>t Con<U+017F>titution, and habit of body, (whether <U+017F>uch naturally, or acquired by much travel and labour) will with le<U+017F>s trouble and hazard of his health, endure any notable alteration, or change of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Soil, than another of a finer Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and compo<U+017F>ure; and who<U+017F>e tone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently is not <U+017F>o re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tive of the impre<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from without, as that of the former. And thus it is ea<U+017F>ie to conceive, why a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on inhabiting neer either of the Poles of the Earth, and removed to, or neer the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator: or the contrariwi<U+017F>e, will find the temper of that Clime more trouble<U+017F>ome
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41619:46"/>
and offen<U+017F>ive to his health, than he <U+017F>hall, that from the middle temperate Region, <U+017F>hall transfer him<U+017F>elf to either of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes. And no doubt, the le<U+017F>s the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is, the ea<U+017F>ier and <U+017F>ooner <U+017F>hall a mans Nature be brought to comply with it. And thus we ob<U+017F>erve, that <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gezes,</hi> do with le<U+017F>s danger, travel and trade into the more Southern Regions of the world, than Northern men can do, who are commonly not otherwi<U+017F>e <U+017F>ea<U+017F>oned, than by <U+017F>ome dangerous Calenture, Flux or Spa<U+017F>m, or other deplorable di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by much, the greater part of them, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly de<U+017F>troyed. All which di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are no other, than the effects the Medium hath upon the Air impri<U+017F>oned in our bodies; which if it finds the humors ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed to a farther degree of fermentation, than what is con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with health, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a Fever or Calenture in <U+017F>ome bodies; in others, a dangerous Flux: and in <U+017F>ome mo<U+017F>t violent Spa<U+017F>mes, upon the forcible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation either of the Air in the nervous parts, or of that, which may po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly be, in the <U+017F>paces between the Mu<U+017F>cles.</p>
            <p n="8">8. From hence probably it is, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41619:47"/>
the fruits of tho<U+017F>e hotter Countryes are <U+017F>o dangerous, e<U+017F>pecially to <U+017F>trangers; for that they are no <U+017F>ooner received into the body, but they are <U+017F>traightways very vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently fermented (and after the <U+017F>ame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ferment the juices of the body, to the di<U+017F>ordering of the whole frame) in <U+017F>o much, that the juice of <U+017F>ome plants, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a deadly poy<U+017F>on, as that of the Root of <hi>Yucca</hi> (while the <U+017F>olider parts are made into a kind of whole<U+017F>ome bread) and po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly, for no other venomous quality, than its over-active fermentation, whereby it not only di<U+017F>turbs, but de<U+017F>troys the Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy of the body. All which, and much more of this kind, that might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <U+017F>eems in great part to depend upon the finene<U+017F>s, or rarity of the Medium, which lying lighter on liquors, and other bodies thus fermented, <U+017F>uffers them more ea<U+017F>ily, and more violently, to expand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves, than, for the mo<U+017F>t part, is <U+017F>uitable with the health of <U+017F>uch as eat them, e<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in any con<U+017F>iderable quantity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And now from what hath hitherto been <U+017F>aid, it may <U+017F>eem exceeding probable, that the Air doth con<U+017F>iderably alter, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41619:47"/>
di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e the humors of our bodies, e<U+017F>pecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon changing one Clime for another; and that our bodies do, more or le<U+017F>s, <U+017F>ympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with the pre<U+017F>ent tone and temper of the Medium; whereby it is not only freed from <U+017F>everal di<U+017F>tempers, but may al<U+017F>o ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often be thereby variou<U+017F>ly di<U+017F>affected, and ca<U+017F>t into divers dangerous di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. But yet, how u<U+017F>eful <U+017F>oever the changing of the Air may be, for the cure of any infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: we find it <U+017F>tands with the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence but of very few, to make <U+017F>uch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movals; for that they cannot well di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e, with the leaving their Families or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, together with other their familiar af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, or imployments. Be<U+017F>ides, Phy<U+017F>itians are not apt to advi<U+017F>e their Patients to it, till they have fir<U+017F>t, in vain, imployed mo<U+017F>t other remedies in the cure of them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by commonly the oportunity is lo<U+017F>t, and the <U+017F>ick per<U+017F>on deprived of that benefit he might, in all probability, have received, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a more <U+017F>ea<U+017F>onable removal. Be<U+017F>ides, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, it would be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, not only to remove to <U+017F>ome neighbouring place, or other, but even to take a journey of <U+017F>ome hundreds of miles, which cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41619:48"/>
by the <U+017F>ick, but with great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. So that what through one impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or other, the thing happens to be but rarely put in practi<U+017F>e; and <U+017F>o Noble a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, is not only neglected, but in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner brought into di<U+017F>e<U+017F>teem with <U+017F>ome, for want of more frequent examples of the great u<U+017F>e of it; while they cannot give them<U+017F>elves a <U+017F>atisfactory account, how <U+017F>uch a change of the Air <U+017F>hould <U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderably work upon our bodies.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Now to the end we may not want the help of <U+017F>o generous a remedy; and for the better avoiding the fore-mentioned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in the u<U+017F>e of it. I hold it a matter of no <U+017F>mall compendium, in this place, briefly to <U+017F>et down, and <U+017F>hew the manner of a certain contrivance, how any per<U+017F>on may receive the benefit he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, upon removal from his abode, to any other place (with intent to change the air) and that almo<U+017F>t indifferently at any <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on of the year, without <U+017F>o much as remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out of his own hou<U+017F>e, or neglecting any occa<U+017F>ions what<U+017F>oever. Fir<U+017F>t therefore, in <U+017F>ome fit place neer, or adjoyning to your hou<U+017F>e, erect a convenient Room, of about
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41619:48"/>
<U+017F>ome twelve or fourteen foot <U+017F>quare, or of what <U+017F>ize you plea<U+017F>e, either bigger or <U+017F>mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler than the former, and let it be exactly well cieled, or vaulted over head, and well paved; or otherwi<U+017F>e <U+017F>o floared at bottom, that the air may not have any vent, to get either out, or in, nor yet through the walls, which it is requi<U+017F>ite <U+017F>hould be of brick or <U+017F>tone, and well plai<U+017F>ter'd on the in<U+017F>ide; and let the windows be likewi<U+017F>e <U+017F>o contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that no air may pa<U+017F>s in or out that way, which the ea<U+017F>ier to prevent, and that they may be al<U+017F>o the <U+017F>tronger, and le<U+017F>s apt to crack, they ought not to be very big, nor many. The door mu<U+017F>t be likewi<U+017F>e <U+017F>o contrived, that it may <U+017F>hut into its frame <U+017F>o exactly, that when it is made fa<U+017F>t, there may not be the lea<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>age left for the air to get in or out of the fore<U+017F>aid Chamber. The particular manner and contrivance of doing all which, I do not here <U+017F>et down, for that I doubt not, but there are ingenious Ma<U+017F>ons and Joyners, that will much exceed any directions, that I can be able to give them. Your Air-Chamber being thus made, you mu<U+017F>t farther provide your <U+017F>elf with a very large pair of Organ Bellows, which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41619:49"/>
mu<U+017F>t be placed in <U+017F>ome convenient part of the Room, where by the help of a Skrew, the No<U+017F>e of them may be exactly joyned to a Copper Pipe, who<U+017F>e other end mu<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>s through the wall of the Room, and have a value, opening outward, exactly fitted to it, as is u<U+017F>ual in Water Engines: and if the <U+017F>aid Value be placed in water, it will do much better. This Brazen Pipe mu<U+017F>t likewi<U+017F>e have another Value to open inward, and both <U+017F>o contrived, that either of them may be <U+017F>et open at any time, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, while the other is imployed. The Bellows being thus fitted, and the door and windows clo<U+017F>e <U+017F>hut, you may at plea<U+017F>ure either fill the Chamber with Air, by force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in what quantity you plea<U+017F>e, till there be twice or thrice as much as there was at fir<U+017F>t, ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the <U+017F>ame be as thick as is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ite. You may likewi<U+017F>e di<U+017F>charge the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of one third, one half, or more of the air it had at fir<U+017F>t in it, till you have on the contrary, brought what remains, to that degree of Tenuity (or thinne<U+017F>s) is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and this by the help of the Bellows; which if the air be to be forced out, mu<U+017F>t lie with their moveable part upwards; and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41619:49"/>
the innermo<U+017F>t Value of the Brazen Pipe, before mentioned, mu<U+017F>t either be taken off, or kept con<U+017F>tantly open: but if air is to be forced into the Chamber, then the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows will need to be turned the wrong <U+017F>ide upward; and the outward Value of the Bra<U+017F>s Pipe mu<U+017F>t be taken off, or kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the innermo<U+017F>t Value <U+017F>uffered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to play. In which ca<U+017F>es, working gently with the Bellows, you may either charge, or di<U+017F>charge (as I may <U+017F>ay) the Air-Chamber at your plea<U+017F>ure, and con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, obtain an Air in it, of what rarity or den<U+017F>ity you plea<U+017F>e. The mea<U+017F>ure of which variety, that you may the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly take an account of (and that there may be very little or no mi<U+017F>take in the u<U+017F>e of this Chamber) it will be ab<U+017F>olutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary, to have con<U+017F>tantly with you, a large Weather-gla<U+017F>s: And you may likewi<U+017F>e have a Tub of gla<U+017F>s, of <U+017F>ome forty inches long, filled with Quick-<U+017F>ilver, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a little Earthen or Wooden Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, half filled, with a quantity of the <U+017F>ame material, after the manner of the Torricellian experiment; and the<U+017F>e are to <U+017F>erve you for Regi<U+017F>ters: for by the a<U+017F>cent,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41619:50"/>
and de<U+017F>cent of the Water, in the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, will be noted to you, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, on the neck of the Gla<U+017F>s, in what prop<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtion you have either rarified or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<U+017F>ed the Air within the Room: and you may by help of it, rectifie the tone of the Air, to what degree is requi<U+017F>ite, or injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The u<U+017F>e of the Quick <U+017F>ilver Tub, is the very <U+017F>ame, but will not give <U+017F>o exact an account, of every <U+017F>mall difference, as the former, by rea<U+017F>on of the <U+017F>mall quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Air contained in it: but yet will not want its u<U+017F>e in other experiments, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Phy<U+017F>ick, which I <U+017F>hall not here touch upon, as too remote from what we here handle. Such therefore, as imploy this contrivance, only in Relation to their Health, may content them<U+017F>elves with a Weather-gla<U+017F>s, which will prove much an exacter Regi<U+017F>ter, than the Quick-<U+017F>ilver Tub, as hath been already <U+017F>hewed.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As to the particular application of the u<U+017F>e of the newly de<U+017F>cribed Domici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, or Air-Chamber, 'twill not be ami<U+017F>s to repeat, what we before a<U+017F><U+017F>erted in the precedent Chapter; namely, that as health it <U+017F>elf, is maintained by a due and <U+017F>uitable
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41619:50"/>
fermentation of the humors in our bodies, and that within a certain latitude. So, if the irregularity of the <U+017F>aid motion, or fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, be great enough, to become the cau<U+017F>e of the manife<U+017F>t abolition, or weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only, of any action of our bodies, the party <U+017F>o affected, is <U+017F>aid to be <U+017F>ick, or di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed: and as all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es may be divided into acute, whereto are tho<U+017F>e of <U+017F>hort continuance to be referred (though they are not u<U+017F>ually termed Acute, taking the word more <U+017F>trictly) and Chronical affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: or el<U+017F>e (which comes to the <U+017F>ame thing) they may properly enough be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, participating of heat, or of cold. The former of which we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready defined, to depend upon <U+017F>uch an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular fermentation of the blood, and Ma<U+017F>s of humors, wherein the <U+017F>ame are more violently moved, than is con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with health: of which kind are all continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and intermittent Fevers, all Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, mo<U+017F>t Fluxes, and <U+017F>everal other di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: and contrariwi<U+017F>e, all Chronical, or cold affections, <U+017F>eem to depend upon <U+017F>uch an irregularity of the fore<U+017F>aid Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby the humors are not <U+017F>o <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41619:51"/>
moved, and agitated, as is requi<U+017F>ite to health; of which kind are the Scurvey, the Rickets, all Drop<U+017F>ies, <U+017F>ome Fluxes, mo<U+017F>t affections of the Spleen, and probably the Gout, and other Arthritical di<U+017F>tempers. Now the method of u<U+017F>ing this Domicil, or Air-Chamber, in general, will be this, that where the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e <U+017F>eems to depend upon a deficient Fermentation of the humors, in <U+017F>uch ca<U+017F>e, the Patient (being put into the <U+017F>aid Chamber, and the door clo<U+017F>e <U+017F>hut) <U+017F>hall, by degrees, di<U+017F>charge the <U+017F>ame, or force the air out; till having con<U+017F>iderably alter'd the tone, and rarified what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, he <U+017F>till finds him<U+017F>elf to breath free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at lea<U+017F>t with no great difficulty; at what time he may ob<U+017F>erve, how low the water is de<U+017F>cended in his Regi<U+017F>ter, or Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-gla<U+017F>s, which will <U+017F>hew him how far he may <U+017F>afely, at another time, di<U+017F>charge the air, without danger of Cramping; which u<U+017F>es to en<U+017F>ue, if the air be too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly rarified. On the other <U+017F>ide, if the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e be Acute, and <U+017F>eem to depend upon the too violent Fermentation of the humors, then it is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary the Chamber be well charged with air, to what degree
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41619:51"/>
of Toleration <U+017F>hall <U+017F>eem convenient. And here we are principally to provide, that no difficulty of breathing en<U+017F>ue, which oftner happens in this practi<U+017F>e of conden<U+017F>ed, than attenuated air. Now the term of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients continuance in the Chamber, at one time, is to be defined in Chronical di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, as well from his own occa<U+017F>ions, as other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<U+017F>tances; and generally two, three, or more hours, may <U+017F>eem <U+017F>ufficient, and that e<U+017F>pecially in the morning, when the u<U+017F>e of other Remedies are found mo<U+017F>t conducible. But in acute di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, it <U+017F>hould <U+017F>eem nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ary, that the Patient continued in the <U+017F>aid Chamber, during the whole cour<U+017F>e of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and that the tone of the air be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently altered, after the directions of <U+017F>ome able Phy<U+017F>itians, according as the times of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e <U+017F>hall <U+017F>eem to require; e<U+017F>pecially in intermittent Fevers, where the time of the whole Paroxi<U+017F>me mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>pent in the Chamber, and the cold fit requires to be treated as a cold di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, with rarifying the air, as the hot fit, by conden<U+017F>ing it, which mu<U+017F>t be carefully ob<U+017F>erved. Now though there may be many di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, as the Stone, the French Pox, and <U+017F>ome other,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41619:52"/>
which do not depend <U+017F>o immediately, upon the afore<U+017F>aid irregularities of the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the humors; yet I <U+017F>hould not doubt, even in the<U+017F>e, to commend the u<U+017F>e of this Domicil, or Air-Chamber: for that while Nature is thereby much <U+017F>trengthened in all her Natural Functions, it mu<U+017F>t needs follow, that <U+017F>he will from hence, at lea<U+017F>t, be enabled the better to endure the conflict with tho<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, if, at la<U+017F>t, <U+017F>he do not wholly get the better of them. It will farther be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary here to add, that in maligne di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and where we require an amendment of the in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible tran<U+017F>piration; we are, as in cold di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, to rarifie, and not conden<U+017F>e the air in the Domicil, where the Indication is rather pre<U+017F>ervative, than curative, as Phy<U+017F>itians u<U+017F>e to <U+017F>peak.</p>
            <p n="12">12. To <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething of the u<U+017F>e of this contrivance, in time of health, we <U+017F>hall only propo<U+017F>e it, as a good expedient to help dige<U+017F>tion, and e<U+017F>pecially in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible tran<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and facilitate breathing and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoration; and con<U+017F>equently, as of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent u<U+017F>e, for prevention of mo<U+017F>t affections of the lungs, where they are feared; and that generally, what ever the benefits of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41619:52"/>
changing the air, are, may be rea<U+017F>onably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the u<U+017F>e of this Domicil; and that after a more certain regular way, than without it, for that by the means of it, a per<U+017F>on may <U+017F>erve him<U+017F>elf with <U+017F>uch air, as were not otherwi<U+017F>e to be found, but on the top of the Pike of Teneriff, or <U+017F>ome other very high Mountain: nay, if it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, as perhaps it may in <U+017F>ome very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious affections, he may rarifie the air to a far higher degree, and make it <U+017F>uch, as is not again to be found upon the face of the whole inhabitable world. But as well in <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, as in health, tho<U+017F>e great exce<U+017F><U+017F>es are not to be ventured upon, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. The u<U+017F>e of this Domicil may be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extended, for preventing the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience which may en<U+017F>ue, upon any great change of air, by travelling into forreign Countryes; whereby a per<U+017F>on may at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure reduce the tone of the air, to that of his own Soil or Climate: and probably, if the <U+017F>ame might be made u<U+017F>e of aboard Ships, it would (with the additional contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of a Chair, or Bed, hung after the manner of a Sea-Compa<U+017F>s) prevent that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41619:53"/>
very trouble affection whereto fre<U+017F>h men are <U+017F>o <U+017F>ubject, called Sea-<U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently, become very <U+017F>erviceable to <U+017F>uch, who<U+017F>e imployments ingage them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take Voyages into very remote parts, and there to re<U+017F>ide, far from their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes. There may, I doubt not, <U+017F>everal o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther con<U+017F>iderable conclu<U+017F>ions be performed, by means of this contrivance: As al<U+017F>o, that the thing it <U+017F>elf is very capable of good improvement, as to the projection of it, far beyond that de<U+017F>cribed by us. All which, together with what hath been already <U+017F>aid, and undertaken by us, on the behalf of it. We leave for farther di<U+017F>covery, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to practi<U+017F>e and experience.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Among the improvements which this contrivance of an Air-chamber is probably capable of, it is in my judgement none of the lea<U+017F>t that may be obtained, by joyning the practi<U+017F>e of S. <hi>Sanctorius,</hi> in his <hi>Medicina Statica,</hi> to this of ours. For as the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the tran<U+017F>piration by the habit of the body (than which, nothing conduces more to the pre<U+017F>ervation of health, and prevention of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es) is one of the mo<U+017F>t
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41619:53"/>
con<U+017F>iderable among tho<U+017F>e many benefits we promi<U+017F>e our <U+017F>elves by it: So, if we <U+017F>hall have, as <hi>Sanctorius</hi> directs, a <hi>Statera Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> in our Air-chamber, it will be of very great con<U+017F>equence, for a<U+017F>certaining the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical u<U+017F>e of it, whereby it will become le<U+017F>s <U+017F>ubject to gue<U+017F>s or hazard. For as the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, before-mentioned, will di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to us, the degrees of rarity and den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity, introduced in the inclo<U+017F>ed air: So the Balance, will with the <U+017F>ame exactne<U+017F>s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, at what rate this <hi>Diaphoretical</hi> tran<U+017F>piration, is either improved or abated: and at the <U+017F>ame time give us the true weight (in Ounces and Drachmes) of tho<U+017F>e in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible <hi>Effluvia,</hi> which continually pa<U+017F>s that way. For the Patient, weighing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf (for in<U+017F>tance) fir<U+017F>t at <U+017F>even of the clock in the morning, and again at nine or ten (having fir<U+017F>t exonerated him<U+017F>elf) and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>taining from meat and drink, in the mean time; <U+017F>hall thereby perceive how much (by weight) of his aliment, or rather of the unprofitable part thereof, in tho<U+017F>e two or three hours, pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly through the pores of his body. Let him again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the <U+017F>ame experiment, the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41619:54"/>
with the <U+017F>ame circum<U+017F>tances, in the Air-chamber: and he will not be a little <U+017F>urprized, to find half <U+017F>o much more, and perhaps, twice the quantity evacuated, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible manner (or <hi>è contra</hi>) and that in <U+017F>uch proportion, as he <U+017F>hall have <U+017F>uffered more, or le<U+017F>s, of the included air, to have pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed into the circum<U+017F>tant Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, (or <hi>è contra</hi>) of what proportion the Weather-gla<U+017F>s, as a faithful Regi<U+017F>ter, <U+017F>hall give him a very particular account. I will not farther inlarge, upon this addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional practi<U+017F>e, of the Scale or Balance: much le<U+017F>s add any thing of the u<U+017F>e of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Tran<U+017F>piration, lea<U+017F>t I might offend <U+017F>uch, as are better ver<U+017F>ed in Statical Experiments; by the unprofitable repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of what they are already <U+017F>o well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with: or by giving an ill account of a book I have but once read over, and that neer twenty years <U+017F>ince, deprive others of that <U+017F>olid benefit they may receive, by peru<U+017F>al of the above-commended Treati<U+017F>e of <hi>Sanctorius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. As this contrivance of the air-chamber, is be<U+017F>t fitted for the improvement of health, and the aboli<U+017F>hing <U+017F>uch Morbo<U+017F>e Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41619:54"/>
as depend upon the over-<U+017F>low, or too nimble fermentation of the Humors. So it were ea<U+017F>ie to project, great Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, after the manner of Cupping-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, <U+017F>ome capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to receive the whole Thighs, others fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Arms: whereby we may at plea<U+017F>ure, (as the <U+017F>eat of <U+017F>ome particular di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>hall direct) make <U+017F>uch powerful revul<U+017F>ions, as <U+017F>hall not only be <U+017F>ufficient, to charm, as it were, and di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of <U+017F>uch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, as Phy<U+017F>itians call <hi>Turgid,</hi> and <hi>Motu Peccantes:</hi> but even di<U+017F>charge particular parts of <U+017F>uch humors, as have <U+017F>eated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves there already; and may, be<U+017F>ides that of Cupping-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, very fitly <U+017F>upply the place of the <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t Ligatures. Which practi<U+017F>e, as it may be very available, in mo<U+017F>t affections of the head: In inflammations, or other tumors or charges, of particular parts: So (not having yet had <U+017F>ufficient op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to confirm this my Opinion, by the frequent u<U+017F>e of it) I <U+017F>hall content my <U+017F>elf at pre<U+017F>ent with having done little more, than named it only.</p>
            <p n="15">15. I <U+017F>hall add farther, that the u<U+017F>e of this Air-chamber, may in <U+017F>ome ca<U+017F>es, but after a weaker and more uncertain manner,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41619:55"/>
be <U+017F>upplied by a long-<U+017F>etting Swing, which is found to be a very agreeable exerci<U+017F>e, by mo<U+017F>t people that have u<U+017F>ed it: if their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies have not been very impure, or fir<U+017F>t duly prepared. And by it many per<U+017F>ons, affected with Chronical di<U+017F>tempers, taking their original from a deficient fermentation, have found benefit. For, motion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <U+017F>o much (as has been <U+017F>aid) to the exciting of all fermentation, (which is vi<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Syrups, and other juices of Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <U+017F>haken, and as a proof of it, that Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee Wine, is accounted the be<U+017F>t, that upon <U+017F>haking bubbles and works mo<U+017F>t) no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>onable continuance of this moderate, reciprocal motion of the Swing, do by degrees, (though not <U+017F>o <U+017F>uddenly as in the fore-mentioned in<U+017F>tances of Syrups, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becau<U+017F>e the humors in our bodies lie not <U+017F>o loo<U+017F>ely as they, in Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of gla<U+017F>s or <U+017F>tone) produce the <U+017F>ame effect, we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve without, in other liquors. Nor is the fermentation (or call it concoction) of the humors in their Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, hereby only advanced: But likewi<U+017F>e the di<U+017F>tribution of the fir<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>econd ways, (if I may <U+017F>o call them) is very much promoted: For
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41619:55"/>
<U+017F>till, as the body is carried forward, <U+017F>o of ten are the Abdominal Mu<U+017F>cles, gently and equally compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, whereby the chyle is the more nimbly pretended from the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tines forward, to mingle with blood. And again, upon the rece<U+017F>s of the body, the Abdomen being le<U+017F>s compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, than if the body <U+017F>et <U+017F>till in the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>cituation, is more dilated than u<U+017F>ually, and con<U+017F>equently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the chyle flowing, more plentifully from the <U+017F>tomack into the Inte<U+017F>tines. So that, if it come fa<U+017F>ter into the guts, and be driven fa<U+017F>ter out, it mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity follow, that the di<U+017F>tribution thereof <U+017F>hall be more readily performed. Now, for what we lately called, the di<U+017F>tribution of the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ways, that <U+017F>eems by the u<U+017F>e of the Swing, to be improved after this manner: while the body moves forward, as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts are more compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed by the Medium, <U+017F>o the back parts are le<U+017F>s compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed (and thereby, as we may <U+017F>ay, their tone weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) whereby the habit doth not <U+017F>o forcibly re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the afflux of humors flowing to that part: as in its middle, natural, and quiet <U+017F>cituation. And thus reciprocally, fir<U+017F>t one part, and then the other, are <U+017F>omewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41619:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed, for the Reception of their ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary juices, which I call the di<U+017F>tribution of the <U+017F>econd ways. And thus much may <U+017F>uffice to have <U+017F>aid at pre<U+017F>ent, concerning this matter. I <U+017F>hall only de<U+017F>ire my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he will not be over precipitious, nor let the novelty of our attempt <U+017F>urprize him to a prejudice: and that he be fir<U+017F>t, for his own <U+017F>ake, well a<U+017F><U+017F>ured, he is Ma<U+017F>ter of tho<U+017F>e principles, upon which this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of ours (as upon <U+017F>o many goodly Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars) <U+017F>tands erected, before he proceed to condemn us. But if upon the <U+017F>erious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<U+017F>al of this Treati<U+017F>e, by <U+017F>uch who<U+017F>e Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Cen<U+017F>ure we mo<U+017F>t value and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, we happen to be found light in our own Balance: We have at lea<U+017F>t to plead, that we have neither mi<U+017F>pent much of our own, or their time in writing, or reading of it. And that though we failed, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign was great and Honourable, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the benefit of mankind, which may in good part plead our excu<U+017F>e, and their good favour make out the re<U+017F>t.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41619:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

