<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of Francesco Redi concerning some objections made upon his Observations about vipers written to Monsieur Bourdelot ... and Monsieur Alexander Morus : printed in Italian at Florence, 1670 / now made English ; together with the sequel of New experiments upon vipers, and a dissertation upon their poyson ... written in French by Moyse Charas ; now likewise Englished.</title>
            <title>Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere. English</title>
            <author>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5968</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13219834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13219834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A58326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 436:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of Francesco Redi concerning some objections made upon his Observations about vipers written to Monsieur Bourdelot ... and Monsieur Alexander Morus : printed in Italian at Florence, 1670 / now made English ; together with the sequel of New experiments upon vipers, and a dissertation upon their poyson ... written in French by Moyse Charas ; now likewise Englished.</title>
                  <title>Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere. English</title>
                  <author>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698.</author>
                  <author>Charas, Moyse, 1619-1698. Nouvelles expériences sur la vipère. Suite. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for John Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Lettera di Francesco Redi sopra alcune opposizioni fatte alle sue Osservazioni intorno alle vipere.</note>
                  <note>"A continuation of the new experiments concerning vipers" (p. [37]-112) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698. --  Osservazioni intorno alle vipere.</term>
               <term>Snakes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
LETTER
OF
<hi>FRANCESCO REDI</hi>
Concerning
Some Objections made upon his
OBSERVATIONS
About
VIPERS:
Written to
Mon<U+017F>ieur <hi>BOURDELOT</hi> Abbot,
and Lord of <hi>Conde</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Leger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And
Mon<U+017F>ieur <hi>ALEXANDER MOR<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>Italian</hi> at <hi>Florence,</hi> 1670.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now made Engli<U+017F>h.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with
The SEQUEL of NEW EXPERI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS
upon <hi>VIPERS,</hi> and a Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ertation
upon their <hi>Poy<U+017F>on:</hi> Serving for
a Reply to a Letter written by Signor
<hi>Franci<U+017F>co Redi</hi> to M. <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> and M. <hi>Morus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Moy<U+017F>e Charas.</hi>
                  <hi>Now likewi<U+017F>e Engli<U+017F>hed.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>John Martyn</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal
Society,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls Churchyard,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:2"/>
                  <head>A LETTER OF
FRANCESCO REDI,
Concerning <U+017F>ome Objections made
upon his Ob<U+017F>ervations about Vipers.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Written to
Mon<U+017F>ieur <hi>BOURDELOT,</hi>
AND
Mon<U+017F>ieur <hi>ALEXANDER MORUS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ROM your liberality I have
received the Book entituled
<hi>NEW EXPERIMENTS</hi>
upon <hi>VIPERS,</hi> learnedly
compo<U+017F>ed by tho<U+017F>e noble <hi>Virtuo<U+017F>i,</hi> who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<U+017F>ome months had met in the Hou<U+017F>e of
M. <hi>Charas</hi> for that purpo<U+017F>e. I have read
it over more then once with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment,
plainly finding that tho<U+017F>e Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
per<U+017F>ons have not <U+017F>crupled by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
labours to confirm the Truth of
tho<U+017F>e Ob<U+017F>ervations, which I al<U+017F>o had made
touching <hi>VIPERS,</hi> until the year 1664.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98525:3"/>
And indeed I think my <U+017F>elf much obliged
to their ingenuity, and do frankly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that whatever worth that rude and
plain piece of mine may have, it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
it from the honourable te<U+017F>timonies,
given to it in <hi>France,</hi> where all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Sciences and Arts do highly flori<U+017F>h, to
the admiration of tho<U+017F>e that profe<U+017F>s them
in the other parts of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I intreat you, Sirs, that you would do
me the favour to repre<U+017F>ent upon occa<U+017F>ion
the<U+017F>e my candid and cordial <U+017F>entiments,
and withall to declare the high e<U+017F>teem I
have for that Book<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the authority of which
is <U+017F>o venerable with me, that, having found
therein <U+017F>ome few things directly contrary
to my own Experiments, I have often
doubted of my <U+017F>elf, and been almo<U+017F>t ready
to believe, that I dream'd when I made,
and when I wrote them. But <U+017F>ome of my
Learned Friends, that were frequently
pre<U+017F>ent at tho<U+017F>e my Operations, have laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
at me for that pronene<U+017F>s of my belief,
and between je<U+017F>t and earne<U+017F>t a<U+017F><U+017F>ur'd me,
that tho<U+017F>e Experiments had by no means
<U+017F>o <U+017F>ucceeded with me in a dream. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding
which, without any regard to
their a<U+017F><U+017F>everations, I re<U+017F>olved to iterate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98525:3"/>
and reiterate them, and that with <U+017F>o great
and careful diligence, that I <U+017F>hould greatly
injure my <U+017F>elf and Truth, if I <U+017F>hould not
freely and candidly tell you, that all tho<U+017F>e
four or five Experiments, which to tho<U+017F>e
Gentlemen in <hi>France</hi> have not <U+017F>ucceded,
do <U+017F>ucceed with me in <hi>Italy</hi> without fail,
as they were formerly recorded by me; on
the contrary, tho<U+017F>e will not <U+017F>ucceed with
me that have been made in <hi>France</hi> and are
contrary to mine.</p>
                  <p>And <U+017F>ince you may perhaps have the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<U+017F>ity
as to de<U+017F>ire to know of what kind
they are, I <U+017F>hall here give you a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of them; a<U+017F><U+017F>uring my <U+017F>elf, that it
will be acceptable to all the Lovers of
Truth, but e<U+017F>pecially to the Authors of
the Book of the <hi>New Experiments,</hi> who
have been induced to write by no other
motive then the <U+017F>ole de<U+017F>ire either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
or to find the Truth of a matter <U+017F>o cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
of which <U+017F>o many under<U+017F>tanding men
have written.</p>
                  <p>In my Letter then of the <hi>Ob<U+017F>ervations
about Vipers,</hi> addre<U+017F><U+017F>ed to the Illu<U+017F>trious
<hi>Lorenzo Magalotti,</hi> <U+017F>peaking of the Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
of tho<U+017F>e creatures, both what it is, and
in what part of the Body it re<U+017F>ideth, I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98525:4"/>
(as I affirm <U+017F>till) that the Poi<U+017F>on
of a Viper is nothing el<U+017F>e then a certain yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowi<U+017F>h
liquor, which lodgeth in the ve<U+017F>icles
that cover the greate<U+017F>t teeth of the Viper;
and that that Juice is not only poi<U+017F>onous,
when it is ejected by the live Viper when
<U+017F>he biteth, but al<U+017F>o when 'tis collected
from a dead Viper, and even <U+017F>uch an one
that hath been dead many days, provided
it be made to pa<U+017F>s into a wound, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
there. Moreover, I added, that this
<U+017F>ame liquor, when taken down into the
<U+017F>tomach, is not deadly, no not <U+017F>o much as
noxious. And this was my opinion, which
hath been confirm'd to me by innumerable
Experiments, made with the greate<U+017F>t exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
I could employ.</p>
                  <p>But the Authors of the Book of the <hi>New
Experiments</hi> do re<U+017F>olutely write, That
that above mention'd Liquor is not poi<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
but a meer and a mo<U+017F>t innocent <hi>Saliva</hi>
or Spitle. Thence they go on to affirm for
an undoubted and experimented Truth,
that the Viper hath no part of her body,
neither limb nor humor, able to poi<U+017F>on;
and that all her poi<U+017F>on con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in the <U+017F>ole
imagination of the Viper, irritated and
made angry by the <hi>Idea</hi> of vengeance, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98525:4"/>
<U+017F>he hath conceived in her head; by the
means whereof the <U+017F>pirits being put into a
violent motion, are darted through the
Nerves, and at times through the Fibres of
the cavities of the Teeth, by which cavities
tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits are carried to infect the blood
of the animal, by the opening made with
the biting teeth. In <U+017F>hort, they conclude,
that if a Viper be not angry, and have not
that vindicative imagination, her bitings
do never poi<U+017F>on, but are very innocent,
cau<U+017F>ing no mi<U+017F>chief at all to him, in whom
they are made. For the<U+017F>e are their words;</p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 36. </hi>in the Engli<U+017F>h Ver<U+017F>ion,<hi> The<U+017F>e
con<U+017F>iderations, <U+017F>upported by many Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
made by Us, and to be related hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
have induced me to call the<U+017F>e Glands</hi>Salival,<hi> and to a<U+017F>cribe to them the very <U+017F>ource
of that yellow liquor, which hath been <U+017F>o much
decried, and withal <U+017F>o little known; and it
nothing el<U+017F>e, but a pure and a very innocent
Spitle. I hope that tho<U+017F>e who <U+017F>hall take the
pains of examining after me, the<U+017F>e Glands,
and this Juyce of the Gums, will not <U+017F>tick to
give me their <U+017F>uffrages.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item p. 105. 106. <hi>But not to <U+017F>tay upon
principles <U+017F>o <U+017F>lightly e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>hed, and ill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd,
for a<U+017F>much as we have on our <U+017F>ide a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98525:5"/>
great number of Experiments, upon which
we are grounded: We <U+017F>ay, that this Juice is
nothing but a pure and plain </hi>Saliva,<hi> of which
we have already ob<U+017F>erved the u<U+017F>e; and that
this Juice contributes nothing to the venomou<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
of the Biting, <U+017F>ince being ta<U+017F>ted and <U+017F>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
(as we have often experimented) it
doth no hurt to man or bea<U+017F>t; and <U+017F>ince al<U+017F>o,
being put upon open wounds, and upon inci<U+017F>ions
made in the fle<U+017F>h, the <U+017F>ame being rub'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
and mingled with the blood, it annoys
nothing at all; notwith<U+017F>tanding the judgment
of a Per<U+017F>on very intelligent, and particularly
in this <U+017F>ubject of Vipers, who a<U+017F><U+017F>ures to have
made a great number of Experiments, which
being contrary to ours, the great opinion we
have of the abilities and the <U+017F>incerity of that
famous man, hath obliged us to employ the more
care and exactne<U+017F>s, and to confirm our <U+017F>elves
by a very great number of Experiments, which
have alwayes been found alike in the truth we
here a<U+017F><U+017F>ert, and of which we <U+017F>hall make evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
and irrefragable proof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item p. cog.<hi> We conclude therefore, that the
imagination of the Viper, irritated by the </hi>idea<hi>of revenge, which <U+017F>he had framed to her <U+017F>elf,
gives a certain motion to the <U+017F>pirits, which
cannot be expre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, and pu<U+017F>hes them violently,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98525:5"/>
through the Nerves and their Fibres, to the
cavity of the teeth as into a funnel, and that
from thence they are conveyed into the blood
of the animal by the opening, which they have
made, there to produce all tho<U+017F>e effects, of
which we endeavour to give a rea<U+017F>on.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item pag. III.<hi> However this be, we mu<U+017F>t
herein agree, that this irritation in the fan<U+017F>ie
or in the <U+017F>pirits of the Viper, is the main cau<U+017F>e
of the activity and piercingne<U+017F>s of its venom,
and that without it the biting would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<U+017F>uch <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ing effects, as tho<U+017F>e are, of
which we have related <U+017F>o many examples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Item pag.<hi> 138. The<U+017F>e Experiments will
prove on the one hand, that the yellow liquor
contributes nothing to the poy<U+017F>on; and on the
other, that the<U+017F>e incen<U+017F>ed <U+017F>pirits, a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ted by
the openings, which the great teeth had
made for them, are the <U+017F>ole and true cau<U+017F>e
thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The<U+017F>e <U+017F>entiments they confirm by <U+017F>ome
Experiments, all which con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t in this, that
they had drop't a quantity of that yellow
liquor into the wounds of a Pigeon, a Dog,
and <U+017F>ome Pullets, which yet dyed not of
it; and that having cau<U+017F>ed a Pigeon to be
bitten by a Viper not enraged, the animal
received thence no hurt at all. For they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98525:6"/>
<U+017F>ay<hi> pag. 115. We al<U+017F>o made a trial upon a
Pigeon, which we wounded under the wing
and in the Leg in the <U+017F>ame moment of time;
and we let into each wound <U+017F>ome of this yellow
liquor, which ju<U+017F>t afore we had drawn from
the gums of two enraged Vipers; then we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
the skin well, to enclo<U+017F>e the <U+017F>aid liquor,
and we bound both wounds over with a band,
that nothing might run out. We can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure,
that the Pigeon felt not any inconvenience
from it, and that we even found upon the
wound, made in the Leg, a coagulated drop of
the juice, round, and of the <U+017F>ame colour as we
had put it there, and the blood of the wound
dryed, and that, <U+017F>oon after, both wounds were
dried up, and healed of them<U+017F>elves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 116. We al<U+017F>o made the like Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
upon a Cat, which we purpo<U+017F>ely wounded
in the Leg, but he received no harm at all by
it: We have al<U+017F>o often experimented it on Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,
and other Pigeons, but alwayes with the
like <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, and without any offence to the
Animals.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ibid.<hi> The <U+017F>ame Trial hath been thrice
made at three <U+017F>everal times, and even twice
in one day upon a Dog, whom we had wounded
on purpo<U+017F>e towards the bottom of the Ear,
where he could not lick his wound; and no
mi<U+017F>chief at all followed upon it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98525:6"/>
Ibid.<hi> We cannot but add here an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the mortal effect of the Enraged Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
without any intervention of the yellow
liquor. We made a Viper <U+017F>everal times to bite
upon a <U+017F>lice of bread, by pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing every time
its jaws again<U+017F>t the bread; and we did this <U+017F>o
often, that not only that juice was altogether
exhau<U+017F>ted, but the blood began to come out of
the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>icles. At the <U+017F>ame time we vexed
the Viper, and made her bite a Pigeon in the
mo<U+017F>t fle<U+017F>hy part; and we ob<U+017F>erv'd that indeed
the effects of the venom of the biting were
not <U+017F>o quick, the Pigeon not dying but an hour
and an half after it had been bitten; but then
we found al<U+017F>o, that the teeth of the Viper were
in a manner covered with the crums of the
bread, from the force of her having bitten at
it, and that that had hindred them from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
a deep entrance; and that having half
<U+017F>top't up the pores of the teeth, a good part of
the angred Spirits could not come forth; <U+017F>o
that the death of the Pigeon could not follow
<U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t, though yet it hapned without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the juice, which had been altogether
emptied.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pag.<hi> 138. The wound made by a Viper
not vexed, who<U+017F>e Jaws were held in, and
who<U+017F>e teeth were at the <U+017F>ame time thru<U+017F>t into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98525:7"/>
the body of a Pigeon, which al<U+017F>o was accompanied
with <U+017F>tore of the yellow juice, and yet not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
with any ill accident.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the<U+017F>e Experiments I have nothing
el<U+017F>e to oppo<U+017F>e, but tho<U+017F>e very many ones,
that were made by me in the year 1664. and
recited in the above-mentioned <hi>Ob<U+017F>ervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
of mine <hi>about Vipers,</hi> and tho<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o that
I <U+017F>hall recite hereafter, made likewi<U+017F>e by
my <U+017F>elf, not with a de<U+017F>ire to confirm the fir<U+017F>t,
but indeed to di<U+017F>cover the Truth. And,
that I may not be put often to repeat <U+017F>ome
things, I <U+017F>hall premi<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome General Ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,
made by me at the time when I dealt
in Vipers.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A viper more ea<U+017F>ily kills a Pigeon, a
Pullet, a Turky-cock, a Squirrel, a Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mou<U+017F>e,
and generally all <U+017F>mall Birds and
Animals, than a great Animal, as a Sheep,
a Deer, a Hor<U+017F>e, a Bull; yea the<U+017F>e greater
ones and tho<U+017F>e that are of an hard skin, very
often a Viper kills not at all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. According to the bigne<U+017F>s of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
bitten, and according to the place where
the Viper biteth, death follows <U+017F>ooner or
later; e<U+017F>pecially according as the place
wounded is a clear texture, or thick <U+017F>et
with veins and arteries; or tho<U+017F>e veins and
arteries are very <U+017F>mall or big.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98525:7"/>
3. If from the wound of a Viper much
blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth, it <U+017F>ometimes happens, that
the Animal nor only dyeth not, but does
not <U+017F>o much as feel any great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It doth al<U+017F>o not <U+017F>eldom fall out, that
an Animal bitten by a Viper <U+017F>uffers grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
Symptoms from the poy<U+017F>on, which
bring it near death, but yet kill it not;
but the creature without any help of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ick
and by the <U+017F>ole work of nature reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Tho<U+017F>e Animals that are bitten of a
Viper dye a little <U+017F>ooner, than tho<U+017F>e, into
the wounds of which hath been on purpo<U+017F>e
conveyed that yellow liquor, which by
art hath been fetch't out of the baggs of the
teeth of that Viper.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. 'Tis nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, that great dexterity
be u<U+017F>ed in making the <U+017F>aid liquor to
penetrate into the wound; becau<U+017F>e, if the
wound be narrow, it pierces difficultly;
if large, it cannot be otherwi<U+017F>e but it will
bleed, and with that blood the <U+017F>aid liquor
will turn back, and <U+017F>o the poi<U+017F>on come out
again.</p>
                  <p>I had then provided a good number of
Vipers which I cau<U+017F>ed to be brought me cut
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98525:8"/>
of the Kingdome of <hi>Naples<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                     </hi> and having in
this moneth of <hi>May,</hi> 1670 wounded ten
Pigeons of the bigger <U+017F>ort in the thighs, I
put into them <U+017F>ome of the yellow liquor
fre<U+017F>hly taken out of the mouth of the live
Vipers; and all the<U+017F>e Pigeons, <U+017F>ome within
the <U+017F>pace of one hour, <U+017F>ome in half an hour,
and <U+017F>ome in two hours, died. This Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment
I repeated upon ten Chickens, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e
wounded in their thighs, with the <U+017F>ame
event that had befallen the Pigeons.</p>
                  <p>Then I cut off the heads of twelf Vipers,
and all the heads being cut off, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
quite dead, I thence extracted the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on,
and cau<U+017F>ed them to be put into the
wounds of eight Turtle-doves, all which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the <U+017F>pace of half an hour.</p>
                  <p>In the month of <hi>June,</hi> having killed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
other Vipers, and gather'd out of the bags
of their teeth and their gums all the yellow
and vi<U+017F>cous Juice that was there, I anointed
therewith <U+017F>ome bee<U+017F>om-rods, <U+017F>harpn'd like
arrowes, and immediately I pricked with
them ten young Pigeons in the more fle<U+017F>hy
part of their che<U+017F>t, leaving them fixed in the
wound; and the Pigeons <U+017F>urvived not above
two or three hours. But le<U+017F>t it <U+017F>hould be
doubted; whether the<U+017F>e Pigeons died not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98525:8"/>
of the wound it <U+017F>elf, enraged by the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
of tho<U+017F>e rods, I made a trial upon
four other Pigeons with rods not infected
with that poy<U+017F>onous liquor; but none of
them dyed, though the wounds became pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent.</p>
                  <p>I al<U+017F>o took eight heads of Vipers, cut off
<U+017F>ix hours before, and, the Vipers being quite
dead, I cau<U+017F>ed eight Turtle-doves to be
bitten by them in the thigh, and not one of
them e<U+017F>caped.</p>
                  <p>Moreover I made the heads of fifteen
Vipers to be cut off: and put them into a
gla<U+017F>s-ve<U+017F><U+017F>el well cover'd, having laid them
upon one another, that <U+017F>o they might remain
moi<U+017F>t. Four dayes after, I <U+017F>truck with tho<U+017F>e
heads five young Cocks, and five great Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons
in the thigh, and they all after a little
while died. The like fell out with other
Viper-heads, which having been killed <U+017F>ix
dayes before, had in all likely hood lo<U+017F>t all
choller and thoughts of revenge. And to
prevent all Objections that might be rai<U+017F>ed
on this occa<U+017F>ion, I <U+017F>hall not omit to relate
to you, that about the beginning of <hi>Augu<U+017F>t</hi>
when two of my Vipers, that alone were
left me in a box, died of them<U+017F>elves of <U+017F>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
I cau<U+017F>ed two Turtle-doves to be <U+017F>truck
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98525:9"/>
by them, which al<U+017F>o, like the former, dyed
in le<U+017F>s than an hours time.</p>
                  <p>But I may go further. I had collected
in a gla<U+017F>s all the poi<U+017F>onous liquor of the
heads of two hundred and fifty Vipers, to
make various Experiments therewith upon
occa<U+017F>ion. But being by much bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
I delayed to accompli<U+017F>h my de<U+017F>ign:
Whence that liquor turn't fir<U+017F>t into a glew,
colour'd like amber; then in 30 dayes it
became altogether dry and friable, <U+017F>o that
it could ea<U+017F>ily be reduced to powder. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
pulveri<U+017F>ed, I had a mind to try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
that powder, let into a wound, did
keep the force of poy<U+017F>oning; and I found
that really it did <U+017F>o, all tho<U+017F>e Pullets, Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and Turtle-doves, into the wounds of
which I had put <U+017F>ome thereof, dying of it in
a little while.</p>
                  <p>Having made this Experiment, I began
to doubt, whether that poy<U+017F>on of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
of the King of <hi>Maca<U+017F>sar</hi> in the I<U+017F>land
of <hi>Celebes,</hi> which commonly are called the
arrowes of <hi>Bantam</hi> in <hi>Java Major,</hi> were not
the poy<U+017F>on extracted out of the mouth of
<U+017F>ome Viper, or of <U+017F>ome other Viper-like
<U+017F>erpent, and perhaps of a more maligne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
becau<U+017F>e of the diver<U+017F>ity of the Climate.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98525:9"/>
I am not much aver<U+017F>e from believing this to
be <U+017F>o; and it may be confirmed by what I
have read in <hi>Pliny, viz.</hi> That the <hi>Scythians</hi>
did infect their Arrows with a Viperin poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on.
His words are, <hi>Scythae <U+017F>agittas tingunt
Viperinâ <U+017F>anie &amp; humano <U+017F>anguine: irremedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abile
id <U+017F>celus mortem illicò levi tactu a<U+017F><U+017F>ert.</hi>
And this was perhaps extracted by <hi>Pliny</hi>
out of <hi>Ari<U+017F>totle,</hi> who in h<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Book, intitul'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <U+017F>oon after de<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
the proce<U+017F>s of preparing it, which I dare
not affirm to be the true one, or to requi<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
<U+017F>o many circum<U+017F>tances and cautions. And
who knows, whether the Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
of which the Fables alledge that they were
imbued with the blood of an <hi>Hydra,</hi> were
not infected with this poi<U+017F>on of Vipers? So
'tis believed by <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> when he
<U+017F>aith, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>.
And <hi>Ovid</hi> gives the name of Viper to the
<hi>Hydra,</hi> when in his ninth Book of <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph.</hi>
he <U+017F>aith;
<q>Pars quota Lerneae <U+017F>erpens erit unus Echiánae.</q>
And afterwards;
<q>
                        <l>—Capit in<U+017F>cius heros,</l>
                        <l>Induitur que humeris Lerneae virus Fchidnae.</l>
                     </q>
To which may be added, that <hi>Philoctetes,</hi>
the Heir of the Bow and Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
being gon in the Grecian Navy to the <hi>Trojan</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98525:10"/>
War, and having unawares wounded him<U+017F>elf
(as <hi>Servius Grammaticus</hi> relates, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Aeneid)</hi>
with one of his Arrows in the foot; was left
among the Grecians in the I<U+017F>le of <hi>Stalimene,</hi>
by rea<U+017F>on of the violence of the pain, and
the intolerable <U+017F>tench of the wound. Whence
<hi>Sophocles,</hi> alluding, it <U+017F>eems, to the kind of
poi<U+017F>on, in a Poetical way and phra<U+017F>e rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,
that <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was left in that I<U+017F>le, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e
he had been bitten by a Viper. His
words are;
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                           </gap>: That is</l>
                     </q>
                     <hi>O Son of </hi>Achilles,<hi> I am he, whom thou may<U+017F>t
have heard to be the po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>sor of the Herculean
Arrows, the Son of </hi>Paean Philoctetes:<hi> whom
the two Armies and the King of the I<U+017F>le of </hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalene<hi><U+017F>hamefully left lying here, pining away
by a cruel di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, <U+017F>truck by the fierce bite of a
murthering Viper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Cicero</hi> him<U+017F>elf in his <U+017F>econd Book of
the <hi>Tu<U+017F>culan Que<U+017F>tions,</hi> and in his Book <hi>De
Fato,</hi> and many other Writers do follow this
opinion, <hi>viz,</hi> That <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was bitten by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98525:10"/>
a Viper. And po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly all of them had an
eye not only to this place of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> but
al<U+017F>o to what <hi>Homer</hi> <U+017F>aid before, in his <U+017F>ix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
Book of <hi>Iliads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though again<U+017F>t this conjecture it may
be <U+017F>aid, that the poi<U+017F>ion of Vipers is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable
in re<U+017F>pect of what Poets do write
of the Arrows of <hi>Hercules,</hi> which by them
are <U+017F>aid not only to have the force of killing
without fail, whether the wound be <U+017F>mall or
great, as happen'd to the Centaure <hi>Chiron</hi>
and to <hi>Ne<U+017F><U+017F>us;</hi> but al<U+017F>o that the blood of
their wounds was become <U+017F>o pe<U+017F>tiferous as to
infect any live body what<U+017F>oever, touched
thereby, and that with <U+017F>uch violence, as to
make the fle<U+017F>h fall off from the bones: which,
<hi>they add,</hi> was experimented by <hi>Hercules</hi> to
his great mi<U+017F>chief, when his Shirt was tinged
with the blood of <hi>Ne<U+017F>sus;</hi> whence <hi>Ovid</hi>
<U+017F>aith,
<q>
                        <l>Victa malis po<U+017F>tquam e<U+017F>t patientia, reppulit
aras</l>
                        <l>Implevit que <U+017F>uis nemoro<U+017F>am vocibus Oeten;</l>
                        <l>Nec mora, letiferam conatur <U+017F>cindere ve<U+017F>tem;</l>
                        <l>Qua trahitur, trahit illa cutim (faedumque
relatu)</l>
                        <l>Aut haret membris, fru<U+017F>tra tentata revelli,</l>
                        <l>Aut laceros artus &amp; grandia detegit o<U+017F><U+017F>a:</l>
                     </q>
This is a Poetical Fable; whence, I am apt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98525:11"/>
to believe, is rai<U+017F>ed that relation concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Arrows of <hi>Maca<U+017F><U+017F>ar,</hi> of which 'tis
<U+017F>aid, that they kill one in that very moment
he receiveth the <U+017F>lighte<U+017F>t wound thereby, and
that al<U+017F>o in the <U+017F>pace of half an hour the fle<U+017F>h
of the killed per<U+017F>on becomes <U+017F>o putri<U+017F>ied,
that it falls off from the bones in many pieces,
whence do exhale <U+017F>uch virulent <U+017F>teams, that
if they light upon any ordinary and not enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed
wound, they mortally infect it, and
without fail kill the Patient.</p>
                  <p>I do here affirm, that I have made many
tryal's with tho<U+017F>e Arrows of the Indians; but
have not found them in <hi>Tu<U+017F>cany</hi> of <U+017F>o fierce
and malignant a nature, as hath been related.
The Dogs I wounded with them, dyed <U+017F>ome
of them in <U+017F>ix, others in <U+017F>even, others in
twelve, others in twenty four hours. And
their fle<U+017F>h was not putri<U+017F>ied, nor fallen in
pieces, nor did their blood or exhaled <U+017F>teams
at all kill other wounded Animals. But I
have often ob<U+017F>erved, that, if one intends to
ki<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l with the<U+017F>e Arrows, it is not enough to
make a <U+017F>imple inci<U+017F>ion of the fle<U+017F>h, but he
mu<U+017F>t by art make them <U+017F>tick a while in the
wound (which is like to what happens in
putting into wounds the powder of the dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
yellow liquor of Vipers:) Whence it is
that tho<U+017F>e Savages make of Wood the <U+017F>harp
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98525:11"/>
ends of tho<U+017F>e Arrows, imbue them with poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on,
and then joyne them to the Arrow <U+017F>tick
in <U+017F>uch a manner, that tho<U+017F>e ends ever remain
in the wound, whether the Arrow do break
or be drawn out; as came to pa<U+017F>s in the Siege
of <hi>Jeru<U+017F>alem</hi> to tho<U+017F>e Heroes of <hi>Flandres, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dofred</hi>
and <hi>Robert,</hi> of whom that great Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin
Poet thus <U+017F>ingeth:
<q>
                        <l>So<U+017F>pingeva il monton, quando è perco<U+017F><U+017F>o</l>
                        <l>Al Sig. de Fiaminghi il lato manco,</l>
                        <l>Si che travia s' allenta, è vuol poi trarne</l>
                        <l>Lo <U+017F>trale, e re<U+017F>ta il ferro entro la carne:</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>That is,
<hi>The Engine di<U+017F>charged<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the left <U+017F>ide of the
Flandrian Princes was <U+017F>o <U+017F>truck, that they were
thru<U+017F>t out of their way, and when they would
draw out the Arrow, the Iron <U+017F>tuck within
their fle<U+017F>h.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is therefore nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, that the Arrows
do <U+017F>tick for <U+017F>ome time in the wound, if they
<U+017F>hall kill: Whence I under<U+017F>tand not, how
the vulgar comes to fan<U+017F>y, that the Blades of
Swords may be envenomed. I do well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
that with the yellow liquor of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
and with other things e<U+017F>teemed veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,
I have <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>lightly tinged Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cets
for letting of blood, and with them have
cut the vein of <U+017F>ome Animal or other, but
death hath not followed upon it. Let <U+017F>u<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98525:12"/>
men rather beware of the Tents of
Chirurgions; for 'tis too hard to cau<U+017F>e
death by poi<U+017F>on'd Lancets or other <U+017F>uch Iron
in<U+017F>truments. Hence it <U+017F>eems to me to <U+017F>avor
of the fable (though the ca<U+017F>e be different)
that <hi>Pari<U+017F>atis</hi> the old Queen of the Per<U+017F>ians,
did poi<U+017F>on her Daughter-in-law by the hands
of her Carver, poi<U+017F>oning the one <U+017F>ide of the
Knife, and therewith cutting a<U+017F>under a
Fowl, of which he gave to the young Queen
to eat that part, which the poi<U+017F>oned <U+017F>ide of
the Knife had envenomed, eating the other
part him<U+017F>elf.</p>
                  <p>I could never <U+017F>ee the truth of what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
of poi<U+017F>ons killing by a meer and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaneous
contact, or by vicinity alone;
as that Stirrups, Sadles, and Benches have
been poi<U+017F>oned, and thereby proved mortal.
Let him believe it that will; I cannot. And
what a certain modern Writer relateth for a
great truth, concerning a prodigious acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
hapned by a kind of Serpents bred in
the Indies, I mu<U+017F>t leave to him<U+017F>elf, who <U+017F>aith,<hi>After I have <U+017F>poken of the<U+017F>e Serpents, I pre<U+017F>ume
it will not be unacceptable to give an account of
the <U+017F>trange effect they produce. If perchance it
happen, that they pa<U+017F>s over a cloath or <U+017F>hirt dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the Sun, there is wont to be bred in the
Kidneys of tho<U+017F>e that u<U+017F>e this cloath, a certain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98525:12"/>
kind of Serpents, which little by little growing
up do encompa<U+017F>s the whole body, and when their
tayl reaches their head, to conjoyn the circle,
then death is unevitable: Wherefore, to avoyd
this mi<U+017F>chief, they kill them with Razors and
Lancets, to prevent their growth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You have found above mentioned three
per<U+017F>ons, wounded by the Arrows of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi>
namely <hi>Chiron, Ne<U+017F><U+017F>us,</hi> and <hi>Philoctetes.</hi>
The two fir<U+017F>t dyed <U+017F>uddenly; the third, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
a long <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s e<U+017F>caped. If the caufes of
this difference were to be given (whether it
be an Hi<U+017F>tory or a Fable) I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ay, that
<hi>Ne<U+017F><U+017F>us</hi> and <hi>Chiron</hi> dyed, becau<U+017F>e they were
wounded whil<U+017F>t <hi>Hercules</hi> was yet living, by
Arrows fre<U+017F>hly envenomed; be<U+017F>ides that
<hi>Ne<U+017F><U+017F>us</hi> was pierced through his heart, as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
hath it,
<q>
                        <l>Jámque tenens ripam mi<U+017F><U+017F>os cùm tolleret ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</l>
                        <l>Conjugis agnovit vocem, Ne<U+017F><U+017F>óque paranti</l>
                        <l>Fallere depo<U+017F>itum; quò te fiducia, clamat,</l>
                        <l>Vana pedum violente rapit? Tibi, Ne<U+017F><U+017F>e bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formis</l>
                        <l>Dicimus, exaudi, nec res intercipe no<U+017F>tras.</l>
                        <l>Si te nulla mei reverentia movit; at orbes</l>
                        <l>Concubitus vetitos poterant inhibere paterni.</l>
                        <l>Haud tamen effugies, quamvis ope fidis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinâ,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98525:13"/>
Vulnere, non pedibus, te con<U+017F>equar. Ultima
dicta</l>
                        <l>Re probat, &amp; mi<U+017F><U+017F>â fugientia terga fagittâ</l>
                        <l>Trajicit; extabat ferrum de pectore aduncum:</l>
                        <l>Quod <U+017F>imul evul<U+017F>um e<U+017F>t, <U+017F>anguis per utrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
foramen</l>
                        <l>Emicuit, mi<U+017F>tus Lernaei tabe veneni.</l>
                     </q>
But <hi>Philoctetes</hi> was wounded long after the
death of <hi>Hercules;</hi> whence 'tis credible, that
tho<U+017F>e Arrows had lo<U+017F>t much of their poi<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
force, even as the powder of the yellow
liquor loo<U+017F>eth of its force, and the Arrows of
<hi>Maca<U+017F><U+017F>er</hi> by length of time grow languid;
which though they poi<U+017F>on and kill if one be
wounded therewith, yet do they no hurt at
all, if their poi<U+017F>on be <U+017F>wallow'd and taken
into the <U+017F>tomach. Which Experiment I have
tryed upon two Doggs, to whom I gave to
<U+017F>wallow two pieces of fle<U+017F>h covered with
the powder of the <U+017F>crapings of <U+017F>uch Arrows;
as al<U+017F>o upon <U+017F>everal Chickens, to whom I
gave the water to drink, wherein tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
had been a long time infu<U+017F>ed.</p>
                  <p>But, to return after this long digre<U+017F><U+017F>ion
to the main thing; you may by the above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
and often repeated Experiments, <U+017F>ee,
that the po<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F>on of the <hi>Italian</hi> Viper con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts
not in an imaginary <hi>idea</hi> of anger rai<U+017F>ed to
revenge, but rather in that yellow liquor,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98525:13"/>
which is voided out of the bags of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
teeth of Vipers; which juyce if it chance
to be <U+017F>pilled in the mouth and upon the
Pallat of tho<U+017F>e animals is able to envenoin
the <U+017F>pittle which moi<U+017F>tens their throat.</p>
                  <p>I <U+017F>hould think it very well worth while
for tho<U+017F>e learned Authors of the book of
the <hi>New Experiments,</hi> that they would
plea<U+017F>e to make their Experiments anew.
And if they <U+017F>hall find them conform to tho<U+017F>e
they have already publi<U+017F>hed, and really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to mine, then we may unanimou<U+017F>ly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that we have lighted upon a truth hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
unknown; which is, That the Poi<U+017F>on
of the <hi>French</hi> Vipers con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<hi>Idea</hi> of a revengeful anger; but that of
the <hi>Italian</hi> ones hath its <U+017F>eat in that yellow
liquor, <U+017F>o often mentioned by me. But if on
the other <U+017F>ide, the <hi>French</hi> Experiments
<U+017F>hould not hold, then it may be affirmed,
that the <hi>French</hi> as well as the <hi>Italian</hi> Vipers
are of one and the <U+017F>ame nature; and have
the <U+017F>ame kind of poi<U+017F>on.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore if in <hi>Italy</hi> the Viper in poi<U+017F>on
certainly lodges in that yellow liquor, it
will be no untruth in me to affirm, that if by
biting, a Viper <U+017F>hould have lo<U+017F>t all that juyce
re<U+017F>iding in tho<U+017F>e bags, and that al<U+017F>o which
may be furni<U+017F>ht by the neighbouring parts, it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98525:14"/>
will, I <U+017F>ay, be no untruth in me to affirm,
that the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>equent bitings will not be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal:
which is the thing I have the<U+017F>e many
years a<U+017F><U+017F>erted, and do <U+017F>till a<U+017F><U+017F>ert, although
the above<U+017F>aid Authors deny it, giving out
that one only Viper, being vexed and <U+017F>well'd
with choller, is able to kill as many animals
as she bites; they tru<U+017F>ting to one Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
in which they <U+017F>ay there died five young
Pidgeons by the biting of one only Viper. <hi>We
hope</hi> (<U+017F>ay they, p. 137.) <hi>that among the many
Experiments tho<U+017F>e of the five Pidgeons, bitten
one after another, by one and the fame viper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<U+017F>perated
every time, and of which the la<U+017F>t bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
died fir<U+017F>t of all, when the viper was mo<U+017F>t
vexed, and mo<U+017F>t exhau<U+017F>ted of its yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I am willing indeed to believe the fact to
be true; but for the confirmation of it I wi<U+017F>h
they had cau<U+017F>ed many more <U+017F>uch Pidgeons,
and many other animals, of different kinds
and bigne<U+017F><U+017F>es, to be bitten of the <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ame Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
which had killed tho<U+017F>e five ones, to <U+017F>ee
whether that angry and cholerick poi<U+017F>on had
an infinite power. For when I examin'd this
matter, I cho<U+017F>e about the beginning of <hi>May</hi>
a Female Viper, one of the bigge<U+017F>t and lu<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t,
and vexed her to bite ten Chickens one
after another, in the right thigh; of which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98525:14"/>
the fir<U+017F>t, <U+017F>econd, and third died almo<U+017F>t in an
in<U+017F>tant; the fourth <U+017F>eemed only to be <U+017F>ick;
but the fifth and all the re<U+017F>t did not only not
dye, but were not at all <U+017F>ick; and yet every
time the Viper did bite, I angred and madded
her exceedingly. In the moneth of <hi>June</hi> I
repeated the experiment in five tame <hi>Ducks,</hi>
bitten by one and the <U+017F>ame Viper, which al<U+017F>o
immediately after bit three young <hi>Turtle-Doves.</hi>
The fir<U+017F>t wounded Duck dyed three
hours after; the <U+017F>econd, five hours after; but
the re<U+017F>t e<U+017F>caped. 'Tis true, that the fir<U+017F>t
wounded of the Turtles dyed, but not the
other two. Of twelve <hi>Ring-Doves</hi> at one
time there dyed but four; but the next day
of twelve others there dyed <U+017F>ix. Of five <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets</hi>
there dyed three<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and of three <hi>Lambs</hi> the
two la<U+017F>t lived, the fir<U+017F>t of them dying two
hours after it had been bitten.</p>
                  <p>I <U+017F>hould be too tedious, if I <U+017F>hould relate
to you all the other experiments: Wherefore
I <U+017F>hall go on to add, that having written in
my<hi> Ob<U+017F>ervations, </hi>that that yellow liquor was
not conveyed to the bags of the teeth from the
bladder of gall, I did <U+017F>ugge<U+017F>t, whether it
might not be di<U+017F>gorged there by certain <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral<hi>Ductus's, </hi>that might be in<U+017F>erted at the
head of them: which did appear the more
probable, becau<U+017F>e that in all Vipers at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98525:15"/>
bottom of tho<U+017F>e ve<U+017F>icles I had always found
two glanduls, which had not, that I knew,
been ob<U+017F>erved or de<U+017F>cribed by any body.
Whereupon the Authors of the<hi> New Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>do affirm, that they could never <U+017F>ee
<U+017F>uch Glanduls as I had named; but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tead
of them they had found two others,
which they call Salival, thus by them de<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,<hi>p. 31, 32. I believed at fir<U+017F>t, following
Signor </hi>Redi,<hi> that there might be Salival ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els
in Vipers, as there have been lately found in
Man and divers other Animals; <U+017F>o that after
many re-<U+017F>earches made with <U+017F>ufficient attention
and patience, in many Vipers heads I di<U+017F>covered
at length <U+017F>uch Glands, proper to forme this
juyce, and to convey it to the Bags; and after I
was well per<U+017F>waded of it my <U+017F>elf, I <U+017F>hewed them
to divers of tho<U+017F>e knowing Phy<U+017F>itians, that had
met at my hou<U+017F>e the la<U+017F>t year. The<U+017F>e per<U+017F>ons had
a mind to <U+017F>ee them with their own eyes; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
I had well examined the parts which I <U+017F>hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
them, they not only found them true, but they
al<U+017F>o <U+017F>aw there a greater number of <U+017F>maller ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>els
then had appear'd to me, of which <U+017F>ome that
are Arteries and Veins pa<U+017F>s above the Glands,
and others that are Lympheducts run below; <U+017F>o
that they judged, that I could confidently a<U+017F><U+017F>ert
and de<U+017F>cribe the<U+017F>e Glands which I call Salival,
and which they had acknowledged together with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98525:15"/>
me; though </hi>Signor Redi<hi> dur<U+017F>t not <U+017F>peak po<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
of them, becau<U+017F>e he had not di<U+017F>covered
them; neither had they been de<U+017F>cribed by any
Author of their knowledge, nor by any one of
mine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag.<hi> 35. As to the <U+017F>mall Glands, which</hi>Signor Redi<hi> hath ob<U+017F>erved at the bottom of the
Ve<U+017F>icles that contain this juyce, I can <U+017F>ay, that I
have with great care and diligence <U+017F>earched af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
them, and that 'tis true, I have there found
the appearances of Glands, but having opened
them, I <U+017F>aw nothing in them but <U+017F>mall teeth that
were fa<U+017F>tned there, without finding any thing of
a Glandular nature there, nor that did in the
lea<U+017F>t approach to the <U+017F>hape, <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of the Glands which I have been de<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing,</hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I do not at all wonder that tho<U+017F>e Writers
have not found tho<U+017F>e Glanduls I named, I <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
they went about to <U+017F>earch them within
the Ve<U+017F>icles of the teeth, and at the bottom of
them: Whereas I never <U+017F>aid that they were to
be found within them, I <U+017F>aid they were to be
found <hi>Sotto'l fondo</hi> (under the bottom) of
tho<U+017F>e bags, and in good <hi>Tu<U+017F>can</hi> language, tis
another thing to <U+017F>ay <hi>nel fondo,</hi> (in or at the
bottom) another <hi>Sotto'l fondo</hi> (under the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.)
And therefore when they <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ought them
where they are to be met with, they ea<U+017F>ily
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98525:16"/>
found them, and they are the <U+017F>ame which they
de<U+017F>cribe, neither are there any other con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
glanduls to be di<U+017F>covered in the heads
of Vipers. Nor could I at all write that tho<U+017F>e
Glanduls lay in the bottom of the Ve<U+017F>icles, if
I was of opinion that the yellow liquor did
run into them after it had pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed through the
Salival Conduits, which yet I imagined might
have their origin from, or connexion with
tho<U+017F>e two Glanduls <U+017F>een by me, and therefore
mu<U+017F>t needs be in a <U+017F>cituation a little di<U+017F>tant
from the Ve<U+017F>icles, and not in the bottom of
them. Now whether the<U+017F>e Glanduls have this
office and this u<U+017F>e, I intend not now to <U+017F>peak
of, let it be what it will, 'tis too incon<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
a matter to make any more words of it.</p>
                  <p>I confe<U+017F>s, that the dangerous experiments
which Vipers have, made them <U+017F>o di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ing
to me, and even <U+017F>o odious, that I re<U+017F>olved
not at all to meddle any more with them; but
that I was tempted thereto by a great de<U+017F>ire
I had experimentally to learn, whether the
volatil Salt of Vipers, Chymically prepared,
were endowed with that pre<U+017F>ent and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
vertue of curing the bitings of Vipers, as
the <U+017F>aid Writers affirm. For my <hi>Genius</hi>
keeps me from much tru<U+017F>ting to tho<U+017F>e things,
that have not been made out to me by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment;
although I do not pre<U+017F>ently reject
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98525:16"/>
them as fal<U+017F>e before Experiment, but rather
being de<U+017F>irous to know whether they be true,
I put them to tryal: But neither do I acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>ce
in one or a few experiments, but I love to
<U+017F>ee more and more, being ever apprehen<U+017F>ive
le<U+017F>t I <U+017F>hould be deceived; as it often hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd
to me, when I have been ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide
in one ha<U+017F>ty experiment. And to <U+017F>ay truth
in the moneth of <hi>June</hi> there wanted not much
but that I had impo<U+017F>ed upon my <U+017F>elf in the
tryal of an experiment, which I am going to
relate to you, and which done I <U+017F>hall ea<U+017F>e you
of further trouble.</p>
                  <p>Having read them in the Book of the<hi> New
Experiments, </hi>that the Head of a Viper, being
eaten of an animal, bitten by another Viper,
did certainly cure the wound; and the thing
being by me looked upon as very u<U+017F>eful, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
and admirable, I had an eager de<U+017F>ire to
try it my <U+017F>elf, that I might <U+017F>peak of it with
more confidence, although tho<U+017F>e learned men
had made the<U+017F>e two following experiments of
it,<hi> viz. </hi>pag. 120. <hi>We had al<U+017F>o a de<U+017F>ire to find
whether a Viper being eaten by an animal, which
<U+017F>he had bitten before, would be cured of that bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.
We therefore cau<U+017F>ed to be <U+017F>lightly broiled
the head of a Viper, which had on it a part of the
neck, newly <U+017F>ever'd from the body; and we cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed
a Dog to be thrice bitten at the ear, by a well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98525:17"/>
enraged Viper, in <U+017F>uch a manner that the blood
came out at the three pricked places. We <U+017F>oon ca<U+017F>t
before him the head and neck; broiled, and yet
hot. The Dog, that was hungry, and felt not <U+017F>o
<U+017F>oon the effects of the bitings, immediately <U+017F>eiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on the head, brui<U+017F>ed it between his teeth, and
<U+017F>wallowed it down. After which we <U+017F>tay'd a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
while to <U+017F>ee, whether the three bitings would
prevail over the devour'd head and neck<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> but the
Dog was free, except <U+017F>ome blewne<U+017F>s and a little
Tumour he had at the places bitten, but which
little by little vani<U+017F>ht in three or four days. We
made al<U+017F>o a Dog to be bitten three times in the
<U+017F>ame place, and without broiling the head of the
<U+017F>ame Viper that had bit him, we ca<U+017F>t it before
him, hoping that he would eat it, becau<U+017F>e he had
not eaten any thing for many hours before; but
the Dog would not touch it. Upon that we brui<U+017F>ed
and <U+017F>tamped that head in a mortar, and <U+017F>o cram'd
it down the Dogs throat, rubbing al<U+017F>o the bitten
places with the blood of the <U+017F>ame Viper; which
done, we expected the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, which was<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> that
this head, raw and brui<U+017F>ed, and if you will, a<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ted
by the blood of the Viper, being applied to the
part bitten, had produced the <U+017F>ame effects with
the former, which had been <U+017F>lightly broiled; in
regard that this Dog was <U+017F>afe, excepting tho<U+017F>e
inconveniencies the former <U+017F>uffer'd, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
that as <U+017F>ound as if he had never been bitten.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98525:17"/>
If the<U+017F>e two Experiments had been made before
that Gentleman, above di<U+017F>cours'd of, was bitten
by a Viper, we <U+017F>hould have been in much le<U+017F>s anx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iety
for his pre<U+017F>ervation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a little before (pag. 119.) they had
<U+017F>aid:<hi> We have tryed, that having cau<U+017F>ed to be
bitten at the thicke<U+017F>t place of the ear, by a <U+017F>uffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
vexed Viper, a young Cat, very lean,
that had but ju<U+017F>t before eaten the Eggs, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,
and all the Guts of a Viper; the biting had
almo<U+017F>t no effect, and there appeared nothing but
a very little <U+017F>welling, and a very incon<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
lividne<U+017F>s in the part bitten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag. 154. <hi>It is very certain, that the
Head of a Viper, broiled and <U+017F>wallowed, healeth
the biting of that Animal. The Heart and the
Liver may do the <U+017F>ame. Rea<U+017F>on and Experience
have confirm'd it; and therefore in an urgent
occa<U+017F>ion the<U+017F>e parts may be very beneficially em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And pag. 156. <hi>We believe, that the Liver
<U+017F>wallowed is capable to heal the biting of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
like the heart, fle<U+017F>h and other parts, of which
we have <U+017F>poken; and that it may much facilitate
the delivery of Women with Child, as doth the
Liver of Eeles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereupon I re<U+017F>olved to imitate tho<U+017F>e Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
and having given a Vipers head half
boiled to a chain'd young Dog, I cau<U+017F>ed him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98525:18"/>
immediately to be bitten by an other Viper
in the right ear, but the Dog dyed not, nor
did he appear to me to have any other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience
than that he <U+017F>tood as 'twere amazed,
and looking grim, and melancholly, for four or
five hours <U+017F>pace. I <U+017F>oon reiterated the <U+017F>ame
Experiment upon another Dog, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
been forced to <U+017F>wallow the head of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
raw and brui<U+017F>ed in a Mortar, gave no
<U+017F>ign of any great poi<U+017F>on, and had very little
and almo<U+017F>t no ill en<U+017F>uing. Whence I was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to reckon this Experiment among things
proved and true, when a doubt coming into
my mind, obliged me to cau<U+017F>e two other
young Dogs to be bitten in their ears, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
they had not eaten the counter-poi<U+017F>on
of a Vipers head, yet dyed not. Whence the
<U+017F>u<U+017F>picion being increa<U+017F>ed in me, I cau<U+017F>ed to
be brought me the raw head of a Viper, and
crammed it into the throat of a young Pullet,
and then had its left thigh bitten by a Viper;
whereupon it pre<U+017F>ently fell to the ground,
and in a little more then the eight part of an
hour died. Whence the <U+017F>u<U+017F>picion growing
<U+017F>till greater, about ten a clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
I made a Capon to eat two raw heads of
Vipers, and afterwards about twelve a clock
I made him <U+017F>wallow two others, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
lo<U+017F>ing any time<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> I cau<U+017F>ed him to be once
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98525:18"/>
bitten by a Viper in the thigh, and the Capon
immediately dyed, without finding any good
in the four <U+017F>wallow'd heads. The next day
I prepared for two young Dogs a di<U+017F>h of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-heads
parboiled, but they would not eat
them, and we were forced to cramm them
down: Soon after, the le<U+017F><U+017F>er of the two Dogs
was bitten in the thigh near the groin, and the
bigger in the tongue; and they both dyed. And
in the like manner dyed eight Chickens, two
Kitlings, two young Hares, and <U+017F>ix Turtle-Doves,
likewi<U+017F>e bitten by Vipers, and Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued
not only by their heads, both raw and
boiled, but al<U+017F>o having their wounds wa<U+017F>hed
with the Viper-blood. And I remember, that I
cau<U+017F>ed tho<U+017F>e 6 Turtle-Doves to be bitten not
by the heads of live Vipers, but by tho<U+017F>e of
dead ones, and <U+017F>uch as had dyed two days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
Moreover, I continued for three days
<U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively to cram two <U+017F>uch other Doves
with Viper-<U+017F>le<U+017F>h, and gave them no other
drink then the broth of that <U+017F>le<U+017F>h; and yet
they could not e<U+017F>cape death, being bitten by
a Viper.</p>
                  <p>Whence I am inclined to believe, that in
<hi>Tu<U+017F>cany</hi> the <U+017F>le<U+017F>h of Vipers is no help or reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
at lea<U+017F>t no con<U+017F>iderable one, to Animals
bitten by Vipers. Mean while I refer my <U+017F>elf
to the Learning, Experience, and Authority
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98525:19"/>
of tho<U+017F>e noble per<U+017F>ons, to whom I do mo<U+017F>t
willingly <U+017F>ubmit this or any other opinion of
mine, and with whom I would never entertain
a controver<U+017F>ie. For I <U+017F>hould apprehend le<U+017F>t
it might befall me, what <hi>Marcus Tullius</hi> was
wont to <U+017F>ay of <hi>Cato,</hi> viz. That it was not le<U+017F>s
trouble<U+017F>ome to him to an<U+017F>wer to the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of <hi>Cato,</hi> then to his <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t arguments.</p>
                  <p>For the re<U+017F>t, I earne<U+017F>tly intreat you, <hi>Sirs,</hi>
that you would pardon the rudene<U+017F>s of this
my Letter, <U+017F>ufficiently appearing to have
been written by a per<U+017F>on full of bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then enjoying lei<U+017F>ure; and that you would
plea<U+017F>e only to regard the naked truth, which
without any pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion I did undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:19"/>
                  <p>A CONTINUATION
Of the
NEW EXPERIMENTS
CONCERNING
VIPERS:
TOGETHER
With a Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e touching their Poy<U+017F>on:
By way of Reply, to a Letter written by
Signor <hi>FRANCESCO REDI,</hi>
to Me<U+017F><U+017F>ieurs <hi>BOURDELOT</hi>
and <hi>MORUS;</hi> Printed at <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
1670.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>MOYSE CHARAS.</hi>
Engli<U+017F>h'd out of French.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>Printed by<hi> T. R. </hi>for<hi> John Martyn </hi>Printer to the<hi> Royal
Society, </hi>at the<hi> Bell </hi>in S.<hi> Pauls Churchyard,</hi> 1673.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:20"/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98525:20"/>
                  <head>A CONTINUATION
Of the
NEW EXPERIMENTS
CONCERNING
VIPERS.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Fini<U+017F>ht in the Pre<U+017F>s at</hi> Paris, <date>
                        <hi>Augu<U+017F>t</hi> 4. 1671.</date>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believed, I had <U+017F>ufficiently e<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli<U+017F>h'd
my opinion touching
the <hi>Poi<U+017F>on</hi> of <hi>Vipers</hi> by abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of Experiments, <U+017F>uppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by Rea<U+017F>ons, heretofore
made publick: But there hath <U+017F>ince appear'd
at <hi>Paris</hi> a Letter of Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> in which
he oppo<U+017F>es my <U+017F>entiments: And he being a
per<U+017F>on, who<U+017F>e merit hath acquir'd him a great
reputation among the Learned, that Letter
of his hath not been without making <U+017F>ome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion
in the minds of many, and in <U+017F>ome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
of tho<U+017F>e, that had reli<U+017F>h'd my opinion, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98525:21"/>
favour of which they <U+017F>eem'd to have already
declared them<U+017F>elves.</p>
                  <p>I might indeed have defended my <U+017F>elf as to
that which is again<U+017F>t me in that Letter, <U+017F>oon
after it appear'd; having rea<U+017F>ons <U+017F>trong and
numerous enough to maintain and ju<U+017F>tifie all
I had advanced in my writing: But I thought
it better to deferr it till Spring, to the end
that after I <U+017F>hould have made New Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and the more a<U+017F><U+017F>ur'd my <U+017F>elf of all, I
might, by a renew'd knowledge of the truth,
afterwards the better per<U+017F>wade the publick
thereof. It will therefore appear by this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel
of Experiments, here <U+017F>et down, that I am
<U+017F>o far from changing my Opinion, that I have
rea<U+017F>on to be more <U+017F>trongly than ever confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
in what I embraced at fir<U+017F>t.</p>
                  <p>I do herewith <U+017F>incerely declare, that when
I publi<U+017F>hed my book, my chief aim was,
faithfully to relate all the truths I had di<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,
and not to offend Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> whom I
exceedingly e<U+017F>teem and honour for his rare
Talents, and who<U+017F>e friend<U+017F>hip I hope to have
a <U+017F>hare in; <U+017F>o far was I from pretending to
do any thing that might make him write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t
my Book, or from fore-<U+017F>eeing that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
I <U+017F>hould have occa<U+017F>ion to labour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
my <U+017F>elf again<U+017F>t him: Which yet I <U+017F>ince
found otherwi<U+017F>e, by the Letter he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98525:21"/>
again<U+017F>t me, and even without honoring
me with a Copy of it, wherewith he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
many per<U+017F>ons at <hi>Paris</hi> and el<U+017F>ewhere, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
after I had had the advantage of <U+017F>ome Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terary
Commerce with him, as I might ea<U+017F>ily
ju<U+017F>tifie.</p>
                  <p>I can be<U+017F>ides prote<U+017F>t, that when I re<U+017F>olved
to contradict certain points of his fir<U+017F>t Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
it was in a manner again<U+017F>t my will, and
becau<U+017F>e I could not at all di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e with it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
I would have baffled my <U+017F>en<U+017F>es, and that
light I <U+017F>aw my <U+017F>elf, together with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of witne<U+017F><U+017F>es. I can al<U+017F>o a<U+017F><U+017F>ure, that I
<U+017F>hould now be very ready to un-<U+017F>ay what I
have affirm'd upon this <U+017F>ubject, and to agree
with him, if I were not altogether per<U+017F>waded
of the contrary in the main things he hath
written again<U+017F>t my Sentiments.</p>
                  <p>After the<U+017F>e Prote<U+017F>tations, being well a<U+017F><U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
as well by Rea<U+017F>on, as by many new Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments
newly made, that I have a<U+017F><U+017F>erted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but what is true; I found<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> my <U+017F>elf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ably
obliged to maintain it, and to
render a good office to the publick, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
to <U+017F>hew that 'tis very difficult rea<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably
to oppo<U+017F>e any thing to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>The difference between Signor <hi>Redi</hi> and
me con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts chiefly in this, That he Pretends,
the Jellow Liquor contain'd in the Ve<U+017F>icles
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98525:22"/>
of the Gums of Vipers, to be the only and
true <U+017F>eat of their Poi<U+017F>on; That this juyce is
not venomous when taken at the mouth, but
that it is <U+017F>o when let into the wounds made
by a Viper whil<U+017F>t <U+017F>he is alive, and even in
tho<U+017F>e, which <U+017F>he may be forced to make <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
days after <U+017F>he is dead, provided that yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor do intervene; That the <U+017F>ame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
drawn from a live Viper, as well as that
of a dead one, is always venomous if let into
wounds, and mingled with the blood of the
Animal wounded, whether it be u<U+017F>ed when li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,
or after it is dryed and reduced to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
and that it generally kills all kind of
Animals into the wounds of which it <U+017F>hall
have been intromitted.</p>
                  <p>But I, who of all the<U+017F>e points can admit of
none but that of the innocence of the yellow
liquor when taken at the mouth, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
my <U+017F>elf to all the re<U+017F>t; do <U+017F>ay, That the
Poi<U+017F>on of a Viper is no where but in her enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
Spirits; that the yellow juyce as well of
a live Viper, and even a vexed one, as of one
that is either newly dead, or hath been <U+017F>o for
<U+017F>everal days, contains in it no poi<U+017F>on at all,
neither in the biting, nor taken inwardly,
nor put into wounds, nor mingled with the
blood, nor any other way wherein it may be
u<U+017F>ed; that it kills nor infects any kind of ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98525:22"/>
and that it is nothing but a meer and
innocent <hi>Saliva.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The que<U+017F>tion mu<U+017F>t principally be decided
by matter of Fact; though it may al<U+017F>o be
cleared by very pertinent rea<U+017F>ons. I am far
from accu<U+017F>ing Signor <hi>Reds</hi> of unfaithfule<U+017F>s in
his Experiments; though they were not made
in publick as mine, and that <U+017F>ome thing might
be <U+017F>aid as to the formalities of the biting, and
the u<U+017F>ing of the yellow liquor: His reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
is too well grounded to be blamed; and
this is the con<U+017F>ideration which troubles me
mo<U+017F>t. Mean time I <U+017F>ee the contrary to what
he hath advanced again<U+017F>t my Book; and the
truths which I there oppo<U+017F>e are <U+017F>o clearly
<U+017F>een in my Experiments fir<U+017F>t and la<U+017F>t, as well
in tho<U+017F>e I have made only in the pre<U+017F>ence of
<U+017F>ome curious per<U+017F>ons, as in tho<U+017F>e I have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
made in publick, and before a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of Phy<U+017F>itians and other per<U+017F>ons very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent
in the<U+017F>e matters. So that I can no<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
ought any longer to hide tho<U+017F>e truths, which
are the chief inducement of writing this di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>We need not wonder that Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
made all his Experiments by order and
at the expence of <U+017F>o great a Prince, who is as
curious as he is Munificent, had Vipers and
all <U+017F>orts of Animals in far greater number than
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98525:23"/>
I had; I, who did all from my <U+017F>elf, at my own
charges, and with a meer de<U+017F>ire to di<U+017F>cern
truth from fal<U+017F>hood. Nor do I think, I was
obliged to multiply expences when the truth
was found <U+017F>ufficiently clear'd up, and all the
by-<U+017F>tanders acknowledged, that I had made
<U+017F>ufficient tryals for every Experiment. For
<U+017F>ince he hath contented him<U+017F>elf with having
made <U+017F>ome of the yellow liquor to be <U+017F>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
by one only Man, one only Duck, one
only Kid, thence to know and to a<U+017F><U+017F>ure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
of its innocence when <U+017F>wallow'd, without
making a greater number of Experiments;
He mu<U+017F>t not blame me for having candidly
bounded my curio<U+017F>ity, after I had in divers
things made many more Experiments, then
he mentions he hath made upon this <U+017F>ubject;
as appears by what he writeth <hi>p.</hi> 17, &amp; 18. of
his fir<U+017F>t Letter. I find therefore, that he hath
no great cau<U+017F>e to complain of me (as he doth,
under the name of <hi>tho<U+017F>e Illu<U+017F>trious Authors,</hi> to
whom he a<U+017F>cribes my Book in his Letter) for
not having vouch<U+017F>afed to make Experiments
enow to confirm the truth of the Ob<U+017F>ervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
about Vipers, contain'd in his fir<U+017F>t Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of 1664. He had not, I <U+017F>ay, great cau<U+017F>e
to <U+017F>peak of it after <U+017F>uch a manner, <U+017F>ince I did
do <U+017F>o but in imitation of him, and becau<U+017F>e he
had in the <U+017F>ame Letter advanced and a<U+017F><U+017F>ured
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98525:23"/>
particulars, which required not I <U+017F>hould
make more tryals then tho<U+017F>e I have de<U+017F>cribed
in my Book: Although I can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure to have
made more then I have recited. He knows
very well, that about the end of pag. 23. of
his fir<U+017F>t Letter he u<U+017F>ed the<U+017F>e words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Equel veleno <U+017F>hizza tutto fuora, <U+017F>e non al
primo, almeno al <U+017F>econdo mor<U+017F>o; <U+017F>i che il terzo (epiù
volte l'ho e<U+017F>perimentato) non è veleno<U+017F>o:</hi>That is,<hi> And that poi<U+017F>on i<U+017F><U+017F>ues all out, if not at
the fir<U+017F>t, at lea<U+017F>t at the <U+017F>econd biting; <U+017F>o that
the third </hi>(which I have often experimented)<hi>is not venomous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if, becau<U+017F>e of the re<U+017F>pect I bear to the
writings of a per<U+017F>on of <U+017F>o high a reputation, I
thought among divers other Experiments,
that having made one and the <U+017F>ame Viper, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
time vexed, to bite five <U+017F>everal Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
which all died, and even the la<U+017F>t of them
<U+017F>ooner then the re<U+017F>t, I might <U+017F>top there; I
think Signor <hi>Redi</hi> hath nothing to reproach
me with. He had a<U+017F><U+017F>ured in his fir<U+017F>t Letter,
and a<U+017F><U+017F>ures the <U+017F>ame in his latter, That all the
poi<U+017F>on did lodge in the yellow liquor, and
that this poi<U+017F>on was all exhau<U+017F>ted if not at
the fir<U+017F>t, yet at lea<U+017F>t at the <U+017F>econd biting, and
that he had often experimented that the third
was no more venomous: So that, if I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>waded,
that all the yellow Liquor mu<U+017F>t be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98525:24"/>
come out by the <U+017F>econd biting made upon the
<U+017F>econd Pigeon, and if, after that, I have <U+017F>een
dye three other Pigeons by the fre<U+017F>h bitings
of the <U+017F>ame Viper that had bitten the two fir<U+017F>t;
I do not think that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath right to
accu<U+017F>e me for not having done enough: He
might rather have done me that ju<U+017F>tice as to
acknowledge, that I had done more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to maintain my Reflexions, and that I
was obliged from that time to <U+017F>eek the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
el<U+017F>ewhere then in the yellow liquor, in
regard it did no longer intervene, according
to him, in the three la<U+017F>t bitings, and that the
three la<U+017F>t Pigeons were as <U+017F>oon, yea <U+017F>ooner,
dead then the two fir<U+017F>t, of the death of which
he could charge the yellow liquor. If I could
not find, no more then Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi> in all the
body of the Viper, any other vi<U+017F>ible or pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
part that was venomous, and that
might ju<U+017F>tly be declared to be the <U+017F>eat of the
poi<U+017F>on, and the true cau<U+017F>e of the death which
en<U+017F>ued upon the three la<U+017F>t bitings; he mu<U+017F>t
not wonder, if I have <U+017F>ought and found it in
the <hi>vexed Spirits,</hi> and if I have grounded my
<U+017F>elf upon the be<U+017F>t evidence, I could get from
Experiments and Rea<U+017F>on.</p>
                  <p>But <U+017F>ince the chief motive of my tryals hath
been the de<U+017F>ire of exactly knowing the Truth
concerning tho<U+017F>e matters; having <U+017F>een that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98525:24"/>
Sign. <hi>Redi, pag.</hi> 31. of his la<U+017F>t Letter hath
de<U+017F>ired I would make new experiments after
his Objections again<U+017F>t me: To be the more a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ured
of all, I have been willing to give him
that <U+017F>atisfaction, in giving it to my <U+017F>elf. For,
in the moneth of <hi>May</hi> la<U+017F>t, in the Chymical La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory
of the Royal Garden, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence
of two or three hundred by <U+017F>tanders,
both Phy<U+017F>itians and others, capable to judge
of it, and worthy to be credited; from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<U+017F>t
many live Vipers, <U+017F>ent me out of <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine,</hi>
and divers parts of <hi>Poitou,</hi> I cho<U+017F>e a
great Femal-Viper, that was lu<U+017F>ty enough
notwith<U+017F>tanding the great way <U+017F>he came, and
having open'd her jawes, I very carefully
cleared and <U+017F>queezed out of them at <U+017F>everal
repetitions, all the yellow liquor contained
in the bags of her gums, and that al<U+017F>o which
might be diffu<U+017F>ed about the neighbouring
parts, with a fine piece of linnen cloth wound
about the handle of a pen knife: Which done,
I took the <U+017F>ame Viper with Pincers about hér
neck, and angred her in making her to fa<U+017F>ten
her teeth into the end of her tail, and in pre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
from time to time her neck with tho<U+017F>e
Pincers; and immediately after I pre<U+017F>ented
to her five Pigeons and two Pullets one after
another, to bite them in the mo<U+017F>t fle<U+017F>hy part
of their Che<U+017F>t, having irritated her every time
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98525:25"/>
of her biting. I purpo<U+017F>ely wounded al<U+017F>o
<U+017F>ix Pigeons and Pullets in divers places, in the
pre<U+017F>ence of all the company, and let into the
wounds <U+017F>ome drops of the yellow liquor,
drawn from the Ve<U+017F>icles of newly enraged Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.
I laid both <U+017F>orts a part; and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
parted about an hour after, before
which time, five of the Pigeons and Pullets,
that had been bitten, were dead, and the two
remaining died about an hour after; but the
Pigeons and Pullets, which I had wounded,
and in who<U+017F>e wounds I had put in <U+017F>ome of the
<U+017F>aid juyce, ailed nothing, but that there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<U+017F>ome lividne<U+017F>s, at the place wounded,
and <U+017F>uch an one as might have been there
from the <U+017F>ole wounding them, and without
any concurrence of that liquor. Two days
after, I <U+017F>hew'd the company the <U+017F>ame woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Pullets and the <U+017F>ame Pigeons, which
were very well, and had their wounds almo<U+017F>t
perfectly healed up, only there remain'd a
little blewne<U+017F>s about the wounded parts. I
would then have wounded the <U+017F>ame animals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
in other places, and intromitted fre<U+017F>h
yellow liquor: <U+017F>ome al<U+017F>o of the by-<U+017F>tanders
propo<U+017F>ed to let into one of the<U+017F>e creatures
<U+017F>ome of this yellow liquor by that way of
Transfu<U+017F>ion, that hath lately been made in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> of <U+017F>ome <U+017F>tranger blood
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98525:25"/>
into the veins of men, that <U+017F>o this juyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
mingled with the blood by the ordinary
circulation, it might be able to di<U+017F>cover what
ever it could do. I readily complied with
their motion, whereupon the intromi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of
this liquor was attempted upon one of the
<U+017F>ame Pigeons that had been wounded two
days before. One Phy<U+017F>itian and two Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
did the work one after onother, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
both the inci<U+017F>ion and the ligature of the
mo<U+017F>t di<U+017F>cernable ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the right wing:
But they let the Pigeon loo<U+017F>e <U+017F>o much blood,
that it dyed <U+017F>oon after. Seeing this, I <U+017F>aid,
that the Pigeon dyed only from the lo<U+017F>s of its
blood, and not from the letting in of the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor; and that it would be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary,
one only Chirurgion of the Company <U+017F>hou'd
make a new operation upon another of the
<U+017F>ame Animals, that had been wounded 2 days
before, and upon whom that yellow Juyce had
al<U+017F>o been tryed. The Operation was made
accordingly at the <U+017F>ame time upon a Pullet,
which did not only e<U+017F>cape again, but was <U+017F>een
the next day and the following days by the
whole company to be very well; as were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o
the other animals that had been wounded
again at the <U+017F>ame time, and received of the
yellow liquor, though without the way of
transfu<U+017F>ion. Yet true it is, that one of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98525:26"/>
Pigeons, that had been the <U+017F>econd time woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
was found dead <U+017F>ome time after its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
wounded, in a clo<U+017F>e earthen Furnace, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
hot, and <U+017F>tanding clo<U+017F>e by <U+017F>uch another,
where I then di<U+017F>tilled <U+017F>ome <U+017F>pirit and oyl of
Tobacco, and the death of which ought to
be imputed to the piercing vapors of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tillation,
or to the exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive heat of the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace
in which it had been <U+017F>hut up, which
was found <U+017F>o hot, that the heat of it could not
be endured by ones hand; be<U+017F>ides that being
clo<U+017F>ed, almo<U+017F>t no air could enter.</p>
                  <p>Which being thus pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed, yet fora<U+017F>much as
the reputation of Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> had acquired
him much e<U+017F>teem and favour from many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons
in <hi>Paris,</hi> I perceived <U+017F>ome of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
yet inclined to doubt, whether this yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
Juyce were always innocent. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
having by me 4 Dogs of different bigne<U+017F>s,
I pre<U+017F>s'd tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>eemed mo<U+017F>t to doubt,
that they would transfu<U+017F>e or cau<U+017F>e to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu<U+017F>ed
<U+017F>ome of that reputed poi<U+017F>onous liquor
into all tho<U+017F>e Dogs, or at lea<U+017F>t into one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of them; but how in<U+017F>tant <U+017F>oever I was,
no body would undertake it. It was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
that tho<U+017F>e Animals were too Robu<U+017F>t
to Succumb under <U+017F>uch an operation, <U+017F>ince
the Pullet, that had endur'd it, and twice felt
the yellow liquor, had e<U+017F>caped as well as the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98525:26"/>
other Animals, that had been wounded again
at the <U+017F>ame time with it, and that had al<U+017F>o re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
into them <U+017F>ome of that liquor. Which
obliged me to prote<U+017F>t, it was not my fault that
it was not experimented a fre<U+017F>h, and to pray
the company to take the refu<U+017F>al of tho<U+017F>e per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons
for an acknowledgment of the innocence
of the yellow liquor.</p>
                  <p>But not being <U+017F>atisfied herewith, I refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the matter to the next day, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed
to have ready new Animals, of a le<U+017F><U+017F>er
<U+017F>ize than tho<U+017F>e Dogs; the more amply to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
the innoxiou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of that Juyce by new
intromi<U+017F><U+017F>ions thereof into wounds.</p>
                  <p>I had then prepar'd <U+017F>ix Pigeons, and two
Carlings; and engaged a per<U+017F>on whom I knew
mo<U+017F>t favourable to Signor <hi>Redi,</hi> to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
the inci<U+017F>ion, and intromit the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
as he <U+017F>hould think be<U+017F>t. He made <U+017F>uch
wounds as he plea<U+017F>ed, and he did even <U+017F>ever
the skin of the fle<U+017F>h round about the wounds
he had made, and <U+017F>o far, that I could not hold
to tell him <U+017F>miling, he did more than Signor
<hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>aid in his Letters he had done;
and added, <hi>Boni e<U+017F><U+017F>e pa<U+017F>toris tondere, non de
glubere,</hi> A good Shepherd did Sheer, not Flea
his Sheep.</p>
                  <p>One of the Catlings was bitten in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilagineous
part of the Ear, without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98525:27"/>
of blood at the place of the biting;
and it e<U+017F>caped. The other, which was much
le<U+017F>s, and a very noted one by the blackne<U+017F>s
of its colour and by having her ears cut off,
was purpo<U+017F>ely wounded on the upper part
of her neck behind, and al<U+017F>o at the lower bone
of the hinder part of the head; its skin al<U+017F>owas
<U+017F>eparated from the fle<U+017F>h round about the
wound, and on both <U+017F>ides, almo<U+017F>t as far as to
the fore part of the neck: And then as much
of the yellow liquor as they would was put
into both <U+017F>ides as well as into the wound.
This Cat held down her head, by rea<U+017F>on
doubtle<U+017F>s of the pain <U+017F>he endured by having
in a manner been flead alive; feeling al<U+017F>o <U+017F>ome
pain in two other places, where <U+017F>he had been
wounded and flead. Some of the by-<U+017F>tanders
began already to mutter, and <U+017F>aid, I <U+017F>hould be
ca<U+017F>t, and the Cat would certainly dye; yet
notwith<U+017F>tanding the Cat did not dye, though
<U+017F>he was very little and taken out from under
her dam; and <U+017F>he was <U+017F>hew'd to the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
24 hours after, <U+017F>ound and <U+017F>afe, although
<U+017F>he had neither <U+017F>uck'd nor eaten any thing all
that time. And 'tis remarkable enough, that
this very Cat, having been returned to a Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
to whom <U+017F>he belonged, and being grown
big, hath yet to this day the hind-part of her
skull unclo<U+017F>ed at the place of her wound;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98525:27"/>
and notwith<U+017F>tanding all that, &amp; the falling off
of <U+017F>ome fle<U+017F>h and skin, that were <U+017F>ever'd from
the places where <U+017F>he was flead, <U+017F>he is very
lively and full of play, and very diverti<U+017F>ing
mimick ge<U+017F>tures.</p>
                  <p>The <U+017F>ix latter Pigeons, that had been woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
at the <U+017F>ame time, and received of the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor, were likewi<U+017F>e produced; and they
were yet kept five or <U+017F>ix days with the other
Pigeons and Pullets that had been twice
wounded before; among which was that al<U+017F>o
on which the transfu<U+017F>ion had been imitated.
At la<U+017F>t they were killed, ro<U+017F>ted, and eaten,
in good company, of which were <U+017F>ome of
tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>aw them wounded; and that found
them very good and <U+017F>avoury meat.</p>
                  <p>Amid<U+017F>t all tho<U+017F>e Experiments I omitted not
to try, whether the heads of Vipers newly
dead, having yet their necks on, with all their
yellow liquor, would be able to kill Animals,
by making them to be bitten by them. I tryed
it upon Pigeons and Pullets, by thru<U+017F>ting the
teeth into them as deep as I could. I employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
al<U+017F>o to the <U+017F>ame purpo<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome whole Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
which I had found dead among the live
ones in the barrils, and which abounded in
the yellow liquor. But this was always with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any inconvenience to the Animals bitten,
<U+017F>o far was it from killing them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98525:28"/>
I here pa<U+017F>s by many other Experiments
made at my hou<U+017F>e, in the pre<U+017F>ence of <U+017F>everal
Phy<U+017F>itians, that did all agree in making out the
innocence of the yellow liquor, and in a<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
the poi<U+017F>onou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s to the enraged <U+017F>pirits.</p>
                  <p>Yet I mu<U+017F>t not leave here un-mentioned,
what was done by three young Phy<U+017F>itians, who
being per<U+017F>waded of the truth of my Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
as well concerning the innocence of the
yellow liquor, as that of bitings made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the angred <U+017F>pirits, cau<U+017F>ed their fingers to
be bitten, to <U+017F>trifes, by a dead Viper having
yet all her yellow liquor, and that <U+017F>o deep,
that the blood of it appeared to all: But they
found no other inconvenience by it, but what
they might have felt from prickings made by
a needle.</p>
                  <p>I had certainly made a far greater number
of Experiments if I had not ob<U+017F>erved, that
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf had already made many
for me, and for the maintaining of my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
and among others that of <hi>pag.</hi> 26. of
his fir<U+017F>t Letter of Ob<U+017F>ervations, where he
<U+017F>aith,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si mori un polla<U+017F>tro mor<U+017F>icato, </hi>&amp;c. That is,<hi>There dyed a Pullet bitten by a Viper, the points
of who<U+017F>e teeth I had cut off; and out of who<U+017F>e
ve<U+017F>sicles I had <U+017F>queezed out all that ill juyce that
it there.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98525:28"/>
For, <U+017F>ince by his own confe<U+017F><U+017F>ion, there dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a Pullet by having been bitten by a Viper,
the points of who<U+017F>e teeth he had de<U+017F>ignedly
cut off, and all who<U+017F>e yellow liquor (which
he calls the ill juyce, and will have to be the
only <U+017F>eat of the poi<U+017F>on) he had carefully
pre<U+017F>s'd out of the ve<U+017F>icles of her Gums; He
hath no more ground then I, to charge the
death of the Pullet upon a liquor, which was
there no more, nor upon the points of the
teeth, which he had cut off. And he cannot
avoid to accu<U+017F>e with me the vexed <U+017F>pirits of
the Viper, and to fall into my opinion, <hi>viz,</hi>
That the venom of the Viper is not a gro<U+017F>s
matter, but <U+017F>omething invi<U+017F>ible and <U+017F>piritual.</p>
                  <p>And to <U+017F>hew again, that Signor <hi>Redi</hi> hath
laboured, without being aware of it, to ju<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
my Sentiment, and that at the <U+017F>ame time he
manife<U+017F>tly contradicts him<U+017F>elf, by de<U+017F>troying
in his la<U+017F>t Letter his fir<U+017F>t Propo<U+017F>itions, which
is, <hi>That all the venom of the Viper i<U+017F><U+017F>ues at the
fir<U+017F>t, or at lea<U+017F>t at the <U+017F>econd biting, and that the
third is venomous no more,</hi> as he a<U+017F><U+017F>ureth to
have often experimented; to <U+017F>hew that, I <U+017F>ay, I
<U+017F>hall alledge the words of pag. 33, 34, and
35. of his la<U+017F>t Letter, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Su'l principio di maggio <U+017F>cel<U+017F>i una vipera, </hi>&amp;c.
That is,<hi> About the beginning of </hi>May<hi> I cho<U+017F>e a
Femal-Viper, one of the bigge<U+017F>t and lu<U+017F>tie<U+017F>t, and</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98525:29"/>
                     <hi>vexed her to bite ten Chickens, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
in the right thigh; of which the fir<U+017F>t, <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
and third died almo<U+017F>t in an in<U+017F>tant; the
fourth <U+017F>eem'd only to be <U+017F>ick; but the fifth and all
the re<U+017F>t did not only not dye, but were not at all
<U+017F>ick; and yet every time the Viper did bite, I
angred and madded her exceedingly. In the
moneth of </hi>June<hi> I repeated the Experiment in
five tame Ducks, bitten by one and the <U+017F>ame Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
which al<U+017F>o immediately after bit three
young Turtle-Doves. The fir<U+017F>t wounded dyed
three hours after; the <U+017F>econd-five hours after;
the re<U+017F>t e<U+017F>caped. 'Tis true, that the fir<U+017F>t men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd
of the Turtles dyed, but not the other two.
Of twelve Ring-Doves at one time there dyed
but four; but the next day of twelve others there
dyed <U+017F>ix. Of five Rabbets there dyed three;
and of three Lambs the two la<U+017F>t dyed; the fir<U+017F>t
of them dying two hours after it had been biten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The<U+017F>e <U+017F>everal Experiments directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to the fir<U+017F>t a<U+017F><U+017F>ertion of Signor <hi>Redi,</hi>
were capable to perplex any other head but
<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is. For fir<U+017F>t, he hath <U+017F>een, that of ten bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
bitten one after another by one only Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
the three fir<U+017F>t dyed <U+017F>uddenly, and the
fourth was <U+017F>omewhat <U+017F>ick; He hath <U+017F>een, that
of five Ducks and of three Pigeons, bitten one
after another by a <U+017F>ingle Viper, the two fir<U+017F>t
Ducks dyed, as al<U+017F>o one of the Pigeons, which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98525:29"/>
had been bitten even after the five Ducks: He
al<U+017F>o <U+017F>aw once, that of twelve Pigeons bitten,
four dyed; that another time of twelve there
e<U+017F>caped but the moiety; and that of five Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets,
likewi<U+017F>e bitten, there were but two that
evaded dying.</p>
                  <p>I cannot but be amazed, that all the<U+017F>e Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
have not been able to change his
opinion, or at lea<U+017F>t to <U+017F>u<U+017F>pend it. Nor do I
doubt but that the number of Animals that
d<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed would have been much greater, if the
bitings had been made in other places but the
legs. For, be<U+017F>ides that they have their bones,
nerves, and tendons, that are able to blunt
the point of the teeth at the fir<U+017F>t biting; they
have al<U+017F>o their Mu<U+017F>cles, which are very vi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous,
and therefore fail not to imbue the teeth
of the biting Viper, thereby <U+017F>topping in part
their Pores, and even hindring them by that
v<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F>co<U+017F>ity from entring far in the en<U+017F>uing bites,
and I likewi<U+017F>e doubt not, but that will come
to pa<U+017F>s more and more in the reiteration of
their bitings. Nor do I wonder, that the
Ducks did not dye <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as the Pullets or
Pigeons, nor that there dyed le<U+017F>s of them; for,
be<U+017F>ides the rea<U+017F>ons ju<U+017F>t now alledged, they
have their skin, bones, and all parts much
harder, and far more difficult to be pierced
by the Vipers teeth, than tho<U+017F>e of Pigeons or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98525:30"/>
Pullets. Now I do not find any part mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
proper to try divers bitings, then the fle<U+017F>hy
part of the che<U+017F>t, which hath neither Nerves,
nor Tendons, nor bones near, nor that Vi<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity
found in the Mu<U+017F>cles of the legs.</p>
                  <p>Mean time the<U+017F>e Experiments made by
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf, mu<U+017F>t oblige him, as far as
I can judge, to relinqui<U+017F>h his fir<U+017F>t A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion:
And if he will per<U+017F>i<U+017F>t to maintain, that the
yellow liquor is the true <U+017F>eat of the poi<U+017F>on,
he mu<U+017F>t needs believe that liquor to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhau<U+017F>tible,
and that always there <U+017F>ucceeds
<U+017F>ome fre<U+017F>h, in all the bitings of a Viper; or,
if he will abandon his opinion, and a<U+017F>cribe
the poi<U+017F>on no more to the yellow liquor, he
mu<U+017F>t find out <U+017F>ome other <U+017F>ubject to a<U+017F><U+017F>ign it
to, except he plea<U+017F>e to take mine, and to
lodge it in the irritated <U+017F>pirits; in regard that
he cannot find it in the yellow liquor, which
is no more there, after the <U+017F>econd biting (as
him<U+017F>elf a<U+017F><U+017F>ureth;) and which mu<U+017F>t yet more
evidently be wanting there, when de<U+017F>ignedly
he had with care taken it out of the bags of
the gums of the Viper that bit the Pullet, and
the bite of which was followed by the death
of the Animal bitten.</p>
                  <p>But if Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> <U+017F>hould now be in an humor
to alter his opinion, and to judge the yellow
liquor to be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in all the bitings of a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98525:30"/>
Viper (though that be an impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible thing;)
his opinion would never be received by di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intere<U+017F><U+017F>ed
per<U+017F>ons, that have <U+017F>een my fir<U+017F>t and
la<U+017F>t Experiments; among which per<U+017F>ons there
are <U+017F>ome, even of the mo<U+017F>t able, who, having
heretofore examin'd the <hi>Salival Glanduls</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the de<U+017F>cription I gave them of it after I
had di<U+017F>cover'd them, did there ob<U+017F>erve al<U+017F>o
<U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall <hi>Lymphatic</hi> Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, more numerous
then tho<U+017F>e that had fir<U+017F>t appeared to me; and
who, having <U+017F>een the la<U+017F>t Letter of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
were willing to <U+017F>u<U+017F>pend their Judgment until
the making of my new Tryals, which have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
confirm'd them in my fir<U+017F>t opinion.</p>
                  <p>For, not to <U+017F>peak of this, that in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence
of divers per<U+017F>ons, even of the be<U+017F>t qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
at <U+017F>everal times and places, in divers a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>emblies,
&amp; even in the Conferences of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot
<hi>Bourdelot;</hi> I have <U+017F>wallow'd <U+017F>ome of the
yellow liquor taken out of the bags of the
gums of many live and enraged Vipers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
finding the lea<U+017F>t inconvenience from it,
no more then the Viper-catcher of Sign. <hi>Redi:</hi>
I can boldly a<U+017F><U+017F>ure all the world, that at no
time, in no place, there ever dyed any animal
of all tho<U+017F>e I have wounded, or <U+017F>een wounded
on purpo<U+017F>e, and into the wounds of which
that liquor hath been intromitted, although
it had been drawn hot out of the Ve<U+017F>icles of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98525:31"/>
the gums of Vipers exceedingly vexed; <U+017F>o far
is it, that the Juyce of dead Vipers was able
to annoy any animal. I can al<U+017F>o a<U+017F><U+017F>ure, that
never any head of a dead Viper, whether the
Animal were who<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, or that head only with
its neck, and though it abounded with that
yellow liquor, hath done any harm to man or
any other Animal, bitten by it.</p>
                  <p>The yellow liquor, which I <U+017F>wallow'd in
one of the conferences of the Abbot <hi>Bourdelot,</hi>
puts me in mind of Letter, which M. <hi>Des
Tapieres,</hi> a very curious, <U+017F>incere and able A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary
of <hi>Bourbon l' Archamband,</hi> had
written to him, which was there read, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
other things did relate, That in the year
1630. he had taken a Viper, who<U+017F>e crook'd
teeth he had cut, and that he carried her in his
bo<U+017F>om; and that after two or three days, a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
taking him to approach her to his face,
pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing her a little, <U+017F>he bit him in his lip, and
thereby cau<U+017F>ed great pain to him; whereupon
he flung her to the ground and in his anger
cru<U+017F>ht her in pieces; that his lip and face
<U+017F>welled; that a Ligature was made upon him;
that Treacle was given him, and <U+017F>ome of it
applied to the bite; that at the place of the
wound there appear'd a little bladder,
whence i<U+017F><U+017F>ued two or three drops of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
of a dark yellow colour, and that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98525:31"/>
his face remain'd very pale for a moneth.</p>
                  <p>If my opinion be asked about this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment,
I declare that there is nothing in it,
which I ought not to believe; and I add al<U+017F>o,
that there hapn'd nothing in it, which agrees
not with the principles by me e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>h'd and
maintain'd. For, although the great teeth
of that Viper had been cut, which might have
gone further, and mingled the enraged <U+017F>pirits
of the Viper with the blood of <hi>M. Tapieres;</hi>
yet they had not cut the point of the <U+017F>mall
teeth, which I <U+017F>hew'd in the <U+017F>ame conference
together with the other neighbouring parts
in the teath of a live Viper, <U+017F>ent to Mon<U+017F>ieur
<hi>Bourdelot</hi> by the <U+017F>ame Apothecary that had
been bitten: of which <U+017F>mall teeth I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
given the de<U+017F>cription and figure, as
well as that of the upper and lower Jawes, in
which they are fa<U+017F>tn'd, as may be <U+017F>een in my
<hi>Anatomy of Vipers,</hi> in the <hi>Section</hi> of the teeth,
and the third <hi>Cut</hi> of that Pook. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
tho<U+017F>e little teeth have not the length
nor thickne<U+017F>s of the great ones; yet they have
the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>hape and the <U+017F>ame matter; for they
are bony, crooked, tran<U+017F>parent, and very
<U+017F>harp; <U+017F>o that the vexed <U+017F>pirits may pa<U+017F>s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them as into <U+017F>mall Funnels, and through
their Pores, as they do thorough tho<U+017F>e of the
bigger ones: But they cannot go very deep,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98525:32"/>
becau<U+017F>e their <U+017F>malne<U+017F>s permits them not to
carry their openings as far as into the fle<U+017F>h;
and all they can doe, is, to open the skin.
Now to rea<U+017F>on upon the accidents that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
<hi>M. Des Trapieres</hi> by this bite, as they
are <U+017F>et down in his Letter; I <U+017F>ee nothing in
them that is not very natural, and very credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
For, although the angred Spirits had
entred by the openings made by the <U+017F>mall
teeth; yet they could not penetrate the fle<U+017F>h,
nor mingle with the blood, becau<U+017F>e tho<U+017F>e a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertures
were not deep enough, and they
could do no more but to make their effort
'twixt the fle<U+017F>h and skin; whence follow'd
the <U+017F>welling of the lip and face, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion
of the pale colour, which appear'd
there during a moneth; which accidents
might at fir<U+017F>t have been ea<U+017F>ily prevented by
one only do<U+017F>e of the volatil Salt of Vipers,
which would have made the enraged Spirits
to tran<U+017F>pire, that lodged between the fle<U+017F>h
and the skin, and could find no entry to pa<U+017F>s
further. As to the little bladder, which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
at the place of the bite, and the two or
three drops of dark liquor that i<U+017F><U+017F>ued after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
that was nothing but a little <U+017F>erous
moi<U+017F>ture that had been gather'd there from
the neighbouring parts, and that had been
cau<U+017F>ed by the compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the Ligature,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98525:32"/>
and by the brui<U+017F>ing made by the teeth and
Jawes at the time of the biting, and without
any intervention of the yellow liquor, which
be<U+017F>ides its innocence, could not have entred
through <U+017F>uch <U+017F>mall apertures.</p>
                  <p>After <U+017F>o many Experiments, and upon <U+017F>o
many Reflexions which I have made, as well
on the yellow liquor, as on the irritated <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
of Vipers, I cannot comprehend, how
the Animals of Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> could dye all and
without any exception by the intromi<U+017F><U+017F>ion
of the yellow liquor into the wounds, he had
made in them, and by the biting of heads <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,
or by that of entire Vipers that had
been dead <U+017F>everal days. I have too many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
to the contrary, and too many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>es,
to put it out of doubt, and to fix me in
my fir<U+017F>t opinion.</p>
                  <p>But, to the end that among the Truths by
me advanced, and con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting in matter of fact,
the publick may find wherewith to be <U+017F>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;
I thought my <U+017F>elf obliged to explain my
<U+017F>en<U+017F>e upon the<U+017F>e matters, and to form to my
<U+017F>elf the Objections, that may be made again<U+017F>t
me.</p>
                  <p>I <U+017F>ay therefore concerning the <hi>Tellow Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,</hi>
That nothing can act from it <U+017F>elf, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to its nature, the di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of the
matter of which it is compo<U+017F>ed, and the force
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98525:33"/>
of its activity. For example, you will not
find in River Water, the ta<U+017F>te, <U+017F>trength, nor
particles that are found in Wine, nor will
<hi>that</hi> inebriate like <hi>this:</hi> it hath not the acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
nor penetrancy of Urine, neither the
colour not bitterne<U+017F>s of Gall: The Spirit of
Wine, that is freed from the aqueous parts,
which hindred the Wine from producing the
effects it was capable of, is much more <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
and <U+017F>trong, then the <U+017F>ame wine whence it
hath been drawn: The Volatil Salt of Wine
hath quite another penetrating force than the
Urine which contained it before its <U+017F>ublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
And not to go from my <U+017F>ubject; the
volatil Salt of Vipers is very different from
the fle<U+017F>h and bones of them, whence it hath
been extracted; and, though in <U+017F>mall quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
it will work more in a moment as well by
its odour as its piercing vertue, than ten times
as much of that matter, whence it hath been
drawn, could effect in many hours: The bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leous,
<U+017F>harp, <U+017F>alt and <U+017F>pirituous <U+017F>ero<U+017F>ity, that
is often form'd in our bodies, will <U+017F>uddenly
produce inflammations in the eyes, tumors in
the cheeks, gums, throat, and many other
parts, as al<U+017F>o Pu<U+017F>tuls, St. Anthony fire, and
the Gangrene it <U+017F>elf; and all that it does by
the compo<U+017F>ition of its parts, and the force of
its activity; whereas the thick and vi<U+017F>cous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98525:33"/>
Phlegme will do no <U+017F>uch thing, but chargeth
nature only by its weight, cold, and tenacity:
This Phlegme, I <U+017F>ay, will ever be incapable
of working with quickne<U+017F>s, and it cannot
produce any effect out very <U+017F>lowly, and in
proportion to its power, which is extreamly
confined.</p>
                  <p>So then, it is not the nature of the yellow
liquor, to pa<U+017F>s <U+017F>wiftly to remote parts, and
there to act with vigor and violence;
which is ob<U+017F>erved in the poi<U+017F>on of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
I <U+017F>ay, that a tough, vi<U+017F>cous, and
in a manner in<U+017F>ipid <hi>Saliva,</hi> cannot make any
great progre<U+017F>s in a moment. I affirm be<U+017F>ides,
that 'tis impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, it <U+017F>hould corporally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
into the holes made by the teeth, which
are very <U+017F>mall and almo<U+017F>t invi<U+017F>ible, and that it
<U+017F>hould al<U+017F>o pa<U+017F>s through the cavities of the
teeth, and much le<U+017F>s through their Pores, if
any would have them pa<U+017F>s that way. I <U+017F>ay
further, <hi>that</hi> although the teeth of a Viper
<U+017F>hould be all over imbued with that Juyce at
the time of her biting; the skin of the Animal
bitten, and the fle<U+017F>h it <U+017F>elf, if need were,
would keep it out of the bitten place, and
hinder it from entring there; <hi>That</hi> though it
<U+017F>hould be able to enter, it mu<U+017F>t have a fit
place to receive it, a great pa<U+017F><U+017F>age to go
through, and a long time to arrive to the parts
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98525:34"/>
remote; I <U+017F>ay al<U+017F>o, that though it were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
there, (if that were po<U+017F><U+017F>ible,) it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
act beyond the forces, which nature hath
re<U+017F>trained it to.</p>
                  <p>Be<U+017F>ides, if this yellow liquor were capable
of any con<U+017F>iderable operation, it would not
fail to di<U+017F>cover it either in whole or in part,
when 'tis <U+017F>wallow'd and got into the <U+017F>tomach;
where the place, the heat, and all things
would <U+017F>eem to concur <hi>either</hi> to make it fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
if its matter were di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed for it, <hi>or</hi> to
reduce its power into action: For, by pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
out of the <U+017F>tomach into the inte<U+017F>tins it
would infect the Chyle, and make of it a poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on,
which would be carried jointly with it
through the milky ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and through the
Thoracique Ductus'<hi>s,</hi> <U+017F>o happily di<U+017F>cover'd
by the illu<U+017F>trious <hi>M. Pecquet,</hi> to de<U+017F>cend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Heart with the blood, the which is the
matter, on which the poi<U+017F>on of Vipers does
<U+017F>o particularly exert its dominion. And this
way is much more ea<U+017F>ie and large, than that of
the opening, made by the teeth, by which
this juyce cannot <U+017F>o much as enter. I <U+017F>ay this
further, that, if it were <U+017F>uch as Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
makes it to be, it would, being taken at the
mouth and let down into the <U+017F>tomach, impre<U+017F>s
upon the places of its pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, and tho<U+017F>e of its
<U+017F>tay, <U+017F>ome mark or other of its power, e<U+017F>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98525:34"/>
if it did contain any <hi>Ar<U+017F>enical</hi> Salts,
which would not fail, <U+017F>oon to manife<U+017F>t them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves
either by their ta<U+017F>te or by <U+017F>ome other
effects: And yet all tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>hall ta<U+017F>te or
<U+017F>wallow this yellow liquor, <U+017F>hall never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
any malignity whether great or <U+017F>mall,
neither in the mouth, nor in the <U+017F>tomach, nor
el<U+017F>ewhere. I conclude therefore from all
the<U+017F>e con<U+017F>iderations, that this juyce contains
in it no part at all, that is able to di<U+017F><U+017F>olve, or
coagulate, or di<U+017F>compo<U+017F>e any part of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;
&amp; that it hath not any quality, manife<U+017F>t or
occult, to <U+017F>hew that 'tis capable of doing <U+017F>o.</p>
                  <p>I add moreover, that this juyce, as flat and
<U+017F>alivous as it is, is always found <U+017F>o yellow in
all parts of <hi>France,</hi> that it can hardly be le<U+017F>s
colour'd than 'tis in <hi>Italy;</hi> and that they both
mu<U+017F>t have altogether alike qualities, or, at
lea<U+017F>t, very near <U+017F>uch. And it would be to
no purpo<U+017F>e, to alledge in favour of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
that the diver<U+017F>ity of places and climate, or
that of aliments might be able to change the
nature of Vipers, and cau<U+017F>e that manife<U+017F>t dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
there is between his Experiments
and mine. For, although <U+017F>ome diver<U+017F>ity may
be ob<U+017F>erved in other things, there can be
found none in this; and if there could be <U+017F>ome
difference, it cannot be that the nature of the
yellow juyce, and that of the Spirits <U+017F>hould
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98525:35"/>
be <hi>quite</hi> changed; <U+017F>ince we find in <hi>France</hi> the
<U+017F>ame marks in that liquor, which Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
hath found and de<U+017F>cribed in that of <hi>Italy,</hi> and
<U+017F>ince our Vipers, without any intervention
of that juyce, do kill as nimbly as his can do.</p>
                  <p>But I think it would be much, if in the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor, or in the enraged <U+017F>pirits, there
could be ob<U+017F>erv'd any <hi><U+017F>mall</hi> degree of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<U+017F>tronger or weaker in <hi>Italy</hi> than in <hi>France.</hi>
For, I have by a great number of experiments
made it out, that all the Vipers of <hi>France,</hi>
though taken in very different places, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<U+017F>uch as are <U+017F>ix <U+017F>core Leagues di<U+017F>tant from
one another, have their poi<U+017F>on altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
and do kill equally. Whence I inferr,
that the difference of the Vipers of <hi>Italy</hi> and
<hi>France,</hi> cannot be con<U+017F>iderable; <U+017F>ince <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiné,</hi>
which is a Province in <hi>France</hi> that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>heth
us with many of them, and is very
mountainous as well as <hi>Italy,</hi> borders upon
<hi>Picmont,</hi> which is the beginning of <hi>Italy;</hi>
and that the <U+017F>ame <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> abounds in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
in its utmo<U+017F>t extremity; and <U+017F>ince al<U+017F>o
all Vipers, we get from thence, have their yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
liquor always very innocent, though high
colour'd. And I can truly <U+017F>ay, that tho<U+017F>e
Vipers, that have <U+017F>erv'd me mo<U+017F>t both in my
fir<U+017F>t and la<U+017F>t experiments, were mo<U+017F>t of them
<U+017F>ent me out of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and that I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98525:35"/>
to make u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>uch, as being commonly
bigger than mo<U+017F>t of tho<U+017F>e that were <U+017F>ent me
out of <hi>Poictou;</hi> that, at lea<U+017F>t, which <U+017F>erv'd
me to bite the five fir<U+017F>t Pigeons, which I <U+017F>pake
of in my fir<U+017F>t Experiments; and that which
bit the <U+017F>eaven la<U+017F>t Pullets and Pigeons, were
of tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and even of the bigger
<U+017F>ort that could be procured.</p>
                  <p>And it would have been to no purpo<U+017F>e to
have u<U+017F>ed any tooth of a Viper <U+017F>ever'd from
the head, and much le<U+017F>s to wipe it dry with
<U+017F>ome bread crums, in hopes it <U+017F>hould kill any
Animal by pricking it therewith; <U+017F>eeing the
teeth, that had of the yellow liquor upon
them, without being <U+017F>eparated from the dead
heads, were not able to do any harm, no not
tho<U+017F>e of live ones, without the concurrence of
the enraged <U+017F>pirits. And if <U+017F>ometimes I have
made u<U+017F>e of bread-crums, <U+017F>ometimes of a <U+017F>ine
linnen ragg, to wipe away all the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
of the ve<U+017F>icles, that was never but in
live Vipers; to <U+017F>hew, that it was not that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
which did kill, but the vexed Spirits
only, entring by means of the biting.</p>
                  <p>We are not to imagine neither, that a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
teareth by biting, unle<U+017F>s having made her
to thru<U+017F>t her teeth into the fle<U+017F>h of <U+017F>ome ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,
you do immediately after draw her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
by the re<U+017F>t of her body: We are not, I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98525:36"/>
<U+017F>ay, to pretend, that a Viper doth, by biting
of her own accord, make any great opening,
at which the yellow liquor is able to enter.
For, <U+017F>he doth no more but thru<U+017F>t in her teeth
far enough, and pre<U+017F>ently draw them out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
with as much ea<U+017F>e as a Cat draws out his
claws when he will. Be<U+017F>ides, you cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
but two very little holes, which do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o
<U+017F>eem as 'twere clo<U+017F>ed again by the fle<U+017F>h,
and which would hardly be di<U+017F>cern'd, if the
pain of the bite, or the accidents en<U+017F>uing, did
not oblige us to look very narrowly to it.</p>
                  <p>We al<U+017F>o never <U+017F>ee, that the poi<U+017F>on fa<U+017F>tens
it <U+017F>elf to the part bitten, nor that the evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
by a mortification, or by a gangrene
there. For, if that were <U+017F>o, and if the venom
did lodge at the entry, it would be much
more ea<U+017F>ie to ma<U+017F>ter it. I know al<U+017F>o by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Experiments, that the poi<U+017F>on never <U+017F>tays
at the place where it enters, but in<U+017F>inuates it
<U+017F>elf very nimbly into the Veines, to mingle
with the blood; e<U+017F>pecially if the bite hath
open'd for it a pa<U+017F><U+017F>age free enough to arrive
there. I know, that there it produces after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
tho<U+017F>e trouble<U+017F>ome accidents, which
en<U+017F>ue upon the biting; and that la<U+017F>tly it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eth
death, if it be not prevented by a quick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.
Which clearly <U+017F>hews, that a poi<U+017F>on of
this nature mu<U+017F>t needs have di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98525:36"/>
penetrate, very differing from tho<U+017F>e that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
in a yellow liquor, that is incapable of
all <U+017F>udden motion and operation.</p>
                  <p>It would al<U+017F>o prove an u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s labour, to
<U+017F>uck at the place of the biting, in hopes of
getting out from thence a Juyce, which could
not enter there. And though I do not di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
this way of <U+017F>uccours on <U+017F>uch occa<U+017F>ion;
yet I know, that all what the <U+017F>ucking can do,
is, to fetch out again part of the enraged <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
that had enter'd by the openings of the
bite. I know al<U+017F>o, that a <U+017F>pecifique reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
taken at the mouth, is far better.</p>
                  <p>I would be in vain, to object unto me the
example of the <U+017F>eed of Animals, which, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding
its vi<U+017F>co<U+017F>ity, <U+017F>erves daily to
propagate that <hi>Species</hi> which produces it;
and that it could in like manner come to pa<U+017F>s
in the yellow liquor to convey the venom in
the biting. For be<U+017F>ides that the <U+017F>eed is the
pure<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t elaborat part which an ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
can produce; it is al<U+017F>o accompanied
with <U+017F>tore of Spirits; and there needs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides,
the concurrence of many other means
as well to introduce and to receive it, as to
form and perfect the <hi>Foetus:</hi> There is more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary an a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of abundance of
<U+017F>pirits from the mothers <U+017F>ide; a juyce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate
and proper for its nouri<U+017F>hment and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98525:37"/>
increa<U+017F>e, and a <U+017F>ufficient time for the <U+017F>ame.
Whereas the yellow liquor, <hi>that</hi> can pa<U+017F>s for
nothing but a juyce excreted out of the Sali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
Glanduls, after it had been <U+017F>ent thither
from the brain and the neighbouring parts,
and <hi>that</hi> is de<U+017F>titute of <U+017F>pirits and of all di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ition
to act; wants al<U+017F>o a pa<U+017F><U+017F>age <U+017F>ufficient
to intromit it, and a place proper to lodge
in. And if you <U+017F>hould grant it an entry, and
a place to <U+017F>ojourn in; it mu<U+017F>t have a much
longer time than the <U+017F>eed, of which I was <U+017F>pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.
But with all this time and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
circum<U+017F>tances, it would <U+017F>till be incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of working any thing at all perfect, and
peri<U+017F>h of it <U+017F>elf; without any remarkable
production.</p>
                  <p>If any <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ay, That this yellow liquor
may have <U+017F>pirits proper and proportionate
to its nature, and that they are not wanting to
make the poi<U+017F>on work at the moment of the
biting; but that, being drawn out of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icles,
and expo<U+017F>ed to the Air, tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits are
di<U+017F><U+017F>ipated, and thereby render it incapable
of all action: I an<U+017F>wer, That, without <U+017F>taying
upon what I have amply made out of its inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
in all kind of u<U+017F>es, Signor <hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf
contradicts it, as I have mentioned above;
<U+017F>ince he pretends, that the Juyce even of <U+017F>uch
Vipers as have been dead for <U+017F>everal days, &amp;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98525:37"/>
that is dryed to boot, cea<U+017F>eth not to in<U+017F>inuate
its venom without any intervention of <U+017F>pirits,
when it is put into wounds. But, be<U+017F>ides all
that, many Experiments have evinced to me,
that death follows the biting without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention
of the yellow liquor, and then
when it hath been perfectly wiped away.
Moreover, it is well known, that 'tis the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of <U+017F>pirits, to be in motion, to fa<U+017F>ten them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves
to, and to follow the parts that have
mo<U+017F>t of them, as for example, the blood. It
is al<U+017F>o to be noted, that the <U+017F>pirits, that do
in<U+017F>inuate the poi<U+017F>on, are not of the nature of
tho<U+017F>e that follow the ordinary motion of the
blood of the animal; <hi>that</hi> they do not joyn
them<U+017F>elves to it, as tho<U+017F>e; and <hi>that</hi> neither of
them have any union with the yellow liquor;
which is but a meer excrement: But that the
<hi>Spirits,</hi> I <U+017F>peak of, do form them<U+017F>elves in the
moment that the Viper conceives the <hi>Idea</hi> of
revenging her <U+017F>elf; and they need not the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bara<U+017F>ment
of <U+017F>uch a dull and vi<U+017F>cous juyce,
which is not qualified to follow them, nor to
pa<U+017F>s through the imperceptible pores of the
teeth, which the <U+017F>pirits only can penetrate,
no more then they can any ways enter through
the holes, which the teeth have made. In a
word; the nature of a gro<U+017F>s, tough and vi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous
juyce is not, to act, penetrate, and be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98525:38"/>
wiftly carried to the mo<U+017F>t remote parts of the
body; but that belongs to <U+017F>pirituous <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances,
to go and come where gro<U+017F>s corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
ones cannot. The<U+017F>e are the only <U+017F>pirits,
that can <U+017F>ubvert the whole Oeconomy of the
body; they are they, that di<U+017F>turb the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of the blood, and that corrupt it; they
are they, that <U+017F>top the natural and animal <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
and hinder them from pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing to the
parts of the body as they were wont to do;
and la<U+017F>tly, 'tis by the let of them, that the
death of the Animal u<U+017F>ually en<U+017F>ueth the biting.</p>
                  <p>As to what may be objected, that 'tis very
difficult, <U+017F>o exactly to evacuate the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,
that there remain none at all; and that
it may very well come to pa<U+017F>s, that a little of
it intervenes in all bitings: I an<U+017F>wer, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides
that this is al<U+017F>o again<U+017F>t the opinion of
Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi> and which he hath renounced in
his fir<U+017F>t A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion; the Salival Glanduls,
though many in number, yet are too <U+017F>mall and
have too little capacity to contain juyce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to furni<U+017F>h for that purpo<U+017F>e; and that
that cannot be expected but from great ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals,
that have tho<U+017F>e Salival glanduls and the
other parts far bigger: And though it were
po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, they <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ufficiently furni<U+017F>h, I
do maintain, that the impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
that juyce, and its evinced innocence,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98525:38"/>
ought to <U+017F>uffice for confuting this Objection.</p>
                  <p>Yet this I <U+017F>hall here <U+017F>ay in favour of Sign.
<hi>Redi,</hi> That I doubt not but that this yellow
liquor, as Salivous and Excrementitious as it
is, contains its Volatil Salt, as well as all the
other parts of a Viper, and all the parts of
Animals, and even all their excrements, and
that con<U+017F>equently it is to be reputed <U+017F>piritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
But then, be<U+017F>ides that the<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirituous
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances are never hurtful, they are yet too
intimately mixed and locked in with their
matter, and they cannot produce their effects
without being <U+017F>eparated from it; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be but by a violent heat, and in ve<U+017F><U+017F>els fit
for it. I <U+017F>ay therefore, that by art there may
be extracted a true Volatil Salt out of this
yellow liquor, &amp; even without any addition
or mixture of other matter; which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
to be of the <U+017F>ame nature with that of the
other parts of a Viper; and that 'tis <U+017F>o far from
being able to work like poi<U+017F>on, that t'is very
proper and effectual to ma<U+017F>ter all the ill acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
which the bite of a Viper may cau<U+017F>e;
of which I do accu<U+017F>e the enraged <U+017F>pirits alone.
Since therefore Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath dried and
laid a<U+017F>ide the yellow liquor of two hundred
and fifty Vipers, and may ea<U+017F>ily obtain much
more of it; 'tis in his power to extract <U+017F>uch
a <U+017F>alt out of it, when he plea<U+017F>eth, to verifie
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98525:39"/>
what I was ju<U+017F>t now <U+017F>aying: And if, to <U+017F>ave
him<U+017F>elf that labour, by rea<U+017F>on of his other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
occupations, he <U+017F>hall plea<U+017F>e to <U+017F>end
me a competent quantity thereof, I do with
all my heart offer my <U+017F>elf to prepare it for
him, thereby to let him <U+017F>ee not only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence
of this juyce, but al<U+017F>o the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
that is hid in it.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Bilious Breath</hi> of a Viper,
that may be charged to intervene with this
yellow liquor, and to envenom it; I am of
opinion, that that is nothing but a di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e of
the enraged <U+017F>pirits. I a<U+017F><U+017F>ert, <hi>That</hi> the true
Breath of a Viper is ever innocent, how bili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<U+017F>oever it be repre<U+017F>ented; <hi>that</hi> there i<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ues
not any ill <U+017F>cent out of her throat, nor
out of her guts, nor from the parts made to
void the excrements; <hi>That</hi> Vipers among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
marks are in this different from Snakes,
that <hi>the<U+017F>e</hi> have their excrements and the parts
containing them very fetide and of a <U+017F>mell of
<U+017F>tinking Urine; whereas you cannot perceive
any ill <U+017F>mell in any part of a Viper; <hi>that</hi> the
Spirits which carry the venom are quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thing than the breath coming from the
Lungs; <hi>that</hi> tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits have no union nor
corre<U+017F>pondence with the Bilious humour;
<hi>that</hi> they are not formed but at the in<U+017F>tant of
the irritation; and la<U+017F>tly, <hi>that</hi> they need no
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98525:39"/>
<U+017F>uch thing as an excrementitious and u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s
liquor, pretended to intervene, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but to gard the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age of the place,
through which the vexed <U+017F>pirits have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
                  <p>But the better to <U+017F>hew the impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of
the intervention of this breath, and to make
it appear, that it never contributes any thing
to the poi<U+017F>on; you may take notice, that a
Vipers head cut off, <U+017F>eparate from the Lungs
and all communication with the Gall, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable
to yield any breath, and deprived
even of all that yellow liquor; yet failes
not to kill by its biting as long as 'tis alive,
if the animal have been provoked; ju<U+017F>t as
would come to pa<U+017F>s, if a bite were made by
the head of a Viper that is whole and alive,
if no remedy were applied.</p>
                  <p>Touching the Communication, that may
al<U+017F>o be pretended to be between the bladder
of Gall and the yellow liquor, by rea<U+017F>on of
<U+017F>ome re<U+017F>emblance of colour; I <U+017F>ay, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides
<hi>that</hi> my Sentiments in the<U+017F>e matters are
very conform to tho<U+017F>e of Sign. <hi>Redi; that</hi> we
have both of us ju<U+017F>tified the innocence of the
juyce contained in the Bladder of Gall; <hi>that</hi>
we have denied, there is any ve<U+017F><U+017F>el carrying
this better juyce into the ve<U+017F>icles of the gums,
to make that yellow liquor which is found
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98525:40"/>
there: and la<U+017F>tly, <hi>that</hi> we have unanimou<U+017F>ly
contradicted the errors of the Antients about
this pretended channel; be<U+017F>ides this; I <U+017F>ay,
the truth of what we have affirmed is very
ea<U+017F>ie to prove, by ta<U+017F>ting the yellow liquor of
the Gall, which is very bitter and very <U+017F>harp,
though very innocent, and by comparing it
with that of the ve<U+017F>icles of the Gums, which
is very flat, though equally innocent. The
<U+017F>ame may be yet better made out by di<U+017F><U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
one or more Vipers; where, no more
than in Serpents and all other animals, you
will never find any ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, that carries<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> this
bile of the Bladder of Gall to the Gums; and
you will there <U+017F>ee nothing but veins and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries
filled With true blood. Of this there
will be no doubt, if you plea<U+017F>e only to ta<U+017F>te
it; for you will find nothing but the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ta<U+017F>te of blood. To be yet more a<U+017F><U+017F>ur'd of
it, you may ta<U+017F>te all that runs out of the body
of a Viper when the head is <U+017F>ever'd from her;
for you <U+017F>hall find no bitterne<U+017F>s at all, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ta<U+017F>t but that of blood. And be<U+017F>ides, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
amply verified, that the yellow liquor
comes from the Salival glanduls alone, and
having given a very exact de<U+017F>cription of
them; I think it needle<U+017F>s to <U+017F>ay any more of
it, what ever the Antients may have written,
or the Moderns may <U+017F>ay of that <U+017F>ubject.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:98525:40"/>
To come now to the <hi>enraged Spirits</hi> of a
Viper, which I do a<U+017F><U+017F>ure to be the true and
only <U+017F>eat of the poi<U+017F>on; methinks Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
hath no rea<U+017F>on to oppo<U+017F>e my opinion, when
I do intere<U+017F>s in it the imagination of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
or her <hi>Idea</hi> of revenge, for the formation
of tho<U+017F>e Spirits. I might here alledge what
<hi>Van Helmont</hi> <U+017F>aith in his Chapt. <hi>De Tumul<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Pe<U+017F>tis,</hi> viz. That not only the <hi>Idea</hi> and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination
of terror are formed in the inward
<hi>Archeus</hi> of the per<U+017F>on invaded by the Plague;
but that the Toad, which hath, <hi>as he <U+017F>aith,</hi> a
perpetual hatred again<U+017F>t man, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
taken, and hanged by one of his hind-legs,
and in a condition of dying, conceives an
<hi>Idea</hi> and an imagination of terror by the
<U+017F>ight of the man, that often pre<U+017F>ents him<U+017F>elf
before his eyes, and whom he looks upon as
his capital enemy, and that the <U+017F>ame <hi>Idea</hi> or
the <U+017F>ame phancy of terror, which the Toad
hath conceived by this means, forms in him
<U+017F>uch impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions and qualities, as are perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
even after his death. Then this Author
will, that of this body, that dyed in tho<U+017F>e <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas</hi>
of terror, mingled with the parts that
have i<U+017F><U+017F>ued thence, and with the wax that
<U+017F>hall have received them, you <U+017F>hall make Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<U+017F>que's,
which being taken inwardly, and
carried about you, or applied, <U+017F>hall have the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98525:41"/>
virtue of curing as well as pre<U+017F>erving from
the Plague, by mortifying by their Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique
quality the terror which the inward <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi>
of the per<U+017F>on may have conceived of
this evil. Now <U+017F>ince this Sentiment of <hi>Van
Helmont</hi> hath found place in the minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
men, yery capable to judge of it; who
have been thence induced even to make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
that preparation of Toads, which he
hath taught in the <U+017F>ame <hi>Chapter,</hi> and which I
can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure I have my <U+017F>elf made to <U+017F>atisfie the
de<U+017F>ire of very able Phy<U+017F>itians; having al<U+017F>o
known many per<U+017F>ons giving great credit to
it, and carrying continually about them of
tho<U+017F>e Troche<U+017F>ques whil<U+017F>t there was talk of
the Plague; methinks, that the formation of
the enraged <U+017F>pirits, which I a<U+017F>cribe to the
<hi>Idea</hi> and imagination of revenge, conceived
by the Viper when <U+017F>he is vexed, is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
more maintainable, and much ea<U+017F>ier to
be comprehended, as well as the entry of the
angred Spirits through the Openings made
by the Teeth; becau<U+017F>e not only the<U+017F>e Aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
are wont to be deep, but al<U+017F>o becau<U+017F>e
the teeth being hollow, <U+017F>erve for a Funnel to
intromit tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits, that accompany the
biting, and that produce afterwards in the
body bitten tho<U+017F>e di<U+017F>mal effects of vengeance,
which the Viper had conceived when <U+017F>he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98525:41"/>
felt the ill done her; And the letting in of
tho<U+017F>e Spirits through the cavity of tho<U+017F>e
teeth is <U+017F>o much the more ea<U+017F>ie, becau<U+017F>e there
is al<U+017F>o at the end of each great tooth a hole,
which, though very <U+017F>mall and almo<U+017F>t undi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable
by the eye, may yet be di<U+017F>cerned by
a Micro<U+017F>cope, &amp; hath accordingly been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<U+017F>een in <U+017F>ome publick A<U+017F><U+017F>emblies at <hi>Paris,</hi>
in the pre<U+017F>ence even of per<U+017F>ons very affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate
to Sign. <hi>Redi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What <U+017F>hall we <U+017F>ay of the imagination of
Fright and Con<U+017F>traint, that a Toad al<U+017F>o im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>es
in a <hi>Wec<U+017F>el,</hi> which having <U+017F>een and
been <U+017F>een by that ugly animal, at a certain
<U+017F>ea<U+017F>on of the year, and always in <U+017F>ummer, can
not avoyd to run a pretty while round about
it making a continual <U+017F>hrill noy<U+017F>e, as if <U+017F>he cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for help, whil<U+017F>t the Toad remains move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s
with his throat open; and which after a
long trouble<U+017F>ome motion is con<U+017F>train'd to
come and render her <U+017F>elf into that throat.
The thing is too well known in divers places
of <hi>France</hi> to doubt of it; and I can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure to
have heretofore <U+017F>een it my <U+017F>elf; and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
I had well ob<U+017F>erv'd and withal wondred
at the force of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Idea's,</hi> appearing in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation
of the Wee<U+017F>el, and in her being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trained
to fall into the mouth of the Toad,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98525:42"/>
I had the <U+017F>atisfaction to kill the Toad in
that moment, and <U+017F>o to <U+017F>ave the Wee<U+017F>el,
which quickly run away, finding her <U+017F>elf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd
by the death of the animal, which was
followed by the extinction of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Ideas,</hi> that
before had had <U+017F>o much power over her. This
effect cannot be ad<U+017F>cribed to the foam, nor
to any material part of the Toad, <U+017F>ince the
Wee<U+017F>el flyes from him naturally, and falls not
into his mouth but in <U+017F>pight of her teeth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides
that the foam of the Toad, which the
Wee<U+017F>el failed not to meet with in his throat,
can work nothing, <U+017F>eeing the Wee<U+017F>el <U+017F>aved
her <U+017F>elf immediately after the death of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal.
We therefore mu<U+017F>t needs <U+017F>eek for
the cau<U+017F>e of all the<U+017F>e effects in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
                  <p>More-over, what will Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> <U+017F>ay of
a mad dog, which, in the pervertion of all
his <U+017F>en<U+017F>es and of all the ordinary functions
of his body, breaths after nothing but mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,
and makes it his bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s to reduce
into the <U+017F>ame mi<U+017F>erable condition all men
he <U+017F>ees, and even his own ma<U+017F>ter, as well as
all animals he can come near and bite? If
then the mad Dog hath the power to make
pa<U+017F>s the <U+017F>ame <hi>Idea's</hi> and the <U+017F>ame imagination,
which have <U+017F>eized on him, into all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98525:42"/>
that he can come to bite, and into man
him<U+017F>elf, though of a very different <U+017F>oul and
nature from his, by doing no more than with
the edge of his teeth to touch the <U+017F>uperfice of
the skin, and that through his coaths that
may retain and wipe off all the foam adhering
to the teeth, and lyable to be accu<U+017F>ed of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
a hand in the mi<U+017F>chief; as is very well
ob<U+017F>erv'd by <hi>Van Helmont</hi> in the <U+017F>ame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?
If, I <U+017F>ay, this dog hath the power of
communicating his evil to all <U+017F>orts of animals,
from one to another, without a limit, and
without excepting any kind; Why <U+017F>hould he
think it incredible, <hi>that</hi> a Viper is able by
her biting to carry her enraged <U+017F>pirits into
the bodies of <U+017F>uch men and other animals as
<U+017F>he can light upon; <hi>That</hi> the<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits are
capable to kill the animal bitten; and <hi>that</hi>
they effect this by the perturbation and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
they introduce into the whole ma<U+017F>s
of blood; fora<U+017F>much as they do manife<U+017F>tly
hinder its circulation, and the communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the natural <U+017F>pirits, that were wont to
be conveyed into all the parts? Con<U+017F>idering
withal, that they do not extend them<U+017F>elves as
far as tho<U+017F>e of the bite of a mad Dog; <U+017F>eeing
none of the Animals bitten by a Viper, have
any venom diffu<U+017F>ible either by their biting,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98525:43"/>
or otherwi<U+017F>e, as long as they live, and that
they may be <U+017F>afely handled, and even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
danger eaten after their death.</p>
                  <p>I <U+017F>ay be<U+017F>ides, that if it be true, that a man,
who hath at all times the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>pitle and the
<U+017F>ame teeth, &amp; who hath them not pointed nor
<U+017F>haped like tho<U+017F>e of a Viper, is capable to
introduce the Gangrene, and to cau<U+017F>e death
it <U+017F>elf by a bite made by him in a rage; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
another and longer bite, made by the <U+017F>ame
man not enraged, is not accompanied with
any ill accident, and is healed like a <U+017F>imple
wound; This being true, I <U+017F>ay, we ought to
think it neither <U+017F>trange nor impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, that
a Viper, which hath long and piercing teeth,
and which <U+017F>hews the force of her being vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the nimblene<U+017F>s of her biting, <U+017F>hould
be able, by biting when enraged, to make
animals feel the mortal effects of her vexed
<U+017F>pirits.</p>
                  <p>What <U+017F>hall we <U+017F>ay of the pricking of a <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantula</hi>
how <U+017F>light <U+017F>oever? <U+017F>hall we declare it
to be exempt from the <hi>idea</hi> and imagination
of this little animal, <U+017F>ince it impre<U+017F><U+017F>es it <U+017F>o
<U+017F>trongly and differently upon per<U+017F>ons that
have been pricked therewith, in<U+017F>omuch that
it perverts in part the <U+017F>en<U+017F>es and <U+017F>pirits,
conforms them to his <U+017F>tirring and skipping
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98525:43"/>
nature, and con<U+017F>trains them at certain and
<U+017F>et times to continual dancing for <U+017F>everal
days, and which having left a contumacious
leaven of the <U+017F>ame <hi>idea's,</hi> faileth not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
the <U+017F>ame effects every year, and, if you
may believe Authors, as long as the <hi>Tarantula</hi>
liveth, and until the <U+017F>ame <hi>idea's</hi> be extinct by
its death. And though I doubt not but
that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath <U+017F>een very many examples
of per<U+017F>ons pricked by <hi>Tarantula's,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<U+017F>tore of them in <hi>Italy;</hi> yet I <U+017F>hall not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
here to recite that of a <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
who hath been the<U+017F>e four years among
the <hi>French</hi> infantry. This Souldier, whom
his Camarads call'd <hi>Tarante,</hi> becau<U+017F>e he had
been pricked by a <hi>Tarantula,</hi> is <U+017F>till to this
very day in the Royal Regiment of <hi>Rou<U+017F><U+017F>illon.</hi>
He never failed to feel every year at a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
time <hi>(viz.</hi> about the 24<hi>th</hi> of <hi>July)</hi>
the effects of that <U+017F>ting, which he had receiv'd
before he came into <hi>France.</hi> He was always
<U+017F>ure of the time about two or three days near
it. And when the <hi>ideas</hi> of the <U+017F>ting were
found exalted to a degree capable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
their effects, he began to dance, and
de<U+017F>ired to hear without interruption the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,
which the Officers of that Regiment cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed
to be play'd for him out of charity; to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98525:44"/>
which he an<U+017F>wer'd continually, keeping time
very well, without being tired, for three
days, eating and drinking, without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his dance; and being very impatient
of any di<U+017F>continuance of the play of the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,
and that the more, if the intermi<U+017F><U+017F>ion
was any thing long; for then he became alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
livid, and fell into grievous <U+017F>wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.
He plea<U+017F>ed him<U+017F>elf whil<U+017F>t he danced,
to have in his hands <U+017F>everal naked <U+017F>words,
one after another; to <U+017F>ee about him many
Looking-gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, to behold him<U+017F>elf in them
dancing; to be environed with much people,
and, that he might hinder them from going
away, to take from them their Gloves, Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons,
and <U+017F>uch other things; being very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to keep all he had taken from them unto
the fourth day, which being come, his ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerne<U+017F>s
to dance abated, and at length quite
cea<U+017F>ed; he remembring all he had done, and
knowing all that were about him, to every
one of whom he rendred very exactly and
without any mi<U+017F>take all he had taken from
them, though he had to do with a thou<U+017F>and
people. After which time, he pa<U+017F>s'd the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder
of that year, and the whole interval
of his Paroxy<U+017F>ines without any inclination
to dance. He was naturally melancholick,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98525:44"/>
in appearance of no great parts, neither had
he learn'd to dance. He hath been <U+017F>een thus
dancing every year by thou<U+017F>ands of people,
and particularly in the Camp Royal <hi>Anno</hi>
1670. where the King him<U+017F>elf and the whole
Court <U+017F>aw him. And this hath been <U+017F>o be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial
to him, that the ordinary time is pa<U+017F>t
this year without any a<U+017F><U+017F>ault of this evil,
which he had great apprehen<U+017F>ions of, finding
him<U+017F>elf at that time engaged in a march,
and fearing he <U+017F>hould want Violins at the
time that the <U+017F>it <U+017F>hould take him.</p>
                  <p>Now <U+017F>ince the pricking of this Animal,
though very <U+017F>mall, and in a manner like that
of a <U+017F>mall fly, being made even thorough
<U+017F>tockings or cloaths, is able to act equally
upon the body and the mind of the per<U+017F>on
<U+017F>tung; as leaving behind <U+017F>uch long and
<U+017F>trong impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions, and cau<U+017F>ing <U+017F>uch irk<U+017F>ome
returns; To what can we ad<U+017F>cribe all tho<U+017F>e
different effects, if it be not to the <hi>idea</hi> or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination
of the animal <U+017F>tinging, or of the
per<U+017F>on <U+017F>tung. 'Tis needle<U+017F>s, to alledge
here the effects of the <hi>idea</hi> or imagination of
Women with Child, nor of that of <hi>Jacob's</hi>
Sheep. I think I have <U+017F>aid enough to ju<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
the po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of the <hi>idea</hi> or imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of a Vipers revengefulne<U+017F>s, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98525:45"/>
of angry <U+017F>pirits, <U+017F>ufficient to impute
unto them all the venom, and to exclude from
it the yellow liquor.</p>
                  <p>After this, Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> mu<U+017F>t not wonder,
if I, <hi>who</hi> make profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion of Chymi<U+017F>try, (of
which I have the honour to read publick Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures
in the Garden Royal) <hi>who</hi> doe every
day exerci<U+017F>e my <U+017F>elf in <U+017F>eparating the <U+017F>piri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
parts from the gro<U+017F>s ones in mixt ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimat
bodies; and <hi>who</hi> have not been able
to find in any corporeal and <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible matter
the true cau<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>trange and <U+017F>uddain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions,
ob<U+017F>erved in the biting of a live
Viper; If I, after all this, I <U+017F>ay, have thought
my <U+017F>elf obliged to <U+017F>eek for it in the <hi>Spirits;</hi>
if having found it there, I have abandon'd
his party, and communicated to the publick
the di<U+017F>covery I have made.</p>
                  <p>Yet I am not over-much <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed, that
Sign, <hi>Redi,</hi> being in this matter prepo<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd
by corporeal gro<U+017F>s things, <U+017F>till per<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in his
<U+017F>entiment, <U+017F>ince in the preparations, that do
altogether depend of my profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and
which I ought to know well, he rejects <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous
<U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances, which he reli<U+017F>hes not,
<U+017F>ticking only to the more material, which
are the lea<U+017F>t, and in very <U+017F>mall quantity;
which doth not keep him from believing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98525:45"/>
them to be the be<U+017F>t. You may <U+017F>ee, what he
writeth of it about the end of <hi>pag.</hi> 76.
and at the beginning of <hi>pag.</hi> 77, of his
fir<U+017F>t Letter of Ob<U+017F>ervations, in the<U+017F>e
words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In que<U+017F>te nuè naturali O<U+017F><U+017F>ervationi ho con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>uinato
gran quantitá, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi> In the<U+017F>e my
natural Ob<U+017F>ervations </hi>I<hi> have <U+017F>pent a great
quantity of Vipers, making of them daily a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
great <U+017F>laughter; and, to extract the <U+017F>ubtile
from the <U+017F>ubtil (if </hi>I<hi> may <U+017F>o <U+017F>peak) </hi>I<hi> always laid
a<U+017F>ide and kept all their fle<U+017F>h and bones, which
being dryed in a Furnace, and afterwards by a
quick fire with long and great labour burnt and
reduced to a<U+017F>hes, </hi>I<hi> thence drew the Salt with
Fountain-water, and purified it, and reduced
it into a kind of Chry<U+017F>tal, </hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Tho<U+017F>e that know all the parts of which
the body of a Viper is compo<U+017F>ed, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
wonder, that a per<U+017F>on <U+017F>o judicious
and knowing hath not found, that the chief
and be<U+017F>t part of a Viper con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in its vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
Salt, and that that Salt would not fail to
avolate and to be wa<U+017F>ted by that preparation
or rather de<U+017F>truction, which Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath
u<U+017F>ed to extract the Salt of Vipers. They will
quickly <U+017F>ee, that when he would draw the
<U+017F>ubtil from the <U+017F>ubtil (as he <U+017F>peaks) he did
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98525:46"/>
quite the contrary, and expelled and di<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated
the volatil and better parts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
only the gro<U+017F>s, the fixed and the lea<U+017F>t.
They will <U+017F>oon judg, that he <U+017F>hould not have
given him<U+017F>elf all that labour and pain, which
he <U+017F>aith he hath taken, to <U+017F>ucceed <U+017F>o ill in his
work; and that he had done much better,
with <U+017F>ilence to pa<U+017F>s over his proce<U+017F>s, then to
publi<U+017F>h it. The way, by him taken, will
be found, I think, received from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,
who knew not, that all Animals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
in <hi>Volatil,</hi> and have little of <hi>Fixed</hi>
Salt: And his preparation, which is very
ea<U+017F>ie, would have plea<U+017F>ed better in tho<U+017F>e
times, e<U+017F>pecially in <hi>Italy,</hi> then that great and
laborious Preparation of the Salt of Vipers,
which was made with <U+017F>o great an <hi>Apparatus,</hi>
and of which I have already given my
thoughts, when I di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>ed of the Remedies
drawn from Vipers.</p>
                  <p>I al<U+017F>o fore<U+017F>ee, that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
any greater advantage by <U+017F>triving to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
to him<U+017F>elf the fir<U+017F>t di<U+017F>covery of the
<hi>Salival glanduls,</hi> which I found on both the
Temples of both Male and Female Vipers,
and which I have de<U+017F>cribed and delineated
in my Anatomy of Vipers: For, he will not
be able to per<U+017F>wade it to tho<U+017F>e, who <U+017F>hall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98525:46"/>
<U+017F>ee <hi>pag.</hi> 44. of his fir<U+017F>t Letter of Ob<U+017F>ervations
the di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e following;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Se non <U+017F>tima<U+017F><U+017F>i vergogna <U+017F>criver <U+017F>enza al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
riprova, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi> If I did not think
it a <U+017F>hame, to write, without other proof, what
came into my phancy, I might <U+017F>ay perhaps, that
that yellow liquor is by no other way intromit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into the above <U+017F>aid gums of the teeth but by
tho<U+017F>e </hi>Salival Conduits,<hi> found out by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi>Thomas Wharton,<hi> and <U+017F>hewn in this
Court by </hi>Lorenzo Billini,<hi> a learned young man
and of great expectation, in other Animals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides
Man, and particularly in Staggs, and
Wood-peckers: Moreover that under tho<U+017F>e
Gums there are two <U+017F>mall Glanduls, found by
me in all Vipers. Yet I would not have you
rely upon this thought of mine, becau<U+017F>e it may
prove a Chimera, as I believe it to be one,</hi>&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I cannot comprehend, how Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
after he hath <U+017F>poken of the <hi>Salival Conduits</hi>
as of a thing that came into his phancy, and
by a <hi>perhaps,</hi> that is to <U+017F>ay, not knowing it;
and who declareth, that he was a<U+017F>ham'd to
write of a thing without verifying it; who
exhorts his friend to whom he writes, not to
relye on his thoughts, and who adds, that it
may prove a Chimera; I know not, I <U+017F>ay,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98525:47"/>
how, after he hath written all this, he can
pretend to be the inventor of the <hi>Salival
Glanduls,</hi> and their Pipes: For <hi>pag.</hi> 55 and
56. of his fir<U+017F>t Letter <U+017F>peaking of the yellow
liquor, he adds,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>E que<U+017F>to veleno altro non è, &amp;c. </hi>That is,<hi>This venom is nothing el<U+017F>e but that liquor, which
humects the Palat, and <U+017F>tagnates in tho<U+017F>e gums
that inve<U+017F>t the teeth, not transmitted thither
from the Bladder of Gall, but bred in the
whole head, and conveyed </hi>perhaps<hi> to the
gums by <U+017F>ome Salival conduits, which </hi>perhaps<hi>are there in<U+017F>erted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where the word <hi>perhaps,</hi> yet twice again
repeated, doth <U+017F>ufficiently <U+017F>hew, that Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> did <U+017F>peak of the <hi>Salival conduits</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwi<U+017F>e
than as of a thing he was not at all
a<U+017F><U+017F>ured of. And though he may <U+017F>ay, <hi>that</hi> he
hath had thoughts of it <U+017F>ooner than I, (who
have not medled with Vipers but <U+017F>ome years
after his fir<U+017F>t Letter,) <hi>that</hi> what he had
written of it gave me from that time occa<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and a de<U+017F>ire to <U+017F>eek for tho<U+017F>e Pipes and
the Glanduls that might convey thither the
yellow liquor; <hi>that</hi> the belief, he had of the
Generation of this juyce in the whole head,
induced me to <U+017F>earch for the Salival Glanduls
higher and farther off than the place <hi>under</hi> the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98525:47"/>
bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles; and <hi>that</hi> I doubt
not, that him<U+017F>elf might have found the<U+017F>e
true Glanduls, if he would have taken pains
for it. I an<U+017F>wer, that, <U+017F>ince he hath <hi>not</hi> done
it, he ought not to be offended at my having
labour'd for him, and <U+017F>ucceeded in <U+017F>o doing:
Neither hath he any right to deny, that I
have fir<U+017F>t found, de<U+017F>cribed, and to the life
repre<U+017F>ented the two heaps of Salival Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duls
of a Viper with all their Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, as well
for forming, as conveying the yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
into the Ve<U+017F>icles that cover the great
teeth.</p>
                  <p>As to what Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> <U+017F>aith of me, <U+017F>peak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Authors of my Book, that I have
changed the words, <hi>under the bottom,</hi> into
tho<U+017F>e, <hi>at the bottom</hi> of the ve<U+017F>icles of the gums,
and there <U+017F>ought in vain for the two <U+017F>mall
Glanduls, which he a<U+017F><U+017F>ures to have found
there in all Vipers: I an<U+017F>wer, that whil<U+017F>t he
is critical as to the letter of the words, <hi>I</hi>
keep to the truth of the matter of fact: And I
can a<U+017F><U+017F>ure, to have <U+017F>earched with much care,
not only <hi>in</hi> the whole bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles,
but every where <hi>under</hi> the bottom of them,
but have not found any, whether great or
<U+017F>mall Glanduls, nor any thing of the colour
of a Glandul, nor that came any way near to
their form.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98525:48"/>
I put it then for a truth, that there is not
to be found any Glandul neither <hi>in</hi> nor <hi>under</hi>
the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles, and that <hi>under</hi> the
bottom there is nothing but <hi>the</hi> gri<U+017F>tly bone
that gives the <U+017F>hape to the no<U+017F>e of a Viper;
<hi>the</hi> two <U+017F>harp ends of the two advanced
bones of the skull, to which the two great
teeth are firmly annexed; <hi>the</hi> conduit of the
<U+017F>mell, <hi>that</hi> of the hearing; <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall vein,
<U+017F>ome little Artery, <U+017F>ome little Nerve, the
extremity of a Mu<U+017F>cle, and the two ends of
the Salival Channels that di<U+017F>charge into the
ve<U+017F>icles; as you may <U+017F>ee it in a manner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribed
in the Anatomy made of it by
me.</p>
                  <p>After this, Signor <hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>hews,
that it was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, there <U+017F>hould be Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duls
<hi>under</hi> the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles, <U+017F>ince he
<U+017F>aith, <hi>pag.</hi> 38. of his la<U+017F>t Letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ne io poteva mai <U+017F>crivere, &amp;c. </hi>that is,<hi> Nor
could I at all write, that tho<U+017F>e Glanduls lay in
the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles, if I was of opinion,
that the yellow liquor did run into them after it
had pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed through the Salival conduits, which
yet I imagined might have their Origin from or
connexion with tho<U+017F>e two Glanduls <U+017F>een by me,
and therefore mu<U+017F>t needs be in a <U+017F>cituation a
little di<U+017F>tant from the ve<U+017F>icles, and not in the
bottom of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98525:48"/>
For <U+017F>ince he <U+017F>aith, to have meant, that the
yellow juyce took its cour<U+017F>e thorough the
Salival conduits before its coming into the
ve<U+017F>icles; He cannot find a way long enough,
nor a di<U+017F>tance great enough, for the need of
long conduits, from the place <hi>under</hi> the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
unto that which is in the bottom of the
ve<U+017F>icles: For, there would have needed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but a little opening in the <U+017F>ame bottom,
to receive the juyce i<U+017F><U+017F>uing out of the two
little Glanduls he hath <U+017F>poken of. And he
<U+017F>hews <U+017F>ufficiently, that he cannot maintain
tho<U+017F>e two <U+017F>mall Glanduls <hi>under</hi> the bottom,
where he would have them to be, <U+017F>ince now he
will needs have them a little di<U+017F>tant from the
ve<U+017F>icles, that he may find, in the intervall, a
<U+017F>pace <U+017F>ufficient for the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that are nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ary
to the cour<U+017F>e of this yellow liquor. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides,
that it is altogether impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for two
<U+017F>mall Glanduls to furni<U+017F>h all that yellow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,
which pre<U+017F>ents it <U+017F>elf in the ve<U+017F>icles;
<U+017F>ince the two great heaps by me found in the
two Temples and behind the Orbits of the
eyes of a Viper, can hardly furni<U+017F>h each a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
a drop in the <U+017F>pace of 24 hours, after
the ve<U+017F>icles have been well voided. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
it is very ea<U+017F>ie to judge by what <hi>Sign.
Redi</hi> <U+017F>aith in his Fir<U+017F>t Letter, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tood
not, the Salival Glands were <U+017F>eated, as
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98525:49"/>
they are, on the two Temples, nor <U+017F>o near the
skull; <U+017F>ince he <U+017F>aith, that what came into his
phancy, was, that the head of a Viper did not
convey that yellow juyce but by certain <U+017F>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
conduits. For if he had been of another
mind, he would not have <U+017F>poken but of glands;
or, at lea<U+017F>t, he would have begun with them
before he had <U+017F>poken of the conduits, which
<U+017F>hews al<U+017F>o <U+017F>ufficiently, that by this means he
hath as 'twere inverted the order of nature:
For, in<U+017F>tead of placing the Glands clo<U+017F>e to
the skul, and afterwards the <U+017F>alival conduits;
he hath begun with the<U+017F>e, and would have
them immediately to receive the juyce of the
Brain, and to carry them to the ve<U+017F>icles of the
gums; and that his two pretended glanduls
are <U+017F>eated between the extremity of the<U+017F>e
conduits, and the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles;
though none be there, and it would be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s, they <U+017F>hould be there, becau<U+017F>e
there are none but they that can at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<U+017F>uck &amp; dige<U+017F>t the humidities of the brain
and the neighbouring parts, and <U+017F>end them
into the ve<U+017F>icles of the gums by the conduits
appointed for this office.</p>
                  <p>But when Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> accu<U+017F>es me of having
taken the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles for that
which is <hi>under</hi> the bottom of them, and of
not having rightly under<U+017F>tood, as he <U+017F>peaks,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98525:49"/>
the <hi>To<U+017F>can</hi> tongue; I may <U+017F>ay, that him<U+017F>elf
hath not very well apprehended, nor duly
explained the <hi>French</hi> terms, u<U+017F>ed by me;
<U+017F>ince he <U+017F>aith at the end of <hi>pag.</hi> 35. and at the
beginning of <hi>p.</hi> 36. of the <U+017F>ame la<U+017F>t letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sovra de chi gli, Autori delle novelle experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
affermano,</hi> &amp;c. That is, Whereupon the
Authors of the New Experiments do affirm,
that they could never <U+017F>ee <U+017F>uch Glanduls as I
had named; but that in<U+017F>tead of them they had
found two others, which they call Salival,
thus by them de<U+017F>cribed, <hi>p.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <p>For neither in all that he hath afterwards
taken the pains to tran<U+017F>cribe out of my book
on that <U+017F>ubject, nor in all the re<U+017F>t of my <hi>Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
upon the Salival Glanduls, he can have
read; that I <U+017F>ay to have found <hi>two Glanduls,</hi>
but, <hi>Glanduls;</hi> there being a great difference
in good French, between <hi>Deux Glandes,</hi> and
<hi>Des Glandes, two Glands,</hi> and, <hi>Glands.</hi> And
when, de<U+017F>cribing the Glanduls, I <U+017F>ay, that
they are <U+017F>eated on the two <U+017F>ides of the <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuns,</hi>
I <U+017F>ay afterwards, that there are many
<U+017F>mall ones joyned together, which may be
call'd <hi>Conglomerate Glanduls.</hi> And yet more;
I <U+017F>peak of an <hi>Heap of Glanduls;</hi> <U+017F>o far am I
from <U+017F>peaking only of one or two Glanduls, as
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath repre<U+017F>ented me to have done.</p>
                  <p>And <U+017F>ince, in hopes of better maintaining
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98525:50"/>
his cau<U+017F>e, he hath given him<U+017F>elf the trouble
of copying word for word, in his la<U+017F>t Letter,
only the mo<U+017F>t general place of my Book, and
that which was the lea<U+017F>t contrary to it, in my
<hi>Section</hi> of the Salival Glands. To <U+017F>hew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
on my part, that the Glands, found by
me, are very different, and that even they are
quite another thing, than the two <U+017F>mall ones
<U+017F>poken of by him; I thought my <U+017F>elf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
to tran<U+017F>cribe hither out of my book
what he thought not nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for him. For
in the <U+017F>ame <hi>Section, p.</hi> 30. (in the Engli<U+017F>h ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion,
<hi>p.</hi> 33) I <U+017F>peak thus of the <U+017F>alival Glands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The<U+017F>e Glands are found in all the heads of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
both Males and Females; they are <U+017F>eated
on both <U+017F>ides, and joining to the skull, in the
hind-part of each round of the eyes, and at the
<U+017F>ame height with them. There are many <U+017F>mall
ones joined together, which may be call'd </hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glomerate
Glands,<hi> that are ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
by their form and colour, which is different
from the Mu<U+017F>cles, neighbouring to them, and of
which there is one, that may be call'd </hi>Temporal,<hi>which in part covers them by its extremity.
This heap of Glands appears there of the bigne<U+017F>s
of the neighbouring eye, and extending it <U+017F>elf
in length, continues its progre<U+017F>s in the Orbite
of the eye, below and in part behind the eye.
Each Gland hath its little Lymphatique ve<U+017F><U+017F>el,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98525:50"/>
which parts from it as from a little Teat, and
goes di<U+017F>gorging it <U+017F>elf into a greater ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, that
runs all along and under the<U+017F>e Glands, and pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eth
into the Ve<U+017F>icle of the Gum, and terminates
in the mid<U+017F>t of the Articulation, which the root
of the great teeth makes with the advancing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of the <U+017F>aid Orbite, and with the little Bone,
which by its other end is articulated in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
of the upper jaw. This principal ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, which
being con<U+017F>ider'd alone, is very little in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
but is not <U+017F>o in effect, <U+017F>eeing it receives the
di<U+017F>charge of all the <U+017F>mall ve<U+017F><U+017F>els that come from
each Gland, empties it <U+017F>elf into the bag of the
gums, and carries thither that </hi>Salival<hi> juyce,
which may have qualities approaching to tho<U+017F>e
of the </hi>Saliva<hi> or Spitle of man, or of the foam or
drivel of divers other Animals.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Nerve, which <U+017F>erves in the No<U+017F>trils
to the faculty of </hi>Hearing,<hi> runs for <U+017F>ome
<U+017F>pace along the<U+017F>e Glands, which are al<U+017F>o, as
I have already <U+017F>aid, <U+017F>mall Veins and Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But having well con<U+017F>ider'd the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
&amp; <U+017F>cituation of the<U+017F>e </hi>Glands,<hi> we judged their
formation not to be in vain; but that their
U<U+017F>e, in all likelyhood, was, to receive the
humidities both of the Brain, the Eyes, and
the neighbouring parts; and that their di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
was very convenient, and even very
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98525:51"/>
nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to the parts, which receive that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor;
as well for moi<U+017F>tening the ligaments
of the great teeth, and to keep them in a
condition of bending at <U+017F>uch time when the
Viper will bite, as for bedewing and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing
the teeth, which Nature hath formed and
<U+017F>et in the mid<U+017F>t of this Juice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the re<U+017F>t, examining and ta<U+017F>ting the
Glands as well as the Juice, we found a
ta<U+017F>te altogether like that of the Gums, which
Sign. </hi>Redi<hi> hath de<U+017F>cribed; namely, very
near the ta<U+017F>te of the Oyle of Almonds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
all bitterne<U+017F>s, though it leave, a while
after, a little acrimony in the mouth, <U+017F>uch
as may be di<U+017F>cern'd in all kind of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could add here, what I <U+017F>aid of the
Salival Glands of <hi>Snakes,</hi> their difference
from tho<U+017F>e of Vipers; and I could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that I believe my <U+017F>elf to be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e
the fir<U+017F>t Di<U+017F>coverer of them. But
becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>o prolix a Citation might prove
tedious, and that tho<U+017F>e that de<U+017F>ire to have
more light therein, may ea<U+017F>ily find the re<U+017F>t
in the above-cited <hi>Section</hi> of my Book, I
<U+017F>hall not tran<U+017F>cribe it hither.</p>
                  <p>Mean time 'tis very ea<U+017F>ie to judge from
my whole Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, and from the exact
De<U+017F>cription, made by me, of the<U+017F>e <hi>Glands,</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98525:51"/>
and their neighbouring parts, that they
were not known to me by <hi>Phancy.</hi> Their
<U+017F>cituation very di<U+017F>tant from that place
<hi>under,</hi> and even from the <U+017F>ides of, the
<hi>bottom</hi> of the ve<U+017F>icles of the gums, <U+017F>hews
<U+017F>ufficiently, that they are neither <hi>in</hi> nor
<hi>under</hi> the bottom of tho<U+017F>e ve<U+017F>icles, as Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> hath pretended; and their great
number makes it appear, that 'tis quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
thing, than the two litle Glanduls
he <U+017F>peaks of, and which are not to be found
neither.</p>
                  <p>I intreat the Reader, well to con<U+017F>ider
tho<U+017F>e I have di<U+017F>cover'd, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F>ented
in my <hi>third Cutt,</hi> as well in that
part where the Temples are of a Head cut,
mark'd C, (where their <U+017F>hape and <U+017F>citua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is repre<U+017F>ented to the life, as they
<U+017F>hew them<U+017F>elves before they are <U+017F>ever'd;)
as in the inclo<U+017F>ure of a Vipers <U+017F>celeton,
which is there al<U+017F>o exhibited; where he
may <U+017F>ee them in their upper and lower
appearance, drawn out of the Head, and
by their ligaments fa<U+017F>tned to the hind-part
of the Eyes, and to the body of the Brain.
I came not to the full knowledge of them
till after much pains, and a very long and
particular <U+017F>earch. I did not content my
<U+017F>elf to <U+017F>eek a great while in the bottom,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98525:52"/>
and under the bottom of the ve<U+017F>icles of
the gums; but, to find the<U+017F>e Glands, I have
flead and di<U+017F><U+017F>ected a great number of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
heads, as dextrou<U+017F>ly and nicely as I
could; and I have u<U+017F>ed all means well to
examine them; among others, I cau<U+017F>ed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
heads to be gently boyled in a little
water, <hi>as well</hi> to con<U+017F>ider the divers <U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
of the skull, and to <U+017F>eparate all the
parts from it; <hi>as</hi> to remark well the form
and the connexion of the<U+017F>e Glands, to draw
them out whole, and joined, as they are,
to the Eyes, and to divers bodies of the
Brain, to which the marrow of the Spaine
is annex'd; and to have all the<U+017F>e parts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,
and <U+017F>uch as I have cau<U+017F>ed them to be
engraven.</p>
                  <p>Me thinks, that all the<U+017F>e cares, follow'd
by <U+017F>o good <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, may well de<U+017F>erve, my
Di<U+017F>covery of this great number of Salival
Glands with all their ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, <U+017F>hould not
be envied me by Sign. <hi>Redi;</hi> con<U+017F>idering
I do <U+017F>ufficiently appear to him incapable of
envying him any of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ine things, he
hath already found, or may find hereafter in
his curious re-<U+017F>earches.</p>
                  <p>There remains no more for me to do, me
thinks, than to <U+017F>atisfie Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> as well
concerning the Uncertainty, wherein he is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98525:52"/>
touching the Power of the Volatil Salt of
Vipers for the curing of their bitings; as
about the Objections, by him made again<U+017F>t
my Experiments of the Head and Neck of
a Viper, for curing Doggs bitten by it, and
which I have al<U+017F>o thought <U+017F>hould be effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
to cure men in the like ca<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>He oppo<U+017F>es nothing to the Vertue of this
Volatil Salt, but that he remits the Reader
to the time he will take, Chymically to
prepare this Salt, and to make the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment
therewith. But he <U+017F>aith, that he
hath made many tryals with the Heads and
Necks of Vipers, and found fir<U+017F>t; That,
having made two great Doggs aforehand to
<U+017F>wallow, each the head and neck of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and, afterwards cau<U+017F>ed both of them
to be bitten by other Vipers, tho<U+017F>e Doggs
dyed not: And that, having cau<U+017F>ed to be
bitten two other Doggs of the <U+017F>ame big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s,
that had eaten neither head nor neck
of a Viper, they dyed neither. He <U+017F>aith
further, that having made a Pullet to <U+017F>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
one head of a Viper, and a Capon two,
and cau<U+017F>ed them to be bitten, they both dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<U+017F>oon after. He adds, <hi>that</hi> having the
next day made ready <U+017F>ome heads of Vipers,
he cau<U+017F>ed them to be forc'd down the throat
of two little Doggs, of which he cau<U+017F>ed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98525:53"/>
the lea<U+017F>t to be bitten in the legg near the
<hi>anus,</hi> and the other, in the tongue, and
that they both dyed; <hi>That</hi> he made the
<U+017F>ame Experiment upon eight Pullets, two
Kitlings, two <U+017F>mall Rabbets, and <U+017F>ix Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
even with rubbing the place bitten
with the blood of the Viper; <hi>That</hi> al<U+017F>o
the <U+017F>ix Pigeons were bitten by the heads of
Vipers, dead <U+017F>everal dayes before, and that
all the<U+017F>e animals dyed; <hi>That</hi> la<U+017F>tly, he had
fed two Pigeons for there dayes with the
fle<U+017F>h and broath of Vipers, and being bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
thereupon, they dyed likewi<U+017F>e, this aid
notwith<U+017F>tanding.</p>
                  <p>For An<U+017F>wer to all the<U+017F>e Experiments, I
make u<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>ame <hi>Generals,</hi> that Sign.
<hi>Redi</hi> hath done again<U+017F>t mine, which are to
be found <hi>pag.</hi> 16. of his la<U+017F>t Letter; where
he <U+017F>aith: <hi>That</hi> a Viper more ea<U+017F>ily kills le<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>er
Animals by his biting, than great ones;
that, according to the bigne<U+017F>s of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
bitten, and according as the place
wounded is more or le<U+017F>s provided with
veins or arteries; that, if from the wound
of a Viper much blood i<U+017F><U+017F>ueth, the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
not only dyeth not, but does not <U+017F>o
much as feel any great inconvenience; that
it al<U+017F>o falls out <U+017F>ometimes, that the Animal
bitten e<U+017F>capeth, after it hath endured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98525:53"/>
mortal <U+017F>ymptoms; and that this may
come to pa<U+017F>s by the <U+017F>ole a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of Nature.</p>
                  <p>As to the two other <hi>Generals,</hi> which he
alledgeth in reference to the letting in of the
yellow liquor; I did not think fit to alledge
them here, <hi>both</hi> becau<U+017F>e I agree not as to the
po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of the fact, <hi>and</hi> that I have el<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
declared my <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ufficiently about it;
as al<U+017F>o that they make not to this purpo<U+017F>e.
But I think it more material, to add here
two other <hi>Generals</hi> to tho<U+017F>e of Sign. <hi>Redi,</hi>
and to <U+017F>ay: That the biting is more or le<U+017F>s
noxious, not only according to the place
bitten, but according to the degree of the
Vipers being vexed when <U+017F>he is to bite, and
according as her teeth have more or le<U+017F>s pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated.
And rea<U+017F>oning particularly upon
the<U+017F>e experiments, I <U+017F>ay, <hi>that</hi> the dogs which
I had cau<U+017F>ed to be bitten every one thrice, &amp;
were cured by making each of them <U+017F>wallow
the head and neck of a Viper, were of a very
midling <U+017F>ize, <hi>that</hi> it is very difficult to found
a certainjudgment upon the great ones, which
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath u<U+017F>ed, as 'tis al<U+017F>o, to pa<U+017F>s it
upon them that had <U+017F>wallow'd the head and
neck of a Viper, and tho<U+017F>e, that had not done
<U+017F>o, <hi>that</hi> all the other little animals, which he
employed, as well the Pullet and the Capon,
as the Pigeons, Catlings, Puppies, and little
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98525:54"/>
Rabbets, had not of them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>trength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t for a time the enraged <U+017F>pirits,
nor to find the effect of the remedy; e<U+017F>pecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
that which was bitten in the tongue. For, I
firmly believe, that there is no animal, great
or <U+017F>mal, which being fiercely bit in the tongue
by a Viper well vexed, can avoid death, what
aid <U+017F>oever you mini<U+017F>ter to it, becau<U+017F>e of the
nerves, veins &amp; arteries, di<U+017F><U+017F>eminated through
the tongue; and becau<U+017F>e that the angred <U+017F>pirits
finding a free entrance, produce there all the
effect they are capable of, with <U+017F>o much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
and nimblene<U+017F>s, that nothing is able to
<U+017F>top them. But in all curable bites I <U+017F>hall not
ea<U+017F>ily be induced to renounce the help, which
may be given by the head, neck, heart, liver,
and divers other parts of a Viper (e<U+017F>pecially
of her that made the bite) for the cure of the
animals that have <U+017F>ufficient <U+017F>trength to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t a
while, and to expect the benefit of this kind
of remedy. I believe al<U+017F>o to have great cau<U+017F>e
not to exclude from it man him<U+017F>elf; as al<U+017F>o to
prefer the parts of the <U+017F>ame Viper that hath
bitten, to tho<U+017F>e of others; becau<U+017F>e they mu<U+017F>t
needs have greater cognation and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent
with the vexed <U+017F>pirits, that i<U+017F><U+017F>ued from
her. Concerning which I think it not ami<U+017F>s, to
impart to the publick an accident that hapn'd
in the Royal Laboratory of this City, whil<U+017F>t
my la<U+017F>t experiments were making.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:98525:54"/>
A young man that had made a good progre<U+017F>s
in his <U+017F>tudies, de<U+017F>irous to perfect him<U+017F>elf in
both ways of Pharmacy, and chiefly addicted
to my cour<U+017F>e of Chymi<U+017F>try, was near me, in
the mid<U+017F>t of a great A<U+017F><U+017F>embly, on the 2<hi>d</hi> day of
my experiments. After I had made <U+017F>ome, whil<U+017F>t
I was entertaining the company, the fancy
took him, in imitation of me, yet without my
knowledge, to take a Viper with his hand, and
to <U+017F>eize on her head: which he did not with
that caution that is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, as not holding
her <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t but that the Viper took her oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity,
and <U+017F>truck one of her great teeth very
deep into the middle of the upper part of his
left fore-finger. Having been made acquainted
therewith, I remov'd, as much as I could, all
fear from his <U+017F>pirit, and advi<U+017F>ed him to betake
him<U+017F>elf to the nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary remedies. The credit
he gave to the truths contain'd in my book, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
read by him, induced him to <U+017F>ay, that if I
thought well of it, he would eat the head and
neck of the Viper that had bit him. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending
his courage, I <U+017F>econded his good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations;
for, I cau<U+017F>ed <U+017F>lightly to be broil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on coals the head and neck of the <U+017F>aid vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and made him eat and <U+017F>wallow it hot, in
the mid<U+017F>t of the company, adding to it the
heart and liver broiled likewi<U+017F>e. After which
I <U+017F>aid, I doubted not but what he had done
would be <U+017F>ufficient to cure him; yet to be the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98525:55"/>
<U+017F>urer, I would give him <U+017F>ome volatil <U+017F>alt of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
e<U+017F>pecially he being a per<U+017F>on whom I did
much e<U+017F>teem, and for who<U+017F>e health I had and
ever <U+017F>hould haue a great concern. I thereupon
immediately gave him a do<U+017F>e a fifty grains of
this volatil <U+017F>alt, di<U+017F><U+017F>olved in four ounces of
water, and a<U+017F><U+017F>ured him there was not any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
after this. The young man remained in the
mid<U+017F>t of the company, &amp; <U+017F>tirr'd not from the
place, till the meeting ended, and then he took
a little fre<U+017F>h air. He was afterwards a couple
of hours in the Royal Garden and the Labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;
during which time he now &amp; then found
<U+017F>ome little <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s about his heart; but being
come to his own lodging, he was ready to <U+017F>up
as he was u<U+017F>ed to do, and would have done it,
if I had not thought it better for him to take
another do<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>ame volatil <U+017F>alt, which had
<U+017F>o good effect, that the next day, after he had
dined well, he came again to our meeting;
which did much <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>e all tho<U+017F>e that had
been witne<U+017F><U+017F>es of the bite. Since that time he
hath ever been very well. Now though his
wound appear'd much deeper then that of the
German gentleman, that was bitten the 1<hi><U+017F>t</hi> day
of my former experiments; yet had he none
of tho<U+017F>e grievous accidents, that befell <hi>him,</hi> &amp;
were by me de<U+017F>cribed in my book: for he had
no other pain but that of the hole of the bite,
nor had he <U+017F>o much as a Fever. The wound
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98525:55"/>
only rendred <U+017F>ome drops of blood, by means
of the ligature, I caus'd to be made on the top
of his wounded finger, which did never <U+017F>well,
and heal'd up as if it had been made by the
prick of a pin, without any Cicatrice appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<U+017F>o far was it from a Gangrene, or Scar, as
<U+017F>ome fancied he would have.</p>
                  <p>The thing hath been too publick, not to be
credited every where; and I think not, that
Sign, <hi>Redi</hi> him<U+017F>elf will doubt of it; but rather
that all things have concurr'd together to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
all I had advanced in my book, of which
he hath conte<U+017F>ted <U+017F>ome particulars, and could
not re<U+017F>olve him<U+017F>elf about others. However,
if he have by him any remedies, more quick
and more <U+017F>ure for the cure of the bites of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
the publick will be much oblig'd to him
when he <U+017F>hall plea<U+017F>e to impart them, as I very
willingly communicate the<U+017F>e I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.
I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>peak here of divers Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
lately made upon Vipers by very
able per<U+017F>ons at <hi>Paris,</hi> which confirm not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the perfect innocence of the jellow liquor
that is in the ve<U+017F>icles of the Gums, but which
warrant at the <U+017F>ame time my ad<U+017F>cribing the
venom to the enraged <U+017F>pirits. The<U+017F>e truths
will be better received from their hands, and
they will be much more advantagious to me,
than if I did attempt to publi<U+017F>h them now.
For doubtle<U+017F>s there will be found in them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98525:56"/>
curious things, and they are like to be of
more importance than what I might be able
to <U+017F>ay of them. Be<U+017F>ides that I am far from u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urping
the honor due to others, and from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing
to me the obligation, which the
publick will owe them for it.</p>
                  <p>For a conclu<U+017F>ion of this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e; <hi><U+017F>ince</hi>
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> hath not found in the whole body
of a Viper any other part but the jellow juice
to which he can a<U+017F><U+017F>ign its venom; <hi><U+017F>ince on my
part</hi> by the new experiments, he hath de<U+017F>ir'd
of me, I have <U+017F>ufficiently ju<U+017F>tified the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
of the jellow liquor in the Vipers of
<hi>France,</hi> and the great conformities, there mu<U+017F>t
needs be in the <U+017F>ame with that of the Vipers
of <hi>Italy,</hi> a<U+017F><U+017F>erting withal the venomon<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of
the angred <U+017F>pirits cau<U+017F>ing the death that en<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the bite; and <hi><U+017F>ince</hi> la<U+017F>tly the Vipers of
<hi>France</hi> do kill as <U+017F>oon and in the <U+017F>ame manner
as tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Italy</hi> do, and even without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention
of the jellow liquor: The<U+017F>e
things being <U+017F>o, I e<U+017F>teem, that Sign. <hi>Redi</hi>
would do very well, if, to <U+017F>atisfie <hi>on his part</hi>
the expectation of the publick, and without
adhering any longer to the jellow liquor,
which is <U+017F>o rea<U+017F>onably conte<U+017F>ted, he would
take the pains to labour to find out <U+017F>ome new
<U+017F>ubject, that might be common to the Vipers
of <hi>France</hi> and tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Italy;</hi> that might have
the <U+017F>ame di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of matter, and the <U+017F>ame
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98525:56"/>
power of acting nimbly; and that might with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
be equally declared the true <U+017F>eat of their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom;
to the end that afterwards he might as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tly
exclude from it the enraged <U+017F>pirits, as I now
exclude from it the jellow liquor. But if on the
contrary it comes to pa<U+017F>s, that he can find none
other, I believe not, that for the future he hath
any ground to maintain his opinion, no more
than to conte<U+017F>t mine.</p>
                  <p>Concluding this di<U+017F><U+017F>ertation I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ay, that
the contrariety of opinions, which is between
Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> and me, in the mo<U+017F>t e<U+017F><U+017F>ential things
of the Vipers poi<U+017F>on, may al<U+017F>o be ob<U+017F>erved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
another account about the <U+017F>ame animal: For,
the more <hi>he</hi> expre<U+017F><U+017F>eth <hi>p.</hi> 39. of his la<U+017F>t letter, the
aver<U+017F>ion and hatred he hath again<U+017F>t it, the more I
e<U+017F>teem it, and the greater plea<U+017F>ure I take to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
to examine, and to prepare it. Nor can I <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
prai<U+017F>e the excellent qualities, which <U+017F>o
rare a <U+017F>ubject po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>eth, nor the admirable reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
which it furni<U+017F>heth: Which are the con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
that have heretofore induced me, and
oblige me <U+017F>till to call the Viper one of the chief
Pillars of Phy<U+017F>ick.</p>
                  <p>It may be, that for this once Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> will
not doubt but that a di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e as rude as this,
compos'd among coals and furnaces, which I
have <U+017F>eldom quitted of late, is mine. He will
doubtle<U+017F>s judge, that, if more under<U+017F>tanding men
had put their hands to it, the rea<U+017F>onings thereof
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98525:57"/>
would be more <U+017F>ubtile, the <U+017F>tyle more polite,
and the expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions more elegant; and the <hi>Greek</hi>
and <hi>Latin</hi> quotations would not have been <U+017F>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
therein, both to <U+017F>trengthen the arguments
thereof, and to adorn &amp; enlarge the volume. But
for all the contrarieties, which the different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions
have bred between Sign. <hi>Redi</hi> and me,
I <U+017F>hall always have a very great and a very di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interre<U+017F><U+017F>'d
e<U+017F>teem for him; and <U+017F>o much the more,
becau<U+017F>e I have great rea<U+017F>on to conceive <U+017F>ome
good opinion of my book, <U+017F>ince it could de<U+017F>erve
that <U+017F>o intelligent &amp; famous a per<U+017F>on hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>afed
to read it again and again with plea<U+017F>ure,
as he <U+017F>aith him<U+017F>elf, that he hath taken the pains
of tran<U+017F>cribing many pages out of it word for
word, and hath made it famous by his an<U+017F>wer, and
by that al<U+017F>o which a per<U+017F>on of great parts, and a
high reputation hath made to it, addre<U+017F>s'd to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
on this <U+017F>ubject. I cannot but much glory in
it, and highly declare my <U+017F>elf his obliged. And
if it <U+017F>hould come to pa<U+017F>s, that the diver<U+017F>ity of
his experiments, the force of his arguments, or
the e<U+017F>teem he hath acquired among the Learned,
<U+017F>hould carry the bell from me in the <U+017F>pirits of all
the world; the victory, which he <U+017F>hould thence
obtain, would not be much le<U+017F>s advantagious for
me, then if the truth of my experiments, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
by my rea<U+017F>onings, had been able to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance
or even to prevail over his Sentiments and
the writings of <U+017F>o Illu<U+017F>trious a Per<U+017F>on.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98525:57"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>

