<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two new novels ... translated out of the French by P.B.G.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F540_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13347468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13347468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A64026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 371:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two new novels ... translated out of the French by P.B.G.</title>
                  <author>La Chapelle, M. de (Jean), 1655-1723. Langage müet. English.</author>
                  <author>Brilhac, Jean-Baptiste de. Agnès de Castro. English.</author>
                  <author>Belon, P. (Peter)</author>
                  <author>Du Vignau, sieur des Joanots. Secrétaire turc. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 pts. ([8], 74, 102 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bently ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: P. Bellon.</note>
                  <note>Each novel has special t.p. and separate paging. Both novels translated out of the French by Peter Belon. The first, a translation of: Le langage müet, is an extract from: Secrétaire turc / sieur de Du Vignau.</note>
                  <note>First English ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Entry cancelled for F540 in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. The art of making love without speaking, writing or enterview of the lovers / [M. de La Chapelle] -- II. The fatal beauty of Agnes de Castro, taken out of the history of Portugal / [J.-B. de Brilhac].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="unk">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99165:1"/>
            <p>Two New NOVELS. I. The ART of making LOVE Without Speaking, Writing or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview of the LOVERS. II. The FATAL BEAUTY OF <hi>AGNES de CASTRO</hi>; Taken out of the HISTORY OF PORTUGAL.</p>
            <p>Tran<U+017F>lated out of the <hi>French</hi> by <hi>P.B.</hi>G.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Licen<U+017F>ed,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>May</hi> 19th. 1688.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bently</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>el-<U+017F>treet,</hi> in <hi>Common-Garden.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99165:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99165:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Virtuou<U+017F>ly Accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hed LADY; My LADY <hi>CHARDIN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough Virtue, Honour, and all the other Accompli<U+017F>hments of the Mind, are not to be reflected on with the least grain of O<U+017F>tentation, by tho<U+017F>e, that the Heavens have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with <U+017F>uch eminent Quallities: Yet certainly, Madam, tho<U+017F>e three Illu<U+017F>trious Per<U+017F>ons, repre<U+017F>ented in this <U+017F>mall piece, which I Humbly offer you, would have thought them<U+017F>elves particularly obliged to
<pb facs="tcp:99165:3"/>
kind Heaven, if it had produc'd in their time, <U+017F>o exact a Pattern o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their own Perfections, as you are Madam; in which without the lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>cruple or offence to Mode<U+017F>ty, they might have admired, with as much Ju<U+017F>tice as Delight tho<U+017F>e Accompli<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which did <U+017F>o vi<U+017F>ibly mark in their own Per<U+017F>ons <U+017F>o great a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the re<U+017F>t of the World. Yes Madam, in you they might have lov'd the rare Qualities which were <U+017F>o con<U+017F>onant to tho<U+017F>e which adorn'd them<U+017F>elves, and which mode<U+017F>ty would not permit them to applaude in their own Per<U+017F>ons.</p>
            <p>Is it not therefore, with great Ju<U+017F>tice, Madam, that I have <U+017F>heltered this little, but true piece of Hi<U+017F>tory, under your <U+017F>afe protection. You who has <U+017F>o great a <U+017F>hare in it; you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,
<pb facs="tcp:99165:3"/>
in whom all the glittering Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Per<U+017F>ons, as great in their Perfections of Minds, as they were in their Births, do <U+017F>o greatly abound, you, Madam, who has <U+017F>o ju<U+017F>t a di<U+017F>cern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all that is excellently good, who has <U+017F>o nice a Judgment in the Critici<U+017F>m's of your own Dialect, and who is <U+017F>o great a Judge of our's. Finally, you, Madam, who can be<U+017F>t Judge of the equity with which I have proceeded, in pre<U+017F>enting to our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<U+017F>h World, the true and lively Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of three Per<U+017F>ons <U+017F>o remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>But, Madam, that you may not be inticed in your turn into <U+017F>ome agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rapture, by too long a contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<U+017F>e Excellent Per<U+017F>ons Merits, give me leave to draw the Curtain over it, and to divert you with a
<pb facs="tcp:99165:4"/>
pretty piece of Turki<U+017F>h gallantry, in which you way behold a certain way of Court<U+017F>hip, as plea<U+017F>ant, as new to us <hi>Europeans;</hi> I am <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible, Madam, it were but rea<U+017F>onable, I <U+017F>hould give you <U+017F>ome more particular accounts of the<U+017F>e two Novels, but that having been done already, <U+017F>ufficiently by the <hi>French</hi> Author, I <U+017F>hall de<U+017F>i<U+017F>t there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from giving you any further diver<U+017F>ion, from your more <U+017F>erious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, and <U+017F>hall only take the Liberty of <U+017F>ub<U+017F>cribing my <U+017F>elf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your mo<U+017F>t humble Servant</hi> P. Bellon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99165:4"/>
                  <p>THE ART Of making LOVE WITHOUT Speaking, Writing, or Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of the LOVERS. A Plea<U+017F>ant NOVEL.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tran<U+017F>lated from the</hi> French.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON, LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>el-<U+017F>treet,</hi> in <hi>Common-Garden.</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="authors_note">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99165:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99165:5"/>
                  <head>THE ART Of making LOVE WITHOUT Speaking, Writing, or Enterveiw of the LOVERS.</head>
                  <p>SInce I had the Honour, Sir, of entertaining you with a Dumb Language, that the <hi>Turks</hi> u<U+017F>e to Expre<U+017F>s without Speaking, without Writing, and without Seeing one another, the <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t of all the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions. You
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99165:6"/>
have been exceedingly pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing in obliging me to put in Writing that which I had Communicated to you in a familiar Conver<U+017F>ation. You extreamly pu<U+017F>le me in it, and I a<U+017F><U+017F>ure you that I had beg'd your excu<U+017F>e, had I but known the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a particular Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e of two Per<U+017F>ons in which all freedom is admitted, and from whence all Affectation is bani<U+017F>h'd, and a <U+017F>tuddied Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, which peradventure you will publi<U+017F>h, and <U+017F>o cau<U+017F>e it to be Criticis'd, in its Phra<U+017F>e, Method, Words, and in all Things el<U+017F>e which tho<U+017F>e that Write are oblig'd to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve</p>
                  <p>I am not Ignorant of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard I run, I prepare my <U+017F>elf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t all the trouble<U+017F>ome con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, that my temerity will draw on me. You are oblig'd to maintain my Reputation, <U+017F>eeing you have fir<U+017F>t engag'd me to <U+017F>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Curio<U+017F>ity, without giving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99165:6"/>
me the lea<U+017F>ure of reflecting on the difficulty of my enterpri<U+017F>e. And if Love is counted the Shipwrack of Liberties and Hearts, he may well be that of my Pen al<U+017F>o. Be it what it will, <U+017F>pare me, I pray you, and expo<U+017F>e not this <U+017F>mall Peice to the public, who will not prove <U+017F>o kind as you are, and that will not con<U+017F>ider, that my de<U+017F>ign is but to Divert you in a manner of making Love, which is wholly new.</p>
                  <p>There are divers ways of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing that Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion. The fir<U+017F>t School in that, is that of Nature, and all tho<U+017F>e Le<U+017F><U+017F>ons which the Poets have given us on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, would remain very u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s without the Aid and A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of this Univer<U+017F>al School Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tri<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>Though the Love of the Brutes is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to the Con<U+017F>ervation of their Species, Nature has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>oning of <U+017F>ome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99165:7"/>
preparatory Agreements, to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Sen<U+017F>es and to <U+017F>tir up the Natural Heat.</p>
                  <p>Man, the mo<U+017F>t rational and <U+017F>en<U+017F>ual of Animals, finds the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure too <U+017F>hort, and endeavours to prolong it, by new Inventions, he <U+017F>ets to work all <U+017F>orts of Means, to expre<U+017F>s unto the belov'd object, what he makes us to feel, and the<U+017F>e Troubles which he cau<U+017F>es in a Lovers Heart; who <U+017F>ometimes expre<U+017F><U+017F>es him<U+017F>elf with the Voice, who employs Writing to <U+017F>et forth in the mo<U+017F>t moving Manner that Ardor which con<U+017F>umes him, and who in defect of Voice and Writing endeavours to expre<U+017F>s by the different Motions of his Face the Sentiments of his Heart.</p>
                  <p>The<U+017F>e are the u<U+017F>ual ways of making Love in a Country of Freedom, where Communication is ea<U+017F>ily obtain'd, and where Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons can See, Speak, and Write to one another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99165:7"/>There are Nation that enjoy not tho<U+017F>e advantages. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t part of the <hi>Turks</hi> can neither Write, nor Read, neither have they the freedom of Conver<U+017F>ing with Women; yet are they not in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible. On the contrary it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Ea<U+017F>tern People are more apt to Love then any other Nation; They wholly Abandon them<U+017F>elves to it, there they fix their <U+017F>overeign good, they rai<U+017F>e their Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion even to a Fury, and I have <U+017F>een <U+017F>ome in their Rage to Stab their Limbs with D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ggers, and then to drop burning Brim<U+017F>tone in the Wounds.</p>
                  <p>There is no wonder therefore that People of <U+017F>o Hot Tempers, when they want the ordinary means of making known their Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, endeavour to invent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ones. Flowers, Leaves, Fruits, Aromatick Woods, Gold, Silver, all Colours, Stuffs, and in fine, almo<U+017F>t all things that are u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99165:8"/>
in the Commerce of Life, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that of Love.</p>
                  <p>All tho<U+017F>e things which the <hi>Turks</hi> call <hi>Selam's,</hi> Salutes, have their <U+017F>ignification, and their Natural or Allegorical Valour, much like the Old way of Poetry, <U+017F>o that a little packet about the bigne<U+017F>s of a Thumb does form by the <U+017F>everal things which it contains, a very expre<U+017F><U+017F>ive Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>This way of Expre<U+017F><U+017F>ing a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, will appear to you as extravagant as new. Yet it wants not its A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements al<U+017F>o, and though it proceeds but from a great want of Liberty, and a defect in the mo<U+017F>t Common of Arts, which is that of Writing and Reading, yet it is <U+017F>o Gallant and Ingenious, that tho<U+017F>e that can both Write and Read, make u<U+017F>e of it al<U+017F>o, and believe that tho<U+017F>e <hi>Selams,</hi> have more force and make a greater impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion on the mind, then the Characters of a Letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99165:8"/>To Initiate you with delight into the Commerce of that Dumb Love, and to give you a perfect Knowledg of it. You mu<U+017F>t be introduc'd by the Knowledg of tho<U+017F>e things, which Compo<U+017F>e that Language.</p>
                  <p>I have reduc'd them in an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetical Order, to ea<U+017F>e the find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of tho<U+017F>e Names. I have Compos'd divers Letters with them, to <U+017F>hew you the way of their Order, and I have In<U+017F>erted them in a Gallant and true Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tory, to give them more A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and the more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you to the reading of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="glossary">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99165:9"/>
                  <head>The Alphabetical Dictionary of the Dumb Language, containing the Name, Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, Worth, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the <hi>Selams.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="A" type="part">
                     <head>A</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>AIna,</hi> Looking-Gla<U+017F>s.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kourban, olaim, boyunga,</hi> I <U+017F>hall become your Slave.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yeuzum <U+017F>ureim païngna.</hi>.. I <U+017F>hall rub my Face with your Feet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Al.</hi> Red.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chimglumj aldung, dgianumj al,</hi> you have taken my Liberty, take al<U+017F>o my Soul.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A<U+017F>ma,</hi> a great <U+017F>tock of a Vine.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yerdekj Yuzu ba<U+017F>ma,</hi> tread not on a Face that is on the ground,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99165:9"/>
di<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e not tho<U+017F>e that are <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Atlas.</hi> Sattin. <hi>Kim<U+017F>e yuzumé bak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</hi> No body ca<U+017F>t their Eyes on me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Arpa.</hi> Barley.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchekmé bizj <U+017F>arpa,</hi> produce no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alma,</hi> Apple.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benden Alma,</hi> take me not.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ku<U+017F>taglighé kalina,</hi> excu<U+017F>e my Freedom.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Aktché A<U+017F>per,</hi> Half-peny.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghetehenelum bir hoktché,</hi> lets di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert our <U+017F>elves together.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Altum, <U+017F>equin,</hi> Peice of Gold.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Albenj <U+017F>atun,</hi> take me, and fell me, di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of me as you plea<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Amberboj, Ambretta,</hi> Flower.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ikimus birboj,</hi> we are the <U+017F>ame height.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Astar,</hi> cour<U+017F>e Cloth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Evignuzj ghieu<U+017F>ter,</hi> <U+017F>hew me where's your Hou<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ak,</hi> White, living.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Aklum aldung,</hi> you have <U+017F>eis'd my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99165:10"/>
mind, I am no longer mine.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Amber,</hi> Amber.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Amver,</hi> <U+017F>atisfie my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A<U+017F>ma yagraghj,</hi> Vine Leaf.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yuzum yagung topaghj,</hi> my Journey is the Earth under your Feet, where I lay my <U+017F>elf under your Feet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Armouth,</hi> Pair.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Albenden bir mout,</hi> take a bu<U+017F>hel from me, that is, <U+017F>atisfie you fully.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="B" type="part">
                     <head>B.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Badian hindj,</hi> Indian Anis.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senden gairj do<U+017F>tum yok Chimdj,</hi> I have no other Friend but you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bakla, Beane Benj goinunga <U+017F>akla</hi>; hide me in your Bo<U+017F>om.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Balmounj,</hi> Wax.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Echkund Artudj dgenounumj</hi> your Love has increas'd my folly, or, I love you even to folly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bolgour,</hi> beaten Wheat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99165:10"/>
                           <hi>E<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>den Evé Kalghir,</hi> you run from Hou<U+017F>e to Hou<U+017F>e, from Fair to Fair.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bogdaj,</hi> Wheat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchekilmez echkung yaj,</hi> let not the bow of your Love be drawn, or, exerci<U+017F>e not over me the power of Love.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iruldgé,</hi> <U+017F>mall white Bean.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bizé ghel bou ghedgé</hi> come and <U+017F>ee us this night.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Koulun olaïm ulundgé,</hi> I <U+017F>hall be your <U+017F>lave till Death.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Badem.</hi> Almond.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bozwktur Madem,</hi> my inwards are tainted, I am peirs'd with Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Neguzel adew,</hi> ah! the Beautiful Man.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Biber,</hi> Pepper.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bizé birbellj L<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>herber,</hi> we know a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Buberié,</hi> Ro<U+017F>mary.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghel berié</hi>: Approach near me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Beyaz,</hi> White.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bir tefter bizé yaz,</hi> Write to us a Note.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99165:11"/>
                           <hi>Bez,</hi> Cloth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bez dum,</hi> I have wearyed, tired, my <U+017F>elf.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="C" type="part">
                     <head>C.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cheker Kamichj,</hi> Sugar Cane.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>m rum gunechj,</hi> Son of my life.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cheftalj,</hi> Peach.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yetter etting bizé alj,</hi> you have deceiv'd us <U+017F>ufficiently.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cheker,</hi> Sugar.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senj Madem techeker,</hi> my own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture draws you, or we both Sympathize.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chemamé,</hi> Pomander, or <U+017F>weet Apple.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sabghideris hamame,</hi> we <U+017F>hall go to morow to the Bath.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chiché,</hi> Gla<U+017F>s.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kaïl olman bou iché,</hi> I con<U+017F>ent not to this bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chab,</hi> Alum.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bize bir chafj dgeuab,</hi> give us a <U+017F>incere an<U+017F>wer.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="D" type="part">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99165:11"/>
                     <head>D.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dgeuiz,</hi> Nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nedurbizé dgeïrigniz,</hi> you give us much trouble.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dug mé,</hi> Button.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bone mungnu kim<U+017F>eyé Amé,</hi> <U+017F>ubmit your <U+017F>elf to no Body.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Darj,</hi> Millet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benj yaktj echkum narj,</hi> the fire of Love hath Burnt me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Deriaj,</hi> Sea green.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchekilurmj demjr yaj,</hi> Canan Iron bow be drawn?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>That is to expre<U+017F>s a <U+017F>trong re<U+017F>olu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dartchin,</hi> Cinamon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Biz Tchekeris hardgin,</hi> we will be at the expence.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dé mir,</hi> Iron.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Beneridum <U+017F>en <U+017F>emir,</hi> I parch, and you fatten.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dginghiarj,</hi> gra<U+017F>s green.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dgenghimus var,</hi> we are in quarrel.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="E" type="part">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99165:12"/>
                     <head>E.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ekmek,</hi> Bread.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Erik,</hi> Plumb.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eridik,</hi> we are Melted.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eudagadgj,</hi> Aloes Wood.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bachimumd il adgj,</hi> Remedy of my head.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>irgan,</hi> Nettle.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Birj biriniz e<U+017F><U+017F>irghen,</hi> take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion of one another.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lazum oldu <U+017F>enj eupmek,</hi> it is nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ary that I <U+017F>hould ki<U+017F>s you.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="F" type="part">
                     <head>F.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Furfelek.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yacumé ej ledum dilek,</hi> I have made an humble petition to my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tris.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fi<U+017F>tik,</hi> Pi<U+017F>tache.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sizé Ku<U+017F>tuk,</hi> I am angry with you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Frag Fourj,</hi> Porcelain.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yolun duchtukche guel berj,</hi> vi<U+017F>it us
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99165:12"/>
if occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>erves.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fe<U+017F>lighen,</hi> the Herb Bafil.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senj <U+017F>iriemdé be<U+017F>leyen,</hi> I <U+017F>hall rai<U+017F>e you in my brea<U+017F>t.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fonduk,</hi> Hai<U+017F>el Nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Felattuk,</hi> we are broke off.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="G" type="part">
                     <head>G.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghemik,</hi> Bone.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nedurgher danuna omik,</hi> who has made this <hi>Succon</hi> at your neck</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gul,</hi> Ro<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guldurdum bejn</hi> you made me laugh, otherwi<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benaglarum <U+017F>en gul,</hi> I weep and you laugh.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gulgulj,</hi> Ro<U+017F>e Colour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sinem bulbulj,</hi> Nightingal of my bo<U+017F>om.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gulpemhé,</hi> Peach Blo<U+017F>om Colour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Serdam bil <U+017F>endé,</hi> learn my pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, what Torments me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghionluk,</hi> Incen<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bizé Ograr<U+017F>en bir Ghionluk,</hi> If you <U+017F>hould come to <U+017F>ee us one day.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="H" type="part">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99165:13"/>
                     <head>H.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hilal,</hi> Earpick.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benj bilé al,</hi> Take me along with you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A<U+017F><U+017F>ir,</hi> mat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sangna olaim e<U+017F><U+017F>ir,</hi> I <U+017F>hall be your <U+017F>lave.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Havaj gall</hi> Colour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tenha aldun mj odaj,</hi> have you cho<U+017F>en a <U+017F>ecret Chamber out of the way?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hindi<U+017F>tan dgeuizi,</hi> Indian Nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Atchun gnuz, tenugnuzj,</hi> Open your brea<U+017F>t.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hindj,</hi> Nutmeg.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benaglarum guler kendj,</hi> I weep, and <U+017F>he laughs.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Halj,</hi> Carpet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nerd hhalungj,</hi> how do you?</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="I" type="part">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Indgir,</hi> Figg.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benj chimler adgj,</hi> does no Body pitty me?</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99165:13"/>
                           <hi>Iplik,</hi> new thred.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gaïr do<U+017F>tumlen<U+017F>ick,</hi> divert your <U+017F>elf with your other Mi<U+017F>tris <hi>otherwi<U+017F>e. Sangna Lazum mj biblick,</hi> <U+017F>tand you in need of being more clear'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Je<U+017F><U+017F>emin,</hi> Je<U+017F><U+017F>mine.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sangna ettum jemin,</hi> I have Sworn to you, <hi>otherwi<U+017F>e Ahumden eridj Zemin,</hi> my <U+017F>ighs cau<U+017F>e the Earth to open.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ibrichim,</hi> twi<U+017F>ted Silk.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Allaha kaldj ichim,</hi> I have laid my bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s on God.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Judgj,</hi> Pearl.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guzellerum, <U+017F>en<U+017F>en ghendgj,</hi> you are a trea<U+017F>ure of Youth and Beauty.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ikj kardak kanj,</hi> a kind of Coral.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hageba, ne ichler numidgia dgiani</hi>; By your leave, what does the Soul of my Soul.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ilimon,</hi> Lemon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ilumumus var,</hi> we are inform'd,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Igné,</hi> Point.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghieuz <U+017F>undé olaim dugmé,</hi> I will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99165:14"/>
cleave to your bo<U+017F>om, as a button to your Ve<U+017F>t.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="K" type="part">
                     <head>K.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kachek,</hi> Spoon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ayak Larumus dolachek,</hi> let's twi<U+017F>t our Leggs together.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kiretch,</hi> Lime.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Do<U+017F>tum ichj i<U+017F><U+017F>e, birinden var ghetch.</hi> If you have two Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F><U+017F>es, you mu<U+017F>t abandon one.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kabouk<U+017F>is fonduk,</hi> a nut kernel.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Biz <U+017F>izé omduk,</hi> you are all my hope.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Klaboudon,</hi> Gold-twi<U+017F>ted on Silk.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iki yuzlu,</hi> Traitor, double-fac'd Man.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Krmizj,</hi> Crim<U+017F>on Red.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bangna miej <U+017F>erzen nazj,</hi> It is not with me that you mu<U+017F>t act the Proud one.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ke<U+017F>tané,</hi> Che<U+017F>nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ke<U+017F><U+017F>elidik,</hi> we have <U+017F>eparated our <U+017F>elves.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Echkunden oldum me<U+017F>tané,</hi> I am
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99165:14"/>
drunk and troubled with love.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kalem,</hi> writing Pen.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benum itchun, tchekmé elem,</hi> <U+017F>uffer nothing for love of me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Khare,</hi> Taby.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yureghim yare,</hi> my Heart is to what I love.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kieten,</hi> Flax.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>mrume yeten,</hi> <U+017F>ufficient during life.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kouroum,</hi> <U+017F>out.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nege guler yarum,</hi> what makes my Mi<U+017F>tris to laugh?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kilim,</hi> Woolen Carpet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yeter ettim bize Zouloum,</hi> you have <U+017F>ufficiently u<U+017F>ed me cruelly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kibritj,</hi> Brim<U+017F>tone Colour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yanum den kon oitj,</hi> drive that Dog from near you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Khiar,</hi> Cow-comber.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Korkarum unglar doyar,</hi> I fear it might be perceiv'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kau,</hi> a Match.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hhalkj bachingden <U+017F>aw,</hi> <U+017F>eparate your <U+017F>elf from <U+017F>o much People.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Khourma,</hi> Date.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99165:15"/>
                           <hi>Muradigna irma,</hi> execute not your de<U+017F>ign.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Katife,</hi> Velvet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yeter ettin latiffe,</hi> you have je<U+017F>ted long enough.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kiomour,</hi> Coal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ben úlurem, <U+017F>ize eumur,</hi> I am willing to dye, <U+017F>o you live.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kacoule,</hi> Indian Anis.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ouyarmi<U+017F>en ma koule,</hi> do you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent to what is ju<U+017F>t?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kiaghit,</hi> Paper.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hholkj bachinden daghit,</hi> <U+017F>end the People from you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kalaj,</hi> Pewter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senj aldatmak kolaj,</hi> you permit your <U+017F>elf to be ea<U+017F>ily deceiv'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kenevis,</hi> Canvas.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yaren gherge bile iz.</hi> To morrow we will pa<U+017F>s the night together.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Korenfil,</hi> Clove.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Karorum yok,</hi> you have no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tancy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kai<U+017F>sj.</hi> Apricock.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Boulamadum <U+017F>enden ei<U+017F>sj,</hi> I find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99165:15"/>
                           <hi>Kiraz,</hi> Cherry.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bize ver bir raz,</hi> give your <U+017F>elf a little.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kebe,</hi> thick covering of Hor<U+017F>e hair.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sout Chume teube,</hi> I repent me of my Fault.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="L" type="part">
                     <head>L.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Laden,</hi> Ladanum.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Boula<U+017F>en Merladen,</hi> God return it you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lale,</hi> Tulip.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kaddumj dunderdum halile,</hi> You have winded my Body as an Ear-pick. <hi>That is to <U+017F>ay,</hi> I have done all you pleas'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lahana,</hi> Cabage.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Neme bouldum behane,</hi> what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is that?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sule,</hi> Pipe Nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchatladum gule gule,</hi> I have bur<U+017F>t my <U+017F>elf with Laughing.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="M" type="part">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99165:16"/>
                     <head>M.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Makas,</hi> Ci<U+017F>ers.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benj kapigne as,</hi> hang me at your door.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mi<U+017F><U+017F>ir bogdaj,</hi> Buck Wheat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sen ulur<U+017F>en birdahj,</hi> If you dye, there are others.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Menevich,</hi> Crim<U+017F>on Violet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yazuktur bize bou itch,</hi> there's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cience in u<U+017F>ing us thus.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Merdgmek,</hi> lentile,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Haua oldu bou dge emek,</hi> all my <U+017F>ervices are lo<U+017F>t.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Menekche,</hi> Violet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Albenj okche.</hi> Take me, and care<U+017F>s me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Madanos.</hi> Par<U+017F>ley.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tenhamj Euignuz,</hi> is your Hou<U+017F>e, out of the Way?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Merdgian,</hi> Coral.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Malum <U+017F>enum durhardgin</hi>; di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of my means.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mechin,</hi> Turky Leather.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yoktur echim,</hi> you have not your like.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99165:16"/>
                           <hi>Mercin,</hi> Mirtle.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Allag <U+017F>eni bangna ver<U+017F>in,</hi> God give you to me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mavj,</hi> Blew.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mail oldum,</hi> I am fallen in love.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mazj.</hi> Gall-nut.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nedur bize nazj.</hi> whence comes this hautine<U+017F>s?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Muskuroumj,</hi> Wall-flower.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchek owtch kourumj,</hi> I am yours. <hi>Mor,</hi> Violet Colour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senj <U+017F>evelu oldum khior,</hi> your Soul has made me become blind,</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="N" type="part">
                     <head>N.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nar.</hi> Pomgranate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yureghim yamar.</hi> My heart burns.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nohoud.</hi> Pitch.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Derdumden oldum bejhhod.</hi> My pain takes away my <U+017F>en<U+017F>es.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nane,</hi> Mint.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sevichelum dgiane,</hi> let's love with all our hearts.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nerkez.</hi> Marry-gold-flower.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Koum olaim herkez.</hi> I'le be your <U+017F>lave on all occa<U+017F>ions.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99165:17"/>
                           <hi>Nebat cheker,</hi> Sugar-candy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Neubet ignize kail oldum,</hi> I yeild, that you have your turn.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="O" type="part">
                     <head>O.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Orondghek,</hi> Spider.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gurmedum yuzunt doinge,</hi> I cannot be <U+017F>atiated with <U+017F>eeing you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ouvez.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yanuma ghel birez<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                           </hi> draw near me.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="P" type="part">
                     <head>P.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pirindge.</hi> Rice.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eteme bize ele gulindge,</hi> expo<U+017F>e me not to laughtuer.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pambouk.</hi> Cotton.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghel bize Konouk.</hi> Come, and lye at our Hou<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Para,</hi> a <U+017F>mall peice of Silver.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghel Ardun Ara,</hi> come and feel me out.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="R" type="part">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99165:17"/>
                     <head>R.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rezene:</hi> Fenel.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rutek gherek ghezene,</hi> Incon<U+017F>tancy mu<U+017F>t be puni<U+017F>h'd</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ratfic tachj,</hi> Antimony Mineral.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Akar, ghieuzumum yachj,</hi> my Eyes melt into Tears.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="S" type="part">
                     <head>S.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sarj.</hi> Yellow.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sarilatum,</hi> let us embrace.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Satche.</hi> Hairs.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Batchimetadge.</hi> Crown of my head.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Santan.</hi> Straw.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Allakton boulaman,</hi> God forgive thee.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Boulachalum bir Zaman,</hi> let us meet <U+017F>ome where.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sunghier.</hi> Spunge.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Etme <U+017F>eu<U+017F>um inkiar,</hi> keep your word.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sarrmuffak,</hi> Garlick.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Birghedge <U+017F>aril<U+017F>ak,</hi> we mu<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>s the night together</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99165:18"/>
                           <hi>Saboun,</hi> Sope.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ettinbene <U+017F>aboun.</hi> You make me Sick.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Supurgbe,</hi> a Broom.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Benj bir yol e<U+017F><U+017F>irghe.</hi> Once take pity of me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sidgim.</hi> Packthread.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nedur <U+017F>outchum,</hi> what is my fault?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ma,</hi> Gold-wyer.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yuzungnu bende najrma.</hi> Turn not your face away from me, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me not.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sandal,</hi> Tafety.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yeter oldu bize bou<U+017F>al</hi>; That cheat is <U+017F>ufficient.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sur<U+017F>am,</hi> Grain of—</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sangna bir <U+017F>eus de<U+017F><U+017F>em,</hi> If I told you a word.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sumboul, a</hi> jacinth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Khoudadan boul,</hi> God reward you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Servj,</hi> Cyprus-tree.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Zeter ettin dge<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rj.</hi> You have caus'd us trouble enough.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sarmachik,</hi> Joy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yum hej boulachik.</hi> Retire, draggle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99165:18"/>
                           <hi>Sakiz.</hi> Ma<U+017F>tick.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ghel bize kiz.</hi> Draw near me; you fair Maid.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="T" type="part">
                     <head>T.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Toprak.</hi> Earth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eskj <U+017F>eudugungj brak,</hi> leave your ancient Love.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kiaadge bize bak,</hi> behold us <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tire,</hi> twi<U+017F>ted thread.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kalbime ghire.</hi> Enter into my Heart.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchira,</hi> Oyly-wood.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Echking ile oldum khira.</hi> Your love has made me as lean as a rake, or, as a Skeelton.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Timin</hi> A peice of five Pence.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Seudugungna aile yemim</hi>: Oath of fidelity to his Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Boulamodum <U+017F>iz den yemin</hi>: You have no word.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Frnak,</hi> a Finger-nail.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kazak.</hi> Ru<U+017F>tick, clowni<U+017F>h, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>human.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99165:19"/>
                           <hi>Tulbend.</hi> Cambre<U+017F>ine.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Echkum getchtj bize bend.</hi> Love has bound us together.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Troup,</hi> Radi<U+017F>h.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Evigniz yolt <U+017F>arp,</hi> It is difficult to get into your Hou<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ychola,</hi> Cloath.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Khalumuze birbacha,</hi> con<U+017F>ider the condition I am in.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tach,</hi> Stone.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Koialum bir ya<U+017F>tiga bach,</hi> let us re<U+017F>t our head on the <U+017F>ame pillow.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tel.</hi> Golden-thread.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bizeghel,</hi> come to us.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Touroddte.</hi> Orange.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Toutzun <U+017F>enj koulendge,</hi> may all evils fall on thee.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Taxta,</hi> Board, or Plank.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dourmaf-<U+017F>on akta,</hi> you are not true to your word.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tchimchir,</hi> Box-wood.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Aklum bachina devjchir,</hi> recollect your mind.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tougla,</hi> Confederacy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yarem bize Ogra.</hi> Come to <U+017F>ee us to morrow.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99165:19"/>
                           <hi>Tuhin</hi> Tobaco.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kalbimus bitum,</hi> my heart is whole.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="V" type="part">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nnap, a Jujube.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bangno yap,</hi> do of me what you plea<U+017F>e.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>zum,</hi> a Rea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ichj ghieulum.</hi> Both my Eyes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>tupj,</hi> Toe, or Flax.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yarum bangna ku<U+017F>tumj,</hi> my Mi<U+017F>tris is angry with me.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ouve.</hi>—</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yanuma ghel bir ez.</hi> Come a little on my <U+017F>ide.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>kulen ustupj,</hi> Toe and Flax mixt together.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Yanun lakaj ben ke<U+017F>tjmj.</hi> Has my Mi<U+017F>tris broke off with me?</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Z" type="part">
                     <head>Z.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Zambak.</hi> Lily.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ben upein, <U+017F>enbak, I'lki<U+017F>s,</hi> while you'l be looking.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99165:20"/>
                           <hi>Zengebil,</hi> Ginger.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Senj <U+017F>everem <U+017F>endebil.</hi> Know that I love you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Zoitun,</hi> an Olive.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>gnum dengheth <U+017F>un mejtun.</hi> May thy Corp<U+017F>e pa<U+017F>s before me.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99165:20"/>
                  <head>A Gallant and True HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>IT is the Cu<U+017F>tom among<U+017F>t the <hi>Turks,</hi> to pa<U+017F>s the three Fe<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Days of the <hi>Bayram,</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic rejoycings. Tho<U+017F>e Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es that have their particular Palaces in the City of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantinople</hi> and near unto it, go to the <hi>Seraglio</hi> to Vi<U+017F>it the Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es, which at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times are not <U+017F>een. There they pa<U+017F>s the<U+017F>e three days, in Sports, Fea<U+017F>ts and Dances.</p>
                  <p>Tho<U+017F>e among<U+017F>t the Slaves, that are not Employ'd in Singing or Dancing, which makes the Chief Diverti<U+017F>ement of the Princes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire them<U+017F>elves in <U+017F>ome Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where they Sport among<U+017F>t them<U+017F>elves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99165:21"/>One day that <hi>Bournaz Atidgé,</hi> the Sultane<U+017F>s, Si<U+017F>ter to <hi>Sultan Morat,</hi> was at the <hi>Seraglio</hi> with <hi>Tarhain</hi> Sultane<U+017F>s <hi>Validé,</hi> Mother to the Grand Segnior now Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Tho<U+017F>e two Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es who were very good Friends, being de<U+017F>irous to entertain them<U+017F>elves in Private, di<U+017F>mi<U+017F>s'd their Slaves.</p>
                  <p>Some of them very good friends, <U+017F>eparated them<U+017F>elves from the re<U+017F>t, that they might with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom entertain one another. They turn'd their Conver<U+017F>ation on the Love of <hi>Gulbeas</hi> white ro<U+017F>e. She was the principal Slave of the Sultane<U+017F>s <hi>Validé</hi>; That Maid, at fir<U+017F>t made <U+017F>ome re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, either through Mode<U+017F>ty, or to <U+017F>pare her <U+017F>elf the Sorrow of the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of a Beloved Lover. Yet <U+017F>he yeilded at la<U+017F>t to her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Importunities.</p>
                  <p>She told them that <U+017F>he had pa<U+017F>s'd divers years without knowing what was Love, though <U+017F>he daily
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99165:21"/>
heard her Companions Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of that Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; which produced <U+017F>uch <U+017F>trange Effects in tho<U+017F>e Maids mind, that <U+017F>he could perceive them to pa<U+017F>s in an in<U+017F>tant, from joy to <U+017F>adne<U+017F>s, and from Love to their Jealou<U+017F>y, and De<U+017F>ire, and that Faces would change as frequently as their Hearts were agitated with different Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions: That <U+017F>o Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Condition had caus'd her to fear <U+017F>uch like Engagements, and that <U+017F>he had <U+017F>hun'd them as much as <U+017F>he could: But at la<U+017F>t, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, Love anger'd at my re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, forc'd me to yeild to his Power, and in<U+017F>pired in me <U+017F>ome Feelings of Tenderne<U+017F>s for a Young <hi>Turk,</hi> Neighbour to a <hi>Jew,</hi> with whom I Boarded, to Learn the Exerci<U+017F>es of Reading, Writing, Singing, Playing on Divers In<U+017F>truments, and Dancing, in Order to be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the <hi>Seraglio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Turk</hi> named <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> Son to <hi>Mahomet</hi> Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a, was both Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99165:22"/>
and good Friend to the <hi>Jew,</hi> and he did frequently come to his Hou<U+017F>e, to hear me Sing. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion for me, that he pa<U+017F>s'd both Days and Nights at his Window, or in his Garden to <U+017F>ee me: And one day, he ventur'd to <U+017F>pake to me of his Love, but his Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>es made <U+017F>o <U+017F>mall Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion on my mind, that I had not at that time the lea<U+017F>t Sentiment of Tenderne<U+017F>s for him.</p>
                  <p>Sometime after that Per<U+017F>on who had put me to the <hi>Jew,</hi> finding me <U+017F>ufficiently In<U+017F>tructed, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ented me to the Sultane<U+017F>s my Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s. Ab<U+017F>ence, which is a great Remedy again<U+017F>t Love, in<U+017F>tead of alaying <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, <U+017F>erv'd but to increa<U+017F>e it, while I liv'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the lea<U+017F>t di<U+017F>turbance in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> where Love had not yet di<U+017F>turb'd my Re<U+017F>t.</p>
                  <p>He did endeavour by all <U+017F>orts of means to learn <U+017F>ome News of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99165:22"/>
the Per<U+017F>on he lov'd; all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours were fruitle<U+017F>s, The Gates of the Womens Apartment are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acce<U+017F><U+017F>ible places. Tho<U+017F>e Cerbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<U+017F>es that keep them, enraged and de<U+017F>perate to find them<U+017F>elves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of that which might render them agreeable to <U+017F>o many Beauties which they have under their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, become Jealous, and have more Eyes then <hi>Argus</hi> to examine all their Actions.</p>
                  <p>So many difficulties had a mo<U+017F>t repuls'd <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> who had con<U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated three years in fruitle<U+017F>s At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. He did Abandon him<U+017F>elf to Grief and complaining, when one of his Friends who <U+017F>har'd in his Sorrow, inform'd him that a Jewi<U+017F>h Woman Merchant, named <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter,</hi> had free Acce<U+017F>s in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> where <U+017F>he <U+017F>old a great many J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wels to the Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> who had Wit, and Means, made good u<U+017F>e of his Friends Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and built great Hopes on it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99165:23"/>
per<U+017F>waded that Money over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes all difficulties, and that Liberality moves the mo<U+017F>t obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Hearts. He re<U+017F>olv'd to confide his Love to this Jewi<U+017F>h Woman, and to engage her in his Concerns.</p>
                  <p>The Enterpri<U+017F>e was not very difficult, con<U+017F>iderable Pre<U+017F>ents, and Promi<U+017F>es of Reiterating them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a favourable Succe<U+017F>s, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Jewi<U+017F>h Woman to <U+017F>erve <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> in his Amours.</p>
                  <p>He put into her hands a Pair of Pendants of Emeralds cut in the <U+017F>hape of Pairs, a pair of Diamond Bracelets, and the Buckles of a Girdle <U+017F>et with Rubies, in Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel'd Gold. He Accompanyed this Pre<U+017F>ent with a Billet, and a Seliman, put up in a Watch Ca<U+017F>e of Enamel'd Gold, <U+017F>et with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds. He Conjur'd his Me<U+017F><U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to u<U+017F>e all her Indu<U+017F>try to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wade and convince me of the exce<U+017F>s of his Love, and to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent to me the Di<U+017F>orders which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99165:23"/>
that Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion had made in his Heart, the deplorable Condition in which it had reduc'd him, that I had been almo<U+017F>t three years in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and could not all that while learn any News of me, that he was ready to Dye if all that he had <U+017F>uffer'd for me was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to molifie me, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pire <U+017F>ome kindne<U+017F>s for him in my Brea<U+017F>t.</p>
                  <p>The Jewi<U+017F>h Woman, who was very Dextrous and Prudent, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Seraglio</hi> as <U+017F>he us'd to do, took her time when the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane<U+017F>s was not vi<U+017F>ible, and <U+017F>eeking of an opportunity of <U+017F>peaking to me conveniently, reque<U+017F>ted that I <U+017F>hould give her leave to re<U+017F>t her <U+017F>elf a while in my Apartment, which I could not in Civility re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu<U+017F>e her, I being <U+017F>he which this Jewi<U+017F>h Merchant be<U+017F>t knew, by rea<U+017F>on of my Place of Trea<U+017F>urer to the Sultane<U+017F>s, to which I had been advanc'd, in a <U+017F>hort time,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99165:24"/>
through the Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es <U+017F>ingular Bounty.</p>
                  <p>Women are naturally Curious, I inform'd my <U+017F>elf of the quality of her Jewels. She heightned their Beauties and Perfections, pulling out of her Bo<U+017F>om a box in which tho<U+017F>e things were put up, <U+017F>he <U+017F>hew'd them me.</p>
                  <p>The fires and <U+017F>parklings of tho<U+017F>e precious Stones, on which I mo<U+017F>t earne<U+017F>tly gaz'd, with an envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eye, invited me to put them on me for a while.</p>
                  <p>The Jewi<U+017F>h Woman, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that I was coming to the Lure, and that this dre<U+017F>s pleas'd me, did invite me with her prai<U+017F>es to frequently Con<U+017F>ult a <U+017F>mall Looking-gla<U+017F>s which I had found by chance, which made me ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve an extraordinary redne<U+017F>s on my Face, caus'd by a Vexation, that Fortune had not favour'd me, with <U+017F>uch a like Trea<U+017F>ure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99165:24"/>
                     <hi>Boullu<U+017F>ter</hi> who ea<U+017F>ily perceiv'd what pa<U+017F>s'd in my Heart, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that every moment was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, thought it high time to Play her Part, and to di<U+017F>cover to me <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion in giving me his Letter and Pre<U+017F>ent.</p>
                  <p>Charming <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, I mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s to you how much I am <U+017F>urpris'd that the Sultan is not yet taken with your Beauty, and with <U+017F>o many Graces which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve in your Face; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in you but what is capable to Produce Love, and if that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror had once <U+017F>een you in this Dre<U+017F>s, the Sultane<U+017F>s would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <U+017F>ome Jealou<U+017F>ie thereon, and I ea<U+017F>ily believe what has been told me of the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion of a Young <hi>Turk</hi> who<U+017F>e Name is <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though I had not heard him mention'd <U+017F>ince I had been Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> no more then of the <hi>Jew</hi> with whom I had
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99165:25"/>
liv'd, that Name made me change Colour, for that young Man's Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion was not unknown to me, <U+017F>eeing he had entertain'd me with it before. I did all I could to di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>e my Surpri<U+017F>al, and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the Motions of my Soul, but that Poi<U+017F>on that had thrown it <U+017F>elf there and <U+017F>o long fomented, without perceiving it, di<U+017F>cover'd it <U+017F>elf again<U+017F>t my will by a Sigh drawn from the bottom of my Heart, which I could not for my Life retain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> made <U+017F>o good u<U+017F>e of the di<U+017F>order in which <U+017F>he perceiv'd me to be, and made me <U+017F>o lively a draft of <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and Merit, that laying a<U+017F>ide her indifferency in that bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he made an end of engaging me, in pre<U+017F>enting me with the Box of Diamonds. I thought at fir<U+017F>t that it had been a Watch: My Curio<U+017F>ity invited me to open it, but in lieu of a Watch Movement I found in it a Billet.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99165:25"/>
Honour made me immediately <U+017F>hut it up again, and return it to the Woman. I Counterfeited the Angry Body, yet would I gladly have been inform'd of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of that Billet, not doubting but that it was <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's,</hi> Declaration of Love, who began to plea<U+017F>e me. The Jewi<U+017F>h Woman who had too much of Experience not to di<U+017F>cern my feigning, did Pre<U+017F>s me to take the Box, I did it prote<U+017F>ting it was meerly in Complai<U+017F>ance, and to free me from her Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities.</p>
                  <p>I pulling out the Billet found under it a little Packet which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd a Selam, but becau<U+017F>e I can Read well, I in<U+017F>tantly open'd the Billet, which was expre<U+017F>s'd in the<U+017F>e Terms.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To See and to Love you Divine Gulbeas have been to me the <U+017F>ame thing. The Gods who have made you <U+017F>o Fair, ought to have made you
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99165:26"/>
more <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible al<U+017F>o, or not have po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd we with <U+017F>o much Love, and <U+017F>o little of hopes. My Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion is as Ancient as the knowledge which I have had of your Merit, and Time which Con<U+017F>umes all things has <U+017F>erv'd but to increa<U+017F>e it. There are pa<U+017F>s'd divers years <U+017F>ince I am no more my <U+017F>elf, and that I live but for you. I pa<U+017F>s both days and nights in that part of the Garden, where I did hear you Sing, and Play on your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truments, and from whence I did <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>pake to you. That place once the Confident of my Delights, is now the <U+017F>ame of my Sorrow, and will <U+017F>oon be that of my Death, if you cau<U+017F>e not my De<U+017F>tiny to alter, not being any longer capable of Life without <U+017F>eeing you. I am not Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the difficulty of the Attempt; but mo<U+017F>t Incomparable Beauty, if you will afford me but a little pitty, who Langui<U+017F>hes for you, and the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of ca<U+017F>ting my <U+017F>elf down at your Feet, leave all the re<U+017F>t to Prudent</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99165:26"/>
Boulla<U+017F>ters <hi>Cares, <U+017F>he will know how to manage my Bli<U+017F>s and your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Reading of this Billet gave me the Curio<U+017F>ity of unfolding the Selam. It was Compos'd of a grain of Grape, a little Race of Ginger, a <U+017F>mall piece of Cole, and Alum, lapp'd up in white and yellow Silk, which <U+017F>ignified as follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I wi<U+017F>h, My Eyes, that you were perfectly inform'd of that Love which I feel for you. It deprives me of my <U+017F>elf, and if you take not pitty of the Condition I am in, I <U+017F>hall Dye while you will enjoy an happy Life: Honour me with an An<U+017F>wer, and put an end to my <U+017F>ufferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though I feign'd not to be well pleas'd at this Declaration which I thought <U+017F>omething too free, my Heart was very well <U+017F>atisfied with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99165:27"/>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> Con<U+017F>tancy. It <U+017F>poke to me in his hehalf, and there needed not any great effects to per<U+017F>wade me of his Love, and to in<U+017F>pire in me <U+017F>ome tenderne<U+017F>s towards him.</p>
                  <p>The Jewi<U+017F>h Woman, who <U+017F>tudied my Countenance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Effects of the Letter, and of the Selam, did pre<U+017F>ently offer me the Jewels with which I was already adorn'd. My rea<U+017F>on, which was not yet wholly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd, made me to refu<U+017F>e them, and to Repre<U+017F>ent to her the wrong which it might do to my Reputation, <U+017F>hould the Sultane<U+017F>s di<U+017F>cover it, and that I could not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a pre<U+017F>ent that would be the cau<U+017F>e of my Ruine. At the <U+017F>ame time I undid tho<U+017F>e Jewels which I return'd her with the Box, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining nothing but the Letter and the Selam.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> who a long Practice had render'd expert, was of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that <U+017F>ometimes a too great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99165:27"/>
earne<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s, does impede the <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s which is mo<U+017F>t de<U+017F>ir'd, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to convince me by a means to which I could make no re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance.</p>
                  <p>She told me that my Beauty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ted with <U+017F>o powerful an Addition, I might plea<U+017F>e the Grand Segnior, and peradventure be made Sultane<U+017F>s. The Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Reigning, at lea<U+017F>t in an Emperors Heart, carried it above my Rea<U+017F>on, and made me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent to receive the Pre<U+017F>ent.</p>
                  <p>She would gladly have had me as ready to have receiv'd <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> in my Appartment: My Heart did not reject the propo<U+017F>ition, had not my rea<U+017F>on render'd me inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Finally after long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances and reiterated intreaties, I con<U+017F>ented to <U+017F>ee him in the Garden.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> could have wi<U+017F>h'd (to acquit her <U+017F>elf hand<U+017F>omly of her Commi<U+017F><U+017F>ion) that I had given her
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99165:28"/>
an An<U+017F>wer; Honour and Rea<U+017F>on oppos'd it, but Love did engage me to let him know by a Selam, that his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion was not unplea<U+017F>ing to me, it was lapp'd up in an Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif of Silk Embroider'd with Gold, wrought with my own Hand, after which the Woman retir'd, pretending before my Companions, who had <U+017F>urpris'd us in the Conver<U+017F>ation, that <U+017F>he left tho<U+017F>e Jewels with me, that I might <U+017F>hew them to the Sultane<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> impatient to learn the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of his enterpri<U+017F>e expected his Agents return, who made him an exact Relation of all that had pa<U+017F>s'd, and gave him that Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif which I had <U+017F>ent him.</p>
                  <p>The Joy which he re<U+017F>ented at the receit of this a<U+017F><U+017F>urance of the acceptance of his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, did Tran<U+017F>port him in <U+017F>uch manner, that without examining what it contain'd, he ki<U+017F>s'd it a thou<U+017F>and times, and water'd it with his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99165:28"/>
Tears, with the mo<U+017F>t tender Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ions, that Love could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> who would not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt him during the height of his Tran<U+017F>port, when he was come to him<U+017F>elf again a little, made him to take Notice of the Selam. It was <hi>I<U+017F>abella</hi> Silk, a Sprig of <hi>Je<U+017F><U+017F>emy,</hi> a little bit of Spunge, <U+017F>ome Time, and <U+017F>ome Mirtle.</p>
                  <p>I cannot expre<U+017F>s to you the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s of the Joy which <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd at it, it was <U+017F>o great that he was <U+017F>truck Speechle<U+017F>s, and that Rapture had la<U+017F>ted longer, if <hi>Boullaster,</hi> as Curious, as he was Contented, had not pre<U+017F>s'd him to give her the Expo<U+017F>ition of it. <hi>I accept your Vows,</hi> <U+017F>aid the Selam, <hi>be per<U+017F>waded of my Constancy, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you be <U+017F>o I pray Heaven to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tow you on me, and that our Souls may be in<U+017F>eparably joyn'd together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible mo<U+017F>t Amiable <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> <U+017F>aid <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> that my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99165:29"/>
is agreeable to, you is it not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecive me, and to Laugh at my Grief, that thus you <U+017F>eek to engage me further, and ki<U+017F><U+017F>ing the Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif, he <U+017F>aid, dear Pledge of the fidelity of <U+017F>he who I adore, will you be it al<U+017F>o of the <U+017F>incerity of her Heart. Then Addre<U+017F><U+017F>ing him<U+017F>elf to the Selam, and you Dumb Mouth, will you a<U+017F><U+017F>ure me the duration of her new Born Love?</p>
                  <p>He had <U+017F>aid more; but all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were Precious to prepare him<U+017F>elf for this Enterview.</p>
                  <p>The difficulty of this enterpri<U+017F>e did ca<U+017F>t him in a new Sorrow, and plung'd him in a Melancholy more profound then the former. He was in a di<U+017F>pair of finding in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> a Friend <U+017F>o faithful as to be tru<U+017F>ted with his Amours, and his Impatiency did increa<U+017F>e, <U+017F>till as he grew nearer the <U+017F>o de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ired time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99165:29"/>After he had much Tormented him<U+017F>elf on the means of bringing about his de<U+017F>ign, he remembred that there was a Ma<U+017F>ter Gardner nam'd, <hi>Ou<U+017F>ta Mehemet,</hi> who was greatly oblig'd to his Father, and that that con<U+017F>ideration, might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to do him Service, he re<U+017F>olv'd to find him out.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ou<U+017F>ta Mehemet,</hi> who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erv'd for <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> a natural Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, receiv'd him with Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trations of a perfect Friend<U+017F>hip, and great prote<U+017F>tations of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of the good Offices which he had receiv'd from the <hi>Ba<U+017F><U+017F>a,</hi> his Father.</p>
                  <p>Though <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> was <U+017F>atisfied of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemets</hi> fidelity, and that he doubted not but that though he <U+017F>hould not grant him the favour which he was about to ask of him, that he would however keep his <U+017F>ecret, he however exacted from him an Oath, on the Head of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, never to reveal that which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99165:30"/>
he would intru<U+017F>t him with, which he ea<U+017F>ily obtain'd from <hi>Mehemet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> di<U+017F>covered his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion to his Friend in <U+017F>uch <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Terms, and <U+017F>o pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing, that though he had not had any mind to <U+017F>erve him, it was no longer in his power to refu<U+017F>e him. <hi>I Love, mo<U+017F>t faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Mehemet, <hi>but what <U+017F>erves my Love, when that I cannot <U+017F>pake to the Object of my Vows. I Love a Fair One, Pri<U+017F>oner in this Place, the inward part of the</hi> Seraglio <hi>which is Guardian of this Trea<U+017F>ure, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t Penetrable, or at lea<U+017F>t the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s is <U+017F>o difficult, that it cannot be attempted without a great hazard; Yet that is not the thing which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> Me, <hi>my Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all limits would make me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake all things, if that <U+017F>he whom I Love would con<U+017F>ent to it. I have only obtain'd to <U+017F>ee her from a little Garden of Flowers which is ju<U+017F>t un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>e's Appartment. You,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99165:30"/>
My Dear</hi> Mehemet, <hi>mu<U+017F>t facilitate the entry of it to me, on you depends the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of this Enterpri<U+017F>e; I have Built on your Friend<U+017F>hip; and if ever you have lov'd, you will judge of the Importancy of the Service, and the greatne<U+017F>s of the Obligation, that I <U+017F>hall be indebted to you for it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That Declaration had made too great an Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion on this Old Mans Mind, the remembrance of tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>orders which a like Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion had formerly Caus'd in his Brea<U+017F>t, did make him conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cend with ea<U+017F>e to <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> reque<U+017F>t, without con<U+017F>idering the danger unto which he expos'd him<U+017F>elf, <U+017F>hould the intreague be di<U+017F>cover'd. He promi<U+017F>ed to introduce him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Gardiners habit, and that he had no more to do, but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve my appointed time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> did pre<U+017F>ently di<U+017F>patch <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> to the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> he gave her no Letter, his Joy was too
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99165:31"/>
great to permit him to write. He only gave her a <U+017F>mall Selam, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of a grain of <hi>Pomegranate</hi> a little piece of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nctious</hi> Wood, lapp'd in white Silk, a Gray-pea, a little piece of Suggar Cane, and the kernel of an Hazel Nut, all which did <U+017F>pake thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fire which your love has kindled in my Hearty, has reduc'd me to <U+017F>uch a Condition, that if you take not pitty of me and that if like the Sun, you enlighten not my mind, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>oon loo<U+017F>e that with my life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though I was highly po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd with Love, I had <U+017F>till <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>on left me, I wa<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> kept in with fear, I dreaded lea<U+017F>t the intreague <U+017F>hould be di<U+017F>cover'd, and that the Sultane<U+017F>s <U+017F>hould cau<U+017F>e me to be <U+017F>everely Puni<U+017F>h'd: Thus I would, yet would not, yet at la<U+017F>t I was forc'd to yeild to the <hi>Syrenes</hi> Enchantments. I promi<U+017F>s'd her that the next day at nine I would render my <U+017F>elf in alow room which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99165:31"/>
an<U+017F>wer'd on the Garden, and which was parted from it but by a Lattice Window, of which I <U+017F>hould open a <U+017F>mall wicket, which would be the <U+017F>ign of my coming, that that was the mo<U+017F>t favourable time, that the Sultane<U+017F>s did u<U+017F>ually re<U+017F>t, and her Women al<U+017F>o, after break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<U+017F>ts; and that all the Eunuchs were on the out<U+017F>ide of the Gate, to prevent all noi<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> had like to have dyed, at the receit of this news, which did cau<U+017F>e him <U+017F>ome re<U+017F>tle<U+017F><U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, through the apprehen<U+017F>ions that his ill Fortune might make him mi<U+017F>carry in this attempt. He pa<U+017F>s'd the whole night with terrible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehen<U+017F>ions, mixt of fear and hope.</p>
                  <p>He render'd him<U+017F>elf at the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> at the appointed hour. <hi>Mehemet</hi> caus'd him to change his rich habit for a Gardiners dre<U+017F>s, made of a cour<U+017F>e red Serge, with a cap a Foot long, of the <U+017F>ame
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99165:32"/>
Stuff. He put a Spade in his hand, and conducted him to the Garden ordering him to dig a border ju<U+017F>t under the Windows of that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment; at every <U+017F>troke the new Gardner would lift up his Eyes, to ob<U+017F>erve whither the wicket did open; but unluckily, the Sultane<U+017F>s being fallen a<U+017F>leep a little latter then u<U+017F>ually, the Gardner had lea<U+017F>ure to dig almo<U+017F>t all the border, before I could come to the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouz.</p>
                  <p>He was very impatient, as I was inform'd, he would <U+017F>ome time hear your great flyes, which <U+017F>eek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for pa<U+017F><U+017F>age would <U+017F>trike again<U+017F>t the Lattice, which made him fancy that I was looking and laughing at his <U+017F>lavery.</p>
                  <p>When I came near the Window, and that through the Lattice, I perceiv'd <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> with the Spade in his hand, I no longer doubted of the <U+017F>trength of his love, and though it was a little unea<U+017F>y to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99165:32"/>
me to <U+017F>ee a Per<U+017F>on of his Quality digging of the ground, to enjoy one moment the <U+017F>atisfaction of <U+017F>eeing me, it gave me a <U+017F>ecret joy, and without reflecting on what my ab<U+017F>ence might make him to <U+017F>uffer, I took a great delight in con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him without <U+017F>hewing my <U+017F>elf. But he having work'd a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable time, and that <U+017F>o har<U+017F>h an exerci<U+017F>e to <U+017F>o tender a Body, did oblige him, to re<U+017F>t often on his Spade, and to ca<U+017F>t up his Eyes from time to time on the place where I was to appear, I open'd the wicket, and <U+017F>aw <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> Pain to redouble, the Spade fell out of his hands, he remain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out motion, like a <U+017F>tatue, but by good Fortune he was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, <hi>Mehemet</hi> who had for<U+017F>een the con<U+017F>equences of this fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight, had <U+017F>et the Gardners at <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance, who were to have work'd in the <U+017F>ame place.</p>
                  <p>There is no greater trouble,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99165:33"/>
then to be in pre<U+017F>ence of that one loves, and not in power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ones grief. That which <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> did <U+017F>uffer by being depriv'd of <U+017F>peaking to me becau<U+017F>e of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of the Sultane<U+017F>s's appartment, was as trouble<U+017F>om to me as to him<U+017F>elf, and notwith<U+017F>tanding all the re<U+017F>ervedne<U+017F>s which I pretended to, I <U+017F>uffered no le<U+017F>s then he did. By good Fortune the Dumb Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which is very much us'd in this Court, and that we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly under<U+017F>tood, did <U+017F>o well <U+017F>upply the defects of our Voices, that we <U+017F>eparated well <U+017F>atisfied with one another. The Eyes, the motions of the face, the <U+017F>igns of the Fingers, and the ge<U+017F>tures of the Body, did all <U+017F>peak more then the mo<U+017F>t fluent tongue could have utter'd, which is frequently Dumb in <U+017F>uch occa<U+017F>ions, and <U+017F>ays nothing at all for having too much to <U+017F>ay. We did <U+017F>o plea<U+017F>e our <U+017F>elves in this conver<U+017F>ation, that it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99165:33"/>
had continu'd longer, if I had not heard <U+017F>ome treading in the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane<U+017F>s's</hi> appartment, which oblig'd me to make <U+017F>igns to <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> to retire; and <U+017F>o I <U+017F>hut the wicket.</p>
                  <p>During all our intreagues, <hi>Boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<U+017F>ter,</hi> who was now the confident of our mutual amours, made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>e Journeys to the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> I took no le<U+017F>s delight at the news of my lovely <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> then he did of his dear <hi>Gulbeas.</hi> He was very rich, and did promi<U+017F>e me to u<U+017F>e all his Endeavours, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all his Friends, to get me out of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and to marry me. This had not doubtle<U+017F>s deceiv'd my hopes, if a precipitated Death caus'd by the Plague had not depriv'd me of my only Joy.</p>
                  <p>Sobbs and <U+017F>ighs, mix'd with Tears, interrupted <hi>Gulbea's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the <U+017F>trength of her grief having di<U+017F>enabled her from fini<U+017F>hing, <U+017F>he intreated one of her Companions, to whom <U+017F>he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99165:34"/>
had di<U+017F>covered her <U+017F>ecret, to go on with the recital of a Death, which had co<U+017F>t her <U+017F>o many Tears. <hi>Patma,</hi> <U+017F>o was that good Friend call'd, continu'd <hi>G<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lbea's</hi> di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. The <hi>Jewi<U+017F>h</hi> Woman, did come twice or thrice a week to the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> though <U+017F>he <U+017F>ould but few things there; but <U+017F>he was <U+017F>ufficiently recompens'd by tho<U+017F>e lovers, who<U+017F>e pre<U+017F>ents did in a <U+017F>hort time make her very rich.</p>
                  <p>Their Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions grew beyond all limits, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> who was impatient at his Incomparable Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s's ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence, would attempt a <U+017F>econd enterview, in which he might freely, with a loud Voice and not by Dumb <U+017F>igns expre<U+017F>s the exce<U+017F>s of his love. He communicated his de<U+017F>ign to his confident, reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting large promi<U+017F>es if <U+017F>he had good <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s. She being won by the gains, did engage to omit nothing that might tend to his <U+017F>atisfaction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99165:34"/>She came to the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> gave <hi>Gulbeas</hi> a Selam put up in an <hi>Agath</hi> ve<U+017F><U+017F>el. It is to be confe<U+017F>s'd <U+017F>aid <hi>Patmas,</hi> that if love <U+017F>harpens Wit, it borders on folly al<U+017F>o, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> would engage his Mi<U+017F>tris with a rich pre<U+017F>ent. This Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el was Garni<U+017F>h'd with circles of Gold <U+017F>tudded with Diamonds, and he endeavour'd to convince her of her pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, by a Selam, compos'd of his Hairs, of Ro<U+017F>e colour Silk, of <hi>Aloes</hi> Wood, of <hi>Antimony,</hi> of Nutmeg, a Sprig of Broom, a grain of Grape, a <U+017F>mall peice of Cloth, and of Cole, all which put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether did <U+017F>ay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Precious Crown of all my wi<U+017F>hes, Nightingal who<U+017F>e Voice is only capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Charm the <U+017F>orrow of my Soul, true remedy of the Evils which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, con<U+017F>ider the Tears which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from my Eyes, while that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you are Laughing at my grief take pity on me, and behold the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in which you have brought
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99165:35"/>
me. I am ready to dye, if you honour me not with your writing, and if you give me not a po<U+017F>itive An<U+017F>wer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Selam, and the relation which <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> made to <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> of the mi<U+017F>erable condition that <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> was in, whom <U+017F>he repre<U+017F>ented to her, langui<U+017F>hing, and dying, did <U+017F>o move her, being put on with pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion and love, that <U+017F>he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ented to a <U+017F>econd enterview, the p<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce and manner, only, did trouble her, and <U+017F>he caus'd him <U+017F>ome by a little Selam, of a Gold Wyer, of a grain of Grape, of a grain of Millet, of a bit of white thred, and of a grain of Wheat, all which <U+017F>aid. <hi>Come my Eyes I am <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of your griefs, my Heart is yours, be per<U+017F>waded of my Constancy. Gulbeas</hi> would not con<U+017F>ent to <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e for his admittance into an appartment which was joyning that of the Sultane<U+017F>s; It was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99165:35"/>
a <U+017F>lippery <U+017F>tep, no le<U+017F>s then honour and life were at <U+017F>take. All tho<U+017F>e con<U+017F>iderations were powerful enough to brake off that de<U+017F>ign, if love who was the <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t had not overpois'd them. <hi>Gulbeas</hi> let her <U+017F>elf be won by <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter's</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wa<U+017F>ion, and gave her leave to bring <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> di<U+017F>guis'd like a Maiden.</p>
                  <p>Three days were employ'd in getting things ready, the rather becau<U+017F>e that too frequent vi<U+017F>its might have been <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected. They were <U+017F>o many Ages to the Amorous <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> for whom neat and proper Cloths were getting ready that his dre<U+017F>s an<U+017F>wering to the Beauty of his Face, where no Hair had yet appear'd the Guards might be with more ea<U+017F>e impos'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>The 4<hi>th.</hi> day <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter,</hi> and her pretended Daughter whom we will call <hi>Gevaher,</hi> which in the <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Language <U+017F>ignifies, Precious-Stone, came to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99165:36"/>
                     <hi>Seraglio.</hi> This She-Merchant who was well known, having told that who accompany'd her was her Daughter, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Black Eunuchs, who let them both enter.</p>
                  <p>Here <hi>Patma</hi> made a pau<U+017F>e, and beginning again with a langui<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accent, <U+017F>he <U+017F>aid, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf, what do<U+017F>t thou doe? you come to <U+017F>ee Gulbeas<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> you <U+017F>eek in her Eyes for a remedy to your Evils, you are going to find the end of them but after a very extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner, your pre<U+017F>ence <U+017F>hall cure her of the Plague which overcomes her, and by a <U+017F>trange counter-blow, you will take in, in approaching her, a Poy<U+017F>on, that <U+017F>hall kill you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of truth, continued <U+017F>he, The <hi>Jewi<U+017F>h</hi> Woman did introduce the fair <hi>Gevaher,</hi> into the dying <hi>Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bea's</hi> Chamber. Judge of the trouble that <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf in, and if the <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>al of <U+017F>uch an unexpected accident were not capable of breaking all
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99165:36"/>
the mea<U+017F>ures of this di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>There little wanted but that he di<U+017F>cover'd him<U+017F>elf, but <hi>Gulbeas</hi> who <U+017F>till pre<U+017F>erv'd a <U+017F>ound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the rigour of her di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, which was at the third day, did intreat her companions, to leave her one moment alone with this <hi>Jewi<U+017F>h</hi> Woman, to <U+017F>ettle <U+017F>ome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts which they had together.</p>
                  <p>When that <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> found him<U+017F>elf alone near <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> he gave full <U+017F>cope to his grief, and forgeting the place he was in, he tore of his vail, and cleav'd to the Beds Head of the <U+017F>ick Per<U+017F>on, who he bathed with his Tears not being able to <U+017F>peak one word. <hi>Gulbeas</hi> on her <U+017F>ide did receive <U+017F>uch pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing <U+017F>trokes of love, with the angui<U+017F>h of her di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, that it cau<U+017F>ing a great revolution in her Body, a Chri<U+017F>is was produc'd, which <U+017F>aved her life, and gave <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> his death who could not be per<U+017F>waded to quit the Boul<U+017F>ter, where he took in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99165:37"/>
the <U+017F>team of a Malignant <U+017F>weat, which peirc'd him to the very Heart, and caus'd him to fall in a fainting Fit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boullaster</hi> <U+017F>trangly confus'd at the <U+017F>wooning of her pretended Daughter, and much more at the con<U+017F>equences that the unraveling of this intreague might produce in ca<U+017F>e that the illne<U+017F>s increa<U+017F>ing, <U+017F>he had been oblig'd to be put into a bed, call'd me to a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t her.</p>
                  <p>When I came in, the feigned <hi>Gevaher</hi> began to breath and to <U+017F>igh, turning her Eyes towards <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> who<U+017F>e name <U+017F>he <U+017F>poke with <U+017F>uch a tender and amourous accent, that I wonder how I perceiv'd it not, I reflected not on it, and did attribute it to an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent acquaintance, that which was a pure effect of love.</p>
                  <p>It pa<U+017F>s'd not <U+017F>o with <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter,</hi> <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o <U+017F>urpris'd that all her <U+017F>en<U+017F>es fled from her, and her face grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pale <U+017F>he fell in a <U+017F>woon, <U+017F>o that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99165:37"/>
I was left alone very bu<U+017F>y, and concern'd. I brought the Daughter near to <hi>Gulbeas</hi>'s Bed, and run to the Mother who was not long fainted, when both were recover'd of their <U+017F>woon, I went to prepare <U+017F>omething for them to take.</p>
                  <p>The Amorous <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> made u<U+017F>e of that moment to <U+017F>ay <U+017F>ome few things to his Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s, which he pronounc'd with a Langui<U+017F>hing Voice. Death, <hi>which per<U+017F>ues me,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>is a le<U+017F>s trouble to me, adorable</hi> Gulbeas, <hi>then the pain which I feel for what you endure. I <U+017F>hould run to it with Plea<U+017F>ure, if I thought it would ea<U+017F>e you, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>waded of it, and that I had rather dye, then abandon you, If I did not expo<U+017F>e you, by my <U+017F>tay here to a danger greater then your Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. I retire, but I retire to dye, not being able to re<U+017F>ist <U+017F>o much <U+017F>orrow. Gulbeas</hi> overcome with the <U+017F>trength of her di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, peirc'd to the quick at <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>oufs</hi> illne<U+017F>s, and weakned with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99165:38"/>
the violence of her Cri<U+017F>is, could not an<U+017F>wer tho<U+017F>e tender a<U+017F><U+017F>urances but with Tears, which made her faint away. Here it was that Poor <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> had need of his whole <U+017F>tock of rea<U+017F>on, to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t <U+017F>o much Grief, and yet Act nothing that might betray the <U+017F>ecret, he was forc'd to re<U+017F>t contented with <U+017F>ighs, which were attributed to his late fainting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gulbeas</hi> was long in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and beginning to Breath again, <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> who fear'd <U+017F>ome new accident, endeavour'd all <U+017F>he could to bring back <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf,</hi> from his afflicted Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>He could not re<U+017F>olve on <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>ad <U+017F>eparation, which he fore<U+017F>aw would be eternal; He would fain have expir'd near what he lov'd, yet he was forc'd to obey his Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s's orders, who made <U+017F>igns to him, not being able to <U+017F>pake, and gave him her hand, which he ki<U+017F>s'd, prote<U+017F>ting that he would not out live her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99165:38"/>All tho<U+017F>e accidents which had accompanyed <U+017F>o <U+017F>ad an enterview, was not <U+017F>ufficient to overcome our unfortunate Lovers. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd that pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing by one of the doors of the <hi>Seraglio</hi> where there <U+017F>tands <hi>Baltadges,</hi> which are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain varlets from without, that one of them di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>ting the feigned <hi>Gevahers</hi> going, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come carele<U+017F>s through her grief and pain; fancy'd it a di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>top'd <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> by the arm; <hi>Boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<U+017F>ter,</hi> who<U+017F>e Wit was always at hand, without <U+017F>peaking to the <hi>Baltadgj,</hi> for fear of bringing more to them, drawing near, dropt into his hand a ring which <U+017F>he pull'd of her own Finger, and pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing his hand <U+017F>he thereby oblig'd him to give liberty to this poor Lover to get out, who thought much le<U+017F>s on the pre<U+017F>ent accident then on <hi>Gulbea's</hi> troubles.</p>
                  <p>So <U+017F>oon as <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> was return'd to his Palace, he went to his Bed,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99165:39"/>
his Feaver increas'd, and finding him<U+017F>elf pre<U+017F>s'd with that di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e which kill'd him, he would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy that little time he had to live, in taking leave of his dear Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s, and to give her his la<U+017F>t farewell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I dye for you, Incomparable</hi> Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas, <hi>and Death is the more plea<U+017F>ing to me, becau<U+017F>e I hope that its Cau<U+017F>e which was your Cri<U+017F>is, will be that of the prolongation of your days. I <U+017F>hould dye without trouble, had I the certain news of it. The di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e pre<U+017F><U+017F>es upon me, and I employ that little time which is left me, in giving you te<U+017F>timonies of a love which I <U+017F>hall carry to my grave: happy if that la<U+017F>t moment can better convince you then divers Years of Sighs and Tears have done. Adieu, all lovely, live and remember that the <U+017F>ame love which re<U+017F>tores you to Life is the Cau<U+017F>e of my Death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No <U+017F>ooner had he ended his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99165:39"/>
Letter, but he immediately <U+017F>ent it with the Ring on his Finger, in which his Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s's name and his were Ingraven on a very clear Ruby, to <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter,</hi> and was pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>eis'd with a di<U+017F>turbance in his head, and a redoubling of his Feaver, which depriv'd him of his Sen<U+017F>es and Speech, which never return'd again but with the la<U+017F>t <U+017F>igh, which he vented, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the lovely name of his Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gulbeas,</hi> who<U+017F>e Cri<U+017F>is had put out of all Danger, the <U+017F>weat having Di<U+017F><U+017F>ipated the Tumors of the Plague, was more Di<U+017F>temper'd in the Mind then the Body, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> <U+017F>ilence, and <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter's</hi> <U+017F>tay from giving her an Account of all that had pa<U+017F>s'd, <U+017F>ince their parting, did <U+017F>trangly Perplex her, and giving her <U+017F>ad Warnings of what was coming, <U+017F>he felt mo<U+017F>t mortal di<U+017F>quiets, <U+017F>he would Weep all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99165:40"/>
Day, and the Night was pa<U+017F>s'd in Watchings, or in Terrible Vi<U+017F>ions, which foretold her nothing but tho<U+017F>e Dangers which <U+017F>he fear'd. The <U+017F>ame night that <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> expir'd, <U+017F>he thought that a Woman of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious height, as Lean as a Skelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and of a frightful Deformity, her Hairs <U+017F>pread abroad approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with the Face of a Fury, a great Knif in her Hand, was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her <U+017F>ide, and pulling out her Heart. All tho<U+017F>e Nocturnal Vi<U+017F>ions, Augmented her Sorrows. She had made Choice of me for her Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ever <U+017F>ince <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> adventure, I did endeavour to Divert her, and turn her off of all tho<U+017F>e Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Thoughts, nothing could Admini<U+017F>ter Comfort to her; But it was much wor<U+017F>s, when <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> came to the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> <U+017F>ome days after <hi>I<U+017F>soufs</hi> Death, to acquit her <U+017F>elf of the la<U+017F>t Commi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, which he had given her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99165:40"/>So <U+017F>oon as <U+017F>he did <U+017F>ee her, <U+017F>he earne<U+017F>tly Inform'd her <U+017F>elf of <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> welfare; but the Jewi<U+017F>h Woman's <U+017F>ilence, who could not di<U+017F><U+017F>emble, nor keep in her Tears, gave her ea<U+017F>ily to under<U+017F>tand that truth which <U+017F>he fear'd to learn, Ah! Cry'd <U+017F>he, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf</hi> is no longer in being! and pre<U+017F>ently fell in my Arms in a Swoon.</p>
                  <p>When <U+017F>he was come to her <U+017F>elf again, <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> Letter and Ring which <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> put into her Hands, not being able to <U+017F>peak one word, did Confirm that Sorrowful News, She Divers times ki<U+017F>s'd tho<U+017F>e dear Pledges of <hi>I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf's</hi> eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tancy, Water'd them with her Tears, and did hang the Ring at her Neck, as a Mark that <U+017F>he Devouted her <U+017F>elf to her Lover's Gho<U+017F>t; and having remain'd <U+017F>ometime without Speech, her Face from Pale as it was, became Red, and as if <U+017F>he were become Furious.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99165:41"/>
                     <hi>Fatal De<U+017F>tiny,</hi> cry'd <U+017F>he, <hi>thou Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me my Life in killing what I Love, and thou <U+017F>elle<U+017F>t me very dear, that which I can no longer Love, <U+017F>eeing that he, with whom I de<U+017F>ign'd to <U+017F>hare it, is no more. Why did<U+017F>t thou not kill me, or why did<U+017F>t thou Conduct him here, that I might be further oblig'd to him of my Life? after <U+017F>o many Services <U+017F>o ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, I will no longer Live after <U+017F>uch an Accident; Alas! what will Life <U+017F>ignifie to me, after that he, who Animated me is Dead. No</hi> I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf, <hi>I de<U+017F>ign'd not to Live but for you, and I <U+017F>hould be unworthy of your Love <U+017F>hould I have any other thoughts. That Death which was to have taken me off, has not <U+017F>pared me, in taking of you. It has doubly <U+017F>lain me in depriving me of what I Love, and permitting me to Linger out a Mi<U+017F>erable Life, which <U+017F>hall be but a Continual Death. You Live</hi> I<U+017F><U+017F>ouf, <hi>and your most happy <U+017F>hade, enjoys at pre<U+017F>ent the Plea<U+017F>ures of the</hi> Eli<U+017F>icum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99165:41"/>
                     <hi>and I <U+017F>hall never cea<U+017F>e Dying till I am reunited to you. Then Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<U+017F><U+017F>ing her <U+017F>elf to the Ring. This Ring, continu'd <U+017F>he, <U+017F>hall be henceforth the Faithful witne<U+017F>s of my Love, and <U+017F>eeing it could not <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nite our Bodies during our Lives, it <U+017F>hall be the indi<U+017F><U+017F>o lubbiletye of our Wills, and the Mark with which I will appear before you, I will continually wear it in my Bo<U+017F>om, and it <U+017F>hall Accompany me in my Grave, <U+017F>eeing you could not have any other thought, when you <U+017F>ent it me at your Death, than that of uniting me more <U+017F>trictly to you in the other World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She had continu'd, and gone on further with her Complaints, if the pre<U+017F>ence of our Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, had not interrupted their Cour<U+017F>e and oblig'd <hi>Boulla<U+017F>ter</hi> to retreat. The Grief for his Death brought her into a Lingering Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which has caus'd that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>hing Condition you <U+017F>ee her in,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99165:42"/>
and of which there is no likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood <U+017F>he will ever be Cured, the cau<U+017F>e of her illne<U+017F>s being too dear to her.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99165:42"/>
                  <p>THE <hi>Fatal Beauty</hi> OF <hi>AGNES de CASTRO</hi>; Taken out of the HISTORY OF Portugal.</p>
                  <p>Made <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> out of <hi>French</hi> By <hi>P.B. G.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="unk">
                        <body>
                           <div type="license">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Licen<U+017F>ed,</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <date>
                                    <hi>May</hi> 19th. 1688.</date>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rinted for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>el-<U+017F>treet,</hi> in <hi>Common-Garden.</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99165:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99165:43"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>TO give an advantageous Character of this Novel, there needed but to name the Per<U+017F>on that Compos'd it. The great Succe<U+017F>s which all the Ingenious Works which, She has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, have had, would be <U+017F>ufficient to put an E<U+017F>teem on this, and none can doubt of its worth after the great Approbations that have been given to all the rest. But in this Particular I am not Permitted to Satisfie the Curio<U+017F>ity of the Publick. Her Will oppo<U+017F>es it <U+017F>elf unto that Glory that She might ju<U+017F>tly pretend from it, and She does re<U+017F>t <U+017F>atisfied with the bare Secret Delight which She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, in that which She Pro<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ares to the Ingenious. Yet I believe not that all Her Cautiou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s can Conceal Her from the knowing. The Nicety
<pb facs="tcp:99165:44"/>
of the Sentiments, the Towr of the Conceptions, the clear and ea<U+017F>ie Stile, all does here Con<U+017F>pire to Her Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. The Virtue of three as Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<U+017F>trious as Unfortunate Per<U+017F>ons, which Vye with one another who <U+017F>hall mo<U+017F>t overcome them<U+017F>elves in Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of Souls, Produces in the Heart <U+017F>uch Motions of Tenderne<U+017F>s and of Pitty as do extreamly Delight. The Character of that Nation, which makes the Subject of this Novel, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <U+017F>o Natural that it will not be Difficult to Believe the Truth of the Principal Events. Tho<U+017F>e that have Read the <hi>Portugal</hi> Hy<U+017F>tory, will agree to it, and I need not make any stay here to Prove it. I <U+017F>hall only <U+017F>ay, that if an Ingenious Fiction, has Power to exite and stir up our Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, a Truth <U+017F>o well Penn'd, as this is, will not fail of moving the lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Per<U+017F>ons, and to draw <U+017F>uch Tears from them, as they would gladly let fall.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99165:44"/>
                  <head>THE <hi>Fatal Beauty</hi> OF <hi>AGNES</hi> de <hi>CASTRO.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THough Love promi<U+017F>es no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Plea<U+017F>ures, the Effects of it are <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>ad. A Tender hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s is not <U+017F>ufficient to attain to a Perfect Happine<U+017F>s; and that <hi>Capricious</hi> Fortune which cro<U+017F><U+017F>es all things, has but very little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate Hearts, when She is in the Humour of producing <U+017F>trange Adventures.</p>
                  <p>Divers Examples of the pa<U+017F>s'd Ages prove the Certainty of this Maxim; But the Reign of <hi>Don, Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> the 4<hi>th.</hi> of that Name King of <hi>Portugal</hi> does furni<U+017F>h us with one the mo<U+017F>t Extraordinary.</p>
                  <p>He was the Son of that <hi>Don Denis,</hi> who<U+017F>e Enterpri<U+017F>es did <U+017F>o well <U+017F>ucceed, that it was <U+017F>aid of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99165:45"/>
him, he did all that he would, and of <hi>I<U+017F>abella</hi> of <hi>Aragon</hi> a Prince<U+017F>s of an Eminent Virtue. After he had inherited a Flouri<U+017F>hing and quiet E<U+017F>tate he Endeavoured to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in it both Plenty and Peace, by all means imaginable.</p>
                  <p>To that end he fix'd the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of his Son <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> who was but eight years old, with <hi>Blanch</hi> Daughter to <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> King of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tile,</hi> who the Young Prince did Marry at <U+017F>ixteeen. She brought along with her at <hi>Coimbria</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Infirmities, and but a few Agreements. <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who had a <U+017F>tock of Mildne<U+017F>s and of Bounty, notwith<U+017F>tanding all tho<U+017F>e incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, did live in good intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with her; But at la<U+017F>t tho<U+017F>e inconveniences being degenerated into a <hi>Paralitic</hi> Di<U+017F>temper, and <hi>Blanch</hi> her<U+017F>elf being de<U+017F>irous of a retreat the <hi>Pope</hi> did annul the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. The Prince<U+017F>s did confine in Solitude all her Langui<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and the Prince for whom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99165:45"/>
other Nuptials had been prepar'd, did marry <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia Manuel,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Don <hi>John Manuel,</hi> Prince of the Blood of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tile,</hi> and famous for that re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, which he made to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> had been promi<U+017F>ed to the King of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tile</hi>; but he break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Word, <U+017F>he was given to a young Prince, who was once to reign over a con<U+017F>iderable number of fair Provinces. He was but in his twenty fifth year, and the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome<U+017F>t Man of all <hi>Spain</hi>: with the mo<U+017F>t advantageous Qualities of the Body, he po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t tho<U+017F>e of the Soul, and in all things, he did prove him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf worthy of that Crown, which was appointed for him.</p>
                  <p>The Prince<U+017F>s <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> was Beautiful, Spirituous, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as much as any Woman in the World, her Merit ought to have Captivated <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he had for her an E<U+017F>teem mix'd with re<U+017F>pect; which might have pa<U+017F>s'd for Love with the le<U+017F>s
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99165:46"/>
Penetrating Per<U+017F>ons. Mean time his more real Flames were re<U+017F>erv'd for another Beauty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> brought forth a Son in the fir<U+017F>t Year of her Marriage; who was Named <hi>Don Louis,</hi> and who <U+017F>carce had the time to di<U+017F>cern the light; The lo<U+017F>s of him did cau<U+017F>e her to feel many Sorrows; but that cold indifferency which <U+017F>he ob<U+017F>erv'd in tho<U+017F>e Cares which her Husband did be<U+017F>tow on her, was much more <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible to her. It had not been difficult for her to give her<U+017F>elf wholly to her Duty, and to <U+017F>ingularly cleave to his tender Affections, but that power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Intere<U+017F>t which bound her <U+017F>o <U+017F>trictly unto the Prince of <hi>Portugal,</hi> did open her Eyes on his actions, where <U+017F>he could not find any thing that was Natural, and that could <U+017F>atisfiy her Nicety.</p>
                  <p>At fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>he thought <U+017F>he had deceived her<U+017F>elf; but time having confirm'd what <U+017F>he fear'd, <U+017F>he did <U+017F>ecretly <U+017F>igh for it, and had <U+017F>o much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99165:46"/>
Con<U+017F>ideration for the Prince as to give him but <U+017F>ome obliging marks of her Sorrow, which <U+017F>he could not Conceal from <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> who lived with her, and the Prince<U+017F>s Affection did di<U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>h her from all the other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <p>This Maiden <U+017F>o dear to the Prince<U+017F>s, did well de<U+017F>erve that preference which <U+017F>he gave her. She was exce<U+017F><U+017F>ively Beautiful, wi<U+017F>e, di<U+017F>creet, Spirituous, and more Affectionate for <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> then <U+017F>he was for her own Intere<U+017F>t, having left her Family, who<U+017F>e name was <hi>Illu<U+017F>trious,</hi> and that did hold a very Con<U+017F>iderable rank, to give her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf wholly to the Prince<U+017F>s, and to follow her into <hi>Portugal.</hi> It was in her bo<U+017F>om that <U+017F>he poured forth her fir<U+017F>t Sorrow, and the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Agnes</hi> omitted nothing that could Admini<U+017F>ter Comfort to her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> was not the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on which Complained of <hi>Don
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99165:47"/>
Pedre,</hi> before the Divorce of <hi>Blanch,</hi> he had expre<U+017F>'d <U+017F>ome Tenderne<U+017F>s towards <hi>Elvira Gonca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> Si<U+017F>ter to <hi>Don Alvar Goncales,</hi> Favorite to the King of <hi>Portugal</hi>; and that Amu<U+017F>ement of the Princes younge<U+017F>t Years, having made a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion on <hi>Elvira,</hi> who<U+017F>e Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition had been flatter'd by <hi>Blanche</hi>'s Infirmities, <U+017F>he had <U+017F>een <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s her place, with a <U+017F>ecret Rage, and to be Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s of Sufficiency of Charms to take from her all to the la<U+017F>t hopes.</p>
                  <p>Her Jealou<U+017F>y left her not long i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; <U+017F>he examin'd all the Prince's Actions, and without difficulty did unravel the Cau<U+017F>e of that indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, which he had for his Spou<U+017F>e: But that did not bring him back to her, and it was with great pre<U+017F>um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, that <U+017F>he mi<U+017F>tru<U+017F>ted <U+017F>ome new Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion in him, which <U+017F>he promi<U+017F>ed to her <U+017F>elf to thwart <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon a<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould find it out. She had a mind that was very fit for bold Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, and her Brothers Credit did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99165:47"/>
rai<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch a pride in her, that all the Princes indifferency was not capable to humble.</p>
                  <p>He did langui<U+017F>h, and none could gue<U+017F>s at the Cau<U+017F>e, he had no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger any reli<U+017F>h for public Sports, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary conver<U+017F>ations were unea<U+017F>y, and <U+017F>olitude only had <U+017F>ome power over him; this change <U+017F>urpris'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very body, Don <hi>Alfon<U+017F>o,</hi> who lov'd his Son, de<U+017F>ign'd to di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e him about it; but the Prince gave no other An<U+017F>wer, than, that it was an effect of his Temper.</p>
                  <p>All this while, time did pa<U+017F>s, and the Prince<U+017F>s was deliver'd of a <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Son, who liv'd and was nam'd <hi>Ferdinando.</hi> Don <hi>Pedre</hi> did force him<U+017F>elf a little to ta<gap reason="illegible: blotted" resp="#PDCC" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> a <U+017F>hare in the public Joy. It was believ'd that the humour was going to alter; but that glimp<U+017F>e of a Calm la<U+017F>ted not long, and he <U+017F>oon did relap<U+017F>e into his deep Melancholly.</p>
                  <p>The plotting <hi>Elvira</hi> was ince<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>antly agitated, in <U+017F>eeking after the Knowledg of his Secret. Chance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99165:48"/>
labour'd for her in it. One day, that <U+017F>he was walking of her fury in the Palace's Gardens, <U+017F>he found the Prince of <hi>Portugal</hi> a<U+017F>leep in an ob<U+017F>cure <hi>Grotto.</hi> Her Fury could not hold again<U+017F>t that Object. She ca<U+017F>t her Eyes on him, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that in <U+017F>pight of <U+017F>leep <U+017F>ome Tears did <U+017F>teal from his Eyes. That <U+017F>hare which he <U+017F>till had in her heart, had no hard task to <U+017F>often it; but <U+017F>he heard him <U+017F>igh, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to expre<U+017F>s the<U+017F>e ill articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Words: Yes, divine <hi>Agnes,</hi> I will dye before I di<U+017F>cover it, and <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> <U+017F>hall have no Cau<U+017F>e to reproach you any thing. <hi>Elvira</hi> was <U+017F>eis'd with horror at that di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e, which pre<U+017F>ently repre<U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her Imagination <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro</hi> with all her charms, and not doubting but that it was <U+017F>he who po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t Don <hi>Pedre</hi>'s heart, <U+017F>he felt more hatred again<U+017F>t that Rival, than <U+017F>he had of Tenderne<U+017F>s for him. The <hi>Grotto</hi> was no <U+017F>it place to make Reflections in, and to form
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99165:48"/>
de<U+017F>igns. Perhaps that her fir<U+017F>t tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port had caus'd her to have awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Prince, had <U+017F>he not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd under his hand a Paper, which <U+017F>he <U+017F>eis'd, and that <U+017F>he might not be <U+017F>urpris'd reading of it, <U+017F>he went forth with as much diligence as emotion.</p>
                  <p>When <U+017F>he was got to her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <U+017F>he open'd the Paper trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and in it found the<U+017F>e Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es writ with Don <hi>Pedre</hi>'s own hand, which it is likely he had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compos'd.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>De<U+017F>i<U+017F>t, Torment no more my Heart,</l>
                     <l>Honour, and Sacred Rights, chief con<U+017F>erns of my Glory</l>
                     <l>Love whi<U+017F>pers me another <U+017F>tory.</l>
                     <l>And I yeild to his Conquering Art.</l>
                     <l>Ye <U+017F>eeming over la<U+017F>ting ties,</l>
                     <l>Conspell'd engagements, Oaths Love never made,</l>
                     <l>You mu<U+017F>t all, at his feet be laid</l>
                     <l>As a Mo<U+017F>t humble Sacrifice.</l>
                     <l>Dear Prince<U+017F>s, you, to whom my Faith is due,</l>
                     <l>Pardon my over-ruling Fate,</l>
                     <l>'Tis confe<U+017F>s'd, I de<U+017F>erve your hate.</l>
                     <l>'La<U+017F>s! tis my Star renders me fal<U+017F>e to you.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99165:49"/>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> knew well <hi>Don Pedre's</hi> Writing, and was not Ignorant that he made Ver<U+017F>es, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erving the <U+017F>ad part that <hi>Hymen</hi> Acted in tho<U+017F>e which was fallen into her hands, She Scrupled not to produce them to the Prince<U+017F>s: That <U+017F>he might not be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected, She appeared not in the lea<U+017F>t; but it being not <U+017F>ufficient to cau<U+017F>e <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> to ob<U+017F>erve how little her Husband Lov'd her, and that it was nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary al<U+017F>o, to inform her, that he was become <hi>Agnes de Castros,</hi> Slave, <hi>Elvira</hi> caus'd the<U+017F>e few Words, in an Unknown Hand, to be Writ under the Princes Ver<U+017F>es, where there was a <U+017F>uffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <U+017F>pace.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sleep betray'd this unlucky Lover</l>
                     <l>Compell'd his own Lips to di<U+017F>cover,</l>
                     <l>The very Dictates of his Heart,</l>
                     <l>Declaring, <hi>Agnes,</hi> makes it Smart.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> did not much <U+017F>tick on the Nicety of Poetry in the la<U+017F>t Ver<U+017F>es, and provided, they had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99165:49"/>
but the Effect which <U+017F>he wi<U+017F>h'd for, <U+017F>he requir'd no more.</p>
                  <p>Her Impatiency would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to <U+017F>tay till the next day to Publi<U+017F>h them. She went to the Prince<U+017F>s Apartment, who was gone forth to walk, and pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing to her very Clo<U+017F>et without being perceiv'd, <U+017F>he conveyed the Paper in a Book which the Prince<U+017F>s did u<U+017F>ually read, and Retired very well <U+017F>atisfy'd with her good Succe<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>So <U+017F>oon as <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, <U+017F>he went into her Clo<U+017F>et, where <U+017F>he found the Book open and in it tho<U+017F>e Ver<U+017F>es that <U+017F>hould co<U+017F>t her <U+017F>o dear. The Prince's Character was well known to her; but be<U+017F>ides the cruel Confirmation of all that <U+017F>he had feared, <U+017F>he learn'd that it was <hi>Agnes</hi> of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ole Friend<U+017F>hip could con<U+017F>olate her Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who was the cau<U+017F>e of it. She did Read an hundred times over the <U+017F>ame thing, <U+017F>eeking to belye her own Eyes and Rea<U+017F>on; but perceiving too well that <U+017F>he was not deceiv'd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99165:50"/>
and con<U+017F>ulting her Thoughts on this Adventure, <U+017F>he found her <U+017F>elf much more po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t with Sorrow then with Anger, when <U+017F>he con<U+017F>ider'd that <hi>Don Pedre</hi> as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous as he was, had <U+017F>till pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erv'd his Love in Secrecy. After having pittyed him without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, her natural tenderne<U+017F>s did cau<U+017F>e her to <U+017F>hed a deluge of Tears, and did in<U+017F>pire her with the de<U+017F>ign of concealing all her Grief.</p>
                  <p>She had certainly done it by the Power of an Extraordinary Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, had not the Prince enter'd with extream ha<U+017F>t, he mi<U+017F><U+017F>ing his Ver<U+017F>es at his awaking, and fearing they <U+017F>hould light into Indi<U+017F>creet Hands, he came into the Palace di<U+017F>turb'd with this Lo<U+017F>s, came to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> ob<U+017F>erv'd her Humid Eyes, and <U+017F>tay'd his own on tho<U+017F>e unlucky Ver<U+017F>es, which had newly e<U+017F>cap'd from his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
                  <p>He pre<U+017F>ently grew Pale, and appear'd <U+017F>o Concern'd that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99165:50"/>
Generous Princes was more <U+017F>en<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his then of her own Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune: Madam, <U+017F>aid he, with Amazement, whence have you that Paper? It cannot come but from <U+017F>ome Enemy of your quiet and mine, reply'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> it is the Work of your own Hand, My Lord, and doubtle<U+017F>s of the Motion of your Heart al<U+017F>o; but fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if my Tenderne<U+017F>s would make it pa<U+017F>s for a Crime, that <U+017F>ame Tenderne<U+017F>s which nothing can alter, would prevent it in me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Moderation did <U+017F>erve but to render the Prince more Confounded. How Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous you are Madam continu'd he, and how Unfortunate am I! Some Tears did Accompany tho<U+017F>e Words, and the Prince<U+017F>s who Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionately Lov'd him, was <U+017F>o <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly mov'd with them that for along <U+017F>pace they both remain'd Mute. At la<U+017F>t <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> broke <U+017F>ilence, and <U+017F>hewing him, what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99165:51"/>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> had caus'd to be added; You have betray'd your <U+017F>elf, My Lord, continu'd <U+017F>he, you have been over-heard, and your Secret is known. It was in that very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the Princes whole Strength did Abandon him, and that his pre<U+017F>ent Condition became worthy of Compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion. He could not forgive him<U+017F>elf that Unvolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Crime which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted again<U+017F>t the Amiable Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Agnes</hi>; and though he was convinc'd of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Bounty, the Vexation which this Prudent, and Mode<U+017F>t Maid might receive from his Conduct, did carry it above all other Con<U+017F>iderations.</p>
                  <p>The Prince<U+017F>s who was exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him with her Eyes, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <U+017F>o many marks of de<U+017F>pair on his Face, that <U+017F>he fear'd the effects of it, and obligingly holding forth her hand to him; I promi<U+017F>e you, my Lord, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, that I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver complain of you, and that <hi>Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> <U+017F>hall ever be dear to me. You
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99165:51"/>
<U+017F>hall not find me inclin'd to make you reproaches; and not being capable of po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ing your heart, Il'e re<U+017F>t <U+017F>atisfyed in endeavouring to render my <U+017F>elf worthy of it. <hi>Don Pedre</hi> more concern'd than before, bowed a Knee before <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> ki<U+017F>s'd with re<U+017F>pect that hand which <U+017F>he had given him, and, perhaps did forget <hi>Agnes</hi> for a moment.</p>
                  <p>But Love did <U+017F>oon put a <U+017F>top to the<U+017F>e <U+017F>mall Progre<U+017F><U+017F>es of <hi>Hymen,</hi> That fatal Planet which did predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate over Don <hi>Pedre</hi>'s Fate, had not yet <U+017F>pent all it's malignity; and one moment of <hi>Agnes</hi> his <U+017F>ight, <U+017F>oon added new Forces to his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
                  <p>That fair Maids con<U+017F>ent had had no <U+017F>hare in her victory, her eyes were exact and di<U+017F>cerning, but they <U+017F>ought not in the Prince<U+017F>s eyes, for that which they would have di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to her.</p>
                  <p>She never did u<U+017F>e to be long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tant from <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> wherefore Don <hi>Pedre</hi> was no <U+017F>ooner gone out of the Clo<U+017F>et but <U+017F>he came into it,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99165:52"/>
and finding the Prince<U+017F>s mov'd and melting, <U+017F>he doubted not but that <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ome ju<U+017F>t Cau<U+017F>e of Sorrow; <U+017F>he put her <U+017F>elf in the <U+017F>ame po<U+017F>ture, that the Prince had been but a moment before, and expre<U+017F><U+017F>ing her di<U+017F>turbance with concerned Looks, Madam, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, in the name of your Bounties, conceal not from me the Cau<U+017F>e of that Trouble I find in you. Alas! <hi>Agnes,</hi> reply'd the beautiful Prince<U+017F>s, what is it you would know, and what am I to tell you? The Prince is in Love. That hand which he once gave me, was no pre<U+017F>ent of his heart, and all the advantage of this Allyance, will but make me the Sacrifice. The Prince in Love! reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> with an Amazement mixt with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation: And what Fatal Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can di<U+017F>pute with yours the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of an heart <U+017F>o ju<U+017F>tly due to you? Ah! Madam, all my re<U+017F>pect cannot hinder me from murmuring again<U+017F>t him. Do not accu<U+017F>e him of any thing, reply'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99165:52"/>
<U+017F>trives all that he can, and I am more oblig'd to his endeavouring to remain faithful to me, than if I really did enjoy his affections. It is not <U+017F>ufficient to fight for to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and the Prince does more in that di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition he finds him<U+017F>elf in, than I ought to have hoped for. In fine, he is my Husband, an amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Husband, to which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting, but that which I have not been able to in<U+017F>pire in him, that is, a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which had rendred me too happy. Ah! Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, cryed out <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> tran<U+017F>ported with her affection for <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi>: He is a blind Prince, who knows not the precious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which he po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es. It mu<U+017F>t needs be that he knows more, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Prince<U+017F>s, mode<U+017F>tly: But Madam, continued <hi>Agnes,</hi> is there any thing either in <hi>Portugal,</hi> or in all <hi>Spain,</hi> that can be compar'd to you? And not to reckon on the Qualities of your Per<U+017F>on, can tho<U+017F>e of your mind be <U+017F>ufficiently prais'd?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99165:53"/>
—My Dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> replyed the Prince<U+017F>s <U+017F>ighing, <U+017F>he that takes my Husbands heart from me, has but too much wherewith to plead his Excu<U+017F>e, <U+017F>eeing it is of thee that Fortune has made u<U+017F>e to give me that woeful blow: Yes, <hi>Agnes</hi> the Prince loves thee, and that Merit which I know to be in thee, puts a <U+017F>top to my Complaints, not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the lea<U+017F>t re<U+017F>entment.</p>
                  <p>The Beauteous <hi>Agnes</hi> little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected what the Prince<U+017F>s had <U+017F>aid to her. Thunder and Lightning, had le<U+017F>s <U+017F>urpris'd and aba<U+017F>s'd her, <U+017F>he remain'd long Speechle<U+017F>s; but at la<U+017F>t fixing her looks on <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>; What <U+017F>ay you Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <U+017F>he, and what thoughts have you had of me? What <U+017F>hould I be capable of betraying you? And in coming here fill'd with Zeal for the quiet of your Life I <U+017F>hould bring with me but a direful Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, that <U+017F>hould di<U+017F>turb it? How <U+017F>hould I dete<U+017F>t that little of Beauty which is found in me, (though
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99165:53"/>
without any de<U+017F>ign in me of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it known) and that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate day in which I fir<U+017F>t beheld the Prince! But Madam it cannot be me certainly that the Heavens have cho<U+017F>en to travers you. They are not <U+017F>o much my Enemy to put me to <U+017F>o <U+017F>evere a Tryal, and if I was that Odious Per<U+017F>on, there would be no Exiles nor Torments to which I would not condemn my <U+017F>elf. 'Tis <hi>Elvira,</hi> Madam, whom the Prince has formerly Lov'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Marriage, and even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Blanch</hi>'s Divorce; <U+017F>ome indi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet reports have been made you concerning that intregue of his Younger days; but that which has happen'd in the time of <hi>Blanch,</hi> has no relation to you. It is mo<U+017F>t certain that <hi>Don Pedre</hi> Loves, you an<U+017F>wered the Prince<U+017F>s, and I have vanity enough to believe that of truth, there is none but you in all <hi>Spain</hi> that can di<U+017F>pute it with me, but his <U+017F>ecret is di<U+017F>cover'd, and he has not deny'd it. What, reply'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99165:54"/>
the Beauteous <hi>Agnes,</hi> with a greater <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>e it is from him<U+017F>elf, that you have receiv'd the Intelligence of his weakne<U+017F>s? Then did <hi>Constantia</hi> <U+017F>hew her the Ver<U+017F>es, and there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was any di<U+017F>pair like hers.</p>
                  <p>While they were in that <U+017F>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ation, Impatient <hi>Elvira,</hi> who was de<U+017F>irous to learn the effects of her Practices came again to the Prince<U+017F>s, where <U+017F>he had a free acce<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he was not hindred from going to her very Clo<U+017F>et, and her Pre<U+017F>ence drew a redne<U+017F>s on the cheeks of two re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s and afflicted Per<U+017F>ons which de<U+017F>ired not her Company, <U+017F>he had the <U+017F>atisfaction of ob<U+017F>erv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Constantia</hi> to lay a<U+017F>ide tho<U+017F>e Ver<U+017F>es, which the Prince<U+017F>s had not <U+017F>een without her Malice, and of an imoderate Sorrow in her Eyes, and in <hi>Agne<U+017F>e</hi>'s al<U+017F>o. She remain'd there ju<U+017F>t <U+017F>o long as needed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form her that <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ucceeded well, but the Prince<U+017F>s who de<U+017F>ired not <U+017F>uch an ob<U+017F>tinate Witne<U+017F>s of the troubles <U+017F>he was in at that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99165:54"/>
pre<U+017F>ent, order'd to be left alone, <hi>Elvira</hi> went out, and <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro</hi> retired at the <U+017F>ame time al<U+017F>o.</p>
                  <p>It was in her own Chamber, that examining more at large her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, <U+017F>he found it as cruel as Death it <U+017F>elf. She Lov'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> with a true Affection, and till then, had not had for the Prince of <hi>Portugal</hi> but an e<U+017F>teem mixed with that admiration which could not be deny'd to his Excellent Qualities, and con<U+017F>idering her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf with extremity of Grief, as the cau<U+017F>e of the Sorrows of <U+017F>uch a Prince<U+017F>s to who<U+017F>e Bountys <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o Indebted, <U+017F>he Employd all the Night in Tears and Complaints, which <U+017F>ufficiently reveng'd <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tantia</hi> of the<U+017F>e Evils which <U+017F>he caus'd her to feel.</p>
                  <p>The Prince was no le<U+017F>s di<U+017F>turb'd, his Wives genero<U+017F>ity increa<U+017F>ed his remor<U+017F>es, without dimini<U+017F>hing his love. He did fear, not without great likeline<U+017F>s, that they who had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99165:55"/>
po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> with tho<U+017F>e Ver<U+017F>es, would al<U+017F>o acquaint the King of his pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, from whom he could not expect <U+017F>o great an Indulgency, and he would freely part with his Life to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf from that extremity.</p>
                  <p>The afflicted <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> did Langui<U+017F>h in a deplorable condition, <U+017F>he could not <U+017F>ee any thing in tho<U+017F>e Per<U+017F>ons that caus'd her Misfortune, but what was apt to move her tender affections. At la<U+017F>t Jealou<U+017F>y de<U+017F>ign'd, (but vainly) to combat that tendency which <U+017F>he had, to Love them. The Prince was not le<U+017F>s dear unto her, and <U+017F>he could not be <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible either of hatred or indifferency towards her rival.</p>
                  <p>While that the<U+017F>e three unea<U+017F>y Per<U+017F>ons did abandon them<U+017F>elves unto their Melancholy, <hi>Elvira</hi> who was re<U+017F>olved not to let her ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance remain imperfect was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving by what means <U+017F>he might accompli<U+017F>h it. Her Brother on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99165:55"/>
whom <U+017F>he did depend, did <U+017F>hew her a great affection, and gue<U+017F><U+017F>ing that the Loves of <hi>Don Pedre</hi> and <hi>Agnes</hi> of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tro</hi> would not be approv'd of by the King, <U+017F>he di<U+017F>cover'd it to <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who was not Ignorant of the former that the Prince had had with his Si<U+017F>ter. He found him<U+017F>elf mo<U+017F>t powerfully concern'd in the news <U+017F>he had told him, through a <U+017F>ecret pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which he had for <hi>Agnes,</hi> which he had concealed in his own Brea<U+017F>t lea<U+017F>t it <U+017F>hould in any <U+017F>ort thwart the <U+017F>mooth cour<U+017F>e of his good Fortune, and he was in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a continuation of <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>es</hi> Favours, whereby to render his Heart, a more con<U+017F>ider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pre<U+017F>ent.</p>
                  <p>He concealed not from his Si<U+017F>ter a Mi<U+017F>tery which he had found very difficult to keep <U+017F>ecret, and it prov'd a duplication of vexation to her, to find <hi>Agnes</hi> the Sovereign of all tho<U+017F>e Hearts over which <U+017F>he had any pretentions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99165:56"/>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> was one of tho<U+017F>e Ambitious men that are <U+017F>o with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Moderation, Proud without Genero<U+017F>ity, of cruel inclination, and who to attain his ends, could not <U+017F>ee any thing, that was either difficult or Illigitimate. He Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaly lov'd not the Prince who in all rea<U+017F>on was to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s the fir<U+017F>t place in <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi>'s Heart, and who <U+017F>et limits unto <hi>Don Alvare</hi>'s good Fortune. But he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tood that he was his Rival, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lou<U+017F>ie increas'd his hatred, and he intreated <hi>Elvira</hi> to employ all her cares to cro<U+017F>s an engagement which could not but be oppo<U+017F>ite to his de<U+017F>igns. She promi<U+017F>ed him all aid and a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, though <U+017F>he was not <U+017F>atisfied, as to her own concerns, and he rely'd on her promi<U+017F>e and dexterity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who had <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly felt the Prince of <hi>Portugal</hi>'s concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in his amours, had no other thoughts but of thwarting and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ing his Merits. He had no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99165:56"/>
hand<U+017F>om pre<U+017F>ence, neither was he of an agreable temper, and <hi>Don Pedre</hi> had tho<U+017F>e advantages, and po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd divers others al<U+017F>o, but being Husband to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> and that he wholly depended on a Father who was ab<U+017F>olute, and that <hi>Don Alvares</hi> was under no re<U+017F>traint, and Ma<U+017F>ter of a con<U+017F>iderable For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he tru<U+017F>ted his good Fortune on that <U+017F>core.</p>
                  <p>He knew well that <hi>Don Pedre</hi>'s Love could not but in<U+017F>pire <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fon<U+017F>e</hi> with a violent anger; and being over diligent in doing evil, his fir<U+017F>t Care was to inform him of it. After he had given <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Lea<U+017F>ure to his anger to rou<U+017F>e unto that Pitch he would have it, he <U+017F>poke for him<U+017F>elf, and <U+017F>oon did render the King Protector of his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
                  <p>Though <hi>Don Alvares</hi> had no other Merits with the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> than a continual blind Complacency, he had poured all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Favours upon him, and in that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99165:57"/>
State in which the Kings Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had placed him; few Women could well refu<U+017F>e his Allegiance, <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi> did a<U+017F><U+017F>ure him the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of his Friend<U+017F>hip and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and did a<U+017F><U+017F>ure him that he him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>hould loo<U+017F>e his authority, or that he would make him Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ter of <hi>Agnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> perfectly learned in the Art of managing his Ma<U+017F>ter did an<U+017F>wer his la<U+017F>t bounties with a profound <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and very fit to continue them. He had never <U+017F>poken to <hi>Agnes</hi> what he did feel for her, but he then thought it time to break forth, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <U+017F>ought after the means to perform it.</p>
                  <p>The galantry of <hi>Coimbria</hi> which lay in oblivion did then rou<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf up again. The King to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure <hi>Don Alvares</hi> under a pretence of diverting of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <U+017F>ome public <U+017F>ports, and it was his Plea<U+017F>ure that all things <U+017F>hould appear very magnificently.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99165:57"/>Ever <U+017F>ince the adventure of the Ver<U+017F>es <hi>Don Pedre</hi> had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd all means to con<U+017F>train him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf and of appearing le<U+017F>s concern'd; but in the bottom he <U+017F>till equally <U+017F>uffer'd, and it was not without great unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s that he fitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf for the Ju<U+017F>ting. And <U+017F>eing that he could not appear <U+017F>o Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licly with <hi>Agnes's</hi> Colours, he took tho<U+017F>e of the Prince<U+017F>s, without any Motto or Agreements.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> <U+017F>et him<U+017F>elf off with <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro's</hi> Liveries, and that beautiful Maid, who found no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in what the Prince<U+017F>s had <U+017F>aid, had this further addition of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> did appear in the Li<U+017F>t extream graceful, and <hi>Don Alvares</hi> who look'd upon this day as his own, did appear all Glittering with Gold and Jewels mixed with blew, which was <hi>Agnes</hi>'s Colour, and his Equipage was all over <U+017F>prinkled with inflamed Hearts, and Love Knots, with aboundance
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99165:58"/>
of double As; his Motto was a <hi>Cupid</hi> breaking out of a Cloud with the<U+017F>e four Ver<U+017F>es under it.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>My Ba<U+017F>hful Love, Bani<U+017F>h all fear,</l>
                     <l>From your concealing Cloud appear.</l>
                     <l>For nows the time, mo<U+017F>t Charming Eyes</l>
                     <l>To know that heart, you made your Pri<U+017F>e.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi>'s Pride was laid humble at <hi>Don Pedre</hi>'s Feet, who bore him down with twenty more, and he alone carried the honour of the day. At Night there was a gallant appearance at <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi>'s appartment, where <hi>Agnes</hi> had not been without an expre<U+017F>s and ab<U+017F>olute order from the Prince<U+017F>s. She did appear very negligently dre<U+017F>t, though <U+017F>till charming with Vexation, <U+017F>he had <U+017F>een her Name and Colours us'd by <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> in a public Solemnity, and if her Heart was capable of any tenderne<U+017F>s it was not for <U+017F>uch a Per<U+017F>on as he, that her Nicety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign'd them. She look'd on him with a Contempt, which hinder'd him not from pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing much upon
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99165:58"/>
her, and <U+017F>he was forc'd to give Ear to what he had a mind to <U+017F>ay.</p>
                  <p>She was not rude, but her Coldne<U+017F>s would have repuls'd all other but <hi>Alvares</hi>: Madam, <U+017F>aid he to her, <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as he could not be heard but by her <U+017F>elf, I had till this pre<U+017F>ent concealed that Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which you had In<U+017F>pired me with; in fear of your di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ure; but it has forc'd my re<U+017F>pect, and I can no longer conceal it from you. I have made no reflections on your Actions, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> with all th<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indifferency imaginable, and if you offend me, you wrong me the more in de<U+017F>iring my taking Notice of it. This Coldne<U+017F>s is of evil Omen to me, reply'd <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> and if you have not this day taken notice of my love, it is to be fear'd, that you will never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it. Alas! what time have you cho<U+017F>en to <U+017F>hew i<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me, contin'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> does it <U+017F>o much Honour me, that you <U+017F>hew it with <U+017F>o mu<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#PDCC" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99165:59"/>
care, and do you believe me <U+017F>o greedy of Glory, as to A<U+017F>pire at that which derives from you? You have ill maintain'd it in the Ju<U+017F>ts, and if it is that vanity which prompts you on, you will make no great Progre<U+017F>s in a Soul which loves not <U+017F>hame. Though you were in Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of all the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which the Prince has merited, yet you ought to reflect on what you are doing, and it is not a Per<U+017F>on like me that can be mov'd by <U+017F>uch re<U+017F>pectle<U+017F>s en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpri<U+017F>es.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e's</hi> Favourite was too Proud, to hear <hi>Agnes</hi> thus <U+017F>pake without Colour; but his de<U+017F>ign being to render her flexible, and not to anger her; he conceal'd his Re<U+017F>entment; and taking No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Ob<U+017F>ervation which <U+017F>he had made on <hi>Don Pedre's</hi> Tryumph with an Addition of Jealou<U+017F>y. If, I have not overcome at the Ju<U+017F>t, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eply'd he, I am not le<U+017F>s Amorous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                     </gap> le<U+017F>s capable of Succe<U+017F>s in other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F>ions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99165:59"/>They were interrupted; but from that day, <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who had gone over the fir<U+017F>t difficulties, no longer ob<U+017F>erv'd any Mea<U+017F>ures, and Per<U+017F>ecuted <hi>Agnes,</hi> to whom the Kings Protection In<U+017F>pir'd not the lea<U+017F>t con<U+017F>iderations for him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> was <U+017F>till Ignorant of the means by which tho<U+017F>e Ver<U+017F>es which he had lo<U+017F>t in the Garden had fallen into <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> hands. The Prince<U+017F>s appearing very Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to him, he had no other trouble but for <hi>Agne's</hi> Intere<U+017F>t. <hi>Don Alvare's</hi> Love, that was now <U+017F>o known did perplex him, and if he had follow'd his own Dictates, he had not left her expos'd to the Per<U+017F>ecutions of that unworthy Rival. On the other hand he fear'd that the King <U+017F>hould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; but he did not then reflect enough on <hi>Elvira,</hi> to fear her Re<U+017F>ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>She Burnt with a de<U+017F>ire to ruine <hi>Agnes,</hi> again<U+017F>t whom all her Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99165:60"/>
was <U+017F>tirr'd up, and <U+017F>he was not tyred with making daily new reports to her Brother, a<U+017F><U+017F>uring him though <U+017F>he had no proofs for it, that <hi>Agnes</hi> did an<U+017F>wer to the Prince's tenderne<U+017F>s, that it was the true cau<U+017F>e of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Grief, and that if that Prince<U+017F>s <U+017F>hould dye of it, <hi>Don Pedre</hi> might Marry <hi>Agnes,</hi> infine <U+017F>he did <U+017F>o irritate her Brothers Jealou<U+017F>ie, that he run, to <U+017F>hew it wholly to <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> who Trembled with Anger at it; My dear <hi>Alvares,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, to him, Marry her, that Beauty that is <U+017F>o dangerous, and let your Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion <U+017F>ecure both yours and my quiet. If I have protected you in other occa<U+017F>ions, Judge what a bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s of <U+017F>uch Importance to me can make me undertake. Act without any re<U+017F>erve. The Powers of the Kingdom are in your Power, and all that I po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s <U+017F>hall be certainly at your di<U+017F>po<U+017F>al, provided you but render your <U+017F>elf. Ma<U+017F>ter of <hi>Agne's</hi> De<U+017F>tiny.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99165:60"/>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> well pleas'd with his Ma<U+017F>ter, took hold of all the Authority that he gave him. He really Lov'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> and was loath to come at fir<U+017F>t to any violence; but he promis'd him<U+017F>elf to be beyond all Management if <U+017F>he <U+017F>till continu'd in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible.</p>
                  <p>Mean time <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro</hi> highly importun'd with his A<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duities, de<U+017F>perate at <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Griefs, and peradventure molified by tho<U+017F>e which <U+017F>he cau<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d the Prince to <U+017F>uffer, did take a Re<U+017F>olu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion worthy of her Virtue. As Amiable as was <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> <U+017F>he could not <U+017F>ee in him but the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of a Prince<U+017F>s that was mo<U+017F>t dear to her, and far from <U+017F>eeking to improve that Power which <U+017F>he had over his Heart, <U+017F>he thought of nothing but ab<U+017F>enting her <U+017F>elf from <hi>Coimbria. Don Alvare's</hi> Pa<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <U+017F>he would not favour did furni<U+017F>h her with a pretence, and pre<U+017F>s'd on with the fears of cau<U+017F>ing at la<U+017F>t a Divorce, mo<U+017F>t
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99165:61"/>
Cruel betwixt the Prince and his Spou<U+017F>e, <U+017F>he found out <hi>Constantia</hi> in a perplexity that all her cares could not conceal.</p>
                  <p>The Prince<U+017F>s ea<U+017F>ily ob<U+017F>erv'd it, and their common misfortune having not alter'd her Friend<U+017F>hip. What's the matter with you <hi>Agnes,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, with her wonted <U+017F>weet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, and what new misfortune does your <U+017F>orrow come to inform me of; That Attachment which I have for you, Madam, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> does put me to a Cruel Tryal, and pouring forth a Flood of Tears, I had limited the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of my Life in the hopes of <U+017F>pending of it near your Per<U+017F>on, yet I find that I mu<U+017F>t Tran<U+017F>port <U+017F>omewhere el<U+017F>e an Uunfortunate Face, that renders me but ill Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and it is to obtain from you that Permi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, that I come to Embrace your Knees, looking on you as on my Sovereign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> was <U+017F>o <U+017F>urpris'd and <U+017F>o mov'd at <hi>Agne's</hi> propo<U+017F>ition,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99165:61"/>
that <U+017F>he remain'd Speechle<U+017F>s; for <U+017F>ome Moments, <U+017F>ome <U+017F>incere Tears expre<U+017F>s'd her fir<U+017F>t grief, and after <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ufficiently <U+017F>hed them to give <hi>Agnes</hi> a <U+017F>ufficient Mark of her Tenderne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he fixed her Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Eyes upon her, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingly holding forth her hand to her, then you will go, my dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> continu'd <U+017F>he, and further expo<U+017F>e me unto the <U+017F>orrow of <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you no more. Alas, Madam reply'd that amyable Maid, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from the Mi<U+017F>erable <hi>Agnes</hi> a Bounty which increa<U+017F>es her Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows. It is not I that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, it is my Duty and my Rea<U+017F>on that will have it <U+017F>o, and tho<U+017F>e days that I <U+017F>hall pa<U+017F>s ab<U+017F>ent from you, cannot promi<U+017F>e me any thing <U+017F>o agreeable as to in<U+017F>pire me <U+017F>uch a de<U+017F>ign if I found not my <U+017F>elf ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olutely compell'd to it. I cannot be Ignorant of what pa<U+017F><U+017F>es at <hi>Coimbria,</hi> and I <U+017F>hould be an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complice to tho<U+017F>e Unju<U+017F>tices which are there committed <U+017F>hould I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ide
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99165:62"/>
there any longer — Ah! I know your Virtue, cryed out <hi>Constantia,</hi> and you may remain here in all <U+017F>ecurity, if I <U+017F>tay you here, and whatever does happen I <U+017F>hall never accu<U+017F>e you of any thing. We mu<U+017F>t not promi<U+017F>e our <U+017F>elves any thing of future, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Agnes</hi> <U+017F>orrowfully, and I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>till remain <U+017F>ufficiently Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <U+017F>o long as my pre<U+017F>ence <U+017F>hall entertain <U+017F>uch thoughts as cannot be accounted Innocent. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Madam, <hi>Don Alvare's</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities are un<U+017F>ufferable, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my <U+017F>elf nothing but Aver<U+017F>ion again<U+017F>t him, that the King protects his In<U+017F>olency, and that he is in a Condition of undertaking much, my flight is ab<U+017F>olutely nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary; But Madam, though he po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es nothing but what is odious to me, I call Heaven to Witne<U+017F>s, that if I could Cure the Prince by Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, I <U+017F>hould not defer it one moment, and finding in my mind, the Con<U+017F>olation of having
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99165:62"/>
Sacrific'd my <U+017F>elf for my Prince<U+017F>s, I <U+017F>hould bear it without any Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur; But in fine though I <U+017F>hould be <hi>Don Alvare's</hi> Wife, <hi>Don Pedre</hi> would <U+017F>till have the <U+017F>ame Eyes, and I find nothing better then to go hide my <U+017F>elf in <U+017F>ome Corner of the World, where I <U+017F>hall certainly Live without Comfort; but where I <U+017F>hould pre<U+017F>erve my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. All that Ju<U+017F>tice which you can find in this de<U+017F>ign, an<U+017F>wer'd the Prince<U+017F>s, <U+017F>hall not oblige me to approve of it. Would your Ab<U+017F>ence re<U+017F>tore me <hi>Don Pedre's</hi> Heart, and would he not fly with you? His Cares, are mine, my Life is link'd with his, reduce him not then to a di<U+017F>pair, if you, love me. I know you, I once again declare it to you, and what power <U+017F>oever you have over the Prince<hi>'s</hi> heart, I <U+017F>hall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that you <U+017F>hould leave us.</p>
                  <p>Though <hi>Agnes</hi> believ'd <U+017F>he had a perfect Knowledg of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> <U+017F>he did not expect <U+017F>uch a fund of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99165:63"/>
Virtue, <U+017F>he found her <U+017F>elf the more Unfortunate by it, and the Prince more Guilty. Oh! Wi<U+017F>dom, Oh! Bounty! beyond Example cry'd <U+017F>he out; why do not the Cruel Fates afford you all that you de<U+017F>erve. You are the Arbiter of all my Actions, continu'd <U+017F>he, ki<U+017F><U+017F>ing one of <hi>Constantia's</hi> hands, I will not do but what you plea<U+017F>e; but I be<U+017F>eech you to think on what rea<U+017F>on ought to prompt you to pre<U+017F>cribe to me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> who had not yet <U+017F>een the Prince<U+017F>s that day, came in ju<U+017F>t then, and finding them both di<U+017F>turb'd he inquired after the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on with <U+017F>ome earne<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s. My Lord reply'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> the too Wi<U+017F>e and too <U+017F>crupulous <hi>Agnes</hi> fears the Effects of her Beauty, and will no longer live at <hi>Coimbria</hi> and it is on that Account, which cannot be plea<U+017F>ing to me, that <U+017F>he is asking my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. At this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e the Prince grew pale, and with more di<U+017F>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance then either of them had.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99165:63"/>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> cannot err, <U+017F>aid he, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing your Coun<U+017F>els; Madam, and I leave you with free Liberty of given them to her. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently went out, and the Prince<U+017F>s who<U+017F>e heart he did <U+017F>o ab<U+017F>olutely po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s, not being able to conceal her di<U+017F>content. My dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd <U+017F>he, though my <U+017F>atisfaction was not chain'd to the <U+017F>ight of you, I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>till de<U+017F>ire it on <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre's</hi> account. It is, the only Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that his Unfortunate Love can hope for, and <U+017F>hould I not be with Ju<U+017F>tice reputed barbarous, if I <U+017F>hould contribute towards his being depriv'd of it? But that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is but a Poi<U+017F>on to him, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> and what <U+017F>hould I do my Dear Prince<U+017F>s, if after <U+017F>o much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>traint, his Mouth <U+017F>hould add to tho<U+017F>e Evils which I have already felt, that of hearing him <U+017F>pake of his flame? You <U+017F>hould hear him without running him into di<U+017F>pair, added <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> and I <U+017F>hould charge that new Obligation on my
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99165:64"/>
Account. You would have me to wait for events that I fear, Madam, an<U+017F>wer'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> I <U+017F>hall obey you. But ye ju<U+017F>t Heavens! If they are Fatal, puni<U+017F>h not for them an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Heart. Thus ended that Conver<U+017F>ation. <hi>Agnes</hi> retir'd into her Chamber; but it was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hopes of being more at ea<U+017F>e.</p>
                  <p>That which <hi>Don Pedre</hi> had learn'd of her de<U+017F>ign, produc'd a <U+017F>trange Di<U+017F>turbance in his mind, he wi<U+017F>h'd he did not Love her, and de<U+017F>ired Death with great earne<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s, but it was too late for him to wi<U+017F>h again<U+017F>t what the Fates had decreed, and whatever he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to re<U+017F>olve him<U+017F>elf to bear as to the Ab<U+017F>ence of <hi>Agnes,</hi> his Love never had the Power to con<U+017F>ent to it.</p>
                  <p>After he had long <U+017F>trove, he firmly re<U+017F>olv'd to do that which he would not have <hi>Agnes</hi> to do. His Courage did reproach to him that idle Life which he lead during his happie<U+017F>t years,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99165:64"/>
and repre<U+017F>enting to the King that their Allies, and even the Prince <hi>Don John Manuel</hi> his Father-in-Law, had bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s in hand which required his pre<U+017F>ence upon the Frontiers, he ea<U+017F>ily obtain'd the Liberty of making that Voyage, unto which the Prince<U+017F>s could make no oppo<U+017F>ition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> did <U+017F>ee him depart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <U+017F>orrow: but that did not proceed from any Aver<U+017F>ion. Then did <hi>Don Alvares</hi> convert his fir<U+017F>t importunity into an open Per<U+017F>ecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He omitted nothing to touch <hi>Agne's</hi> Heart, and for <U+017F>ome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable time employ'd none but the. Arms of Love, but finding that his re<U+017F>pect and <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion were fruitle<U+017F>s, he took another Cour<U+017F>e, and fram'd mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>trange De<U+017F>igns.</p>
                  <p>The King deferring all things to his Advices, he did ea<U+017F>ily in<U+017F>pire in him what he pleas'd; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of <hi>Agne's</hi> Ingratitude, and fail'd not to let him know that it was but through her too great
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99165:65"/>
<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibility for the Prince that <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible to him, <U+017F>o that <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi> apt to be irritated, reiterated all tho<U+017F>e Promi<U+017F>es, which he had already made him.</p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> had not yet di<U+017F>cours'd <hi>Agnes</hi> in Favour of <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> and not doubting but that his Will would overcome all <U+017F>orts of Ob<U+017F>tacles, he <U+017F>ought after an opportunity of Entertaining her, and putting her at <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance from tho<U+017F>e that might over-hear them, I did think <hi>Don Alvares</hi> to be of a <U+017F>ufficient Merit, he <U+017F>aid, to obtain <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall <U+017F>hare in your E<U+017F>teem, and I did not think it nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary that I <U+017F>hould require it of you for him, I know you are all charming, but he has nothing unworthy of you, and on the lea<U+017F>t Reflection you might make of the Choice that my Friend<U+017F>hip has made of him, among<U+017F>t all the re<U+017F>t of my Courtiers, you would doubtle<U+017F>s readily do him more Ju<U+017F>tice. His Fortune is not to be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99165:65"/>
di<U+017F>puted, <U+017F>ince I am the Protector of it. He is of a Noble Birth, his Courage does him Honour, he adores you, and in my opinion <U+017F>o many rea<U+017F>ons ought to over-come your Scorns.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes's</hi> Heart was <U+017F>o little di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to give it <U+017F>elf to <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> that all the King of <hi>Portugal</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agerations prevail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d nothing in his behalf. Though <hi>Don Alvares</hi> were without Merits, Sir, She reply'd, he po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es <U+017F>ufficiently of Advantages in tho<U+017F>e Bounties with which your Maje<U+017F>ty does Honour him, to <U+017F>upply all other defects. It is not to find any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in him that I an<U+017F>wer not his wi<U+017F>hes; But, Sir, through what Obligation would he have me to Love him, if the Heavens have not furni<U+017F>hed me with a tender Soul? and why does he pretend that I <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ubmit my <U+017F>elf to him, when that nothing ought to be more dear to me then Liberty? You are neither <U+017F>o free nor <U+017F>o in<U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99165:66"/>
as you <U+017F>peak, reply'd <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fon<U+017F>e,</hi> blu<U+017F>hing with Anger, and if your Heart was free from all <U+017F>orts of Affections it might receive a more rea<U+017F>onable one then that which po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es it. But Imprudent Maid, that you are guided by an ill fate, added he with Fury, what can you pretend from <hi>Don Pedre?</hi> Hither to I have conceal'd the <U+017F>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that his and your weakne<U+017F>s have caus'd me; but it has not been the le<U+017F>s violent for that; and <U+017F>ince you oblige me to let it break forth, I ought to tell you that though my Son were not tyed to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> his Marriage <U+017F>hould never con<U+017F>ern you. Renounce tho<U+017F>e vain Ideas, and take a cour<U+017F>e that may cure him and ju<U+017F>tifie your <U+017F>elf.</p>
                  <p>The Courageous <hi>Agnes,</hi> was <U+017F>carce Mi<U+017F>tri<U+017F>s of her fir<U+017F>t Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>port, at a Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e <U+017F>o full of Scorn, but calling her Virtue to <U+017F>econd her Anger, <U+017F>he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came her <U+017F>elf by her own rea<U+017F>on,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99165:66"/>
con<U+017F>idering the wrong which <U+017F>he <U+017F>u<U+017F>tained not as proceeding from a great King, but from a Man blinded and wholly po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd by <hi>Don Alvares.</hi> She thought him not worthy of her re<U+017F>entment. Her fair Eyes were animated with a <U+017F>parkling brightne<U+017F>s, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>ed the purity of her intentions, and fixing them on <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi>; if the Prince <hi>Don Pedre</hi> has failings <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, with an Air that inclin'd <U+017F>omething to di<U+017F>dain, he has never inform'd me of them, and I do not believe that I have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to them. To cure your di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tru<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>et my Honour <U+017F>afe, I <U+017F>hall live at a di<U+017F>tance from him, and all that belongs to you. Yes, Sir, I <U+017F>hall contentedly leave the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad of <hi>Coimbria,</hi> and as to that Man <U+017F>o dear to you, added <U+017F>he, with a Noble boldne<U+017F>s, of which the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was very <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible, that Favorite, who is <U+017F>o wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s the mo<U+017F>t tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of a great Prince, I do a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99165:67"/>
you that in what part of the World <U+017F>oever my Fortune leads me, I <U+017F>hall not carry the lea<U+017F>t thought of him with me. At the<U+017F>e words, <U+017F>he made a profound Bow, and did <U+017F>o <U+017F>uddainly di<U+017F>tance her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf from <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> that he could not oppo<U+017F>e him<U+017F>elf again<U+017F>t her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement.</p>
                  <p>He believ'd more then ever that <U+017F>he did Favour <hi>Don Pedres</hi> pa<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pa<U+017F>s'd into <hi>Con<U+017F>tantias</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, to in<U+017F>pire her with the <U+017F>ame thought; but <U+017F>he was not capable of receiving <U+017F>uch impre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions, and following her Natural inclination, <U+017F>he generou<U+017F>ly defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Agnes's</hi> Virtue, <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> vexed to find her <U+017F>o well di<U+017F>pos'd on her rivals account, whom he would have her to hate, did mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur again<U+017F>t her goodne<U+017F>s, and went to joyn his anger to <hi>Don Alvare</hi>'s rage who no longer wa<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ma<U+017F>ter of him<U+017F>elf after he had <U+017F>een that his Ma<U+017F>ter's Negotiation wa<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of no effect. That Proud one
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99165:67"/>
braves me, Sir, <U+017F>aid he, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns the Honour that your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have made her, that I might renounce <U+017F>o fatal a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; but I mu<U+017F>t love her again<U+017F>t my will, and though that Flame <U+017F>hould co<U+017F>t me my Life, I plainly feel that I can not put it out. What i'st that I can do for you? replyed <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi>? Alas! <hi>Sir,</hi> reply'd, <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> that which I can never hope for from Proud <hi>Agne's</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent. Well, added the King <U+017F>eeing that I mu<U+017F>t not Publicly authori<U+017F>e any Violence in the Center of my Kingdom, chu<U+017F>e from among<U+017F>t all my Subjects <U+017F>uch as thou <U+017F>halt Judge mo<U+017F>t capable of <U+017F>erving thee; carry off that Beauty which charms thee, and if <U+017F>he yeilds not to thy Love, make u<U+017F>e of all that force can do for thee, to force her to Marry thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> ravi<U+017F>h'd with <U+017F>uch a propo<U+017F>ition, which at once did Flatter his re<U+017F>entments and his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99165:68"/>
love ca<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf at <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi>'s Feet, did expre<U+017F>s his acknowleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to him, <U+017F>et forward his Zeal, with new prote<U+017F>tations, and thought no longer but to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his unju<U+017F>t authority again<U+017F>t <hi>Agnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> had been ab<U+017F>ent above three Months, when <hi>Don Alvares</hi> did undertake that which the King had advis'd him to do. Though the Prince<U+017F>s moderation was well known to him, he fear'd his pre<U+017F>ence, and was loath to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the return of a rival with whom nothing had yet been di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</p>
                  <p>One night that the <U+017F>orrowful <hi>Agnes,</hi> full of her daily Di<U+017F>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, was in vain expecting <U+017F>leep, <U+017F>ome unknown men, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>teps were well order'd did take her out of the Palace, and after carried her out of <hi>Coimbria,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being hindred by any Ob<U+017F>tacle, <U+017F>he could not well tell on whom to fix her Su<U+017F>picions. <hi>Don Alvares</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99165:68"/>
<U+017F>eem'd too powerful to <U+017F>eek for his Satisfaction after <U+017F>uch a manner, and <U+017F>he did not taxe with this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt a Prince of whom <U+017F>he had too good an Opinion. All that <U+017F>he could <U+017F>ay, did not hinder her ill adventure; <U+017F>he was carried away with dilligence, and before day, <U+017F>he was already con<U+017F>iderably di<U+017F>tant from the City.</p>
                  <p>At the fir<U+017F>t Glimps of day, <U+017F>he look'd on all tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>urrounded her, not knowing <U+017F>o much as one; and perceiving well, that both out-cries, and tears, were in vain to <U+017F>uch cruel minds, <U+017F>he re<U+017F>ted contented in imploring the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Heaven, and <U+017F>o aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd her <U+017F>elf to her Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</p>
                  <p>While <U+017F>he was overwhelm'd with Sorrow, and uncertain of her doom, <U+017F>he perceiv'd a Body of Hor<U+017F>e to advance towards the Troops that conducted her; The ravi<U+017F>hers did not avoid it, beleiving it to be <hi>Don Alvares</hi>; but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99165:69"/>
near, they perceiv'd that it was the Prince of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowledg of this oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of <U+017F>erving <hi>Agnes,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>Coimbria</hi> full of her <hi>Idea,</hi> after he had perform'd all that he was to do in his expedition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes,</hi> who did not expect him alter'd her mind, and thought that it was by his orders that <U+017F>he was forc'd away. Ah! my Lord, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, in that thought, was it you that was thus to tare me from the Prince<U+017F>s? and mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>o cruel a blow fall on me from a hand <U+017F>o dear to her? What will you do with a mi<U+017F>erable wretch who <U+017F>eeks but for Death? and why will you Tarni<U+017F>h the Glory of your life, by a de<U+017F>ign <U+017F>o un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of you?</p>
                  <p>That Language did no le<U+017F>s <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>e the Prince, then the <U+017F>ight of <hi>Agnes</hi> had done. He Apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <U+017F>he had been forc'd away, and in<U+017F>tantly re<U+017F>enting the mo<U+017F>t peircing <U+017F>trokes of Anger, he gave
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99165:69"/>
her to under<U+017F>tand with one <U+017F>ingle look, that he was not the ba<U+017F>e au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of her grief. I, tare you from <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> who are all her joy, <U+017F>aid he, what thoughts have you of <hi>Don Pedre</hi>? If you <U+017F>ee me here, I am wholly Innocent of that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which is offer'd you, and which I <U+017F>hall prevent. Then did he turn him<U+017F>elf towards the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>hers; but his pre<U+017F>ence had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready di<U+017F>pers'd them. He order'd his Men to pur<U+017F>ue them, and at lea<U+017F>t to <U+017F>ei<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome from whom he might learn the authority by which they did Act.</p>
                  <p>During this, <hi>Agnes</hi> was not le<U+017F>s confus'd then before, <U+017F>he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd the conduct of her Fortune, who brought the Prince at the very moment that he was <U+017F>o u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to her. Her equity did <U+017F>oon redre<U+017F>s the wrong which her di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>ts had caus'd her to do him. She felt <U+017F>ome joy to have e<U+017F>caped a Misfortune which appear'd <U+017F>o certain to her, but it was no quiet
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99165:70"/>
joy, when <U+017F>he con<U+017F>ider'd that her deliverer was her lover too, and <U+017F>uch a lover as de<U+017F>erv'd her entire acknowledgments, but that al<U+017F>o owed his Heart to the mo<U+017F>t ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prince<U+017F>s in the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who fear'd being <U+017F>een near to <hi>Coimbria,</hi> and who delay'd Pro<U+017F>ecuting of <hi>Agnes</hi> till <U+017F>he was at a di<U+017F>tance from it, had confided his de<U+017F>ign to <U+017F>ome Friends, which he jug'd capable to execute it, and that had done it had not the Prince interpos'd.</p>
                  <p>During the time that his Men were per<U+017F>uing of the Ravi<U+017F>hers of <hi>Agnes,</hi> he remain'd almo<U+017F>t alone with her, and though he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olv'd always to avoid her pre<U+017F>ence, his Fortitude could not with<U+017F>tand <U+017F>o fair an occa<U+017F>ion. Madam <U+017F>aid he, is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible that Men born among<U+017F>t tho<U+017F>e that obey us, <U+017F>hould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of offending you? It was not to the care of Puni<U+017F>hing <U+017F>uch a Crime that I thought my <U+017F>elf re<U+017F>erv'd; but <U+017F>ince the Heavens have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99165:70"/>
that you <U+017F>hould receive it, I mu<U+017F>t peri<U+017F>h or cau<U+017F>e you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it. My Lord, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> more mov'd at this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, then at <hi>Don Alvares</hi>'s enterpri<U+017F>e, tho<U+017F>e that want re<U+017F>pect for the Prince<U+017F>s and for you, may be di<U+017F>pens'd from having any for me. I no longer doubt but that <hi>Don Alvares</hi> is the Author of this attempt, and I judge what I may expect from him, by that which his importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has made me <U+017F>uffer. He is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Kings protection, and he de<U+017F>igns to make him partner in his crimes; But my Lord the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens have conducted you mo<U+017F>t happily here for me, and to you do I owe the Liberty of again <U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Prince<U+017F>s. You would do for <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> that which is impo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible not to perform for you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> your goodne<U+017F>s binds you to her, and others For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes does for ever engage them to you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99165:71"/>The mode<U+017F>t <hi>Agnes,</hi> who dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, as much as the danger which had been prevented, made no other an<U+017F>wer then to ca<U+017F>t down her looks, and the Prince who under<U+017F>tood her di<U+017F>order, left her to <U+017F>pake to two of his Men, who brought him back one of tho<U+017F>e that <hi>Don Alvares</hi> had employ'd. He pardon'd him, and did not think that he <U+017F>hould puni<U+017F>h him, for having obey'd a man, who was made Almighty through his Fathers weakne<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>After this, <hi>Agnes</hi> was brought back to <hi>Coimbria</hi> where her being forc'd away, began to be highly cen<U+017F>ur'd. The Prince<U+017F>s, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Afflicted, and at fir<U+017F>t be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd it was a con<U+017F>equence of that de<U+017F>ign which that Fair Maid had expre<U+017F>s'd to her of her retirement; but <U+017F>ome Women that waited on her, having declar'd that violence had been offer'd to her, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> went and made her complaints to the King, who gave no great atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99165:71"/>Madam, <U+017F>aid he, let that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Plague that deprives you of your Husbands Heart, be remov'd from you, and be not Afflicted at her ab<U+017F>ence, rather thank Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with me for it.</p>
                  <p>The generous Prince<U+017F>s took <hi>Agne</hi>'s part, with a great deal of courage, and <U+017F>he was <U+017F>till di<U+017F>puting with the King, when <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> came to <hi>Coimbria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fir<U+017F>t object which <U+017F>truck his Eyes was <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who was cro<U+017F><U+017F>ing one of the Courts of the Palace, in the mid<U+017F>t of a Cloud of Courtiers, which his Favour did fa<U+017F>ten to him. The <U+017F>ight of him caus'd <hi>Don Pedre</hi> to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>turb'd, but the <U+017F>ight of <hi>Don Pedre</hi> and <hi>Agnes</hi> gave him much greater troubles, he ea<U+017F>ily gue<U+017F>t that it was <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who had re<U+017F>cued her from his Men, and if his fury could have Acted all that it would have done, it had produc'd very <U+017F>ad Effects, at that very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99165:72"/>
                     <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> <U+017F>aid the Prince to him, is it thus that you employ that authority which the King my Father gives you? have you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Employs, and Power from his bounty, but to employ them in perfidiou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s and in abu<U+017F>ing of Women? Were you ignorant of that intere<U+017F>t which the Prince<U+017F>s has in this Maid, and did you not know what a tender affectionate e<U+017F>teem <U+017F>he has for her? No, reply'd <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> with <U+017F>uch in<U+017F>olency as did quite anger the Prince, I was not Ignorant of it, nor of that <U+017F>hare your Heart has in it. Ba<U+017F>e wretch, reply'd the Prince, neither that favour which thou abu<U+017F>es, nor that in<U+017F>olence which makes thee p<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate, <U+017F>hall hinder me from Puni<U+017F>hing of thee, were thou worthy of my blows; but there are other ways to humble thy Pride, and it is not <U+017F>uch an arm as mine that mu<U+017F>t take on it the vile employ of Cha<U+017F>ti<U+017F>ing <U+017F>o mean a thing as thou art.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99165:72"/>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> went forwards at the<U+017F>e words, and left <hi>Don Alvares</hi> in <U+017F>uch a rage as cannot be expre<U+017F>s'd mad to <U+017F>ee an enterpri<U+017F>e fail, which he believ'd <U+017F>o <U+017F>ure, and at the Prince<U+017F>s <U+017F>corn of him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>s'd to him<U+017F>elf to Sacrifice all to his revenge.</p>
                  <p>Though <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi> lov'd his Son, he was too much prepo<U+017F><U+017F>es'd with his pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, to Pardon him what he had newly done, and he did condemn an action of great Ju<U+017F>tice, as if it had been an heinous Crime.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> who the <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s of hope had flatter'd for <U+017F>ome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, beheld <hi>Agne's</hi> return with a mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Sorrow, which left her no other thoughts then of <U+017F>tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up her Brother to revenge.</p>
                  <p>In fine the Prince did <U+017F>ee <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> but in<U+017F>tead of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by him with that joy which he owed to the good <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of his expedition, he <U+017F>hewed him nothing but a clo<U+017F>e Anger. After he had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99165:73"/>
render'd, him his fir<U+017F>t re<U+017F>pects, and and exact account of his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings he <U+017F>poke to him of that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which had been offer'd <hi>Agnes de Castro,</hi> and complain'd of it in the Prince<U+017F>s<hi>'s</hi> Name as well as his own. You ought to be <U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in that re<U+017F>pect, reply'd the King, and that motive which cau<U+017F>es you to <U+017F>pake, is <U+017F>o <U+017F>hameful that I blu<U+017F>h and <U+017F>igh for you. What concerns it you whether that maid, who<U+017F>e pre<U+017F>ence troubles me, be remov'd from hence or not? <U+017F>o long as I would have it <U+017F>o. But Sir, reply'd Don <hi>Pedre,</hi> was open force, craft and the night Sea<U+017F>on, to be employ'd, where the lea<U+017F>t of your orders was <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient? <hi>Agnes</hi> had obey'd you, and if <U+017F>he remains here <U+017F>till, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure it is again<U+017F>t her will. However, Sir, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> is offended at it, and without the fear of di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ing you, which, retains me, that action had not remain'd unpuni<U+017F>h'd. How happy are you,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99165:73"/>
reply'd <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> with a <U+017F>corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <U+017F>mile, to make u<U+017F>e of <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia's</hi> name in this, to maintain the intere<U+017F>ts of your Heart. Do you think I know them not, and that that unfortunate Prince<U+017F>s, looks on the wrong you do her with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency? never more mention <hi>Agnes</hi> to me continu'd he, in a <U+017F>evere Tone, be <U+017F>atisfy'd that I Pardon you for what is pa<U+017F>s'd, and think well on the kindne<U+017F>s which I have for <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> when ere you de<U+017F>ign any thing again<U+017F>t him. No, Sir, an<U+017F>wered the anger'd Prince, I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>pake any more of <hi>Agnes</hi>; but neither <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> nor I will any longer <U+017F>uffer her to be any more expos'd unto the in<U+017F>olency of your Favorite.</p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Portugal</hi> had like to have broke forth at this Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e; but <U+017F>ome Reliques of Prudence prevented it. Retire, <U+017F>aid he to <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> and go make Reflections on what I can do, and what you owe me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99165:74"/>During this Conver<U+017F>ation, <hi>Agnes</hi> was receiving from the Prince<U+017F>s, and from all the Ladies of the Court, great Expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions of Joy and Friend<U+017F>hip, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> <U+017F>aw again her Husband, with a great deal of <U+017F>atisfaction and far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <U+017F>orry at what he had lately done for <hi>Agnes,</hi> <U+017F>he privately return'd him thanks for it, and <U+017F>till was the <U+017F>ame towards him, nothwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding all the Jealou<U+017F>y which was endeavour'd to be in<U+017F>pired in her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> who found in his Si<U+017F>ter, a Maliciou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s worthy of his tru<U+017F>t, did not conceal his fury from her. After <U+017F>he had made vain attempts to moderate it, in blotting <hi>Agnes</hi> out of his Heart, <U+017F>eeing that his Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e was incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <U+017F>he made him under<U+017F>tand, that <U+017F>o long as <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> <U+017F>hould not be Jealous, there was no hopes. That if <hi>Agnes</hi> <U+017F>hould once be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected by her, <U+017F>he would not fail of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning her, and that then it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99165:74"/>
would be ea<U+017F>ie to get Satisfaction, the Prince being now <U+017F>o Proud of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> indulgency. In giving this Advice to her Brother, <U+017F>he promis'd to <U+017F>erve him effectually, and having no need of any body but her <U+017F>elf, to perform ill things, <U+017F>he recommended <hi>Don Alvares</hi> to manage well the King.</p>
                  <p>Four Years were pa<U+017F>s'd in that Melancholy <U+017F>tation, and the Prince<U+017F>s be<U+017F>ides her fir<U+017F>t dead Child, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> who was <U+017F>till Living, had brought two Daughters into the World.</p>
                  <p>Some Days after <hi>Don Pedre's</hi> return, <hi>Elvira,</hi> who was mo<U+017F>t Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous in the Art of well Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Wicked De<U+017F>ign, did gain one of the Servants which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Chamber; <U+017F>he fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>poke her fair, than over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd her with Pre<U+017F>ents and Gifts, and finding in her as ill a Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition as in her <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>he readily re<U+017F>olv'd to employ her.</p>
                  <p>After <U+017F>he was <U+017F>ure of her, <U+017F>he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99165:75"/>
compos'd a Letter, which was after Writ over again in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Hand, which <U+017F>he depo<U+017F>ited in that Maids Hands, that <U+017F>he might deliver it to <hi>Constantia</hi> with the fir<U+017F>t opportunity, telling her that <hi>Agnes</hi> had dropt it; This was the Sub<U+017F>tance of it.</p>
                  <p>I employ not my own Hand to Write to you, for Rea<U+017F>ons that I <U+017F>hall acquaint you with. How happy am I to have overcome all your Scruples! And what Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s <U+017F>hall I find in the Progre<U+017F>s of our Intreague! The whole Cour<U+017F>e of my Life, <U+017F>hall continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F>ent to you the <U+017F>incerity of my Affections; pray think on the <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Conver<U+017F>ation that I require of you. I fancy <U+017F>till, that all Per<U+017F>ons that approach you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of <U+017F>omething of my due. I dare not <U+017F>pake to you in public; Therefore come this Night where you know, I conjure you to it by all that I have <U+017F>uffered; Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> to me; <U+017F>he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99165:75"/>
mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>atisfy'd with my E<U+017F>teem, <U+017F>ince that my Heart could be none but Yours.</p>
                  <p>The fal<U+017F>e <hi>Portugui<U+017F>e</hi> Servant, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd <hi>Elvira</hi> exactly, the very next day perceiving <hi>Agnes</hi> coming from the Prince<U+017F>s <U+017F>he brought the Letter to <hi>Constantia,</hi> who receiv'd it, and found in it, that which <U+017F>he was far from thinking on. Never did tenderne<U+017F>s produce <U+017F>o <U+017F>orrowful an Effect as then. Alas! they are both Guilty, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he <U+017F>ighing, and notwith<U+017F>tanding that Tendency which I find in my Heart to ju<U+017F>tifie them, my rea<U+017F>on mu<U+017F>t needs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them. Unfortunate Prince<U+017F>s, Sorrowful Subject of Fortunes Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricios, why can<U+017F>t thou not Dye, <U+017F>eeing thou art not of a Humor to Revenge thy <U+017F>elf! <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> ought you to give me your Hand, when you knew you could not give me your Heart? And thou fair and ungreateful <hi>Agnes,</hi> wer't thou born to produce the Evil of my Days, and to be the cau<U+017F>e of my
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99165:76"/>
Death? After <U+017F>he had given <U+017F>ome Moments unto the violence of her Sorrow, <U+017F>he call'd to her that Per<U+017F>on who had brought her the Letter, charg'd her not to <U+017F>pake of it to any body, and then order'd that no body what<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <U+017F>hould be Admitted into her Chamber.</p>
                  <p>Then did <U+017F>he with more Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty think on him whom <U+017F>he could not in<U+017F>pire with Love, and on her that betray'd her. The trouble of her Soul did not hinder her from <U+017F>eeking <U+017F>ome means to excu<U+017F>e them. And de<U+017F>irous to do all that <U+017F>he could for <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> <U+017F>he took a firm Re<U+017F>olution of not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elvira</hi> was not long, without being Inform'd of what pa<U+017F>s'd, and of the Prince<U+017F>s<hi>'s</hi> Sorrow, whence <U+017F>he hoped for all that <U+017F>he could wi<U+017F>h.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> far from imagining any <U+017F>uch Storm, return'd to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> and learning her indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, <U+017F>he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99165:76"/>
pa<U+017F>s'd the re<U+017F>t of the day at her Chamber door, to learn <U+017F>ome News of her; but <U+017F>he was not permitted to enter. That No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty did <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>e and di<U+017F>turb'd her. The Prince had the <U+017F>ame fate, and was <U+017F>tartled at an order that was not to concern him.</p>
                  <p>Finally the next day <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> appear'd; but with <U+017F>o much De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that it was difficult to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <U+017F>he had <U+017F>uffer'd much. <hi>Agnes</hi> was the mo<U+017F>t pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach her. The Prince<U+017F>s could not contain her Tears. They both kept <U+017F>ilence along time, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> did attribute that of <hi>Agnes,</hi> to <U+017F>ome remor<U+017F>e, and that Unfortunate Maid not being able to contain any longer; is it po<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Madam, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, that two days can have depriv'd me of all that Bounty which you had for me? What have I done? And for what Crime are you thus to puni<U+017F>h me? The Prince<U+017F>s look'd lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>hingly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99165:77"/>
upon her, and did not an<U+017F>wer her, but with a <U+017F>igh, and <hi>Agnes</hi> offended at <U+017F>uch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ervedne<U+017F>s, went out after an ha<U+017F>ty manner, which contributed much to make her be thought Guilty.</p>
                  <p>After this the Prince came, who found <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>turb'd then u<U+017F>ually, and he mo<U+017F>t obligingly did Conjure her, not to neglect her Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition. My greate<U+017F>t good, is not the Pre<U+017F>erva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Life, My Lord, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wer'd <U+017F>he, I <U+017F>hould take more care of it, did I love you le<U+017F>s; But — <U+017F>he could not go on, and the Prince being put into a Con<U+017F>ternation through her di<U+017F>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, did mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>orrowfully <U+017F>igh'd without an<U+017F>wering, which caus'd her an increa<U+017F>e of Sorrow. To this <U+017F>ome grains of anger being added, and all things tending to per<U+017F>wade the Prince<U+017F>s that <U+017F>he was Sacrificed among<U+017F>t them, <U+017F>he did not enter on any di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e that might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99165:77"/>
a right under<U+017F>tanding, <U+017F>o left her Husband retire without <U+017F>peaking to him.</p>
                  <p>Nothing is more capable of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>turbing our Rea<U+017F>on, and of alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Health, then the <U+017F>ecret Motions of Jealou<U+017F>y and Solitude. <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> who was accu<U+017F>tom'd, to <U+017F>pake freely to <hi>Agnes,</hi> and who beleiv'd <U+017F>he was deceiv'd by her, did Abandon her <U+017F>elf to <U+017F>uch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity as quite did overcome her. She fell violently Sick. The whole Court was concern'd at this Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; and <hi>Don Pedre</hi> was real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Afflicted at it: But <hi>Agnes</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd more Concern'd then all the Re<U+017F>t.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Coldne<U+017F>s towards her, her continual <U+017F>ighs, and her ob<U+017F>tinate Di<U+017F>temper, caus'd that after <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ought after the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ion of it, in all that <U+017F>he could recal into her Memory, <U+017F>he began to fear her <U+017F>elf, and to reproach her <U+017F>elf for all that the Prince<U+017F>s did <U+017F>uffer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99165:78"/>Mean time the Di<U+017F>temper did <U+017F>o increa<U+017F>e that <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Life was extreamly fear'd, and that <U+017F>he her <U+017F>elf began to find that it was time to think no longer of it; that though caus'd her no di<U+017F>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, She look'd on Death as a great good, and perceiv'd the de<U+017F>pair tho<U+017F>e Per<U+017F>ons approach'd her were in without the lea<U+017F>t Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi> who lov'd her and knew her Virtue, was mov'd at the Extremity <U+017F>he was in, and <hi>Don Alvare's</hi> who had not lo<U+017F>t the lea<U+017F>t occa<U+017F>ion, of making him conceive that it was Jealou<U+017F>y which caus'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Death, did but too much Exa<U+017F>perate him again<U+017F>t <U+017F>uch Criminals as were mo<U+017F>t worthy of Compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was not of a Temper long to Conceal his Anger. You give Examples, <U+017F>aid he to the Prince, that will render your Memory very Illu<U+017F>trious, and <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Death, of which none
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99165:78"/>
but you can be accus'd, is the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Effects of a Guilty Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion. Dread Heaven after this, and look on your <U+017F>elf as a Mon<U+017F>ter that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erves not to Live. If my Blood did not <U+017F>till Plead in your behalf, what might you not fear from my ju<U+017F>t Re<U+017F>entments? But what may not the Imprudent <hi>Agnes,</hi> to whom nothing Binds me, expect, if <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> Peri<U+017F>hes? She that in my Court Foments your fooli<U+017F>h Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion with vain hopes, and cau<U+017F>es us to loo<U+017F>e <U+017F>o Amiable a Prince<U+017F>s, that you were not worthy to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> knew, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tantia</hi> was not Ignorant of his concerns for <hi>Agnes</hi>; but he al<U+017F>o knew with what Moderation <U+017F>he had always expre<U+017F>s'd her <U+017F>elf on that point. The Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach was very <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible; but his fault not being voluntary, and that an Imperious Accident did force him to Love in de<U+017F>pight of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99165:79"/>
all his re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, he appear'd more Afflicted, then Confounded. Without well examining of me, you have accus'd me, Sir, an<U+017F>wer'd he, and if my intentions were well known to you, you would not, may be, find me <U+017F>o guilty, I <U+017F>hould take the Prince<U+017F>s whom you <U+017F>ay I Sacrifice for Judge of my Actions, were <U+017F>he in a Condition to be Con<U+017F>ulted. If I am Guilty of any Weakne<U+017F>s, her Equity has never reproach'd me of it, and my Mouth has never informed <hi>Agnes</hi> of it. But Sir, though I had Committed <U+017F>ome Fault wherefore would you Puni<U+017F>h an Innocent Maid for it? Who would perhaps Condemn them as much as you do? Ah! Wretch reply'd the King, <U+017F>he has but too much favour'd you, and thy flames had not been <U+017F>o con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tant had they not been well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. Sir, reply'd the Prince, peirc'd with Sorrow for the wrong which was offer'd to <hi>Agnes,</hi> you
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99165:79"/>
offend a Virtue mo<U+017F>t pure, and tho<U+017F>e expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions which proceed from your Anger, do not become you. <hi>Agnes</hi> has afforded me no Favours, I did never ask her any, and I prote<U+017F>t that I have not had <U+017F>o much as a thought again<U+017F>t what I owe to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>While they were in this Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e one of the Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men came all in Tears to Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>e <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> that <U+017F>he was at the la<U+017F>t Ga<U+017F>pe. Go look on your Work, <U+017F>aid the King, and expect no longer, from a Father, who has but too much <U+017F>par'd you, but that Severity which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve.</p>
                  <p>The Prince did run to <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> who he found Dying, and <hi>Agnes</hi> in a Swound in the Arms of <U+017F>ome Women. That which had caus'd that redoubling of illne<U+017F>s, was that <hi>Agnes,</hi> who could no longer bear the Princes indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, had Conjur'd her to tell
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99165:80"/>
her what her Crime was, and either to deprive her of life or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tore her Friend<U+017F>hip to her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> who felt that <U+017F>he mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>uddainly Dye, would not retain a <U+017F>ecred Anger again<U+017F>t <hi>Agnes,</hi> and after <U+017F>ome words that prepar'd her to a <U+017F>orrowful clearing of the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s <U+017F>he <U+017F>hew'd her that Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Note, which <hi>Elvira</hi> had Compos'd. Ah! Madam, cry'd out the Beautiful <hi>Agnes,</hi> after <U+017F>he had Read it, Ah! Madam, how many <U+017F>orrowful di<U+017F>quiets had you <U+017F>pared me, if your Heart had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F>s'd it <U+017F>elf with its accu<U+017F>tomed Bounty. It is not hard to <U+017F>ee that this Letter is Artificial, and that I have mo<U+017F>t Mercile<U+017F>s Enemies. Can you believe the Prince <U+017F>o Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to employ another Hand, then his own in <U+017F>uch an occa<U+017F>ion as this? And do you think me <U+017F>o <U+017F>imple as to keep that te<U+017F>timony of my <U+017F>hame with <U+017F>o little Cautiou<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s? you are not betray'd, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99165:80"/>
by your Husband, nor by me I call Heaven to Witne<U+017F>s, and tho<U+017F>e Attempts which I made to get out of <hi>Coimbria.</hi> Alas! My Dear Prince<U+017F>s, how little have you known <U+017F>he that you have <U+017F>o Honour'd. Believe not that if I have ju<U+017F>tify'd my <U+017F>elf, I <U+017F>hall ever <U+017F>uffer the Worlds Conver<U+017F>ation. No, no, there is no retreat di<U+017F>tant enough for me to flye to, and I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>o well conceal my face, that it <U+017F>hall never give offence.</p>
                  <p>The Prince<U+017F>s mov'd at <hi>Agnes</hi> di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e and Tears, did pre<U+017F>s her hand, which <U+017F>he held, and fixing her looks on her, capable to move compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion in the mo<U+017F>t in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Souls; If I have done you any wrong, my dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> an<U+017F>wer'd <U+017F>he, Death which I expect every moment will avenge you of it. I ought al<U+017F>o to prote<U+017F>t to you, that I have not cea<U+017F>ed loving you, and that I believe all that you <U+017F>ay, in giving you again my mo<U+017F>t tender affection.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99165:81"/>It was then that that <U+017F>orrow, which acted on them both did reduce them to that extremity, which caus'd the Prince to be call'd in. He was incapable of doing any thing at the fight of them, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding tho<U+017F>e tender motions that inclin'd him towards <hi>Agnes,</hi> he run directly to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Prince<U+017F>s, unto whom a cold clammy <U+017F>weat did denounce her la<U+017F>t moment, felt that <U+017F>he had no time to loo<U+017F>e and cau<U+017F>ing all Per<U+017F>ons to withdraw that <U+017F>he <U+017F>u<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, my Lord, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he to <hi>Don Pedre.</hi> Though I quit my life without repining, I leave not you without regret and trouble. But dear Prince I mu<U+017F>t overcome even dying, and I will wholly forget my <U+017F>elf, to turn my thoughts only on you. I reproach you not, well knowing that it is inclination alone that di<U+017F>po<U+017F>es of Hearts, and not rea<U+017F>on. <hi>Agnes</hi> is <U+017F>ufficiently Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, to in<U+017F>pire mo<U+017F>t ardent pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99165:81"/>
and <U+017F>ufficiently virtuous to de<U+017F>erve the be<U+017F>t Fortune in the World. I al<U+017F>o ask her Pardon for <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall wrong which I have done her, and recommend her to you, as a Per<U+017F>on mo<U+017F>t dear to me. Promi<U+017F>e me, before I expire, to give her my Place in your domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It cannot be better fill'd. You cannot make choice of a more perfect Prince<U+017F>s for your People, nor a better Mother for your Children. And you my dear and faithful <hi>Agnes,</hi> continu'd <U+017F>he, lend not an ear to a too <U+017F>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous virtue, which might oppo<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf to the Prince of <hi>Portugals</hi> happine<U+017F>s. Refu<U+017F>e him not, an Heart that he is worthy of, and give him that Friend<U+017F>hip which you had for me, with that which you owe to his Merit. Take care of young <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> and of the two little Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve me in you, <U+017F>pake of me <U+017F>ometimes to them. Farewell
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99165:82"/>
live both happy, and receive my la<U+017F>t embraces.</p>
                  <p>The afflicted <hi>Agnes,</hi> who had recover'd a little of <U+017F>trength, lo<U+017F>t once more all her <U+017F>en<U+017F>es. Her faintne<U+017F>s was follow'd with <U+017F>uch violent Convul<U+017F>ions that her life was in very great danger. But <hi>Don Pedre</hi> kept clo<U+017F>e to <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> what, Madam, would you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; and with a belief that it were an advantage to me. Ah! <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> if my Heart has in any wi<U+017F>e wrong'd you, your own vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue puni<U+017F>hes it, again<U+017F>t your will for it. Think you me <U+017F>o barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous —as he was going to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue he perceiv'd that Death was clo<U+017F>ing for ever the generous Prince<U+017F>s<hi>'s</hi> Eyes, and it little wanted that he did not follow her.</p>
                  <p>But what an aby<U+017F>s of Sorrow was this to <hi>Agnes</hi>? <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as <U+017F>he learn'd, during a re<U+017F>pite, that her rea<U+017F>on receiv'd that <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> was newly expir'd, <U+017F>he would have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99165:82"/>
de<U+017F>troy'd her <U+017F>elf, and gave a full <U+017F>cope to her di<U+017F>pair.</p>
                  <p>At the Noi<U+017F>e of this Death both the City and Fields were in an uproar, <hi>Elvira</hi> who then <U+017F>aw <hi>Don Pedre</hi> free to di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf, repented for having contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Death of the Prince<U+017F>s. <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who accus'd him<U+017F>elf of it, did condole his Misfortune; And <hi>Agnes</hi> who thought her<U+017F>elf the true cau<U+017F>e of it, did promi<U+017F>e to her grief that <U+017F>he would never forgive her<U+017F>elf for it.</p>
                  <p>There was rea<U+017F>on to watch her for diver<U+017F>e days, in which <U+017F>he dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not her Tears The Prince im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd them in a deep Mourning; But when the fir<U+017F>t Notions of grief were over, tho<U+017F>e of his love made him <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible that he was <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who fear'd now the Prince's di<U+017F>engagement, made new attempts to gain <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> who was become in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99165:83"/>
all things but of her own di<U+017F>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. <hi>Elvira</hi> de<U+017F>irous to reap advantage from her own dexterity, imploy'd all the Art, and Craft in her brains, to rekindle tho<U+017F>e fires wherewith the Prince had formerly courted her; but his incon<U+017F>tancy was already limited, and <hi>Agnes</hi> alone was to reign over his Heart.</p>
                  <p>She had taken a firm re<U+017F>olution <U+017F>ince the Death of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> to give her <U+017F>elf wholly up to retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s for the re<U+017F>t of her Life. Maugre all the Cautiou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s which <U+017F>he us'd to conceal her de<U+017F>ign, the Prince was inform'd of it, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd all he could to di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e his con<U+017F>tancy to <U+017F>ubmit to it. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiv'd him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>tronger then he was in that point; but after he had well Con<U+017F>ulted him<U+017F>elf, he knew but too well, how much <hi>Agnes's</hi> pre<U+017F>ence was nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. Madam, <U+017F>aid he to her one day, his Heart ready to break,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99165:83"/>
and his Eyes full of Tears, which of the Actions of my Life, may have caus'd you to re<U+017F>olve on my Death! Though I have never told you how much I Love you, I am Per<U+017F>waded that you are not Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it. I have been forc'd to <U+017F>ilence during many years, for yours, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's,</hi> and my own <U+017F>ake; But it is no longer in my power <U+017F>o to con<U+017F>train my <U+017F>elf, and I ought to expre<U+017F>s my <U+017F>elf at lea<U+017F>t once with you. Receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the a<U+017F><U+017F>urance of a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, full of re<U+017F>pect and of heat with the offer of my Fortune, which I <U+017F>hould not wi<U+017F>h better, but to <U+017F>hare it with you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> an<U+017F>wer'd not at fir<U+017F>t to the<U+017F>e words but with abundance of Tears; at la<U+017F>t having dryed them up, and looking on <hi>Don Pedre</hi> with an Air, which gave him to under<U+017F>tand that <U+017F>he was not well agreed with her wi<U+017F>hes; If I were capable of that Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99165:84"/>
which you would in<U+017F>pire me with, My Lord, reply'd <U+017F>he, you were oblig'd to Puni<U+017F>h me for it. What, <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> is <U+017F>carce in her Tomb, and you would have me to offend her thus? No my Dear Prince<U+017F>s, added <U+017F>he, with more vehemency, No, <U+017F>he who you have <U+017F>o much weighed down with favours, <U+017F>hall not de<U+017F>erve the cur<U+017F>e of Heavens and the <U+017F>corn of Men by <U+017F>o perfidious an action. Do not therefore, my Lord, <gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<U+017F>tinate your <U+017F>elf in a de<U+017F>ign which I <U+017F>hall never approve of. You owe <hi>Constantia</hi> ever after her Death, <U+017F>uch a fidelity as may ju<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you; and I, to repair tho<U+017F>e Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which I have caus'd her, I ought to avoid all Conver<U+017F>ation with you. Go Madam, reply'd the Prince, changing Colour, go and expect the News of my Death, in tho<U+017F>e places where your Cruelty <U+017F>hall Conduct you. They <U+017F>hall follow you clo<U+017F>e, and that War,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99165:84"/>
that now employs our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours will <U+017F>oon procure it me.</p>
                  <p>Tho<U+017F>e words made the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Agnes</hi> of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tro</hi> to feel that her innocence was not altogether <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>he had taken it to be, and that her Heart did concern it <U+017F>elf for the Prince. You owe the Pre<U+017F>ervation of your Life unto the Prince and Prince<U+017F>s, that <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> has left you, <U+017F>he tenderly reply'd. Would you abandon their Youth to <hi>Don Alvares</hi>? Live, my Lord, live, and Permit the mo<U+017F>t unhappy <hi>Agnes</hi> to fall a <U+017F>ingle Sacrifice? Ah! thou Cruel Maid, reply'd the Prince, why do you order me to Live, if I cannot live without you? Is it an effect of your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred? No, My Lord, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> with <U+017F>ome concern, I hate you not; and would to Heaven that a little of indifferency would come and a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t my Weakne<U+017F>s, cau<U+017F>e me not to <U+017F>ay more. You perceive my Blu<U+017F>hes, expound them as you
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99165:85"/>
plea<U+017F>e; but <U+017F>till con<U+017F>ider, that the le<U+017F>s Aver<U+017F>ion I find in me towards you, the more guilty I render my <U+017F>elf, and that I ought not to <U+017F>ee or <U+017F>pake to you. In fine, My Lord, if you oppo<U+017F>e my retirement, I declare that <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> as odious to me as he is, <U+017F>hall <U+017F>erve me as a fence again<U+017F>t you, and that I <U+017F>hall rather re<U+017F>olve to marry a Man which I abhore, than to favor a pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion which has caus'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> Life. Well, <hi>Agnes,</hi> reply'd the Prince with looks full of <U+017F>orrow, follow tho<U+017F>e Motions that your Barbarous Virtue in<U+017F>pires you with. Take tho<U+017F>e cautious Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ures which you judg mo<U+017F>t ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary, again<U+017F>t an Unfortunate Love, and enjoy the Glory of having refus'd all to my de<U+017F>ires.</p>
                  <p>He retired at the<U+017F>e words, and all troubled, as was <hi>Agnes,</hi> <U+017F>he would not retain him; Her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage overcame her Grief and <U+017F>he thought more then ever on her depart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99165:85"/>It had been difficult for her to leave <hi>Coimbria,</hi> without the Kings con<U+017F>ent, and not to defer that which appear'd <U+017F>o nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to her, <U+017F>he was at <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>es</hi> Apartment. Maugre <hi>Don Alvares</hi> intere<U+017F>ts, he <U+017F>hew'd her a <U+017F>evere brow, and yet not being able to give his con<U+017F>ent to her reque<U+017F>t, you <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>tir from hence, <U+017F>aid he, and if you are wi<U+017F>e, you will here <U+017F>hare and enjoy any Friend<U+017F>hip with <hi>Don Alvares.</hi> I have de<U+017F>ign'd another way, Sir, an<U+017F>wer'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> and the World has no <U+017F>hare in it. You might except <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> reply'd the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> his condition may <U+017F>atisfy an ambitious Per<U+017F>on; but you would not <U+017F>ucceed <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> who <U+017F>o tenderly lov'd you; and <hi>Spain</hi> hath more Prince<U+017F><U+017F>es wherewith to fill, a part of that Throne, which I am to leave to my Son, Sir, reply'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> touch'd to the quick with that di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. If I had any di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions for Love,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99165:86"/>
and de<U+017F>igns of mariage, the Prince <U+017F>hould be perhaps the only Per<U+017F>on, on whom I could fix them, and you, Sir, know that if my ance<U+017F>tors wore no crowns yet they were not unworthy of them. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I will be gone, and I believe not my <U+017F>elf a Slave in a place in which I came free.</p>
                  <p>This bold An<U+017F>wer, which di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd truly <hi>Agne's</hi> Character, did <U+017F>tartle <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> and at the <U+017F>ame time did vex him al<U+017F>o. You <U+017F>hall go, when we <U+017F>hall think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, reply'd he, and without being a Slave at <hi>Coimbria</hi> you <U+017F>hall however expect our orders there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> well <U+017F>aw that there was no <U+017F>hrinking from thence and <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o troubled at it, that <U+017F>he kept her Chamber for many days, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daring to inquire after the Prince; and that <U+017F>olitude <U+017F>av'd her the labour of <U+017F>eeing <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vares.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>During this <hi>Don Pedre</hi> fell <U+017F>ick,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99165:86"/>
with <U+017F>o much violence and danger, that the fear of his Death was general. <hi>Agnes</hi> could not doubt but that it was an effect of his troubles <U+017F>he at fir<U+017F>t believ'd her <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ufficiently <U+017F>trong to <U+017F>ee him dye, rather then prove favourable; but <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall reflections did <U+017F>oon convince her of the contrary. She found not in the bottom of her Heart that cruel con<U+017F>tancy, which <U+017F>he thought to be <U+017F>o firmly e<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli<U+017F>h'd there. She felt <U+017F>ome trouble and di<U+017F>order, <U+017F>hed Tears, made wi<U+017F>hes, and finally di<U+017F>covered all her Weakne<U+017F>s.</p>
                  <p>None could behold the Heir to the Crown, and a Prince that <U+017F>o well de<U+017F>erv'd it in that extremity, without a general affliction. The People who lov'd him, did pa<U+017F>s whole days at the Palace Gates, to learn news of his health, and the Courtiers were <U+017F>orrowful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> alone could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal a Malicious Joy before the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99165:87"/>
King, under <U+017F>orrowful appearances. <hi>Elvira</hi> full of tenderne<U+017F>s, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of remor<U+017F>e <U+017F>uffer'd on her part al<U+017F>o. The King who though he condemn'd his Sons love, did however love him, could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olve to loo<U+017F>e him, and <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> who knew the exce<U+017F>s of his grief expected the end with <U+017F>trange agitations.</p>
                  <p>Finally after more then a Month of fears, <U+017F>ome little hopes did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. The Prince him<U+017F>elf, with Don <hi>Alvares,</hi> were the only two, that had no joy at it, but <hi>Agnes</hi> did feel enough for all the re<U+017F>t.</p>
                  <p>Don <hi>Pedre</hi> perceiving that he mu<U+017F>t re<U+017F>olve to live, again<U+017F>t his own will, thought no longer then how to pa<U+017F>s <U+017F>orrowful days, <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as he was able to go, he <U+017F>ought after <U+017F>olitarine<U+017F>s, and even gain'd <U+017F>o much over his weakne<U+017F>s, as to go in all Places where <hi>Agnes</hi> did not appear but her Idea follow'd
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99165:87"/>
him <U+017F>till every where, and his memory very faithful in repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>enting her to him with <U+017F>o many Charms, did <U+017F>till render her dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
                  <p>One day, that he had been conducted in the Garden, he <U+017F>ought after a Labyrinth which was at the farthe<U+017F>t end, there to conceal his Melancholy during <U+017F>ome hours, he found the <U+017F>orrowful <hi>Agnes,</hi> who had been brought thither by thoughts little differing from his, and her <U+017F>ight which he expected not, caus'd him to <U+017F>tagger, <U+017F>he perceiv'd in his Palene<U+017F>s, and weakne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>ome relicks of his di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. His Eyes full of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>hments, di<U+017F>turb'd her; and notwith<U+017F>tanding the de<U+017F>ire <U+017F>he had to fly, an unknown Power retain'd her, and it was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for her to retreat.</p>
                  <p>After <U+017F>ome moments of <U+017F>ilence which was interrupted with many <U+017F>ighs, <hi>Don Pedre</hi> did ri<U+017F>e from a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99165:88"/>
place where his weakne<U+017F>s had caus'd him to re<U+017F>t, he <U+017F>hew'd to <hi>Agnes</hi> coming towards her, <U+017F>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful marks of his <U+017F>ufferings, and not contented to con<U+017F>erne her pitty by her Eyes; you had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olv'd my Death, cruel <hi>Agnes,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, to her, my will was agreed to it; but the Heavens would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve me for greater evils, and I again behold you, as unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, but more in amour'd then I was before;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> wanted not tho<U+017F>e words to molify her, the Prince's languid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s did <U+017F>pake, and that fair Maids Heart was but too well di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to render up it <U+017F>elf. She then believ'd that <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia</hi> ought to re<U+017F>t <U+017F>atisfied. Love who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated for <hi>Don Pedre,</hi> did triumph over Friend<U+017F>hip, and found out that happy moment, after which the Prince of <hi>Portugal</hi> had <U+017F>o long <U+017F>ighed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99165:88"/>Reproach me not of that which has co<U+017F>t me more then you, my Lord, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, and accu<U+017F>e not an Heart that is neither ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful nor barbarous. I mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>ay that I love you; but when that is confe<U+017F>s'd what do you require more?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who expected not <U+017F>o favourable a revolution, did feel a double <U+017F>atisfaction, and falling at <hi>Agnes's</hi> Feet; he told her more, with a <U+017F>ilence which his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion had caus'd then all the mo<U+017F>t E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent words could have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F>s'd.</p>
                  <p>After he had been <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of all his happine<U+017F>s, he conferr'd with <hi>Agnes</hi> on what they had to fear from <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e.</hi> They concluded that the unfortunate Paper which had di<U+017F>turb'd <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia's</hi> la<U+017F>t days, could not proceed but from <hi>Elvira,</hi> and <hi>Don Alvares.</hi> The Prince who knew that the King was <U+017F>eeking already after new
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99165:89"/>
alliances for him, and that would have his Favorite to Marry <hi>Agnes,</hi> did <U+017F>o tenderly conjure her, to prevent her per<U+017F>ecutions, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent to a <U+017F>ecret Marriage; that <U+017F>he agreed to it after a long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, I <U+017F>hall do all that you plea<U+017F>e my Lord, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, though I have but very <U+017F>orrowful fore<U+017F>ights. All my Blood freezes when I think on that Marriage, and <hi>Constantia's</hi> Image <U+017F>eems as if it would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it.</p>
                  <p>The amorous Prince did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>cruples, and parted from <hi>Agnes</hi> with a <U+017F>atisfaction, which <U+017F>oon recover'd all his <U+017F>trength. He after that did <U+017F>ee her, with the Plea<U+017F>ure of mi<U+017F>tery in love, and at la<U+017F>t the day of their union was come. <hi>Don Gill,</hi> Bi<U+017F>hop of <hi>Guarda,</hi> performed the ceremonies of their Marriage, in pre<U+017F>ence of divers witne<U+017F><U+017F>es that were Faithful to <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who became po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd of all <hi>Agnes's</hi> Charms.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:99165:89"/>She liv'd not quiet for being now the Prince of <hi>Portugals</hi> wife. Her Enemies who <U+017F>till Pro<U+017F>ecuted her did not leave her without di<U+017F>turbance; and the King who was offended at her re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, did ab<U+017F>olutely command her to Marry <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> with threats to force her will if <U+017F>he continu'd refractory.</p>
                  <p>The Prince did highly take her part, and that joyn'd to the refu<U+017F>al which he made of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a Prince<U+017F>s of <hi>Arragon,</hi> gave <U+017F>u<U+017F>picions of the truth to the King his Father.</p>
                  <p>He had a <U+017F>econd, but too much intere<U+017F>ted in the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, not to unravel it. <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> and his Si<U+017F>ter did act in it with <U+017F>uch cares, gave <U+017F>uch largne<U+017F>s, and made <U+017F>o many promi<U+017F>es, that at la<U+017F>t they did di<U+017F>cover the <U+017F>ecret engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt <hi>Agnes</hi> and <hi>Don Pedre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99165:90"/>There little wanted but that the King at fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>o highly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ported, had not broke forth in a cruel manner again<U+017F>t the fair Prince<U+017F>s. <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who<U+017F>e love did change into a violent hatred, did <U+017F>top his fir<U+017F>t fury in making him conceive that though the Marriage could be made void he <U+017F>hould not be <U+017F>ufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd, and he <U+017F>o well did Poi<U+017F>on <hi>Alfon<U+017F>es</hi> mind, that he made him con<U+017F>ent to <hi>Agnes's</hi> Death.</p>
                  <p>The Barbarous <hi>Don Alvares</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd his arm for that horrid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and his rage did <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently an<U+017F>wer for the certainty of the <U+017F>acrifice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> who thought the honour of his Family to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by this alliance, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly his in his Son's proceedings, did give a full power unto that executioner who animated him.</p>
                  <p>It was not very ea<U+017F>y to execute that de<U+017F>ign though the Prince did
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99165:90"/>
not <U+017F>ee <hi>Agnes</hi> but in <U+017F>ecret, all his cares were <U+017F>till watching for her good, and he had been above a Year her husband, when <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vares</hi> found the occa<U+017F>ion which he had <U+017F>o long <U+017F>ought after.</p>
                  <p>The Prince did not take much Plea<U+017F>ure, nor but rarely did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance him<U+017F>elf from <hi>Coimbria.</hi> One unfortunate day, and <U+017F>et a part by the Heavens, for <U+017F>o hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid an act, he made a match at Hunting, towards a <U+017F>tately Hou<U+017F>e that the Kings of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> have near to the City.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes</hi> lov'd all that could plea<U+017F>e him, but a <U+017F>ecret trouble did make her to fear that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate journey. My Lord <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he to him, being alarm'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing for what, I tremble <U+017F>eing you to day, as if it was the la<U+017F>t time in my life. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve your <U+017F>elf my dear Prince,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99165:91"/>
and though the exerci<U+017F>e you are going about is not always dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, con<U+017F>ider the lea<U+017F>t of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and bring me back all that I confide in you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Pedre</hi> who had never <U+017F>een her <U+017F>o Fair and <U+017F>o Charming, did divers times embrace her, and went out of the Palace with his retinue not to return thither again till the next day.</p>
                  <p>While he was going, the cruel <hi>Don Alvares</hi> was preparing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf for that Bloody execution which he had re<U+017F>olv'd. He thought it of that importance as not to ingage him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>ingly, and made choice, to accompany him in it of <hi>Don Diego Lopes Pacheo,</hi> and <hi>Pedro Cuello,</hi> two <U+017F>uch mon<U+017F>ters as him<U+017F>elf, who<U+017F>e cruelties had been a<U+017F><U+017F>ur'd him by his pre<U+017F>ents.</p>
                  <p>They <U+017F>tay'd till night, and the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99165:91"/>
Bautiful <hi>Agnes</hi> was in her fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>lumber, which was the la<U+017F>t of her life, when tho<U+017F>e murtherers came to her bed <U+017F>ide. Nothing had oppos'd <hi>Don Alvares,</hi> who was all powerful, and who was introduced near <hi>Agnes,</hi> by the blacke<U+017F>t of furies. She did awake and perceiv'd, drawing the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by the light of a Taper, left lighted, the dagger with which <hi>Don Alvare's</hi> hand was arm'd. He having not covered his face <U+017F>he ea<U+017F>ily knew him, and forgetting her own danger to think of the Princes. Ju<U+017F>t Heavens! <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he lifting up her Eyes, if you will avenge <hi>Con<U+017F>tantia,</hi> re<U+017F>t contented with all my Blood, and <U+017F>pare <hi>Don Pedre</hi>'s. The barbarous Villain who heard her, gave her not time to <U+017F>ay more, and having not had the Fortune to move <hi>Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes's</hi> Heart, he receiv'd the horrid <U+017F>atisfaction of <U+017F>tabbling it through with a Dagger, His partners did
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99165:92"/>
give her <U+017F>ome blows al<U+017F>o, and there needed not <U+017F>o many to put an end to her innocent life.</p>
                  <p>What a Spectacle, for tho<U+017F>e that approach'd her Bed the next Morning, and what news for the mo<U+017F>t unfortunate Prince of <hi>Portugal.</hi> He pre<U+017F>ently return'd to <hi>Coimbria</hi> at the fir<U+017F>t rumour of this adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and did behold that which had certainly co<U+017F>t him his life, if one could dye of grief. After he had a thou<U+017F>and times embrac'd the bloody Corp<U+017F>e of <hi>Agnes,</hi> and <U+017F>aid all that a ju<U+017F>t de<U+017F>pair could prompt him to <U+017F>peak, he run up and down the Palace like a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tracted Man, requiring the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of his wife from things that under<U+017F>tood him not. He at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>aw the King, and without ob<U+017F>erving any re<U+017F>pect, he gave a full <U+017F>cope to all his re<U+017F>entments, after he had long <U+017F>poken, he fell oppre<U+017F>s'd with grief into a faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s which la<U+017F>ted all the re<U+017F>t of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99165:92"/>
the day. He was carried into his appartment, and <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e</hi> believing that this evil would prove his cure, did not repent him of what he had done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Alvares</hi> with the two others went out of <hi>Coimbria,</hi> and that ab<U+017F>ence di<U+017F>cover'd their guilt, of which the mo<U+017F>t af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Prince did promi<U+017F>e a <U+017F>uddain revenge unto fair <hi>Agnes</hi>'s A<U+017F>hes, being re<U+017F>olv'd to per<U+017F>ue them to the very end of the World. He made a con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble party of tho<U+017F>e that were affectionate to him, and after he had made havok of tho<U+017F>e Territories which are water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Duero,</hi> he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>u'd that War unto the Death of <hi>Alfon<U+017F>e,</hi> incee<U+017F><U+017F>antly mixing of Tears with the blood which he <U+017F>pilt in revenge of his dear <hi>Agnes's</hi> Murther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99165:93"/>Thus was the end of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Amours of <hi>Don Pedre</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and of the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Agnes de Ca<U+017F>tro,</hi> who<U+017F>e memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Prince did faithfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve on his Throne, on which he <U+017F>et by Birth-right after the Death of <hi>Don Alfon<U+017F>e.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>

