<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zelinda : an excellent new romance translated from the French of Monsieur De Scudery, by T.D. gent.</title>
            <title>Histoire d'Alcidalis et Zélide. English</title>
            <author>Voiture, Monsieur de (Vincent), 1597-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A71220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 616:4 or 902:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zelinda : an excellent new romance translated from the French of Monsieur De Scudery, by T.D. gent.</title>
                  <title>Histoire d'Alcidalis et Zélide. English</title>
                  <author>Voiture, Monsieur de (Vincent), 1597-1648.</author>
                  <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
                  <author>D'Urfey, Thomas, 1653-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 127, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and N.T. for James Magnes and Richard Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [10].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Histoire d'Alcidalis et Zélide.</note>
                  <note>This item is identified as Wing S2164 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) at reel 616:5, and as Wing V684 at reel 902:44.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:1"/>
            <p>ZELINDA: An Excellent New ROMANCE. Tran<U+017F>lated from the <hi>French</hi> of <hi>Mon<U+017F>ieur De Scudery. By</hi> T. D. <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nos haec novimus e<U+017F><U+017F>e nihil.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>N. T.</hi> for <hi>James Magnes</hi> and <hi>Richard Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>el-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> near the <hi>Piazza's, Anno Dom.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THe World is grown as uncon<U+017F>cionable to <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>s men of Wit, and Parts, as greedy Hou<U+017F>e-Wives to poor Co<U+017F>termongers; though they have never <U+017F>o much Tra<U+017F>h for a little Money, they mu<U+017F>t have a Ca<U+017F>t into the Bargain; a Prologue, or a Preface: and they expect Wit in them too, though there is none any
<pb facs="tcp:56550:3"/>
where el<U+017F>e. This extortion was a while gratified, but the Nine Si<U+017F>ters are <U+017F>o beggered with the Maintenance of their Multiplicity of Gallants, that the in<U+017F>atiable Critick mu<U+017F>t take down-right Railing, for Wit: And I <U+017F>hould but imitate my betters, if I rak'd in the honour'd a<U+017F>hes, and recited the little failings of my ingenious Predece<U+017F><U+017F>ors, tho<U+017F>e renowned and never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Authors of <hi>Amadis de Gaul, the Knight of the Oracle, Bevis of Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and Unfortunate Jack.</hi>—Or I might with others tax the impudence of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary
<pb facs="tcp:56550:3"/>
Scriblers, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending <U+017F>o audaciou<U+017F>ly to Wit and Poetry, when none has more confidence or le<U+017F>s merit then my <U+017F>elf.—No! I am for Peace and Policy; Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ies and Di<U+017F>putes among Divines, make Tub-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Athei<U+017F>ts;—Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, An<U+017F>wers, Replys and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynders between Doctor. <hi>N.</hi> and Doctor. <hi>S.</hi> concerning each others Practice, expo<U+017F>ed the failings of both to Vulgar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and rai<U+017F>ed the repute of Quacks and hedge Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: while <hi>Wil. Pen</hi> and the Anabapti<U+017F>t were hurling Fire &amp; Brim<U+017F>tone at one another in
<pb facs="tcp:56550:4"/>
               <hi>Alder<U+017F>gate-Street, Muckle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> damned them both over a Pot of Ale. I <U+017F>ay, let the green Faggot-<U+017F>ticks of Poetry cling together in the band of Amity, and in<U+017F>pite of the fierce Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks puffing, they may Hi<U+017F>s, Pipe on, and be Courted, while he blows his Nails: But when the inte<U+017F>tine fire of Envy di<U+017F><U+017F>olves the <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nion, by giving light and plea<U+017F>ure to others, they con<U+017F>ume them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves. I think this is a good <hi><U+017F>imile</hi> now.—Let us conceal each others Faults, and be great; and let not him that is found out, and ju<U+017F>tly condemned, di<U+017F>cover all the
<pb facs="tcp:56550:4"/>
re<U+017F>t to <U+017F>ave him<U+017F>elf, like a faint-hearted Padder.——Why <U+017F>hould the Taylor call the Miller a Thief.—</p>
            <p>Book-Sellers too are grown <U+017F>uch Saucey Ma<U+017F>terly Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, they do even what they plea<U+017F>e; my friend Mr. <hi>Bentley</hi> calls this Piece an excellent Romance; there I confe<U+017F>s his Justice, and Ingenuity. But then he <U+017F>tiles it a Tran<U+017F>lation, when (as <hi>Sancho Panca</hi> <U+017F>aid in another Ca<U+017F>e) 'tis no more <U+017F>o then the Mother that bore me.—In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful to envy his friends Fame! Though Sir <hi>Martin</hi> fetch his Plot from <hi>Pre<U+017F>ter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56550:5"/>
               <hi>John</hi> and the Stingies, <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> will manage all.—But I write not for Glory, nor Self-Interest, nor to gratifie Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, nor Revenge; Now the impertinent Critical Reader will be ready to ask, for what then? For that and all other que<U+017F>tions to my prejudice, I will borrow Mr. <hi>Bays's</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wer, and <U+017F>ay, Becau<U+017F>e—I glad Sir, I will not tell you.—I de<U+017F>ire to plea<U+017F>e but one per<U+017F>on in the World, and (as one Dedicates his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Heroes to <hi>Cali<U+017F>ta,</hi> another to <hi>Urania,</hi> &amp;c.) at the feet of her my adored <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> I lay all my Giants and
<pb facs="tcp:56550:5"/>
Monsters: to any other Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urer I <U+017F>ay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non vides id Manticae quod in tergo e<U+017F>t.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to her I Bow, her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour I Implore; and to her Sentence I <U+017F>ubmit, as becomes her,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Admirer and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant, T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:6"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. l. 15. for <hi>unwritting</hi> r. <hi>uniting.</hi> p. 6. l. 21. for <hi>for,</hi> r. <hi>from.</hi> p. 7. l. la<U+017F>t, for <hi>or,</hi> r. <hi>of<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi> p. 16. l. 14. for <hi>I injured,</hi> r. <hi>I believe.</hi> p. 26. l. 15. for <hi>required,</hi> r. <hi>injured.</hi> p. 34. l. 8. for <hi>not unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onable,</hi> r. <hi>unrea<U+017F>onable.</hi> p. 39. l. 15. for <hi>with,</hi> r<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
               <hi>which.</hi> p. 44. l. 16. leave out <hi>this.</hi> p. 47. l. 20<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> for <hi><U+017F>ee,</hi> r. <hi><U+017F>he.</hi> p. 49. l. 12. for <hi>re<U+017F>olved,</hi> r. <hi>re<U+017F>erved<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56550:6"/>
            <head>ZELINDA; A ROMANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time when <hi>Spain</hi> was divided, not only among<U+017F>t <U+017F>everal Kings, but divers Nations; the <hi>Goths,</hi> the <hi>Moores,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> having each of them a Share: <hi>Arragon</hi> was ruled by one, who in the mid<U+017F>t of tho<U+017F>e Wars that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled his Neighbours, had ju<U+017F>t abilities e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to keep his own Subjects in Peace; and was Famous only for being the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him, who is the Subject of this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56550:7"/>
Hi<U+017F>tory. His Wife after having brought him one Son, dyed: At the <U+017F>ame time the Dutche<U+017F>s of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> a Young and Beautiful Prince<U+017F>s, had newly lo<U+017F>t her Husband, though he was already old. His Council thought it very nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> he <U+017F>hould have more Heirs then one, for his own as well as his peoples Security; and therefore in behalf of all his Subjects, de<U+017F>ired him to choo<U+017F>e a Wife to his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either in his own, or his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Dominions. The Beauty of this Dutche<U+017F>s was well known further then <hi>Arragon;</hi> and be<U+017F>ides that in Policy, the occa<U+017F>ion was not to be let <U+017F>lip of unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Kingdom <U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderable a Town as <hi>Barcellona;</hi> the Kings own incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation made him conceive that Policy the better. Though <hi>Ro<U+017F>alava</hi> had great Beauty, <U+017F>he had yet more Wit than Beauty, <U+017F>o that being already ab<U+017F>olute; nothing le<U+017F>s then a Crown could have tempted her to think of a <U+017F>econd Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; but having an only Daughter as well as he an only Son; She thought this Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch would not make her<U+017F>elf only Queen of <hi>Arragon,</hi> but her Daughter too, and that <U+017F>he could not be blamed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56550:7"/>
if being in the mid<U+017F>t of ambitious Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, <U+017F>he <U+017F>ecured her <U+017F>elf by a way <U+017F>o advantagious and Honourable. She ea<U+017F>ily then con<U+017F>ented, in<U+017F>tead of Dutche<U+017F>s of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> to be called the Queen of <hi>Arragon;</hi> where <U+017F>he was received with the u<U+017F>ual joy and Magnificence upon <U+017F>uch occa<U+017F>ions: Being Young, Agreeable and Di<U+017F>creet, She <U+017F>oon governed her Husband, and con<U+017F>equently the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Now no bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s of Importance was done without her Con<U+017F>ent, who<U+017F>e Satisfaction was the Kings only care; but this great authority <U+017F>he made u<U+017F>e of mo<U+017F>t, in that de<U+017F>ign of Marrying her Daughter to the Prince, which <U+017F>he was much more de<U+017F>irous of, <U+017F>ince <U+017F>he knew what kind of one he was like to be. <hi>Alcidalis</hi> was born <U+017F>o propitiou<U+017F>ly, and with <U+017F>o many natural advantages; That being a Kings Son, was the lea<U+017F>t con<U+017F>iderable: He had a Beauty which won the Hearts of all that <U+017F>aw him, a Wit in his very Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood not to be equalled, and a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of Mind that made every body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pect and fear him: The fir<U+017F>t years of <hi>Alexander</hi> were not more Miraculous than his; and there was not a day in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56550:8"/>
which he did not <U+017F>ay, or do <U+017F>omething to the a<U+017F>toni<U+017F>hment of all about him. Tho<U+017F>e that pretended to skill in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ognomy, by looking on his Face, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told glorious and incredible actions; and they that took <U+017F>urer mea<U+017F>ures by tho<U+017F>e he had done already, fore<U+017F>aw the Crown of <hi>Arragon</hi> would prove too little for <U+017F>uch a head: The Queen ob<U+017F>erved his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections better than any body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grew extreamly Fond of him, and impatient to bring about her Daughters happine<U+017F>s; which <U+017F>he thought con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed le<U+017F>s in being Queen of <hi>Arragon,</hi> than Wife to <hi>Alcidalis.</hi> But how <U+017F>lightly <U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we <U+017F>peak of Fortune, we mu<U+017F>t al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hers to be the only Wi<U+017F>dom, and con<U+017F>equently count our own but folly<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Her de<U+017F>igns are layed <U+017F>o far off, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by ways <U+017F>o impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that they never fail to <U+017F>ucceed in <U+017F>pite of all our endeavours to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and <U+017F>he allows us <U+017F>ometimes to throw in her way our vain oppo<U+017F>itions only to have the plea<U+017F>ure of making then <U+017F>o: Thus far <U+017F>he dallied with <hi>Ro<U+017F>alva</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving to be at length too har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> brings from another Country
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56550:8"/>
young Child, who though both a <U+017F>tranger and an Orphan) was to ruine all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igns of this powerful and politick Queen. The Prince of <hi>Tenara</hi> of a family in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labria,</hi> <U+017F>o Illu<U+017F>trious, as formerly to have given Kings to <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> had <U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderable an E<U+017F>tate newly fallen to him in <hi>Arragon,</hi> that he re<U+017F>olved to take him<U+017F>elf Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of a Right which was a little di<U+017F>puted<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and loving his Wife extreamly, who was as fond of an only Daughter they had about <U+017F>ix years old, they could not think of parting; and therefore tran<U+017F>ported their whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to <hi>Arragon,</hi> where they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the King and Queen with all the civility and kindne<U+017F>s due to Strangers of <U+017F>o great Merit and Quality. But <U+017F>oon after the Prince of <hi>Tenara</hi> grew <U+017F>ick of a di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e that in a few dayes ended him, and left his afflicted wife in <U+017F>o di<U+017F>pairing a condition, as made her not only wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but likely to follow him. She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Queens kindne<U+017F>s, (who began to love her,) all the comfort and a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance which either her afflictions, or affairs were capable of: The Queen had always liked her, but <U+017F>ince this misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56550:9"/>
Pity increa<U+017F>ing her affection, <U+017F>he loved her tenderly. Fate <U+017F>eldom ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>hing our joyes from us, till we have <U+017F>et upon them the highe<U+017F>t value, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we never prize them enough, till the danger of their being lo<U+017F>t makes us do it too much: She lodged her in her own Palace, and took <U+017F>uch care to be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, with her that <U+017F>he <U+017F>eemed to mi<U+017F>s a part of her <U+017F>elf when they were a<U+017F>under. However, all this indulgence of the Queens, (enough to have cured her of any other Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e) only allayed this, by making her bear it with le<U+017F>s de<U+017F>pair and impatience: And yet neverthele<U+017F>s, her Husbands death, with the <U+017F>ad circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances of time and place, was <U+017F>o great a blow, and made <U+017F>o deep an impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, that all the Queens care and kindne<U+017F>s was unable to pre<U+017F>erve her from a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Sickne<U+017F>s; which proceeded for want of Sleep and Nouri<U+017F>hment. The Queens trouble was proportionable, who be<U+017F>ides her Grief for the lo<U+017F>s of <U+017F>uch a friend, was not a little concern'd to <U+017F>ee two <U+017F>uch fatal accidents happen in her Dominions, to a Family newly come to dwell there. Phy<U+017F>itians were conjured
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56550:9"/>
to u<U+017F>e their utmo<U+017F>t endeavours; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did <U+017F>o, her Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e was too <U+017F>trong for their <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t Remedies; and therefore her own Judgment as well as theirs, giving the fatal warning, <U+017F>he re<U+017F>olved to quit the World with as much tranquility, as that dear pledge <U+017F>he left in it would allow her, which <U+017F>ure could not be great, when <U+017F>he reflected upon the age and place <U+017F>he left her in; An Infant in a <U+017F>trangers Country: While <hi>Camilla's</hi> thoughts were thus <U+017F>adly imployed, the Queen once asking her how <U+017F>he<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> did? She gently look't up upon her, and taking her by the hand, ki<U+017F><U+017F>ed it <U+017F>everal times before <U+017F>he was able to <U+017F>peak a word; but at la<U+017F>t told her <U+017F>he was very <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of the obligations <U+017F>he had to <U+017F>o indulgent a Queen that <U+017F>ince <U+017F>he enquired of her health <U+017F>o kindly, <U+017F>he would pre<U+017F>ume to tell her, that though <U+017F>he knew death <U+017F>o near, it was not her greate<U+017F>t apprehen<U+017F>ion, and that her Daughters helple<U+017F>s condition was the rea<U+017F>on why <U+017F>he could not but leave the World uncomfortably; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beg'd leave to manage to the be<U+017F>t her few remaining hours, by ea<U+017F>ing her <U+017F>elf of a heavy burden, and powring out or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56550:10"/>
her own brea<U+017F>t into the Queens her dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t tender thoughts: She told her <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould thank Heaven for giving her leave <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon to follow the Prince her Husband, if <U+017F>he were only <U+017F>ure the pre<U+017F>ent <U+017F>he now made her would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable; a pre<U+017F>ent of all <U+017F>he held dear and precious in the World: Then having dryed her eyes of tears which tho<U+017F>e la<U+017F>t words had drawn from her, <U+017F>he went on to a<U+017F><U+017F>ure her that among<U+017F>t all her mi<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <U+017F>he could <U+017F>carce think Fortune her enemy, that had brought her to the honour of <U+017F>uch a Friend<U+017F>hip, by a journey which <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould think pro<U+017F>perous, were it not for her Lords death, though it proved her own too, <U+017F>ince her kindne<U+017F>s, was a Jewel <U+017F>he could not pay too dear for, and the only thing in the World <U+017F>he valued: But was more comforted with the hopes of her Daughters <U+017F>ucceeding her in that, then in all the Fortunes <U+017F>he left her; and therefore conjured her to look upon her always as the dying pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent of one <U+017F>he e<U+017F>teem'd, and not di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to prove a Mother to the Daughter of a friend, whom <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould think in that better provided for, then in the two
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56550:10"/>
Principalities <U+017F>he was Heir to. And then her death would not be unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, <U+017F>ince not unhappy; for <hi>Zelinda,</hi> who by this change would have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, of being Bred by a Queen every way <U+017F>o extraordinary: Having <U+017F>aid this, <U+017F>he took from under her Pillow a little Box of Jewels, which for her Daughters <U+017F>ake <U+017F>he had always taken care of, and accordingly now put into the Queens hands. <hi>Camilla's</hi> afflicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the manner <U+017F>he expre<U+017F><U+017F>ed it in, were both <U+017F>o moving, that the Queen had not been able to refu<U+017F>e her reque<U+017F>t, though <U+017F>ure of its fatal con<U+017F>equence. She threw her Arms about her, and a<U+017F><U+017F>ured her <U+017F>he received her pre<U+017F>ent with joy, and upon condition <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould never revoke it, which <U+017F>he hoped her recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry would give her lei<U+017F>ure, though not unkindne<U+017F>s to do: That from that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <U+017F>he reckoned her <U+017F>elf to have two Daughters, between whom <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould no more di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h than Twins, of which <U+017F>he did not di<U+017F>pair to have her a Witne<U+017F>s: This cured <hi>Camilla's</hi> mind, though not her body, and made her life ea<U+017F>ier, though not longer; for two
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56550:11"/>
days after <U+017F>he left the World with that Cheerfulne<U+017F>s which the Queens promi<U+017F>es gave her; and the Queen capable of no comfort but the hopes of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. Thus we <U+017F>ee <hi>Zelinda</hi> in le<U+017F>s then three Months become a perfect Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, by burying both her Parents in their Graves, who<U+017F>e Inheritance they came to enjoy; We <U+017F>ee her but <U+017F>ix years old, in a <U+017F>trange Countrey, a thou<U+017F>and Miles from her own; and what is yet wor<U+017F>e in the ab<U+017F>olute power of one who was in time to prove her greate<U+017F>t enemy, and the cau<U+017F>e of all her Mi<U+017F>eries. But none are <U+017F>o <U+017F>afe as tho<U+017F>e in the hands of Fortune, who never fails <U+017F>uch as relie upon her either by choice or nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity: She took into her charge this di<U+017F>tre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Orphan, and <U+017F>o ordered this di<U+017F>a<U+017F>trous beginning, as to make it a means of <U+017F>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her in the Throne of two mighty Kingdoms. <hi>Zelinda</hi> was the mo<U+017F>t per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect creature Heaven ever made; her Per<U+017F>on was as miraculous as her life, and this Story, though very natural in every other part, is incredible where it <U+017F>peaks of her. Since the Sun went round the World he never <U+017F>aw <U+017F>o exact a Beauty, and in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56550:11"/>
this Beautiful body, there was a Wit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the imagination of ours, and <U+017F>uch a one as no other body but hers had been worthy of: In the age when others <U+017F>carce <U+017F>pake Words, <U+017F>he <U+017F>poke Sen<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>uch as might have become any mouth. At her Birth all the Stars were agreed to contribute their be<U+017F>t influences; And <U+017F>he appeared <U+017F>o Divine a thing, as one could not but imagine her fallen from Heaven by a Miracle: She was <U+017F>o natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined to Good, that doing it, in her was <U+017F>carce a Virtue; and it was not in her power, at lea<U+017F>t not without great <U+017F>elf-denyal, to avoid the practice of all things commendable; If we could look into the minds of the mo<U+017F>t extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, we <U+017F>hould not find them <U+017F>o fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s as their lives; and though their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue at la<U+017F>t gets the better, 'tis a victory like tho<U+017F>e in Civil Wars by which they mu<U+017F>t needs <U+017F>uffer, <U+017F>ince their Re<U+017F>olutions are no more their own, then the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that oppo<U+017F>ed them. But in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Creature, Vertue reigned by Birth, and not by Conque<U+017F>t; and therefore <U+017F>he could never fail of doing well, while <U+017F>he did what <U+017F>he liked be<U+017F>t: Be<U+017F>ides the<U+017F>e
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56550:12"/>
perfections which are to be de<U+017F>cribed, tho<U+017F>e Names, Charms, and Secret graces, which make us love <U+017F>o often we know not why, <hi>Zelinda</hi> po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t in <U+017F>uch abundance; that <U+017F>he was the general inclination of every man and woman. All her moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were <U+017F>o agreeable, that no others Beauty was half <U+017F>o Charming, and in her gentle Voice there was <U+017F>omthing like Enchantment. Perhaps this is not all that might be, but 'tis certain, all <U+017F>he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved cannot be expre<U+017F>t, and it will be ea<U+017F>ily much imagined that where there was <U+017F>o much, there mu<U+017F>t be a great deal more. And <U+017F>ince, Madam, by this De<U+017F>crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <U+017F>he appears <U+017F>o very like you, I had as good confe<U+017F>s ingenuou<U+017F>ly, that in the <U+017F>tory there were <U+017F>o many remarkable things of her, that though I minded it extreamly, I could never have drawn <U+017F>o good a Picture if you had not <U+017F>at before me. The<U+017F>e were the Arms with which <hi>Zelinda</hi> was to be victorious, and there needed no other, <U+017F>ince they were enough to Conquer<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
               <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> who would ea<U+017F>ily conquer the re<U+017F>t: She was received into Court with <U+017F>o general a joy, that it <U+017F>eemed an Omen of her future Greatne<U+017F>s there, of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56550:12"/>
which <U+017F>he then took po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion. The Queen who thought her <U+017F>elf uncapable of any comfort <U+017F>ince her Mothers death, found the contrary whenever <U+017F>he was with her, and the Kings affections <U+017F>carce knew a difference between her and his only Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alcidalis</hi> and <hi>Zelinda,</hi> were of that Age in which Painters repre<U+017F>ent Cupids, and had all the agreeable Beauties, the greate<U+017F>t Ma<U+017F>ters in that Art could give them; Their Charms were <U+017F>o equally taking, though extreamly different, and their very childhood was <U+017F>o extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, that none <U+017F>aw them without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding them Born for one another, and each had been an unparallel'd wonder of the World, if it had not <U+017F>een them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Indeed though they had the hearts of all that <U+017F>aw them, they could never have been loved equally to their Merit by any but them<U+017F>elves; no Souls but their own being capable of a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion great enough to de<U+017F>erve theirs. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the God of love, intending to make his power remarkable by <U+017F>hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in per<U+017F>ons <U+017F>o extraordinary, <U+017F>ettled it in their hearts <U+017F>o very early, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56550:13"/>
they felt it long before they knew it, and were not <U+017F>uffered to pa<U+017F>s in quiet that fir<U+017F>t part of life, which Nature <U+017F>eems to allow undi<U+017F>turbed by Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions: Thus the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight of <hi>Zelinda</hi> wrought the <U+017F>ame effect upon <hi>Alcidalis</hi> which it was wont to do upon others, and he made <U+017F>ome impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion upon the heart of <hi>Zelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> which <U+017F>he had never felt before. The Queen in pur<U+017F>uance of her great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign, had bred up this Prince with all the artifice imaginable, that might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline him to love her Daughter. His fir<U+017F>t pratling was taken advantage of, that he might be u<U+017F>ed to call her his Mi<U+017F>tris: he was dayly brought to <U+017F>ee her, and tho<U+017F>e about him <U+017F>till took all occa<U+017F>ions to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend before him either her Face or Fa<U+017F>hion. But his inclinations were not the <U+017F>ame with the Queens, he that had Softne<U+017F>s and Complai<U+017F>ance for all the World, <U+017F>eemed to want it only for her Daughter, and was no where <U+017F>o con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trained as in her company: Whether his high Spirit di<U+017F>dained to be thus given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without his own con<U+017F>ent, or that his Stars, which brought him into the World, for <hi>Zelinda</hi> gave him a natural
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56550:13"/>
aver<U+017F>ion to who<U+017F>oever would u<U+017F>urp that place they had de<U+017F>igned her. But from the fir<U+017F>t moment <U+017F>he came to Court, and was by the Queen made her Daughters Companion, his mind appeared imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately changed, he was perpetually in the Dutche<U+017F>s's apartment, and no where <U+017F>o well plea<U+017F>ed as there. Love to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him<U+017F>elf ea<U+017F>ily into our <U+017F>ouls, at fir<U+017F>t comes alwayes accompanied with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Beauty; and makes no <U+017F>hew of violence or Cruelty, till he knows him<U+017F>elf Ma<U+017F>ter of the place, and too <U+017F>trongly fixed to fear being di<U+017F>po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t. At fir<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e young lovers felt his power in nothing, but an extream plea<U+017F>ure in <U+017F>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, and then <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>weet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s mixt with joy, <U+017F>pred it <U+017F>elf about their Countenance, that it was very vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible their love made them appear more lovely. <hi>Zelinda</hi> had <U+017F>till then been like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of her age, but now began to be more lively; and <hi>Alcidalis</hi> when he <U+017F>aw her, was <U+017F>o gay and agreeable, that it look't as if he had re<U+017F>erved for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <U+017F>ome particular Grace, and the be<U+017F>t of his humour. In that innocent age they enjoyed a plea<U+017F>ant tranquillity of mind
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56550:14"/>
for <U+017F>ome Months, in which they were much happier, then in many more that followed.</p>
            <p>But their pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions increa<U+017F>ed daily with their under<U+017F>tandings, and Love became <U+017F>o powerful, that he quickly made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf be both felt and under<U+017F>tood; <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalis</hi> now grew more thoughtful then ordinary, and when <hi>Zelinda</hi> was ab<U+017F>ent, with an unu<U+017F>ual <U+017F>adne<U+017F>s paid dear for the plea<U+017F>ure of having <U+017F>een her, there was no <U+017F>port for him in any diver<U+017F>ions, but tho<U+017F>e he took with her, for <U+017F>eeing her was his only plea<U+017F>ure; or if any thing el<U+017F>e was not indifferent to him, it was talking him<U+017F>elf, and hearing others talk of her. That heart which even from his Childhood was <U+017F>et upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering the World, now hath no hopes nor thoughts but of gaining <hi>Zelinda;</hi> or if <U+017F>ometimes tho<U+017F>e of his former am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition return, it is but with de<U+017F>ign of rendring him<U+017F>elf more worthy of her, by laying at her feet as many Crowns as <U+017F>he de<U+017F>erved. When ever <U+017F>he quitted the room, he was as if fallen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and next to her company he loved none be<U+017F>t. When alone (which for her
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56550:14"/>
<U+017F>ake he was often) he was perpetually reflecting upon all her words and actions; and having con<U+017F>idered them the <U+017F>everal wayes, they were capable of being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, drew from them accordingly either hopes or fears; then remembring his own expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions of kindne<U+017F>s, was never <U+017F>atisfied with him<U+017F>elf; <U+017F>ometimes he thought he was too timerous, <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too bold, and remained alwayes at la<U+017F>t as much di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ed with him<U+017F>elf, as plea<U+017F>ed with her: He begun by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to give over all tho<U+017F>e recreations he was wont to be fond of, Hunting, which he loved be<U+017F>t, became a dull thing to him when <U+017F>he was not there, and if he <U+017F>till minded his Exerci<U+017F>es, it was but to appear more agreeable to her: In a word, he con<U+017F>idered <hi>Zelinda</hi> as if there had been no Body in the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides.</p>
            <p>Love on the other <U+017F>ide had got into the heart of <hi>Zelinda,</hi> but had not made <U+017F>o great a progre<U+017F>s; whether it were that fearing her high <U+017F>pirit, he dur<U+017F>t not make him<U+017F>elf known to her at fir<U+017F>t, or that <U+017F>he being the younger by two years, was le<U+017F>s <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56550:15"/>
pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion: Yet <U+017F>he was not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned, for when ever <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw the young Prince, <U+017F>he had more care of her beauty and dre<U+017F>s than ordinary; <U+017F>he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Counte<U+017F>s the le<U+017F>s, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>he was de<U+017F>igned for him, and every little re<U+017F>pect that out of decencie he paid her, took <U+017F>omewhat from the <U+017F>atisfaction of the fair <hi>Zelinda.</hi> Yet as <U+017F>he had a Soul, generous, re<U+017F>olute, and infinitely <U+017F>en<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and by con<U+017F>equence capable of none but pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions of the <U+017F>ame nature, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Alcidalis</hi> formed in it an affection as fair and perfect as it <U+017F>elf.</p>
            <p>Love between Per<U+017F>ons of <U+017F>o eminent quality (like fire upon a Beacon) is <U+017F>o impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be concealed, that it is <U+017F>een a great way off. The affections of <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalis</hi> and <hi>Zelinda</hi> was <U+017F>oon ob<U+017F>erved by all the World, and a great many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they were in Love one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before they di<U+017F>cover'd it them<U+017F>elves. In the beginning when Childi<U+017F>hne<U+017F>s made their actions le<U+017F>s ob<U+017F>ervable, though they <U+017F>aw one another with great joy, no body thought there was any other Love between them, then that of the innocent diver<U+017F>ions they took together.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56550:15"/>
But as by degrees <hi>Zelinda</hi> grew more <U+017F>erious, and <hi>Alcidalis</hi> began to <U+017F>hew him<U+017F>elf ma<U+017F>ter of a judgment fit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern his Fathers Kingdom, and a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage capable of conquering any other. There was <U+017F>carce any body in the whole Court, but judged their Souls to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, that it would be almo<U+017F>t an equal difficulty to part'em from their bodies, or from each other. The Queen who was politick beyond her Sex, and de<U+017F>igned nothing <U+017F>o much as marrying her Daughter to <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> was the earlye<U+017F>t jealous of <hi>Zelinda</hi>'s beauty, and con<U+017F>equently the fir<U+017F>t that took notice of this amour; But having a great confidence in her Intere<U+017F>t, and more in her <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>he thought they at la<U+017F>t would be the only Sufferers, and feared no <U+017F>tubborn re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance from minds <U+017F>o tender.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the beauty of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> increa<U+017F>ed daily; and though it dawned but a while ago, now <U+017F>hone with <U+017F>uch light and lu<U+017F>tre, that <U+017F>he <U+017F>eemed to proclaim open War again<U+017F>t the Queen, and all her de<U+017F>igns. On the other <U+017F>ide the young Prince <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56550:16"/>
his birth and parts, began to be weary of living under the <U+017F>lavery of a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the conduct of a Woman. That heart great and Royal by Nature, when filled with Love, di<U+017F>dained any other Empire but <hi>Zelinda</hi>'s; He began to carry his inclinations for her a little more openly, and favoured none but <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>he recommended: He run at the Ring only in her colours, all his motto's <U+017F>poke of her, and he was <U+017F>o proud of her Chains, that he hated all the World <U+017F>hould not <U+017F>ee them; There were none who in their hearts did not favour their affection. The Queen <U+017F>oon began to fear <U+017F>he had dallyed too long with a flame <U+017F>o fatal to all her purpo<U+017F>es, &amp; which now required her utmo<U+017F>t care and endeavours to extingui<U+017F>h it: Yet <U+017F>he re<U+017F>olved to trie violent remedies at la<U+017F>t; and <U+017F>trove by all fair means to win upon the di<U+017F>po<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Alcidales,</hi> which <U+017F>he perceived to grow le<U+017F>s tractable to her every day than other: She u<U+017F>ed all the Arts <U+017F>he could to Eclip<U+017F>e the beauties of <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and to advance tho<U+017F>e of her own Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whom <U+017F>he daily in<U+017F>tructed, both what to <U+017F>ay and do, never <U+017F>uffering her
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56550:16"/>
to appear but with pompe and lu<U+017F>ter But <hi>Zelinda</hi> tru<U+017F>ting <U+017F>till to Nature, whom <U+017F>he had been <U+017F>o much obliged to already, neglected by her <U+017F>elf, was more admired by others, and without any Pearl but tho<U+017F>e of her teeth, or any Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies but tho<U+017F>e of her lips, and <U+017F>uch other Jewels as a waiting Woman Mu<U+017F>e, dre<U+017F><U+017F>es a Poetical Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s in, out-<U+017F>hone the other, though adorned with all the glories of the <hi>Ea<U+017F>t;</hi> <U+017F>o much the wealth that Heaven be<U+017F>tows, Ecclip<U+017F>es what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Earth can lend her Favourites.</p>
            <p>The Queen <U+017F>eeing the danger of their continuing any longer in the <U+017F>ame place, and di<U+017F>pairing of all other wayes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt their increa<U+017F>ing affection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olves to trye if ab<U+017F>ence (though it be the greate<U+017F>t torment of a <U+017F>ettled) might not prove the cure of a growing incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And to that purpo<U+017F>e, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <U+017F>ome indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, de<U+017F>ires leave of the King her Husband to pa<U+017F>s two or three Months in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and having gained his con<U+017F>ent, <U+017F>he commanded all things to be in readine<U+017F>s for her journey, and <U+017F>aid, <U+017F>he would have none attend her but the Ladies. This news extreamly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56550:17"/>
<U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed our Lovers, who had never felt the <U+017F>ting, and been only acquainted with the <U+017F>weets of Love, and except <U+017F>ome few apprehen<U+017F>ions for the future; which makes but <U+017F>light impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions in minds <U+017F>o young, and full of confidence, their joy had been without trouble, and their inclination without the lea<U+017F>t check. <hi>Alcidalis</hi> was mo<U+017F>t concerned, or at lea<U+017F>t could wor<U+017F>t di<U+017F><U+017F>emble; there was nothing he would not have attempted to divert this journey, &amp; a thou<U+017F>and extravigances pa<U+017F>t through his imagination about it, but <U+017F>eeing the time drawn on, and the Queens re<U+017F>olution invincible, he re<U+017F>ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, at lea<U+017F>t not to let <hi>Zelinda</hi> part without a full and open declaration of his pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion for her, which till then, (though all his actions continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to her) his words had never pre<U+017F>umed to offer the lea<U+017F>t hint of: Whether it were that he wanted confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>idence, or thought it needle<U+017F>s to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion that none could ever hide. The la<U+017F>t night being come, he went on the Queens <U+017F>ide; where, after <U+017F>ome time, he found an opportunity of entertaining <hi>Zelinda</hi> alone, it was the fir<U+017F>t minute
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56550:17"/>
that ever <hi>Alcidales</hi> knew what fear was. He attempted once or twice to di<U+017F>cover his pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion; but having not re<U+017F>olution enough to go on, was fain to turn his di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e to <U+017F>omething el<U+017F>e, and though at other times he was the gaye<U+017F>t Man in the World, near <hi>Zelinda</hi> he was then the mo<U+017F>t perplext. But at la<U+017F>t his heart beating, and his colour perpetually changing, he with a confu<U+017F>ed and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling voyce, <U+017F>aid: <hi>I do not doubt</hi> Ze-Linda; <hi>But that you know I love you but; how well, after I have <U+017F>aid all I can, mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>till be left to your imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I tell you this, that if you find me kill'd by your ab<U+017F>ence, you may know the nature of your lo<U+017F>s<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> though your Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be compos'd but of a few dayes to the re<U+017F>t of the World; they will to me <U+017F>eem many Years, and may perhaps out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<U+017F>t me. If you con<U+017F>ider me and your <U+017F>elf, you will find the one too Charming to give a moderate affection, and the other incapable of a weak impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion: From the fir<U+017F>t moment I <U+017F>aw you, my pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion was at the <U+017F>ame height, that time, or favours ever advanc't any other to: And <U+017F>ince every Look, every Word, every</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56550:18"/>
               <hi>Motion of yours has added <U+017F>omewhat to it; whil<U+017F>t I was a Child, I cou'd not expre<U+017F>s it to you; and <U+017F>ince I never dur<U+017F>t; and now I tremble only in <U+017F>aying, I adore you; and if I read not <U+017F>uddenly, <U+017F>omething favourable in your eyes for me, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>oon want the power to let you know the greater part of that I have to <U+017F>ay.</hi> At tho<U+017F>e words, <U+017F>he who had till then kept her eyes upon the ground, look't gently up at him; <hi>Alcidalis</hi> <U+017F>eem'd to have received a new life, and thus continued. <hi>Though inclination be but a blind guide; I mu<U+017F>t needs confe<U+017F>s my <U+017F>elf infinitely fortunate, in that which led me to adore the incomparable</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda; <hi>in whom I hourly di<U+017F>cover <U+017F>uch eminent perfections, as may change even an Aver<U+017F>ion to its contrary: Judge then what a pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion I mu<U+017F>t have conceived for her, <U+017F>ince it was <U+017F>o advantagiou<U+017F>ly born, and has been <U+017F>o continually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd: I confe<U+017F>s freely, Humility is a vertue that you alone have made me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, I ever thought the whole world too narrow for me; but now I think my <U+017F>elf, and that world infinitely below you; I know the la<U+017F>t</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56550:18"/>
               <hi>thing that you con<U+017F>ider in me, is my Quality; If I po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s any thing worthy of you, 'tis my heart, which I offer to you; and which I can <U+017F>ay with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to be Great and Generous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to merit a place in yours. I would not prai<U+017F>e it thus, were it any longer my own: But now I think ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiou<U+017F>ly of it, as I mu<U+017F>t ever do of all things that belong to you. It never had but two de<U+017F>ignes, whereof the fir<U+017F>t, and that which entertained its Childhood, was the Conque<U+017F>t of the World: But <U+017F>ince it has been more a<U+017F>piring, and more rea<U+017F>onable, it has de<U+017F>ired</hi> Zelinda. Here he <U+017F>topt, and waited for her an<U+017F>wer, who in the condition <U+017F>he was in, had much a do to get out the<U+017F>e few words. <hi>Sir, I am <U+017F>o a<U+017F>toni<U+017F>ht at a di<U+017F>eour<U+017F>e of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from you; and to find the eyes of the whole Court upon us, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ire you will give till my return to make you an an<U+017F>wer: Which I beg of you to believe, I wi<U+017F>h may he very <U+017F>udden:</hi> Every body ob<U+017F>erved <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extraordinary between them, but the Queen e<U+017F>pecially, whom their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56550:19"/>
made very unea<U+017F>ie; <U+017F>he ro<U+017F>e from her place, and Smiling upon <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidalis<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi> <U+017F>ay'd, <hi>Sir you entertain</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda <hi><U+017F>o <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly and with <U+017F>o much concern in your face, that I doubt you have had <U+017F>ome little quarrel; if it be <U+017F>o, make me Judge, and i'le <U+017F>ee her do you rea<U+017F>on before <U+017F>he goes. Alcidalis</hi> having overcome the fir<U+017F>t difficulty of declaring his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion to <hi>Zelinda,</hi> was impatient of being interrupted, <U+017F>o that without almo<U+017F>t looking toward the Queen; he an<U+017F>wered her carele<U+017F>sly<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
               <hi>Madam I injured</hi> Zelinda <hi><U+017F>o ju<U+017F>t, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> <U+017F>he had required me, I would yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ire no Judge but her <U+017F>elf, and what quarrel <U+017F>oever we have, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>till have a wor<U+017F>e to them that go about to part us.</hi> This <U+017F>harp reply was ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>erved by all the Court; but the Queen who was concerned at it<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> <U+017F>eemed lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to mind it, and chang'd the Di<U+017F>cou<U+017F>e. The next morning <hi>Zelinda</hi> was hur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri'd away before <hi>Alcidalis</hi> could <U+017F>pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to her, and left him in the fir<U+017F>t great affliction he ever knew; it was all as great to her, and more in<U+017F>uppor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able, in that <U+017F>he was forced to di<U+017F>gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56550:19"/>
her <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of it, and cover al<U+017F>o with a cheerful Face a di<U+017F>contented Mind, hiding her mi<U+017F>fortune in publick with as many Smiles, as <U+017F>he lamented it in private with Teares.</p>
            <p>Of all the troubles that love brings with it, ab<U+017F>ence is one of the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible, there are <U+017F>ome violent; <U+017F>ome <U+017F>harper pains, as that of jealou<U+017F>y, but none <U+017F>o hard to bear; and that <U+017F>o oppre<U+017F><U+017F>es all <U+017F>ort of vigour.</p>
            <p>She was no <U+017F>ooner gone, but <hi>Alcida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> <U+017F>hut him<U+017F>elf up in his Chamber, threw him<U+017F>elf upon the Bed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a <U+017F>torme of Sighs, and a Sea of Tears, he grieved for her, rather as dead then Ab<U+017F>ent; not con<U+017F>idering that love takes ever back with Intere<U+017F>t the joyes be lends, and lets few of his Debtors re<U+017F>t <U+017F>o long as he had done him: Having continued <U+017F>even or eight dayes without <U+017F>eeing any but the King, and him as <U+017F>eldom as his duty would permit, he re<U+017F>olved to follow <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and rather Peri<U+017F>h in an attempt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards happine<U+017F>s, then tamely expect a certain death from her ab<U+017F>enc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> After <hi>Hebrius</hi> one of the mo<U+017F>t famous Rivers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56550:20"/>
of <hi>Spain,</hi> has pa<U+017F>t along the Walls of <hi>Sarago<U+017F>a</hi> (as if there were nothing el<U+017F>e worthy of him in <hi>Arragon</hi>) he takes the way of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> where receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his pa<U+017F><U+017F>age many rivolets, to make his entry more <U+017F>tately into the Sea; he comes at la<U+017F>t within half a League of <hi>Torto<U+017F>a:</hi> The Countrey he waters is very Fruitful, and full of Trees, which is the more agreeable, in that the re<U+017F>t con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts of dry naked Places, and Mountains <U+017F>corcht up by the heat of the Sun, fifteen Leagues from his Mouth. He pa<U+017F><U+017F>es through a Valley two Leagues long, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably broad on both <U+017F>ides, encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<U+017F>t with Mountaines: Tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia</hi> keeps it from the North-Winds, <U+017F>o that it is always Green, and the Inhabitants never feel that Winter, which they <U+017F>ee continually upon the neighbouring Hills: 'Twas in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice that <hi>Zelinda</hi> pa<U+017F>t her Purgatory; and where the Pallace of the Queen <U+017F>tood; She alone was <U+017F>ad where all nature appeared to <U+017F>mile; and lo<U+017F>t hourly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat lu<U+017F>ter, which every thing there abouts <U+017F>eem'd to have borrowed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56550:20"/>
of her; The ab<U+017F>ence of <hi>Alcidalis</hi> troubled her continually, and her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly was not confin'd to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent, but had likewi<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome pre<U+017F>ages of the ills to come, <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and her <U+017F>elf, and <hi>Alcidalis</hi> more dear then both, in the power of the Queen; She con<U+017F>idered, that though the courage of the Prince was great, and his love greater, his Authority was yet but weak. That he would never be <U+017F>uffered to de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Barcelonia,</hi> which fortune of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him <U+017F>o opportunely with the Queens Daughter: To Marry an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, and a Stranger, who had no Fortune, no Support, but afar off, that he alone would not be able to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the commands of the King, the good of the Kingdom, and the de<U+017F>ignes of the Queen, who governed both, that whil<U+017F>t they were Children, though all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd their affection, yet none ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd their Marriage: That many look't upon her already as an enemy of the State, and the Torch that was <U+017F>ooner or later to <U+017F>et the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom on a Flame: The<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>uch
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56550:21"/>
thoughts continually tormented her, and the further <U+017F>he look't into the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the more terrible her pro<U+017F>pect grew. One day above the re<U+017F>t, as <U+017F>he was walking with the Queen in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream thick Wood, <U+017F>he <U+017F>lipt from the company, attended only with one Maid, 'twas no <U+017F>mall ea<U+017F>e to her to have the liberty of venting her Grief; which at other times <U+017F>he almo<U+017F>t dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by di<U+017F><U+017F>embling, and reflecting on various Accidents of her life, what <U+017F>he had already <U+017F>uffered, and what <U+017F>he was hourly threatned with: Her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t her <U+017F>o entirely, that without thinking of the way <U+017F>he found her <U+017F>elf by the Banks of <hi>Hebroes:</hi> The Charms of <U+017F>o delightful a place, the <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s of the Air, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure <U+017F>he took in being alone, invited her to continue her walk; but fearing the Queen might wonder at her ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ence, <U+017F>he <U+017F>topt when the noi<U+017F>e of a Horne, which <U+017F>eemed not to be far off, made her turn her head towards a Neighbouring Mountain, where <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw as <U+017F>he thought, two men clos'd, and falling together from a Rock; but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56550:21"/>
upon a <U+017F>econd view, <U+017F>he found it was a Bear and a man; when immediatly on the place from whence the other fell, <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw a young man very well Hor<U+017F>t, leap down after them, the <U+017F>trength of the Hor<U+017F>e, the addre<U+017F>s of the Hor<U+017F>eman, or the Fortune of both, was <U+017F>uch, that they took no hurt; he immediately kills the Bear at one <U+017F>troak, with his Javelin, and <U+017F>aves his friend. This generous Action <U+017F>o <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized <hi>Zelinda,</hi> that <U+017F>he was almo<U+017F>t angry that any but <hi>Alcidalis</hi> had done it: But he that was on Hor<U+017F>eback came towards her, and pa<U+017F>t the River in a place where it was Fordable. She began to think it was <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> but not being perfectly a<U+017F><U+017F>ured; <U+017F>he askt her Woman if <U+017F>he knew that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; who an<U+017F>wered: Madam, a far off we might have known him by his Action; but now we may <U+017F>ee it is the Prince. As he came nearer, a<U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>hment, fear, and joy, all at once, <U+017F>o <U+017F>ei<U+017F>ed <hi>Zelinda,</hi> that <U+017F>he could not readily find words to receive him with, The Prince who had a longer time to prepare him<U+017F>elf, though not without
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56550:22"/>
<U+017F>ome di<U+017F>order, <U+017F>aid; <hi>Madam, you are not to wonder at any confidence, from a man that is already guilty of that, of having declared he loves you; your la<U+017F>t words gave me an impatiency, that turned every hour of your ab<U+017F>ence into an Age, and I had been unworthy of your return or an<U+017F>wer, had I been able longer to expect either: What I <U+017F>aid then, was but what I mu<U+017F>t always think, and if it were ever Criminal, am come to tell you, I am <U+017F>till Impenitent. Sir <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, if you will give me the lei<U+017F>ure to make you the an<U+017F>wer I promi<U+017F>ed you, when I left</hi> Sarago<U+017F>a: Then (finding her <U+017F>elf Blu<U+017F>h, and that he perceived it) <U+017F>he went on thus: <hi>This Colour that ri<U+017F>es in my Face, proceeds rather from that I am going to <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omewhat I never did before, then from a thought that I do therein any thing again<U+017F>t my honour, I know not whether it be always a <U+017F>hame for a Maid to owne <U+017F>he loves, but if ever it were excu<U+017F>able, <U+017F>ure it is in me. I will not <U+017F>ay that my Stars, or your eminent Qualities forc't me to it; tho<U+017F>e are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that any one may u<U+017F>e; I will only urge <U+017F>uch as are more peculiar to my</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56550:22"/>
               <hi>ca<U+017F>e. I lov'd you</hi> Alcidalis <hi>before I knew it was a fault, and conceived an affection for you before I was cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, of tho<U+017F>e Laws that forhid it to our Sex. None can blame me for giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entrance to a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, which I <U+017F>eem'd rather to have found there, then received into my heart, and which has been <U+017F>o long here; that I can no more remember its Birth more then my own. The fir<U+017F>t inclination I ever had, was for you, and <U+017F>elf love <U+017F>o early, and <U+017F>o natural in all the world, came to me later, then my friend<U+017F>hip for</hi> Alcidalis: <hi>My Rea<U+017F>on (which appeared not in a great while after) found it <U+017F>o well <U+017F>ettled that it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t lookt like rebellion to attempt any thing again<U+017F>t it; be<U+017F>ides it <U+017F>eemed <U+017F>o innocent, and <U+017F>o ju<U+017F>t, that <U+017F>he rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to <U+017F>trengthen, then oppo<U+017F>e it, I <U+017F>ay all this to excu<U+017F>e it both to you and my<U+017F>elf, and to make you know that the <U+017F>oul the free<U+017F>t from weakne<U+017F>s, and mo<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>onable in the World, might have been <U+017F>urpris'd, as mine was: If you are plea<U+017F>ed that I love you, thank not me, but Heaven that would have it <U+017F>o. If</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56550:23"/>
               <hi>you are at all obliged to me, it is only for owning of it to you: Thus, though I had not the power of extingui<U+017F>hing my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I had certainly that of concealing it, I could have di<U+017F><U+017F>embled it all my life time, or as mo<U+017F>t of our Sex do, have <U+017F>howne it you by little, and little; after having made you long de<U+017F>ire it; were it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea<U+017F>onable or unworthy either of you or me: It would never he time to di<U+017F>cover it; but one the contrary, if it be only <U+017F>uch as</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda <hi>ought to have for</hi> Alcidalis. <hi>Why <U+017F>hould I not from this Minute, give him the joy of knowing, and being a<U+017F><U+017F>ured of it. I tell you then I love you</hi> Alcidalis. <hi>and though I <U+017F>ay it with Blu<U+017F>hes, I do it without <U+017F>hame, I accept that heart which you gave me; which I e<U+017F>teem a Trea<U+017F>ure far beyond the Crown you promi<U+017F>ed with it, I am plea<U+017F>ed, to find all the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of your mind truly Royal; but I could wi<U+017F>h your Birth were le<U+017F>s <U+017F>o; for I fear Fortune to take that Crown away, which is the thing I lea<U+017F>t e<U+017F>teem in you, will rob me one day of all the re<U+017F>t. I <U+017F>ee from this hour all the Misfortunes that threaten me, I know your love will cau<U+017F>e the hatred of the Queen, but <U+017F>he that</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56550:23"/>
               <hi>hath to her own the heart of</hi> Alcidalis <hi>can fear nothing: I will re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t all with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olution that <U+017F>hall amaze you; and <U+017F>ince Heaven decreed I <U+017F>hould have affection, I will accompany it with <U+017F>uch a Vertuous Con<U+017F>tancy, that what is ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procht in my Sex, <U+017F>hall be in me e<U+017F>teemed, and wondred at. Alcidalis</hi> from the very fir<U+017F>t Minut <U+017F>he began, had <U+017F>till hearkened to her as one who<U+017F>e fate depended on her Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it much more to his advantage then he dur<U+017F>t have hoped, was <U+017F>o far from being able to expre<U+017F>s his joy, that he even wanted words for an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment: But after a while coming to him<U+017F>elf, &amp; finding her that followed out of <U+017F>ight, he put one knee on the ground; but as he began to <U+017F>peak, the Queen appeared near; the thickne<U+017F>s of the bu<U+017F>hes having hid her approach, <U+017F>o that he aro<U+017F>e again as <U+017F>oon as po<U+017F><U+017F>ible. <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> was extreamly troubled to be <U+017F>o unluckily <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed: And <U+017F>aid, <hi>Sir, you will I fear have cau<U+017F>e to repent this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary humility. Madam,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>I do already, but 'tis only that 'twas no earlier adre<U+017F>t:</hi> Whil<U+017F>t they were talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56550:24"/>
the Queen advanc't, and <hi>Alcidalis</hi> coming up to her, <U+017F>he received him with a Countenance <U+017F>o gay, and full of <U+017F>atisfaction, that <hi>Zelinda</hi> her <U+017F>elf could do no more. After the fir<U+017F>t Complements were over, the Prince having told her how the Chace bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him within <U+017F>even or eight Leagues, he thought him<U+017F>elf obliged to ki<U+017F>s her hands; the Queen <U+017F>eemed to thank Fortune, for having conducted him <U+017F>o near her. <hi>But Sir,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, <hi>I believe you are already paid for all the trouble you have given your<U+017F>elf, for its to be imagined the favour that</hi> Zelinda <hi>granted you ju<U+017F>t now, was not incon<U+017F>ider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: Since you thanked her upon your Knees for it, as we <U+017F>aw; truly it made me not know you at fir<U+017F>t, and I thought it had been <U+017F>ome of your Servants, but I am very glad it was none but your<U+017F>elf who received that <U+017F>atisfaction: Pray let us know what it was, that we may partake in your Good-Fortune, and thank her with you. Zelinda</hi> did not grow red upon this, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>he had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <U+017F>o, <U+017F>ince her di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e with <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidalis,</hi> and fearing what the Queen
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56550:24"/>
<U+017F>aid, might <U+017F>urprize him; womens Wits being ever readie<U+017F>t on <U+017F>uch occa<U+017F>ions; <U+017F>he an<U+017F>wered and <U+017F>aid. <hi>Madam, I was asking</hi> Alcidalis <hi><U+017F>ome News of</hi> Saraco<U+017F>a, <hi>he (who without doubt, was thinking of his Hunting) did not an<U+017F>wer me, I then reproacing him with his heedle<U+017F><U+017F>ene<U+017F>s and Silence, he kneel'd to me of a <U+017F>uddain, and thought by other exce<U+017F>s of Civility to repair the neglect he had <U+017F>hew'd in not replying <U+017F>ooner to what I <U+017F>aid. 'Twas very civil in him,</hi> <U+017F>aid the Queen, <hi>and becau<U+017F>e you believe the Prince is think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Hunting <U+017F>till, you have taken care to an<U+017F>wer for him. Zelinda</hi> <U+017F>eeing the Queen pre<U+017F>s her <U+017F>o hard quitted the Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. But <hi>Alcidalis</hi> perceiving the pain <U+017F>he was in, came to her a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance as <U+017F>he had done before to his, and began a relation of <U+017F>ome little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, the King had <U+017F>uffered in her ab<U+017F>ence, <U+017F>o that the Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e was quite changed. The good humour <hi>Zelinda</hi> had put him into, made him entertain the Queen with infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance, and addre<U+017F>s him<U+017F>elf more then formerly to her Daughter. But our young Lovers were not cunning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56550:25"/>
to deceive her; <U+017F>he perceived the alteration and concluded the gayety of <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> and the re<U+017F>pect he treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Daughter with, to be but effects of <U+017F>ome obliging a<U+017F><U+017F>urance he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and from that moment took the re<U+017F>olution of parting them. The Prince went the next day to <hi>Saragu<U+017F>a,</hi> whether the Queen was forced to return eight dayes after, this ab<U+017F>ence was much more <U+017F>upportable to him then the other, for he had in it the comfort of knowing he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd by the per<U+017F>on in the World he mo<U+017F>t e<U+017F>teem'd, they pa<U+017F>t <U+017F>ome Months <U+017F>o well, and with <U+017F>uch Tranquility, that <hi>Alcidalis</hi> could almo<U+017F>t have forgot there was a happine<U+017F>s beyond it.</p>
            <p>But there is a fatal point which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ever pa<U+017F>s, and fortune is <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as weary of the joyes of Lovers, as of the weight of Empires, the highe<U+017F>t happine<U+017F>s has this fault that its then neare<U+017F>t its end. This was <U+017F>ure the only cau<U+017F>e of all the misfortunes that per<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted <U+017F>o innocent an affection: The a<U+017F><U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that <hi>Alcidalis</hi> had of <hi>Zelindas</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, made him live with more di<U+017F>creti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:56550:25"/>
&amp; more fear of di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ing the Queen, then ever he waited on her Daughter oftner, &amp; conver<U+017F>t le<U+017F>s with <hi>Zelinda,</hi> <U+017F>he who from her Childhood had been ever <U+017F>erious, began to be more and more <U+017F>o<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> to <U+017F>ee and <U+017F>peak to the Prince with great Caution and re<U+017F>pect, and do all things that might make their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections le<U+017F>s <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected; but this di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, as it did ever between Lovers, come too late, the Queen who could not be deceived, with much care, <U+017F>ecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and diligence, gave order for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting a de<U+017F>igne which <U+017F>he had in hand, as tho<U+017F>e which are in a place with their enemies<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> <U+017F>ecretly undermine, for the mo<U+017F>t part fear lea<U+017F>t of all the ruine they mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>ink into, and live in <U+017F>ecurity whil<U+017F>t men dig Graves under their feet; <U+017F>o our Lovers not imagining what was contriving again<U+017F>t them, enjoyed a perfect Tranquility, and if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended any mi<U+017F>chief from the Queen, they neither apprehended it <U+017F>o great, <U+017F>o <U+017F>uddain, nor in that dreadful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it was to befall them. Four Months after the Queen came back from <hi>Catalonia,</hi> <U+017F>he took an occa<U+017F>ion to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56550:26"/>
in the beginning of the Spring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, giving no notice of any <U+017F>uch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, till the day before. <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalis</hi> and <hi>Zelinda</hi> were <U+017F>o <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed, that they had <U+017F>carce lea<U+017F>ure to take leave one of the other, as the Prince was expre<U+017F><U+017F>ing to her, the Grief he left her with. <hi>Sir,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, <hi>Remember you promi<U+017F>ed me, never to complain or fear the combination of the whole World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t you, whil<U+017F>t I was for you: Minds a<U+017F><U+017F>ured one of another, like Martyrs in the mid<U+017F>t of all their Sufferings, have <U+017F>till their thoughts fixt together with joy, on their reward to come, we <U+017F>hall meet again, and even in ab<U+017F>ence, our Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <U+017F>hall make our pa<U+017F>t Satisfactions ever pre<U+017F>ent to us, and our imagination <U+017F>hall entertain us with tho<U+017F>e to come:</hi> At that word <U+017F>he took a Ring from her fair hand; <hi>and bad him keep it with her heart. Alcidalis</hi> received it with all the joy his own was capable of, and was almo<U+017F>t in love with the <U+017F>ad occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> that drew <U+017F>o obliging a Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e from her; then taking another of the <U+017F>ame ine<U+017F>timable value, <U+017F>ince it came from him, he gave it her with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56550:26"/>
the <U+017F>ame words, at which they parted with as much Grief as ever they had met with Joy: Tears <U+017F>tole down both their Faces, which both <U+017F>trove to hid from each other, as a<U+017F>hamed of <U+017F>uch a vulgar mark of Sorrow in <U+017F>o Tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant a concern. The Queen went away next Morning, and <U+017F>taying but one day at her own hou<U+017F>e, <U+017F>he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have received <U+017F>ome News from <hi>Barcellona,</hi> which obliged her to go thither, leaving her Daughter with a great part of her Train: She took only <hi>Zelinda</hi> with her, who imagined there was <U+017F>omewhat extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in it; but was not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the rea<U+017F>on; <U+017F>o that knowing not what to fear, <U+017F>he feared every thing: The Queen <U+017F>pent the remainder of that day in <U+017F>eeing the Town, and the magnificent reception that was made for her; the next morning <U+017F>he was told that a Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el bearing her own Name, which <U+017F>he had built not long ago, was newly come into the Port, there was then an hundred Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els in the Port of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> which <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as the Queen appeared, <U+017F>aluted her
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56550:27"/>
with all the Guns, <U+017F>o that for a while there was nothing to be <U+017F>een but Fire and Smoak, the Ships being hid with a Cloud of their own making, they <U+017F>oon made them<U+017F>elves heard in a <U+017F>ound of Trumpets and Howboys: The Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ick and all the Naval Pompe, together with the <U+017F>ight of that Element, which at fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ei<U+017F>es the Eyes and Minds of all the World with Admiration, could not in the lea<U+017F>t divert <hi>Zelinda;</hi> her, heart pre<U+017F>aged tho<U+017F>e ills at hand, <U+017F>he had <U+017F>o long fore<U+017F>een. The Queen put her <U+017F>elf into a Boat, to go and <U+017F>ee this Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, and took <hi>Zelinda</hi> with her and <U+017F>ome few Servants; She found in the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, the Captain and his Wife, with whom <U+017F>he <U+017F>hut her <U+017F>elf up a while, which extreamly increa<U+017F>t the jealou<U+017F>ies of <hi>Zelinda,</hi> <U+017F>he lookt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Spain</hi> with Tears in her Eyes, and began to de<U+017F>pair of <U+017F>eeing it again: An hour after, the Captain and his Wife came out of the Cabine, and told <hi>Zelinda,</hi> the Queen expected her there, her Blood <U+017F>traight Froze in her Veins, and <U+017F>he grew <U+017F>o Pale, that <U+017F>he <U+017F>eemed rather her own Gho<U+017F>t then her <U+017F>elf;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56550:27"/>
the Queen <U+017F>hutting the dore upon her, thus began. <hi>Though it be a long time</hi> Zelinda <hi><U+017F>ince we lo<U+017F>t both; you the be<U+017F>t Mother in the world, and I the be<U+017F>t Friend; Neither the affection that I had for her, nor the la<U+017F>t words <U+017F>he recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you to my care, with <U+017F>hall ever be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: And had the<U+017F>e former con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations been wanting, your Beauty, your Wit, and Di<U+017F>cretion, would have <U+017F>ince obliged me to it. Having Bread you up <U+017F>o long, and having found all the<U+017F>e Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities that gained her my affection, <U+017F>hine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in you with more Lu<U+017F>ter: I were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea<U+017F>onable had I not the <U+017F>ame Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hip for you, that I profe<U+017F>t to her. Then <U+017F>ay I have done more for you then ever <U+017F>he askt of me, <U+017F>he only de<U+017F>ired me to love you as her Daughter, and I have loved you like my own; my Daughter lo<U+017F>t the Title of an only Child from the day your Mother dyed. Since when I have con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered you both as equally my own, and con<U+017F>equently none of your actions or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns have been indifferent to me, <U+017F>o that you may imagine it is impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible but I mu<U+017F>t have taken notice of that pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which your Beauty (though without</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56550:28"/>
               <hi>leave) has rai<U+017F>ed in the heart of</hi> Alcida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis: <hi>I have been no le<U+017F>s then your <U+017F>elf in pain for the injury it might do you. You know how little a<U+017F><U+017F>urance there is in the the words of men of his age and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; both which gave him a licen<U+017F>e to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and fal<U+017F>ifie his Promi<U+017F>es: Be your own Judge, whether his affection can ever be any advantage to you, you <U+017F>ee how many rea<U+017F>ons oppo<U+017F>e it, and <U+017F>hould it ever come into his power and yours, you are too ju<U+017F>t, too grateful, to take him from the Daughter of one you are <U+017F>o much obliged to. I know your Vertue</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda, <hi>but as great as it is you cannot hinder the Prince from <U+017F>eeing you, nor the World from Talking of it; your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue may avoid the ill, but cannot e<U+017F>cape the noi<U+017F>e; I know the prejudice <U+017F>uch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports are to tho<U+017F>e of your Sex, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the di<U+017F>content they give tho<U+017F>e of your Scrupulous Vertue: I thought it then my duty to lead you out of this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and that it was now high time to fulfill the Promi<U+017F>e I made your Mother. The Prince of</hi> Tarentum <hi>is Wi<U+017F>e, Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Valliant, one of the mo<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable Princes in</hi> Italy; <hi>He has by his</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:56550:28"/>
               <hi>Letters and Amba<U+017F><U+017F>adors, made ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<U+017F><U+017F>es to me, that he might have you in Marriage; I would never acquaint you with particulars till all was <U+017F>ettled<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s ripe for Execution. I hear he expects <U+017F>uddainly to lay at your Feet his Per<U+017F>on, and Dominions; the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of this Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el left him fifteen days ago, and obliged him<U+017F>elf in as many more to bring you to him, according to my Orders, Diligence and Secrecy for <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>ons which I cannot yet let you know, are very important to this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, therefore you mu<U+017F>t go away imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and without any Train. I doubt not but this your good nature finds <U+017F>ome trouble in this <U+017F>uddain parting, but though the Sea <U+017F>eparate us for a while, nothing <U+017F>hall divide our affections; and I hope one day to <U+017F>ee you with a Lu<U+017F>ter and Magnificence, which <U+017F>hall recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the private condition you leave us in<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and <U+017F>ure you ought to be glad, you are returning into a Countrey where you <U+017F>hall find your Fortune, your Friends, and the place of your Birth. But although it were not your inclination, it is enough that I will have it <U+017F>o: Be<U+017F>ides the power</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56550:29"/>
               <hi>of a Queen; I claim al<U+017F>o the intere<U+017F>t of a Mother in you: Con<U+017F>ent then willingly to a thing (which be<U+017F>ide that it is a thing very ju<U+017F>t) is al<U+017F>o no le<U+017F>s nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary; in following readily what I coun<U+017F>el you, and perhaps command you, you will <U+017F>hew that Mode<U+017F>ty that you owe to your <U+017F>elf, and a re<U+017F>pect no le<U+017F>s due to me: At the<U+017F>e words <U+017F>he embrac't her; pretending <U+017F>he would not take a formal leave of her, le<U+017F>t it <U+017F>hould too much <U+017F>often both their hearts, <U+017F>he left the Cabin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sorrow, Rage, and Indignation, <U+017F>o overwhelmed the mind of <hi>Zelinda,</hi> that for a while <U+017F>he was neither able to <U+017F>peak nor move, <U+017F>o that <U+017F>he remained in the condition the Queen left here in<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Which yet was the happie<U+017F>t <U+017F>he found her <U+017F>elf in for many Months, <U+017F>ince the greatne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>uddainne<U+017F>s of her mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, took from her all <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of it for the time. All our faculties are <U+017F>o limited, that they are only capable of moderate Objects<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> too much light blinds us, a great noi<U+017F>e makes us deaf<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> great Joys oppre<U+017F>s our Sen<U+017F>es. After having been without any <U+017F>ign of life for half an hour, her Spirits began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56550:29"/>
and with them her Fear, her Love, and all the pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions of a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Mind; Her life came back to her in <U+017F>uch a company that <U+017F>he hated it; her fir<U+017F>t thought was that of throwing her <U+017F>elf at the Queens Feet, in hope to change her Cruel purpo<U+017F>e; but <U+017F>he was gone, and the Ship <U+017F>o far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't, that one could hardly <U+017F>ee the tops of Hou<U+017F>es of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> <U+017F>he turned her eyes that way, and reflecting on what <U+017F>he left, and what <U+017F>he was going to: And having <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly weighed them a while, <U+017F>he turned her <U+017F>elf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tho<U+017F>e that accompanied her with a Countenance more cheerful and Serene then ordinary: and <U+017F>eem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have received <U+017F>ome <U+017F>atisfaction from the con<U+017F>olation they gave her: See went to Bed, and entreated them to leave her to her Re<U+017F>t: Fear and hopes are the two contrary winds of Souls, which never cea<U+017F>e, and there is no tempe<U+017F>t, whereof one or other of them is not the Cau<U+017F>e: The pre<U+017F>ent is but a point, and would be incon<U+017F>iderable to us, if one or other of the<U+017F>e pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions did not give us <U+017F>ome feeling of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56550:30"/>
               <hi>Zelinda</hi> thought that Fortune had plac't her below her own power of helping, or harming farther: And <U+017F>o was in that fatal Tranquility where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in men neither fear nor hope, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the end of their Misfortune, with that of their lives, In all the<U+017F>e Mi<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <U+017F>he had not that of trying <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral remedies, which is commonly the greate<U+017F>t paine of the unfortunate. Having well con<U+017F>idered what <U+017F>he would do, and knowing it could not be long e're <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould be freed from her afflictions, <U+017F>he pa<U+017F>t the night in thinking how <hi>Alcidalis</hi> would receive the News of her lo<U+017F>s: And though <U+017F>he was infinitly grieved to part with him, <U+017F>he had <U+017F>ome <U+017F>atisfaction when <U+017F>he thought of the eminent proof it, would give him of her love, and re<U+017F>olution. The Captain of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el (be<U+017F>ides that <U+017F>he was then their charge) had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular e<U+017F>teem of <hi>Zelinda<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi> having known her at Court; as <U+017F>oon as they thought <U+017F>he was awake they went into her Chamber, and askt her what <U+017F>he would eat, <U+017F>he an<U+017F>wered that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <U+017F>he would not eat then, but that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56550:30"/>
<U+017F>he would never eat more; this reply amazed them extreamly; but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <U+017F>he was relap<U+017F>ed into her former Melancholly, and a little Time, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer Remedy, then any di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e. Three or four hours after, finding that <U+017F>he called no body, they returned, and employed all Prayers, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wa<U+017F>ions to make her receive a little Nouri<U+017F>hment; to which <U+017F>he an<U+017F>wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only with a Sullen <U+017F>ilence, and a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heaviour <U+017F>o cold, and <U+017F>o re<U+017F>olved, that <U+017F>he <U+017F>carce <U+017F>eemed to have heard them: They left her this <U+017F>econd time, but began to apprehend <U+017F>ome Tragical event of this <U+017F>trange re<U+017F>olution. The next night they came again with a Neece of theirs, who was of the <U+017F>ame age with <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and kneeling to her, begged her to have a care of her life, with as many Tears, and as much ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s, as if they had askt their own of her, but all in vain; <U+017F>o that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, and left her to her <U+017F>elf. Three dayes pa<U+017F>t thus whil<U+017F>t neither Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Tears, or Per<U+017F>wa<U+017F>ions, could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with <hi>Zelinda</hi> to <U+017F>peak one word; but the fourth day the<U+017F>e good people
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56550:31"/>
with their Neece, came to make their la<U+017F>t attempt: And de<U+017F>ired her not to be her own Murderer, and commit a Cruelty upon a Per<U+017F>on <U+017F>o excellent, as even the rude<U+017F>t Barbarians would both <U+017F>pare and Wor<U+017F>hip: <hi>Zelinda</hi> having hearkned a while to their Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e, fetcht a deep Sigh, and ri<U+017F>ing from her Seat, <U+017F>hewed her <U+017F>elf plain to them<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> which made them the better perceive the extremity <U+017F>he was in; in the Beautifulle<U+017F>t Face in the World, they beheld a frightful Image of di<U+017F>pair and approaching Death, and <U+017F>omewhat that gave at once horrour and pitty; having looked round upon them all, <U+017F>he thus broke the Silence, <U+017F>he <U+017F>o long had kept.</p>
            <q>My Friends, you ask of me a thing, that only you can give me, you would have me live, and I would willingly obey; but have re<U+017F>olved never to come alive upon the Shore of <hi>Italy,</hi> and here I <U+017F>wear it once more, to the Gods above, by Fire, and Light, and to tho<U+017F>e below by the Gho<U+017F>ts of my Ance<U+017F>tors: My life is then no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56550:31"/>
longer in my power, it now depends on your carrying, or not carrying me to <hi>Italy;</hi> be not then my Murtherers, you to who<U+017F>e care I was committed. The Duke of <hi>Tarentum</hi> expects me, he has never <U+017F>een me, you have here your Neece of my Age and Stature, and not unlike me in the Face; you may put her in my place, and <U+017F>o at once advance her Quality and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the World, and <U+017F>ave me from the greate<U+017F>t Misfortune I know how to fear; 'tis true you will deceive the Duke in giving him another then was promi<U+017F>ed him, but could you bring me to him in the condition, and weakne<U+017F>s I am now, <U+017F>he whom I would per<U+017F>wade you to give him, would much better re<U+017F>emble that <hi>Zelinda</hi> he has heard of. The Duke will <U+017F>ure be happier in a Wife that will receive, if not meet his love, then in the forc't Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of another, who upon <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious con<U+017F>ideration has preferred her Grave to his Bed. But 'tis not me he aims at, <U+017F>ince he never <U+017F>aw me, it is the Dutchy of <hi>Otrante</hi> that he de<U+017F>ires, and I give it this minute to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56550:32"/>
your Neece, with the Quality and Name of <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and call to Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s the <U+017F>ame Gods I have <U+017F>o lately Sworn by, that none <U+017F>hall ever know the contrary from me, and that I never will repent of it. The Queen I know commanded you to carry me where he expects me, but you will do her better <U+017F>ervice in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Will, than her Words; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can you think if <U+017F>he were here now and <U+017F>aw the condition I am now in and knew the re<U+017F>olution I have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken: That <U+017F>he had not rather <U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me <U+017F>afe in any part of the World then to <U+017F>eed me dead into <hi>Italy;</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>he command you to put me alive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dead into the hands of the Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tarentum;</hi> do not you believe <U+017F>he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>igned my Happine<U+017F>s and Advancement in this Marriage, and that <U+017F>he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had <U+017F>o great a care of my Fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would have a much greater care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my Life: When I am dead and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the World <U+017F>hall reproach the Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with this inhumane Cruelty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not <U+017F>he <U+017F>ay <U+017F>he was mo<U+017F>t Innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in that <U+017F>he did not know my Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56550:32"/>
my Aver<U+017F>ion to the Match, and la<U+017F>t of all my De<U+017F>perate Re<U+017F>olution: May <U+017F>he not ju<U+017F>tly lay the whole fault on you, but what need you give her any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at all; This Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el is your own where ever Wind or Waves have pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>age you may go.</q>
            <p>Then taking out a little Box the Queen had left her, where all the Jewels of her Mother were, <U+017F>he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</p>
            <q>The<U+017F>e Jewels are of infinite Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, the Queen cannot make you a greater Pre<U+017F>ent; except <U+017F>he gives you <hi>Barcelona.</hi> Take them, and give me nothing in return, but my Life and Liberty; and <U+017F>ince Liberty it <U+017F>elf, is more then all the Riches of the World, I <U+017F>hall acknowledge my <U+017F>elf <U+017F>till your Debtor; too many would kill the Innocent <hi>Zelinda,</hi> for half the Wealth I offer you to <U+017F>ave her: I buy a good Virtuous Action of you, at a Price able to engage many men in the the mo<U+017F>t Barbarous: If you make a <U+017F>cruple of di<U+017F>obeying the Queen, you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56550:33"/>
ought to have an horrour for the death of an Innocent; will you rather choo<U+017F>e to de<U+017F>troy one of her Friends, then to break one of her commands; If you are afraid of her di<U+017F>plea<U+017F>ure or wrong, you <U+017F>hould con<U+017F>ider, that <U+017F>hortly <hi>Alcidalis</hi> will be greater in <hi>Arragon</hi> then <U+017F>he, who will <U+017F>eek you all over the World, and bring you to a <U+017F>evere account for my Life, and Per<U+017F>on: But if all the<U+017F>e rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons <U+017F>hould not prevaile, I conjure you by the Friend<U+017F>hip you have profe<U+017F>t to me, by the compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion you <U+017F>hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but now, by the<U+017F>e Tears, and all that is dear to you, to deliver me from this Di<U+017F>traction I am in, your <U+017F>uddain re<U+017F>olution will double the Obligation, and incline me to believe, that you were di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to it more through your generous Pitty of my afflicted innocence, then any other con<U+017F>ideration: But if neither my Prayers, nor Tears, nor Offers, can prevail with you: This Tongue that has pleaded my Cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>o un<U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <U+017F>hall never <U+017F>peak again, and death in a <U+017F>hort time will give me that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which you refu<U+017F>e.</q>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:56550:33"/>
            <p>Then <U+017F>he <U+017F>hewed them all her Jewels, which Charmed their Eyes, as much as her Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>es had done their Ears, <U+017F>o that they were no longer able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>t that double violence: The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was a Souldierly man, and very Brave, who had run through divers Fortunes without ever making his own: He thought now was the time or never, <U+017F>o that <U+017F>traight computing how many Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els he might <U+017F>et out with a good part of that Wealth he <U+017F>aw; immediatly all <hi>Zelinda</hi> had <U+017F>aid to him appeared unan<U+017F>werable, he thought him<U+017F>elf oblidged in Honour to relieve <U+017F>o Lovely and Injured a Prince<U+017F>s: Be<U+017F>ides, that he might one day re<U+017F>tore her to <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from him as great a recompence, as he had done for her. He was a great while without <U+017F>peaking, <U+017F>o that <hi>Zelinda</hi> fearing his Silence, proceeded from his irre<U+017F>olution, doubled her intreaties, till at la<U+017F>t he yielded, and vow'd to obey what ever <U+017F>he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: She engaged to go into a Mona<U+017F>tery, and never to leave it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his con<U+017F>ent: <hi>Zelinda</hi> was <U+017F>o over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56550:34"/>
at this deliverance from the Prince of <hi>Tarentum</hi> that <U+017F>he a while for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got <U+017F>he was al<U+017F>o <U+017F>eparated from <hi>Alcida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis;</hi> this <U+017F>atisfaction <U+017F>oon re<U+017F>tored her to Health and Beauty; but they let her appear as little as po<U+017F><U+017F>ible; and their Neece <hi>Crimina</hi> was every day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructed to Per<U+017F>onate <hi>Zelinda;</hi> when <U+017F>he had her Le<U+017F><U+017F>on perfect, they Landed her in <hi>Italy;</hi> though <hi>Zelinda</hi> <U+017F>aw all things go very well, and that the Captain and his Wife were very zealous to have this de<U+017F>ign <U+017F>ucceed; yet her heart began to beat when <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw Land, and was extream impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, till <hi>Crimina</hi> was <U+017F>ettled with the Duke, that <U+017F>he might be gone: Not to expo<U+017F>e the fal<U+017F>e <hi>Zelinda</hi> at fir<U+017F>t, to the eyes of too many People, under the pretence of <U+017F>ome <U+017F>mall Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition, they made her to be carryed in a Chair, into the very Pallace, and under the <U+017F>ame pretence avoided <U+017F>eeing much Company, till <U+017F>he had confirmed her <U+017F>elf in the Meen and Per<U+017F>on of a Princes; <U+017F>o that <U+017F>he let none <U+017F>ee her when <U+017F>he could well avoid it but the Duke; who though he did not find in her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56550:34"/>
that Prodigious Beauty that had made <U+017F>o much noi<U+017F>e, was very well Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with her, and attributed her Alteration partly to her Indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, partly to her Voyage, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <U+017F>omewhat for the Extravagance of Report, which is ever in Extreams. The Captain and his Wife having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived very con<U+017F>iderable Pre<U+017F>ents, took their leave of the Duke, and put to Sea, pretending an Impatience they had to give the Queen an account of their happy Voyage. <hi>Zelinda</hi> <U+017F>tayed all this while in the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, and when <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw the Captain and his Wife A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, pre<U+017F>t them to Hoy<U+017F>t Saile, and <U+017F>hed as many Tears of Joy at her leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Italy,</hi> as <U+017F>he had of Sorrow at her quitting <hi>Spain:</hi> But what avails it, the unhappy to e<U+017F>cape one Misfortune; or what Sanctuary is there for the<U+017F>e whom Fortune is re<U+017F>olved to Per<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute; all the earth is <U+017F>ubject to her Empire, but the Sea <U+017F>eems to be particularly under her Dominion, it is there <U+017F>he excerci<U+017F>es her Power mo<U+017F>t Tyrannically; and mo<U+017F>t Treacherou<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, enriching her Favourites with the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56550:35"/>
Spoiles of the Indu<U+017F>trious: Yet as if there were nothing more to be feared, <hi>Zelinda</hi> thanked Heaven, and being on an Element the mo<U+017F>t deceiptful of the four, among people <U+017F>he could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing farther from, having nothing more to bribe them with. She imagined her <U+017F>elf as <U+017F>ecure as if <U+017F>he had been in a Pallace, and in the mid<U+017F>t of her Friends: They made towards <hi>Sardignia,</hi> where the Captain de<U+017F>ign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leave <hi>Zelinda;</hi> with a Si<U+017F>ter of his, till he could find an opportunity to re<U+017F>tore her to <hi>Alcidalis;</hi> they had Sailed three dayes with a Fair Wind, when two hours before the Sun <U+017F>et, he upon the Watch, from the top of the Ma<U+017F>t, cryed he <U+017F>aw three Sailes making towards them; Men live no where with <U+017F>o little <U+017F>ecurity, as upon that Element, The Water, Earth, Air, and Fire, are all Enemies of tho<U+017F>e that are at Sea; but Men mo<U+017F>t of all, and there is nothing that one Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el apprehends <U+017F>o much, as the Meeting of another; not long after they looked again, and they <U+017F>aw the Tops of three Sailes, which <U+017F>eemed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56550:35"/>
not to be above three Leagues off; an hour after they came more in View, <U+017F>o that they knew them to be Pyrates. Our Captain commanded his men to Hoi<U+017F>t all their Sailes and run for't: The next Morning as <U+017F>oon as it was broad day, they perceived the Pirates were a<U+017F>ide of them, and within <U+017F>ix Miles, <U+017F>o that if they gained upon them in the Morning proportionably to what they had done in the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they judged that by Noon they would be within Cannon-Shot; tho<U+017F>e that were in the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el were a little apprehen<U+017F>ive, the fearful took them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves to Crying and Howling, the mo<U+017F>t re<U+017F>olved, to their Arms: And the mo<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>onable, concluded, that neither the one nor other were to any great purpo<U+017F>e; Though the Captain had experience enough to know that he could not Defend him<U+017F>elf long, yet he cho<U+017F>e rather to die like a man of Honour, then to yield and loo<U+017F>e that Wealth he was <U+017F>o lately and <U+017F>o luckily po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t of. In this Alarum and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral confu<U+017F>ion, <hi>Zelinda</hi> alone was not a<U+017F>toni<U+017F>ht, and whil<U+017F>t others feared for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56550:36"/>
their Goods, and their Liberties, <U+017F>he to whom all the<U+017F>e things were indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, thought only for pre<U+017F>erving her Honour: After having throughly con<U+017F>idered the danger <U+017F>he was in, and the remedies it was capable of; She <U+017F>hut her <U+017F>elf into her Chamber with the Captains Wife, where the fir<U+017F>t thing <U+017F>he did, was to throw all her Ornaments into the Sea, lea<U+017F>t they <U+017F>hould di<U+017F>cover her, then cutting off the Fine<U+017F>t Haire in the World, <U+017F>he Wept a while in the con<U+017F>ideration of what Fortune had reduced her to; but at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>he called for a Suit of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of the Captains, and Di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>ed her <U+017F>elf and Sex. In the mean time the three Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els which they knew belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Coa<U+017F>t of <hi>Africa,</hi> came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Cannon-Shot of them, and Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged a Gun, to <U+017F>ee if they would Strike Saile, but finding they did not, but pretended to defend them<U+017F>elves, when they came within convenient di<U+017F>tance they gave them a Broad-Side: tho<U+017F>e of the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el did the <U+017F>ame, but with a very different <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no harm at all to the Enemies,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56550:36"/>
they had their Ma<U+017F>t and two of their Sailes Shot in pieces, their Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly Shattered, and many of the Souldiers killed; at this noi<U+017F>e <hi>Zelinda</hi> came out of her Chamber, and put her <U+017F>elf among the foremo<U+017F>t, hoping that <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould by that means either be killed the <U+017F>ooner, or di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e her <U+017F>elf the better, the Combate was <U+017F>o un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal that it was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibie it <U+017F>hould la<U+017F>t long, and all the re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance they were able to make, could not hinder the Pirates from Boarding the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el; where after they had killed ten or twelve of the mo<U+017F>t Re<U+017F>olute, and among<U+017F>t the re<U+017F>t the Captain, the Seamen threw down their Arms, and yeilded to Mercy The Captain of the<U+017F>e Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els was of the Kingdom of <hi>Barca,</hi> the people of it are very Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, they drive no Trade at all, what we call Robbing, they call Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Enemy, and whatever they purcha<U+017F>e with their Blood, they count <U+017F>till the bravelier, and mo<U+017F>t Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>tly gotten; and would be a<U+017F>hamed of any other Title to it. This man being the mo<U+017F>t powerful in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56550:37"/>
Valliant and Skilfull in Sea Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, was a long time the Terrour of all the Coa<U+017F>ts of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> he had Mercy, and Genero<U+017F>ity more then his Country, or indeed his Profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion allowed of, naturally and without knowing they were Vertues: As there are in the North, <U+017F>ome Veins of Gold as perfect as tho<U+017F>e in the Indies, though not in <U+017F>o great quantity. So nature in all Climates does produce now and than an extraordinary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, which <U+017F>he in<U+017F>tructs and cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivates her <U+017F>elf, and indues with all imaginable perfection without help of Art. As <hi>Orcantes</hi> (for <U+017F>o this Pyrate was called) was looking over his Captives and the Prize he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. The Maje<U+017F>ty and Beauty that <U+017F>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Zelindas</hi> Face, compelled him to ask her who <U+017F>he was, <U+017F>he an<U+017F>wered <U+017F>he was a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and her name was <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidan,</hi> Nephew to the Captain of that Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, he had taken, that <U+017F>he wi<U+017F>ht her <U+017F>elf with him, and e<U+017F>teemed him happy to have pre<U+017F>erved his Liberty with the lo<U+017F>s of his Life: She <U+017F>aid this with a meen worthy of a better
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56550:37"/>
Fortune, and with an a<U+017F><U+017F>urance more u<U+017F>ual in the Conquerours then the vanqui<U+017F>ht, her Con<U+017F>tancy, her Courage, prevailed more on the Generous Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ition of the Captain, then all the mean Submi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the re<U+017F>t, he was charmed with the Greatne<U+017F>s of her Mind, and Beauty of her Per<U+017F>on, and de<U+017F>ired her to be of good Courage, <U+017F>ince <U+017F>he was fallen into the hands of one, who made Slaves of none but <U+017F>uch as de<U+017F>erved to be <U+017F>o. That for him<U+017F>elf he <U+017F>ought Glory more then Gain upon the Sea, and took more plea<U+017F>ure to give Liberty, then to make Slaves. That he left the re<U+017F>t of the Prize to his Souldiers, and de<U+017F>ired only <hi>Zelidan</hi> for him<U+017F>elf, and that the fir<U+017F>t brave Action they were in, <U+017F>hould be his Ran<U+017F>ome. <hi>And Sir,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>If the advantages of your Mind, an<U+017F>wer tho<U+017F>e of your Per<U+017F>on, I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>oon be more a Captive to your Worth, then you are to my Arms. Zelinda,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected nothing of this nature from a Barbarian, and a Pyrate, was almo<U+017F>t as much amazed as he was plea<U+017F>ed; and the lo<U+017F>s of Liberty, as a Slave to <hi>Orantes,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:56550:38"/>
was <U+017F>o much more <U+017F>upportable then it would have been to her<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> as Wife to the Prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> that <U+017F>he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to bear it with <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ort of <U+017F>atis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. She thought there was no misfortune but to be given to another, nor no Happine<U+017F>s but to be Married to <hi>Alcidalis:</hi> All things el<U+017F>e were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to her. And <U+017F>o her great Soul worthy of the Empire of the World, <U+017F>ubmitted to her pre<U+017F>ent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with le<U+017F>s concern then the meane<U+017F>t Seaman that was taken with her. But <hi>Zelidan</hi> for <U+017F>o we mu<U+017F>t here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after call her, be<U+017F>ides that Heaven had given her all Advantagious Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, both of Mind and Body, was indued with all tho<U+017F>e Graces, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly create Love &amp; Re<U+017F>pect, born to command and not to obey: She <U+017F>oon got the a<U+017F>cendant over her new Ma<U+017F>ter, the Slaves, Souldiers, Seamen, all loved her <U+017F>o well, that <U+017F>he Governed ab<U+017F>olutely, in the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el where <U+017F>he was Pri<U+017F>oner; <U+017F>eeing the kindne<U+017F>s <hi>Orantes</hi> had for her, <U+017F>he judged that it would turn to Love, if once <U+017F>he were di<U+017F>covered; and then his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56550:38"/>
(which el<U+017F>e would be of great advantage to her) would be infallibly her ruine<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> She took all the care imaginable to conceal her <U+017F>elf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually exerci<U+017F>ing her Courage, and all the<U+017F>e Qualities that her Sex is lea<U+017F>t capable of. They pa<U+017F>t all that Summer without ever landing, but to take in Fre<U+017F>h-Water, in which time the new <hi>Zelidan</hi> <U+017F>ignalized him<U+017F>elf on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions: There was no Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el taken where he was not the fir<U+017F>t Aboard<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> <U+017F>o that the Pirate found no difficulty to pay him the full e<U+017F>teem and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hip he had promi<U+017F>ed: The Winter coming on, and the Sea growing fuller of fears, then hopes even for Pyrates them<U+017F>elves, they laid up their Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el in the fir<U+017F>t Port of <hi>Barca: Orantes</hi> gave <hi>Zelidan</hi> his Liberty with a great many Complements, and profe<U+017F><U+017F>ions of perpetual Friend<U+017F>hip: He de<U+017F>ired to bring him to Court, <U+017F>aying he would <U+017F>hew the King the Riche<U+017F>t Prize he ever took upon the Sea. In the mean while <hi>Alcidalis</hi> who was informed of the Queens whole proceeding, believed <hi>Zelinda</hi> in the Arms of the Prince of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56550:39"/>
               <hi>Tarentum,</hi> and thought her capable though not of loving, yet of <U+017F>uffering another, the generous re<U+017F>olution of <U+017F>tarving her <U+017F>elf to death, which <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> was ready to have executed, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidalis</hi> was not able to imagine: But after he had given <U+017F>ome time to a help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s and a mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>peechle<U+017F>s <U+017F>orrow, he lo<U+017F>t all fear, all re<U+017F>pect, together with his hope, and had no other though but that of Revenging him<U+017F>elf immediately upon the Queen, or of forcing <hi>Zelinda</hi> from the Arms of the Prince of <hi>Tarentum.</hi> But at la<U+017F>t his Body being unequal to the violent Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his Mind, he fell into a Feavour, accompanied with <U+017F>uch Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Fits, as all that knew their true cau<U+017F>e, had rea<U+017F>on to believe he would never outlive them; he was in a <U+017F>hort time without any <U+017F>trength, and which was happie<U+017F>t for him without any thought at all: thus Fortune can mock at all our Purpo<U+017F>es, and confine him a whole Month to his Chamber; Who threatned <U+017F>traight to <U+017F>earch the whole World for <hi>Zelinda.</hi> A Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Love, and Jealou<U+017F>y, which are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56550:39"/>
certainly the greate<U+017F>t ills of Mind and Body, raged at once in <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> every one of them with their mo<U+017F>t de<U+017F>perate Circum<U+017F>tances: So that each <U+017F>eemed incurable and altogether un<U+017F>upport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: But at length contrary to all expectation he recovered, but with his Health, his Grief, his Love, and all cares returned; <U+017F>o that without <U+017F>taying till he was perfectly recovered, or making any one acquainted with his de<U+017F>igne, he <U+017F>tole out of <hi>Sarago<U+017F>a,</hi> and going a by way to the Kingdom of <hi>Valentia,</hi> he embarqued at the neare<U+017F>t Port, and pa<U+017F>t over into <hi>Italy:</hi> Where he hoped to <U+017F>ee <hi>Zelinda,</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation was all the Happine<U+017F>s he was capable of in her ab<U+017F>ence; The fal<U+017F>e <hi>Zelinda</hi> had better Fortune then the true one, and her de<U+017F>ignes better <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he had, as ob<U+017F>erved, a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Beauty, and that kind of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding that gives us cunning and <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility for the Affairs of the World, <U+017F>eeing what a dangerous bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s <U+017F>he had undertaken, <U+017F>he endeavoured all <U+017F>he could to gaine the Prince her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Heart, and <U+017F>o fortifie her <U+017F>elf
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56550:40"/>
again<U+017F>t all accidents: He was of tho<U+017F>e years wherein men begin to feel the approaches of Old Age, and to be <U+017F>omewhat le<U+017F>s confident of them<U+017F>elves, and where the mo<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>onable and be<U+017F>t de<U+017F>erving cannot hope to be loved by Women, but out of gratitude or duty: So that the Beauty, Conduct, and Kindne<U+017F>s, of his Young Wife, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him intirely: As we are never <U+017F>o fond of Flowers, as in the beginning of the Spring, or towards the end of Autumne; the fir<U+017F>t for their Novelty, and the others becau<U+017F>e we think we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee them no more: So the plea<U+017F>ures of love are at no time <U+017F>o dear to us, as in the buginning of our Youth, and the approaches of our Age: It is <U+017F>o great and unexpected a Happine<U+017F>s for an Old Man to be loved, that there is no folly they are not capable of in that condition, but the knowledge they have of them<U+017F>elves, <U+017F>carce <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them ever to be firmly per<U+017F>waded of it. The Duke was no <U+017F>ooner in love, but he became Jealous; That pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which in other Countries is an acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal effect of love, is there in<U+017F>eperable
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56550:40"/>
from it<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> they conclude there cannot be a great de<U+017F>ire, without a great fear. Love and Jealou<U+017F>y are Twins with them, and ever born together. Were it then the exce<U+017F>s of kindne<U+017F>s, the Air of his Countrey, or his own natural di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>t, or that he had heard <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what concerning <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> that had cau<U+017F>ed that effect; his Jealou<U+017F>y arrived to that height, that he never thought her <U+017F>afe but when <U+017F>he was with him, and even then had <U+017F>carce patience <U+017F>he <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>een by any eyes but his own. She who for another rea<U+017F>on cared not to be <U+017F>een much, ea<U+017F>ily complied with his Humour, and told him <U+017F>he loved all the effects of his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion equally, that his very fears were agreeable to her <U+017F>ince they were marks of his Love: That her greate<U+017F>t content was to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his, that in having him, <U+017F>he thought <U+017F>he had all the World, and cared not if <U+017F>he was <U+017F>hut up for ever on the<U+017F>e Tearms. He receives the<U+017F>e offers of hers with great joy, and made u<U+017F>e of the Liberty <U+017F>he gave him to take away all hers, <U+017F>o that cutting off dayly <U+017F>omwhat of her Attendants, and of a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56550:41"/>
great Pallace, which before <U+017F>he had the freedom of, he reduced her to four or five Rooms, and a few nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary Servants, as the Duke gave her many marks of his Jealou<U+017F>y, he al<U+017F>o gave her <U+017F>ome of his Love. And <U+017F>trove to make her Pri<U+017F>on as agreeable to her as po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, there was no part of the World that did not contribute its greate<U+017F>t varieties to her Clo<U+017F>ets. Art and nature <U+017F>eemed to <U+017F>trive which <U+017F>hould mo<U+017F>t adorne her Retirement. And <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw all things <U+017F>he could wi<U+017F>h, but men, and tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw only out her Windows. The Duke bought the Lu<U+017F>tie<U+017F>t and Hand<U+017F>ome<U+017F>t Slaves that could be found which (to divert the Malancholy which mu<U+017F>t needs attend <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>olitude) he cau<U+017F>ed to be taught to Fence, Ride, run at the Ring, and all the exerci<U+017F>es of the Nobility, by the be<U+017F>t Ma<U+017F>ters of <hi>Italy;</hi> the<U+017F>e were called the Slaves of the Dutche<U+017F>s, thrice a Week they were brought into a Court all <U+017F>trewed with Sand, where they did all their Exerci<U+017F>es: The Duke had two de<U+017F>igns in this, one of divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Dutche<U+017F>s, and the other of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56550:41"/>
making her de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e all men; by letting her <U+017F>ee in Slaves, the <U+017F>ame Qualities which are admired in people of the highe<U+017F>t Birth, and mo<U+017F>t advantagious Education. <hi>Alcidalis</hi> at his coming into <hi>Italy,</hi> was informed of all this, and judged that no Quality would <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon introduce him, as that of a Slave to the Dutche<U+017F>s; he communicated his de<U+017F>igns to his Gentleman, who had always attended him; who Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui<U+017F>ing him<U+017F>elf like a Merchant, went to the Officers that had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Slaves, and expo<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>ale <hi>Alcidalis;</hi> who having all the Qualities nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary in a very eminent degree; was <U+017F>oon Bought, and <U+017F>o one of the greate<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t accompli<U+017F>ht men in the World, became a Slave: A while he was fain to learn of them he might have taught<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and <U+017F>eeming to learn every day <U+017F>omewhat of his exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<U+017F>es; he in a <U+017F>hort time <U+017F>o advanced, that he was admired of all the World; if he were challenged to run, Wre<U+017F>tle, Fence, or Ride, he was <U+017F>o con<U+017F>tant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful, that at la<U+017F>t he <U+017F>eemed but to be invited to <U+017F>o many Victories:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56550:42"/>
There was no Prize that any one, or number of his Companions, dur<U+017F>t di<U+017F>pute with him: Yet among all the commendations he obtained, he felt a <U+017F>ecret <U+017F>hame in him<U+017F>elf, that his Victories were gained only over a few Slaves, for he had a heart as Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous as that Prince, who <U+017F>corned to Run with any but Kings, though he did all things with an incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Grace, it was with <U+017F>o much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and contempt of what he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, that it was no hard matter to <U+017F>ee his thoughts were <U+017F>omewhere el<U+017F>e: When ever he entered the Li<U+017F>ts, for the Diverti<U+017F>ement of the Dutche<U+017F>s, he came the fir<U+017F>t, and went away the la<U+017F>t; In all his exerci<U+017F>es he had his Eyes and Heart fixt upon the Window, he thought <U+017F>he <U+017F>tood at. For the Jealous Duke had <U+017F>o contrived it; that <U+017F>he could <U+017F>ee without being <U+017F>een: What Mi<U+017F>takes and Errors are not men cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of, the mo<U+017F>t Faithful Lover upon earth adores now a Beauty he has never <U+017F>een, Sighs before her, and gives her at his eyes his heart: And being born a Slave to <hi>Zelinda,</hi> has blindly
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56550:42"/>
<U+017F>old him<U+017F>elf to another: <hi>Alcidalis</hi> who had been remarkable among<U+017F>t the mo<U+017F>t accompli<U+017F>ht Princes, was ea<U+017F>ily <U+017F>o among the<U+017F>e Slaves. The fir<U+017F>t day <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw him, his Beauty, and the Graces that accompanied all his Actions, attracted the eyes of the Dutche<U+017F>s; afterward he gained her e<U+017F>teem, and then her admiration; and having con<U+017F>idered how through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <U+017F>he thought <U+017F>he <U+017F>aw in his Mine and Courage, <U+017F>omewhat worthy of a Nobler de<U+017F>tiny, and much above his pre<U+017F>ent Fortune: She took notice how fixtly he looked up at her Window, of the Palene<U+017F>s and Sadne<U+017F>s of his Face, which all the applau<U+017F>es continually given him were never able to change for a Minute: All this together gave her at fir<U+017F>t Pity, then Curio<U+017F>ity, and at la<U+017F>t Love.</p>
            <p>One Night as this Illu<U+017F>trious Slave went out of the Palace of the Duke, in a dark Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age he felt him<U+017F>elf pulled<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> by one, whom by that light he could only perceive to be a Woman; who taking him a<U+017F>ide, <U+017F>aid, <hi>Clariantes,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:56550:43"/>
(for that was the name he cho<U+017F>e to be called by in this Di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e) <hi>If you are as truly Brave as you appear, come to morrow morning at two a Clock to the foot of the</hi> Greek-Tower, <hi>there you <U+017F>hall be put in a way of being the Happie<U+017F>t man living:</hi> She <U+017F>aid this in great ha<U+017F>te, and left him, without <U+017F>taying for his an<U+017F>wer. But this was enough to <U+017F>et his Thoughts a work: Since Fortune began to per<U+017F>ecute his love, this <U+017F>eem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him the fir<U+017F>t Moment <U+017F>he began to remit of her u<U+017F>ual Rigour; he made no que<U+017F>tion but this Me<U+017F><U+017F>age came from <hi>Zelinda,</hi> <U+017F>ince to make him Happy was in the power of none but her: Yet whether it be that men <U+017F>o extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hold <U+017F>ome little intelligence with their de<U+017F>tiny, or that the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate entertain hope but Coldly, which has <U+017F>o oft deceiv'd them: he dur<U+017F>t not be confident of his good Fortune, but expected the hour <U+017F>he had a<U+017F><U+017F>ign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively agitated by Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Hope, and Fear. The time <U+017F>o much longed for being come, as <U+017F>oon as it was dark he came to the foot of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56550:43"/>
the Tower, which was an old Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which entered <U+017F>ome fifty Foot into the Sea; <hi>Alcidalis</hi> came in a <U+017F>mall Fi<U+017F>her Boat, which having fa<U+017F>tned to the Wall, he attended the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of his Adventure an hour before any body came to him: His Mind all the while no le<U+017F>s to<U+017F>s'd between Hope and Fear, then the <U+017F>mall Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el he was in by the Waves of the Sea: Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions which though they are very contrary, are very often together; the Wind was <U+017F>o high, that there was <U+017F>mall hope the Rope that held the Boat would endure much longer, <U+017F>o that every Minute he imagined it would break; at la<U+017F>t, as he began to de<U+017F>pair of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Happine<U+017F>s, and entertain the di<U+017F>male<U+017F>t thoughts the Night, the Sea, and ri<U+017F>ing Storm could furni<U+017F>h him with; he heard a noi<U+017F>e from the top of the Tower, which he an<U+017F>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to, and immediatly <U+017F>omthing fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Boat, which he <U+017F>oon perceived to be a Ladder of Rope: <hi>Alcidalis</hi> then gave him<U+017F>elf entirely into the Arms of a deceitful hope, and was confident he <U+017F>hould once more behold his unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56550:44"/>
               <hi>Zelinda:</hi> which made him <U+017F>light all dangers, and run up the Ladder as fa<U+017F>t as he could have done the ea<U+017F>ie<U+017F>t Stairs in the World; when he was at the top, he found a Window open, and a Woman who gave him her Hand, and without <U+017F>aying any thing, brought him through a great many turnings into a Clo<U+017F>et, the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<U+017F>t Furni<U+017F>ht that ever he had <U+017F>een, lighted with three Lamps of Gold: He perceived then <U+017F>he was the <U+017F>ame Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had <U+017F>poke to him before in the dark Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age; then putting all things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he concluded <U+017F>he came from <hi>Zelinda,</hi> and had now no fear but that of not <U+017F>taying long enough with her: He had a thou<U+017F>and <U+017F>everal and <U+017F>ome contrary Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions at once in his Mind, which cannot be repre<U+017F>ented on Paper, <U+017F>ince the Soul of man, and among<U+017F>t them, only the Lovers, is capable of <U+017F>uch confu<U+017F>ion: He was for an hour in the <U+017F>tille<U+017F>t Silence imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but at la<U+017F>t he heard, as he thought, the tread of a Woman, and the noi<U+017F>e of a Key, to which turning his Head about, he <U+017F>aw a Door open, and the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56550:44"/>
<U+017F>ame per<U+017F>on enter who gave him her hand at the Window; who Smiling upon him, <U+017F>aid, <hi>Clariantes, I do not doubt but you will pardon me for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made you wait thus long, and confe<U+017F>s the Honour you are going to receive, an abundant recompence for all you have <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</hi> The Prince thanked her; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ired <U+017F>he would inform him a little what this Honour was <U+017F>he meant; She pau<U+017F>ed a while, and then replyed, <hi>Were I not by the Greatne<U+017F>s of your Meen and Courage, <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently a<U+017F><U+017F>ured of that of your Mind, I <U+017F>hould not venture to let you know your good Fortune thus at once, le<U+017F>t exce<U+017F>s of joy <U+017F>hould overpower your Spirits; but it is to be <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed a man of your Merit can never be <U+017F>urprized at his good Fortune, whatever it be; know then, that you are now in</hi> Zelinda's <hi>Clo<U+017F>et, and <U+017F>hall immediatly be brought into her Chamber; the Dutche<U+017F>s has taken notice of your good Qualities, and finding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ami<U+017F>s in you but your Fortune, is re<U+017F>olved to better that her <U+017F>elf; and to that end de<U+017F>ires your acquaintance: On your part <U+017F>ee you make good u<U+017F>e of this occa<U+017F>ion, and <U+017F>hew as much Di<U+017F>cretion</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:56550:45"/>
               <hi>and Conduct hereafter, as you have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <U+017F>hewn Courage and Genero<U+017F>ity.</hi> Having <U+017F>aid this, <U+017F>he led him into the Dutche<U+017F><U+017F>es Chamber. How <U+017F>trangely are our Minds wrought upon? <hi>Alcida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> whom death it <U+017F>elf would not have di<U+017F>compo<U+017F>ed, trembles in a place where he knew there were none but Women; that heart which would have encountered a world of Enemies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear, melts at the imaginary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the only per<U+017F>on upon earth he loves, and knows him<U+017F>elf to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved by: The Chamber had ju<U+017F>t the light that <U+017F>uch affairs required, which was not much; the <U+017F>hame and di<U+017F>order of a Young woman unpractis'd in the Thefts of Love, made her conceal her <U+017F>elf <U+017F>o much, that had <hi>Alcidalis</hi> been le<U+017F>s prepo<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t then indeed he was, he could not ea<U+017F>ily have found his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>take: He immediately fell upon his Knees to her, and after a few words confu<U+017F>edly uttered, and wor<U+017F>e follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he <U+017F>topt in the middle of his Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e; Amazement, Joy, and Love <U+017F>ei<U+017F>ed him <U+017F>o in an in<U+017F>tant, that half<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> be<U+017F>ide-him<U+017F>elf he let fall his head upon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56550:45"/>
the Bed of the young Prince<U+017F>s, who lifting it up with her hand, brought him a little to him<U+017F>elf; but a con<U+017F>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s of his di<U+017F>order kept him <U+017F>till in it, <U+017F>o that he could only <U+017F>ay at la<U+017F>t,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Zelinda,</hi> Heaven has had <U+017F>ome pity on the unhappy <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> and once before I die given me a <U+017F>ight of tho<U+017F>e perfections I would have dyed to have <U+017F>een; my love is <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame, and I am not the le<U+017F>s yours for your being anothers; the Tyranny of Fate may force our Per<U+017F>ons out of our own di<U+017F>po<U+017F>al, but hearts are given by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves alone, and <U+017F>ure what is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ju<U+017F>tly taken, we ju<U+017F>tly may recover.</q>
            <p>Here his Sighs interrupted his Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cout<U+017F>e, and as he would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it, they heard a great noi<U+017F>e in the Palace, which <U+017F>he that was intru<U+017F>ted came out of Breath to tell them it was the Duke, and that he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready on the Dutche<U+017F>s Side: Who, good man, far from thinking what had happened, had de<U+017F>igned to <U+017F>pend two
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56550:46"/>
or three days in Hunting; but whether it were Love, or Jealou<U+017F>ie, or that he thought, that for being le<U+017F>s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he <U+017F>hould be the more welcome to the Dutche<U+017F>s; he returned the very day, and the fir<U+017F>t thing he did, came to vi<U+017F>it her. I hate him for coming <U+017F>o un<U+017F>ea<U+017F>onably; for I would fain have <U+017F>een what reply <U+017F>he would have found to a Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e <U+017F>he <U+017F>o little compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and le<U+017F>s expected; and had I made the Story, <hi>Alcidalis</hi> <U+017F>hould have made him—what the Dutche<U+017F>s plea<U+017F>ed: But as things were, there was no <U+017F>taying any longer, and the Lady that brought him, in all ha<U+017F>te conducted him to the <U+017F>ame Window he came in it. Seeing and dete<U+017F>ting this la<U+017F>t Treachery of Fortune, he had more mind to precipitate him<U+017F>elf, then to make u<U+017F>e of his Ladder of Ropes, and had done it, but for the hope of Climing up by it another time. The <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s of that thought per<U+017F>waded him to live a little longer, but with many ra<U+017F>h Vows and deep Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not to <U+017F>urvive <U+017F>uch another Jilting trick; and brought him <U+017F>afe,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56550:46"/>
and unob<U+017F>erved to his Lodging; for the Dukes unexpected arrival had rai<U+017F>ed all from <U+017F>leep, and put the Court in <U+017F>uch Confu<U+017F>ion, that they ran again<U+017F>t each other as if it had been at blind-mans-Buffe: (a Recreation much u<U+017F>ed at Courts in that Age, and not yet wholly di<U+017F>e<U+017F>teem'd.) To <U+017F>ave the trouble of making doleful Speeches<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and avoid the danger of <U+017F>peaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, or wor<U+017F>e then he did, I will not pre<U+017F>ume to relate exactly how often <hi>Alcidalis</hi> Sighed, Tumbled, and Rouled in his Bed, <U+017F>omtimes Rayling at, and <U+017F>ometimes wheadling For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; or whether he tore his lovely Hair, which in a thou<U+017F>and Curls adorned his <U+017F>preading Shoulders; for he being then under the qualification of a Slave, had no attending E<U+017F>quire to hear and di<U+017F>cover his Soliloquies. But let the ingenious Reader imagine, after a long and pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate Court<U+017F>hip of <U+017F>o Beautiful a Lady as <hi>Zelinda,</hi> if he was Kneeling by her Bed, (<hi>the Altar of Love</hi>) pre<U+017F><U+017F>ing her <U+017F>oft Palm, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his amorous head on her panting Brea<U+017F>t, in the height of exta<U+017F>ie, ju<U+017F>t
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56550:47"/>
at the Minute of fruition, (for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s they had been naught together, if the Dukes coming had not prevented them) how it would <U+017F>tir him to be di<U+017F>appointed: And then let him plea<U+017F>e his fancy with Speeches <U+017F>uitable to his own Humour.—Here <U+017F>ome Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Zealots may perhaps accu<U+017F>e me of a gro<U+017F>s mi<U+017F>take, in <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing a Prince <U+017F>o <U+017F>ubllmely Virtuous as <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalis</hi> is Characteriz'd, could be guilty of the common Failings of meaner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons: But I refer my <U+017F>elf to the Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judgement of this ripe-witted Age, whether that Lover is not mo<U+017F>t per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, who<U+017F>e Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion has no Limits (maugre the Cruel examples of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis de Gaul,</hi> that flower of Chivalry, and all the Rabble of ob<U+017F>olete Heroes) but in per<U+017F>uance of its de<U+017F>ign, which is enjoyment one way or other, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is pretended to the contrary; tramples all danger, or rea<U+017F>on under Foot; I'le believe it granted, and proceed to my Story.—The <U+017F>ame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s of kindne<U+017F>s, or Jealou<U+017F>ie rather, which hurried the Old Duke from his Countrey diver<U+017F>ions, ha<U+017F>tened him to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56550:47"/>
the Chamber of his Trembling Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<U+017F>s; who received him with mo<U+017F>t extraordinary marks of unu<U+017F>ual Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne<U+017F>s, the better to palliate her Errour; often renewing her <U+017F>trict Embraces, with a melting voice, <U+017F>he <U+017F>aid,</p>
            <q>My Deare<U+017F>t Lord! The only joy of my Life! Are you well? Are you in my Arms? Oh <U+017F>peak! and confirm me that I am not yet in a Dream—</q>
            <q>No, Dear Madam! <hi>an<U+017F>wered the over joyed Duke,</hi> it is no Dream; or if it be, it is <U+017F>o ravi<U+017F>hing to me, that I could be contented it <U+017F>hould never end: But what, my dear <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda,</hi> has <U+017F>o much di<U+017F>compo<U+017F>ed you? Your heart pants and <U+017F>truggles, as if it were weary of its Seat, and <U+017F>ought for <U+017F>helter in my Brea<U+017F>t—</q>
            <q>Oh Sir, <hi><U+017F>he replyed,</hi> receive it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then! and let it ever dwell there, that it may no more be frighted with your ab<U+017F>ence. Your coming wakened me from a dreadful Dream; a great
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56550:48"/>
Buck, me-thought, a<U+017F><U+017F>aulted you in a<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> dark Thicket, and was ju<U+017F>t ready to goar your Maje<U+017F>tick forehead with his Horns; Ha! Horns, cryed the Duke, (<U+017F>tarting as if his evil Genius had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared) Heaven avert the Omen! If your pre<U+017F>ence had not di<U+017F>turbed my bu<U+017F>ie Fancy, certainly the Dream had gone one, <U+017F>ays <U+017F>he, and I had dyed with apprehen<U+017F>ion—</q>
            <q>Be comforted, Madam! <hi><U+017F>ays the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected Duke,</hi> Dreams are but faint reflections of tho<U+017F>e la<U+017F>t thoughts, which imployed the imagination when <U+017F>leep <U+017F>urprized the Active Sen<U+017F>es; <U+017F>o when the Glorious Sun for<U+017F>akes our Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>phear, a Ro<U+017F>ie glimmering lighr <U+017F>till guilds the Clouds.</q>
            <q>Ah Sir! I will never con<U+017F>ent that you <U+017F>hall leave my Arms, <hi>cryed the pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ionate Dutche<U+017F>s,</hi> for if your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious life <U+017F>hould be de<U+017F>troyed, how wretched would the unfortunate <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> be!</q>
            <p>Repeating her Care<U+017F><U+017F>es with <U+017F>uch
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:56550:48"/>
exqui<U+017F>ite Artifice, and <U+017F>eeming Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, that the Duke, believing him<U+017F>elf mo<U+017F>t egregiou<U+017F>ly Happy in a Kind and Faithful Spou<U+017F>e, when her heart was all that time inventing new Cur<U+017F>es for him, committed all his cares to a <U+017F>ound <U+017F>leep; which Age, and a little forc'd exerci<U+017F>e to retaliate his Ladies kindne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>oon brought upon him.</p>
            <p>The next day was <U+017F>olemniz'd with more then u<U+017F>ual Sports, where <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidalis,</hi> <U+017F>welled with joyful hopes, performed <U+017F>uch extravagant Deeds of Agility and Strength, as I dare not particularize, le<U+017F>t the incredulous Reader <U+017F>hould di<U+017F>tru<U+017F>t the truth of all the re<U+017F>t. The Duke unable to make good returns of Love two nights to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <U+017F>hut up his Exchequer, and as an uncivil Debtor that cannot Pay, avoids the <U+017F>ight of his obliging Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor; he <U+017F>tole away as abruptly to his Country-Hou<U+017F>e in the Evening, as he had come from thence the Night-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; leaving a Letter to inform and comfort the poor Dutche<U+017F>s, with plentifull a<U+017F><U+017F>urances of a <U+017F>peedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56550:49"/>
adding, that he feared to bid her Farewell, le<U+017F>t her Grief <U+017F>hould betray him to a weakne<U+017F>s misbecoming a Prince. She had ob<U+017F>erved his clo<U+017F>e manner of retiring, and gladly gave him opportunity to Cheat him<U+017F>elf, while he thought to deceive her: but could not read his Con<U+017F>olatory E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<U+017F>tle, without downright Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing—Old Age, Flannell, and Brandy, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, farewell! and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately calling <hi>Florella,</hi> (for that was the Lady of her intrigue) <U+017F>ent her to <hi>Clariantes;</hi> concealing <U+017F>till from her, that it was the Prince <hi>Aleidalis,</hi> (who<U+017F>e Name and Actions the Court was well acquainted with) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olving to continue his mi<U+017F>take of her for the true <hi>Zelinda;</hi> ordered, that when he came, there <U+017F>hould be no light at all in her Chamber. <hi>Florella</hi> found him walking where he had received the former Summons, and failed not to deliver the <U+017F>econd Challenge; nor he to repair immediatly to the place appointed. Now Fortune <U+017F>eemed to fix her un<U+017F>teady Wheel; Smooth and Gentle, as a Frozen River, did the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56550:49"/>
Sea appear; and the amicable Moon, an indulgent cheri<U+017F>her of all Exploits of Love and Art, (like a well-wi<U+017F>hing Procurer with a dark Lanthorn) from behind a <U+017F>able Cloud, di<U+017F>played ju<U+017F>t light enough to lead him on, and not betray him. Swift as a <U+017F>ealed Dove, and as blind too with his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, he mounted to his Heaven, the Window, and in one moment more pro<U+017F>trated him<U+017F>elf at the Shrine, the Bed of his Saint. Like a gay plum'd Phoenix, wrapped in perfumes, and langui<U+017F>hing in Flames of Love, <U+017F>he lay; yet trembled like a new yean'd Lamb upon a <U+017F>heet of Snow, with eagerne<U+017F>s of fierce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ire. After his fir<U+017F>t a<U+017F><U+017F>ault of Ki<U+017F><U+017F>es on her melting Hand, his Tongue got liberty to cry, <hi>Ye Gods! do I again behold the fair</hi> Zelinda? (a very pertinent Que<U+017F>tion, for it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred there was no Light) then overcome with exta<U+017F>ies of joy, his head <U+017F>unk gently on her downy Brea<U+017F>ts, which proudly <U+017F>welled to welcom <U+017F>o de<U+017F>ired a Gue<U+017F>t, and meet his burning Ki<U+017F><U+017F>es; while with her tender Arrms, more White then Alpine Snow, <U+017F>he
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:56550:50"/>
kindly pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed him clo<U+017F>er! <hi>Oh my ador'd</hi> Zelinda, (he panting cryed) to which <U+017F>he Ecchoed <U+017F>oftly with a Sigh, <hi>Oh my much loved</hi> Alcidalis! <hi>I had been too happy had I been only thine.</hi>—Here their Speech was Smothered with reiterated Ki<U+017F><U+017F>es and Embraces, till urged by opportunity, and <U+017F>timulated with greatne<U+017F>s of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, with a re<U+017F>pective Boldne<U+017F>s he continued—<hi>Why was the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate</hi> Alcidalis <hi>permitted to <U+017F>ee <U+017F>uch dazling Glories, and hope for <U+017F>uch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expre<U+017F><U+017F>ible bli<U+017F>s, as Gods would quit again their Heaven for,—and not—En—j</hi>—! There with a Balmy Ki<U+017F>s, <U+017F>he put a period to his Words; and with a pretty kind of obliging violence, <U+017F>he checked his wandring hands, while he pur<U+017F>ued his purpo<U+017F>e thus—<hi>If my adored Prince<U+017F>s thinks my Sufferings yet too incon<U+017F>iderable to merit her e<U+017F>teem, if cuitting the powerful Charms of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soveraignty, and for<U+017F>aking an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent dying Father, to wear the de<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Garb, and do the mean<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Offices of Common Slavery, de<U+017F>erve no Pity; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:56550:50"/>
               <hi>new Chains, Tortures, Deaths, and <U+017F>ee how readily I will imbrace them for</hi> Zelinda's <hi><U+017F>ake—Too much, too much already,</hi> replyed the cunning yielding Dutche<U+017F>s, <hi>has my beloved Prince endured—But—But!—But what!</hi> cryed the impatient <hi>Alcida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis—But you are anothers, you perhaps would <U+017F>ay: Ah Madam! were you not fir<U+017F>t mine? were you not Ba<U+017F>ely, Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rou<U+017F>ly Ravi<U+017F>hed from my Arms? And if a Thief has Robbed me, <U+017F>han't I <U+017F>eize my Trea<U+017F>ure where I find it?</hi>—Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding with a clo<U+017F>e imbrace,—<hi>Go, ye are an unkind naughty man,</hi> <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he—<hi>and I wont love—you indeed—if—you offer</hi>—Sighing, and gently <U+017F>triving to defend, what <U+017F>he had rather have dyed then keep—What, oh powerful opportunity! may not be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by thy a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance? How <U+017F>weet a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence did the mi<U+017F>taken <hi>Alcidalis</hi> think he had, for all his pains! and what a full revenge on Fortune for her Jilting Tricks, while he lay dying in the Arms of his <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed Deity!—But oh the <U+017F>hortne<U+017F>s, and uncertainty of humane felicity! Who would not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56550:51"/>
think the tired Duke now taking large Arrears of <U+017F>leep, for his la<U+017F>t nights Di<U+017F>turbance! Who would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he <U+017F>hould <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon a <U+017F>econd time mole<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e Lovers! Yet <U+017F>o it was; for in the height of all their Bli<U+017F>s, <hi>Florella</hi> almo<U+017F>t Breathle<U+017F>s with her ha<U+017F>te, ru<U+017F>hed in; ca<U+017F>ting back <U+017F>uch frightfull Looks, as if <U+017F>ome gha<U+017F>tiy Phanta<U+017F>m had pur<U+017F>ued her; and by the Blazing light of a great Wax Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which <U+017F>he brought, di<U+017F>covered to the <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> the fal<U+017F>e <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda;</hi> and e're he could di<U+017F>charge his Sen<U+017F>es, from the Amazement that object rai<U+017F>ed, <U+017F>he increa<U+017F>ed it by cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>The Duke! The Duke was privately returned, and ju<U+017F>t entered the Palace:</hi> which truth their ears imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly confirmed, by the ha<U+017F>ty Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teps which they heard.—The Dutche<U+017F>s, Pale and Trembling, had not power to <U+017F>peak, but with up-lifted Hands and Eyes, <U+017F>eemed to implore the a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of <hi>Alcidalis;</hi> while <hi>Florella,</hi> who<U+017F>e Sen<U+017F>es were more at liberty, threw a loo<U+017F>e Robe and Head-Tyre of the Dutche<U+017F><U+017F>es on <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> hiding
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56550:51"/>
his Face as much as the Dre<U+017F>s would permit. Scarce was this done, when the Duke entered, cla<U+017F>ped him in his Arms, and <U+017F>pake the kinde<U+017F>t things a doting Husband could invent, to oblige the be<U+017F>t Wife in the World: To which he dar'd make no reply; but <hi>Florella</hi> freed him from that trouble, telling the Duke, a <U+017F>uddain Tooth-ach, got by a cold <U+017F>he took the preceding night, made <U+017F>peaking extreamly trouble<U+017F>ome; and <U+017F>welled her Face <U+017F>o, <U+017F>he dared not expo<U+017F>e it to the Air, le<U+017F>t it increa<U+017F>ed her Malady. <hi>Alcidalis</hi> took the hint, and began to Groan <U+017F>o La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably, it put his Grace into <U+017F>uch mortal apprehen<U+017F>ions of her danger, that it was hard to judge who was in the greate<U+017F>t perplexity, He, the Prince, or the Dutche<U+017F>s, who lay quaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Bed-Cloathes, like a Child frighted with the Tale of Raw head and bloody Bones. Death was the lea<U+017F>t puni<U+017F>hment the Lovers could expect, if they were di<U+017F>covered. A hundred times did <hi>Alcidalis</hi> re<U+017F>olve to force his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age over the Dukes feeble Body: But the con<U+017F>ideration of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56550:52"/>
Dutche<U+017F><U+017F>es danger, as a Woman in di<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s, though her impo<U+017F>ture had much incen<U+017F>ed him, diverted all tho<U+017F>e thoughts to a Generous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olution of freeing her, or <U+017F>haring in her de<U+017F>tiny. Thus Affairs <U+017F>tood, when Fortune <U+017F>eemed weary of tormenting them, and gave <U+017F>ome pro<U+017F>pect of hope, for the Uxorious Duke would him<U+017F>elf be the Me<U+017F><U+017F>enger to call the Phy<U+017F>itians; which gave all hopes of <U+017F>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things right 'ere he returned; but their Joy vani<U+017F>hed like a <U+017F>wift reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sun ca<U+017F>t from a moving Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Gla<U+017F><U+017F>e; for the blind Quean, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ole delight con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in Tantalizing tho<U+017F>e that tru<U+017F>t her, thru<U+017F>t them the next Minuit on the very brink of Ruine. The Duke unable to leave his Dear <hi>Zelinda</hi> without a Ki<U+017F>s, found a <U+017F>trange unu<U+017F>ual Roughne<U+017F>s on his Chin, and <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed with a <U+017F>udden fit of Jealou<U+017F>ie, <U+017F>urveying him the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tant from Head to Foot, imagined his dimen<U+017F>ions <U+017F>ix times as big as his <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda's</hi> (for Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion blinds the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tanding, as <U+017F>ome Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es cheat the Sight) and rending off the Head-Dre<U+017F>s,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:56550:52"/>
<U+017F>aw not only a man, but his Slave <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riantes,</hi> who<U+017F>e extraordinary valour had made him worthy of his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar knowledge.—Immediatly running out, with loud Exclamations of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, Trea<U+017F>on! the Guard repaired to his aid; when his back was turned, you may think <hi>Alcidalis</hi> was not idle, but ca<U+017F>ting off that faetal Robe, with a bravery of Spirit which never for<U+017F>ook him, he prepared, though unarmed, to di<U+017F>pute his Life<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> But e're he went, turning to the Dutche<U+017F>s who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<U+017F>t drowned in Tears, <q>Madam, (<hi><U+017F>ays he</hi>) if extravagancy of Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, had not wholly <U+017F>eized my Rea<U+017F>on with my Sen<U+017F>es, your Deportment, <U+017F>o contrary to her <U+017F>trict and <U+017F>potle<U+017F>s Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, had a<U+017F><U+017F>ured me you were not the ncomparable <hi>Zelinda;</hi> but if you give me not <U+017F>ome account of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince<U+017F>s, by all the Gods I <U+017F>wear! to unvail your impo<U+017F>ture, and expo<U+017F>e you to the ju<U+017F>t Cruelty of the deluded Duke, though my death accompany your Infamy.—Ah Sir, (<hi><U+017F>aid the deplorable Dutche<U+017F>s</hi>) can you with <U+017F>uch extream rigour
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56550:53"/>
pay my exce<U+017F>s of Love? ingrateful man! the too happy <hi>Zelinda</hi> (<U+017F>ince <U+017F>o e<U+017F>teemed by you) lives in the I<U+017F>le of <hi>Sardignia;</hi> it was to <U+017F>ave her life, I con<U+017F>ented to become a Dutche<U+017F>s—'Tis not, Cruel Prince! to the care of my own <U+017F>afety you owe for this di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, for with your <U+017F>elf, you take from me all de<U+017F>ire to live: But to pre<U+017F>erve your Life, (notwith<U+017F>tanding all your unkind contempt) ten thou<U+017F>and times dearer to me then my own. I once more tell you, your too happy <hi>Zelinda</hi> lives yet in <hi>Sardig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia;</hi> in obedience to her own de<U+017F>ire, attended thither by my Father. Shortne<U+017F>s of time forbids to tell you more: Now leave me to the <U+017F>everi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an incen<U+017F>ed Jealous Husband; but when you think of my failing, remember the Cau<U+017F>e, and pity me.</q>—Here the noi<U+017F>e of the Dukes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <U+017F>tayed her Speech. <hi>Alcidalis</hi> had dyed in her defence, <U+017F>o graceful, and <U+017F>o moving was her grief, but hopes of <U+017F>eeing the true <hi>Zelinda</hi> bani<U+017F>hed all other <U+017F>entiments. With Courage, even to ra<U+017F>hne<U+017F>s, he ca<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf amid<U+017F>t
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56550:53"/>
the Guard, and got <U+017F>afely off; for their too much ha<U+017F>t, (the Mortal enemy of mo<U+017F>t de<U+017F>igns) brought the Guard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
               </gap> with <U+017F>o little light, that in the Confu<U+017F>ion it was not difficult to pa<U+017F>s without being di<U+017F>cerned. The inra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Duke entring, found his Dutche<U+017F>s <U+017F>tanding in that very Dre<U+017F>s and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture he left <hi>Clariantes,</hi> only the Head-Tyre he had di<U+017F>ordered, was again put on, and by the advice of <hi>Florella</hi> (who was old excellent at <U+017F>udden Shifts) <U+017F>he was <U+017F>o placed. Strait he cryes out to his Guard, <hi>There! There behold the audacious Traytor! take him, <U+017F>eize him, away with him to Tortures; let him be 100 Years dying.</hi> The Guard <U+017F>eeing none but the Dutche<U+017F>s, like Statues <U+017F>tood without motion; The Duke <U+017F>tormed, Vowed all were in the Plot, &amp; <U+017F>hould dye together; but fir<U+017F>t that Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain <hi>Clariantes:</hi> Andrunning at the Dutche<U+017F>s with his Drawn Sword, had certainly killed her, if <hi>Florella's</hi> <U+017F>hriek at his fir<U+017F>t motion, had not made her <U+017F>tart a<U+017F>ide. Yet <U+017F>he e<U+017F>caped not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Wound in her Side, which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her fright, ca<U+017F>t her on
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56550:54"/>
the Bed in a <U+017F>woun: and by the falling off of her Head-Tyre, <U+017F>hewed the Duke what he had done.—He did not (as <U+017F>ome would expect) <U+017F>earch round the Chamber, and the Palace for <hi>Clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes,</hi> but wholly <U+017F>ubmitted to his Uxorious Love; which like an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous Tyde, bare down his Anger, Faith, and Rea<U+017F>on; <U+017F>eeing his dear Dutche<U+017F>s Bleeding, and as he thought breathing out her Soul by his accur<U+017F>ed hand, he threw him<U+017F>elf at her Feet, beat his Head again<U+017F>t the Ground, tore his Hair, and rooted up his Comely Beard (hold! let me not lye neither, perhaps Beards were as much out of Fa<U+017F>hion then, as now, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equently he wore none; I would not have Po<U+017F>terity impo<U+017F>ed upon in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <U+017F>uch weight; truth will go through the World.) But I am <U+017F>ure he called him<U+017F>elf a thou<U+017F>and thick <U+017F>culled Ophes, Jealous Cox-combs, Villains, Murtherers, and turning to his Guard, begged them to Di<U+017F>patch him, for he was a Tyrant, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to live but among Bea<U+017F>ts; from intreaties he proceeded to commands,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:56550:54"/>
and threats; but <U+017F>eeing them rever<U+017F>e their Faces, and hang their Heads at his <U+017F>trange Propo<U+017F>ition. <hi>Why,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>will you be cruel to your Prince? and deny him the only favour he ever begged from you, or that you can grant? I have mo<U+017F>t inhumanely pierced my own <U+017F>oul, what <U+017F>afety can you hope from me? My hearts blood <U+017F>tains the Floor, and I can gaze upon't without dying; can you expect Ju<U+017F>tice from <U+017F>uch a Mon<U+017F>ter? Gods! Why do I de<U+017F>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d to Petition <U+017F>o poorly, for what is in my power. Oh my</hi> Zelinda! <hi>the Blo<U+017F><U+017F>oms that enriched the early Spring, and with their fragrant <U+017F>eent perfum'd the gentle Southern Wind, were not <U+017F>o <U+017F>weet, nor half <U+017F>o Beautiful as thee: 'twould undoe the va<U+017F>t <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>niver<U+017F>e to purcha<U+017F>e <U+017F>o rich a Jewel as I have ra<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thrown away—What ean my hated Carka<U+017F><U+017F>e, this dull Clod of earth do in the World, when my Sun that gave it warmth, and life, lyes here Eclip<U+017F>ed? Fool! Fool! Fool! that I am</hi>—Then he ca<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf again on her Body, and <U+017F>triving in vain to find <U+017F>ome <U+017F>igns of life, cryed out, <hi>Zelinda!</hi> Zelinda! <hi>She's gone;—for ever, for ever gone.—if</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:56550:55"/>
               <hi>thy injured <U+017F>oul is yet hovering in the ambient Air, as <U+017F>ure it is loth to go far from <U+017F>o rich, <U+017F>o beautiful a Cabinet, let it behold the Sacrifice I offer for its Peace.</hi>—Starting up, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ca<U+017F>t him<U+017F>elf on his Sword, but was prevented, &amp; by the Phy<U+017F>itians and Chyrurtgeons who were then arrived, the Dutche<U+017F>s was recovered from her <U+017F>woun: and her life a<U+017F><U+017F>ured, if no new accidenr prevented their care.—The Duke begged a thou<U+017F>and pardons for his folly, and <U+017F>tirred not from her Bed till <U+017F>he was Cured;—bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him<U+017F>elf with many vows, never to be Jealous again; nor did I ever hear of any farther difference between them; therefore I will leave them, with the <U+017F>ame farewell people give their departed Friend, who dyed with a <hi>Lord have mercy upon me</hi> in his Mouth, (though he lived impiou<U+017F>ly) <hi>doubtle<U+017F>s they are Happy.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Oh Woman! Woman! thou dark aby<U+017F><U+017F>e of Subtilty; 'tis ea<U+017F>ier to trace a wandring Swallow through the pathle<U+017F>s Air, then to explicate the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56550:55"/>
crafty wyndings of thy Love, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: Thy <U+017F>wift excu<U+017F>es, and eva<U+017F>ions, <U+017F>till like the <hi>Hydra's</hi> Heads increa<U+017F>e: As Wizzards, in a moment y'are transformed to various Shapes, and when the injur'd Friend, or Husband, thinks to cru<U+017F>h a Serpent that has poi<U+017F>oned all his Health and Peace, <U+017F>trait in the form of a Dove-like inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence you Baffle and Betray his ju<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t Rage. Angels would emulate the perfect Glory, and the Ble<U+017F>t e<U+017F>tate of man, were he not <U+017F>ubject to the <U+017F>ubtil Snares of your frail deceiving Sex<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader ought to pardon this Satyrick excur<U+017F>ion to the Author, who has been more Injured by Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then e're the Duke or <hi>Alcidalis</hi> was.—That Prince, it may be concluded, <U+017F>oon found his Gentleman which lay incognito receive his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and taking his Jewels, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired immediatly to the Sea <U+017F>ide, where a Ship being ju<U+017F>t ready to leave the Port, (for that mu<U+017F>t never be wanting to a <hi>Hero</hi> upon the Ramble) without asking whither <U+017F>he was
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56550:56"/>
Bound, they went Aboard, and <U+017F>oon lo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight of that unfortunate Coa<U+017F>t. With a pro<U+017F>perous Wind let them proceed, while we return to the di<U+017F>tre<U+017F><U+017F>ed real <hi>Zelinda,</hi> whom we unkindly left in mans Habit, under the name of <hi>Zelidan,</hi> in a <U+017F>trange place, at <hi>Barcha</hi> in <hi>Africa.</hi> By the favourable a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of that <U+017F>ame generous Pyrate <hi>Orcantes,</hi> that gave her liberty, <U+017F>he obtained a Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age for <hi>Spain;</hi> and without meeting any extraordinary adventure, <U+017F>afely landed at the <U+017F>ame Port of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> from whence <U+017F>he had been forced away by the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jealous Queen.—The <U+017F>ight of that Fatal place, pre<U+017F>enting all pa<U+017F>t Fortune fre<U+017F>hly to her Memory, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed her Brea<U+017F>t with Sighs; which Tempe<U+017F>t was allay'd by a <U+017F>hower of Chry<U+017F>tal drops from her fair Eyes; <hi>Ah</hi> Alcidalis, <U+017F>aid <U+017F>he, <hi>if you do <U+017F>till pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erve your vowed affection for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Zelinda, <hi>what rea<U+017F>on will <U+017F>he have to glory in her Sufferings?</hi> Here <U+017F>he pau<U+017F>ed a while, plea<U+017F>ing her <U+017F>elf with that delightful thought; but on a <U+017F>udden breaking <U+017F>ilence, <U+017F>he went
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:56550:56"/>
on;—<hi>No! wretched</hi> Zelinda, <hi>no! never hope <U+017F>uch Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ings were ordained for thee; doubtle<U+017F>s the Authority of a King, and Father, managed by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>inuating artifice of the Prudent de<U+017F>ign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Queen, the intere<U+017F>t of State, and the Beauties of the too charming Prince<U+017F>s, to which adde his belief of my being Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Prince of</hi> Tarentum, <hi>have prevailed, and he is now for ever chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the imbrace of that fortunate Prince<U+017F>s.—Die! die</hi> Zelinda! <hi>let not the imperious Queen in<U+017F>ult ore thy Di<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s.</hi> Already was her hand upon her Sword, when Heaven, that never quite for<U+017F>akes the Virtuous, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pired her with more rea<U+017F>onable thoughts—That death was the extreme<U+017F>t refuge of the mi<U+017F>erable; and might <U+017F>afely be deferred as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy always in her power, <U+017F>ince no earthly Tyranny could compel the Wretched to live longer then they plea<U+017F>ed, if they had courage enough to die.—She plea<U+017F>ed her <U+017F>elf with the fancy, that to die in his <U+017F>ight (which <U+017F>he vowed if he were fal<U+017F>e to her) would extract remor<U+017F>e, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56550:57"/>
pity from him; <U+017F>o much does Love mi<U+017F>guide the Judgement of the mo<U+017F>t prudent, that even in death they cheat them<U+017F>elves with vain hopes of a future <U+017F>atisfaction they can never be <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of.—In this humour <U+017F>he po<U+017F>ted towards <hi>Saracu<U+017F>a,</hi> but near the Gates was <U+017F>topped by a great pre<U+017F>s of people? <U+017F>ome driving Bea<U+017F>ts of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, laden with variety of Goods; others carrying on their backs, tho<U+017F>e whom Infancy or Age rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>t them<U+017F>elves; as if they fled from the fury of <U+017F>ome Foreign In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vader, or from the mercilc<U+017F>s rage of a devouring flame. Loud Sighs, and doleful Groans, were all the an<U+017F>wers <U+017F>he could gain to her enquiry of the cau<U+017F>e; long u<U+017F>e of Arms, and Virile exerci<U+017F>e, had added much to her courage, in which <U+017F>he naturally out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triped her Sex: That (with a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined purpo<U+017F>e to behold the rea<U+017F>on of this Con<U+017F>ternation) carried her through the <U+017F>moaking bloody Streets, which were <U+017F>trewed with dead and mangled Bodies (the <U+017F>ad marks of a Civil War) <U+017F>trait to the Pallace, amid<U+017F>t a thou<U+017F>and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:56550:57"/>
Swords, and other In<U+017F>truments of Death.—There <U+017F>he beheld the Gates <U+017F>hut, and the Queen and Prince<U+017F>s out of a large Window, with begging Eyes, Hands, and Voices, in vain <U+017F>triving to infu<U+017F>e compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion into the enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Rabble, who roared ince<U+017F><U+017F>antly, <hi>Give us our King! re<U+017F>tore us our Prince! down with the Murtherers Zelidan</hi> not knowing the occa<U+017F>ion of their Mutiny, nor enquiring now, but led by a generous principle of a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>ting the di<U+017F>tre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, made her way through the Croud, beckoning with her hands (for their noi<U+017F>e made all <U+017F>peech u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s) for <U+017F>ilence, and liberty to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e; having attained to their Front, <U+017F>he faced them; and turning up her Beaver, <U+017F>hewed them a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance which never failed of gaining a re<U+017F>pect from the mo<U+017F>t Barbarous: The Grandeur of her Meen, and the Maje<U+017F>tick <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s of her Eyes, <U+017F>oon converted their confu<U+017F>ed Bauling to a <U+017F>ilent admiration: which <U+017F>he, who<U+017F>e greatne<U+017F>s of Spirit was ever pre<U+017F>ent in the extreme<U+017F>t' danger, <U+017F>trait im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the advancement of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igne,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:56550:58"/>
the relief of the be<U+017F>ieged Queen and Prince<U+017F>s. Bowing her body then, with a charming re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s Grace pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar only to her <U+017F>elf, thus <U+017F>he harangu'd them.—</p>
            <q>Valiant Souldiers! and mo<U+017F>t worthy Citizens! who<U+017F>e Valour and unque<U+017F>tioned Loyalty have <U+017F>till been the <U+017F>upport and glory of your own, as well as the envy of all neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes; who<U+017F>e free born hearts with joy <U+017F>ubmit to all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees that bear the <U+017F>tamp of unbribed Ju<U+017F>tice; why are tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>hining Weapons brandi<U+017F>hed now again<U+017F>t weak Women? again<U+017F>t your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted lawful Queen? that u<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>trike a Trembling horrour in your bolde<U+017F>t Foes?—Are you injur'd in your Trade? are your due Liberties re<U+017F>trained?—Behold your good; your gracious Queen, ready to offer, nay intreat you to make your own Conditions. Behold Maje<U+017F>ty, in the form of an humble <U+017F>uppliant; have you the hearts of men, and look on this without being moved to duty and <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion?—Had your
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:56550:58"/>
Wives and Daughters been ravi<U+017F>hed, your E<U+017F>tates given for a prey to the In<U+017F>olent Souldier, had your Friends been lawle<U+017F>sly Impri<U+017F>oned, nay put to cruel unde<U+017F>erved deaths, (all which the great Gods forbid!) the de<U+017F>ola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your City, and killing of each other would be no recompence: Look round about you, behold your yet burning habitations, <U+017F>ee how <U+017F>cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Limbs and torn Bodies pave your Streets; look how the de<U+017F>tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people flye tho<U+017F>e Buildings which the fire has <U+017F>pared, as if <U+017F>ome deadly Plague po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s'd them, or the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sword of a Barbarous Foe were at their backs.—Will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert your <U+017F>tately Rooms to Graves? your City to a De<U+017F>art? and your <U+017F>acred Temples to noi<U+017F>ome Denns for Woolves? and ba<U+017F>e Receptacles for Batts and Owls <U+017F>hrieking Harbingers of Death?—Go on! let every neighbour hide his Treacherous Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in his Friends heart<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> con<U+017F>ume each other bravely! and leave your Wives and Children a mi<U+017F>erable Prey to the next Invader, that will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>afe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56550:59"/>
<U+017F>afe to <U+017F>eize and drive them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Slavery.—I that am a <U+017F>tranger, cannot without Tears of Compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion fore<U+017F>ee that de<U+017F>olation which you <U+017F>eek; my heart bleeds, and an univer<U+017F>al horrour runs through all my Veins;- if you are injured, my life <U+017F>hall be <U+017F>acrificed to your <U+017F>atisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.—</q>
            <p>
               <q>Methinks I <U+017F>ee a noble Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in your eyes, and a true remor<U+017F>e in Blu<U+017F>hes ri<U+017F>e upon your Cheeks; how generous, how becoming does it look! Oh make ha<U+017F>te to perfect your Repentance; let not future Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles deliver to <U+017F>ucceeding Ages, the <hi>Saracu<U+017F>ans</hi> Swords were <U+017F>tained with the Slaughter of Poor, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>aken, helple<U+017F>s Women: But follow me to Safety, Wealth, and Honour: All that love their Liberty, their Countrys Peace, and the Honour of the great Gods, follow me!—</q> Then ca<U+017F>ting her <U+017F>elf from her Hor<U+017F>e, with her drawn Sword <U+017F>he began to lead them off.—
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56550:59"/>
When one, that <U+017F>ought his particular Advantage from the general Ruine; that had fomented the Rebellion, as <U+017F>ome <U+017F>et Hou<U+017F>es on fire, to Steal with more advantage and <U+017F>afety; cryed out, <hi>Companions! Friends! and Brothers! whither are you going, like Bea<U+017F>ts to the Sacrifice? And what is this bold imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Stranger that dares</hi>—There <hi>Zelidan</hi> put a full <U+017F>top to his Seditious Oration, and his Life together, by a thru<U+017F>t which pierced his heart: An Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which might have branded her with ra<U+017F>hne<U+017F>s, (<U+017F>o boldly to hazard the Fury of a yet di<U+017F>contented Multitude) but the Succe<U+017F>s ju<U+017F>tified its Prudence; (in <U+017F>uch extreams no middle paths are <U+017F>afe) for without a murmur all the re<U+017F>t followed her, marching over his body <U+017F>he had killed, to the Market-place; where with another Speech, <U+017F>he <U+017F>ent them pacified to their <U+017F>everal hou<U+017F>es;—and by one of the mo<U+017F>t under<U+017F>tanding, was informed, That the long ab<U+017F>ence and <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed lo<U+017F>s of <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> and the late death of the King, were charged as Crimes upon the Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queen; and the Commonalty
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:56550:60"/>
<U+017F>tirred up by <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>contented Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, had <U+017F>ought revenge by force of Armes: which cau<U+017F>ed that dreadful noi<U+017F>e and de<U+017F>truction which he <U+017F>o hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily had <U+017F>topped. Scarce was this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation fini<U+017F>hed, when a Me<U+017F><U+017F>enger from the Queen entreated, <hi>That by his pre<U+017F>ence at the Court, he would a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure that Life and Honour he had <U+017F>o ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerou<U+017F>ly repriev'd.</hi> The joy <hi>Zelidan</hi> conceived to find the Prince ab<U+017F>ent, and as <U+017F>he believed con<U+017F>tant to his Vows, (for the nimble faith of Lovers keeps equal pace with their wi<U+017F>hes) obtained an ea<U+017F>ie Pardon for all other injuries, and ha<U+017F>ten'd her to the <U+017F>ervice of the Queen: whom <U+017F>he found with the Prince<U+017F>s her Daughter, and all the Train that di<U+017F>tracted time would allow, ready to receive her in the fir<U+017F>t Court. The troubled thoughts that filled their Brea<U+017F>ts at their meeting, darted through their trembling Eyes, and in un<U+017F>ettled colours <U+017F>pread them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves upon their Cheeks; though the cau<U+017F>es were different, and a <U+017F>ecret to all but them<U+017F>elves. <hi>Zelidan</hi> (maugre all her goodne<U+017F>s) could not <U+017F>ee the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56550:60"/>
in<U+017F>trument of her <U+017F>orrows; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <U+017F>ome <U+017F>trange emotion in her heart; nor could the Queen behold <hi>Zelidan,</hi> (who<U+017F>e believed re<U+017F>idence at <hi>Tarentum,</hi> and her di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ecured <hi>Zelinda</hi> from the mo<U+017F>t prying eyes) notwith<U+017F>tand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Prudence, and experienced conduct, without di<U+017F>playing to the <U+017F>trict ob<U+017F>erver, <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ymptoms of that pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion which had newly <U+017F>eized her: For the little audacious God of Love, had hovered <U+017F>till round <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidan,</hi> and while he appea<U+017F>ed the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous Rabble, began a new and more dangerous in<U+017F>urrection in her Brea<U+017F>t; <U+017F>ending from every word and action of this charming Amazon, a Golden Arrow to her heart, which her pre<U+017F>ent Dangers, nor the Grief for her yet <U+017F>carce breathle<U+017F>s Husband, could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her from. But the con<U+017F>traint <U+017F>he impo<U+017F>ed upon her <U+017F>elf, in <U+017F>triving to conceal her Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, expo<U+017F>ed it more openly, e<U+017F>pecially to <hi>Zelidan,</hi> who marked it with much <U+017F>atisfaction: hoping from thence an opportunity of a full and innocent revenge.—In <U+017F>hort, the amorous Queen received
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56550:61"/>
him as a Me<U+017F><U+017F>enger of Happine<U+017F>s from Heaven: <hi>What recompence,</hi> (<U+017F>aid <U+017F>he) <hi>Illu<U+017F>trious Stranger! can we offer you, to who<U+017F>e miraculous Relief we owe our Lives, and all we have to give? If the <U+017F>acred powers could admit a Rival in their wor<U+017F>hip, our adoration to you were a ju<U+017F>t debt. Madam,</hi> an<U+017F>wered the <U+017F>eigned <hi>Zelidan</hi> (bowing with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reverence) <hi>to your own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equalled Virtues you owe your <U+017F>afety, and I the glory of my <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s; had not my indulgent Stars <U+017F>ent me to your aid, the Gods had by <U+017F>ome Miracle pre<U+017F>erved in you the brighte<U+017F>t Ornament of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> (Many fine things were <U+017F>aid on this occa<U+017F>ion, for they were both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent at reparties and rejoynders, but my treacherous memory has lo<U+017F>t them: Be<U+017F>ides, I believe the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be as tedious to the Reader, as to my <U+017F>elf; therefore I'le on to the matter, which was thus.) <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidan</hi> was treated with all the Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and Honour, gratitude and love could invent: and failed not by her di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet conduct, to <U+017F>ettle a perfect cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<U+017F>pondence again between the Court
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56550:61"/>
and City; but her thoughts were <U+017F>till hankering after <hi>Alcidalis;</hi> purpo<U+017F>ing after a little re<U+017F>t, and what light <U+017F>he could get by enquiry, to guide her on,—to <U+017F>earch the World, till <U+017F>he found him.—The Queen gave every hour new marks of her Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and <U+017F>ought occa<U+017F>ion of di<U+017F>covering it more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Zelidan;</hi> who by all returns his different Quality would petmit, added Fewel to augment the Flame: And by the Sighs and Torments he ob<U+017F>erved her <U+017F>uffer, (for her great heart was loath to make the fir<U+017F>t addre<U+017F>s; and he as po<U+017F>itively determined, as he had good rea<U+017F>on not to ea<U+017F>e her by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the fir<U+017F>t Court<U+017F>hip) received <U+017F>ome compen<U+017F>ation for her former injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous treatment. The poor Prince<U+017F>s was as unable to defend her <U+017F>elf from the a<U+017F><U+017F>ault of this Victorious Amazon, as the Queen, and with deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<U+017F>entment ob<U+017F>erved her Mothers Pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion. Thus did the feigned <hi>Zelidan</hi> revenge, what the true <hi>Zelinda</hi> had endured: Love and Jealou<U+017F>ie, was the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s of the Court; and the Queens <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed Marriage with <hi>Zeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:56550:62"/>
the di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of the City. For the blind fears, or unrea<U+017F>onable wi<U+017F>hes of the incon<U+017F>iderate Multitude, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways anticipate the intentions of their Princes; transforming their very <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ed thoughts into Acts, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their publick cen<U+017F>ure, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plau<U+017F>e, e're they have Being. The Queen ob<U+017F>erving how carefully <hi>Zeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> declined all occa<U+017F>ions of being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqu'd, re<U+017F>olved to pu<U+017F>h on her de<U+017F>tiny, by a naked Declaration of her Love. In pur<U+017F>uance of her inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having commanded her Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to convenient di<U+017F>tance, while <hi>Zelidan</hi> was leading her in a walk of Oe<U+017F><U+017F>amine, who<U+017F>e interwoven Branches made <U+017F>o thick a Shade, that the Sun in its Meridian <U+017F>trength and lu<U+017F>tre could not pierce them; with the gentle pre<U+017F><U+017F>ings of his hand, reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Sighs, and <U+017F>peaking looks, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <U+017F>trove in vain, to prevent the <U+017F>hame of a plainer di<U+017F>covery, at la<U+017F>t with broken interrupted Language, thus <U+017F>he <U+017F>pake;—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, that the owner of <U+017F>o many</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:56550:62"/>
               <hi>accompli<U+017F>hments as wait on the Illu<U+017F>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Zelidan, <hi><U+017F>hould be in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of that noble Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, which is to others the very cau<U+017F>e of all hrave Actions, and the great reward at which they aim? has Love, that reigns o're all the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides, no power in our Court? or is there no Object worthy of your Sighs?</hi> ca<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her eyes on tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Zelidan,</hi> which were fixed on the earth, <U+017F>he pau<U+017F>ed, and in a re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s Agony waited his An<U+017F>wer: which he had ju<U+017F>t began, when a Gentleman, who<U+017F>e earne<U+017F>t bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ine<U+017F>s might well warrant his rude interruption of their Privacy, relieved him, by crying to the Queen, <hi>Save your <U+017F>elf, Madam! Save your <U+017F>elf by <U+017F>udden Flight, the Rebellious Citizens are again in Arms, and Headed by a de<U+017F>perate Stranger, like an impetuous Torrent that has o'reflowed its Banks, are rouling to the Palace, overthrowing all oppo<U+017F>ition with their re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s Fury. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tice and Liberty is Ecchoed through the Streets, but Blood &amp; Mi<U+017F>chief is their aim.</hi> E're his unwelcome Me<U+017F><U+017F>age was fini<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the <U+017F>cattered Courtiers came throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Queen, and <hi>Zelidan,</hi> like
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:56550:63"/>
frighted Chickens <U+017F>eeking <U+017F>helter from the ravenous Kite. He <U+017F>trait attended the Queen into the Pallace<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> a<U+017F><U+017F>uring her by the way, <hi>That his <U+017F>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> victory or death, <U+017F>hould evince the great de<U+017F>ire he had to <U+017F>erve her.</hi> And <U+017F>taying not for her an<U+017F>wer, (which doubtle<U+017F>s, would have been, That if he had any re<U+017F>pect to her <U+017F>afety, he <U+017F>hould pre<U+017F>erve it in that of his own; for her fate was <U+017F>o in<U+017F>eparably linked to his, that <U+017F>he could not <U+017F>urvive his death; or <U+017F>ome <U+017F>uch obliging thing) <U+017F>natched what Arms he <U+017F>oone<U+017F>t found, and ran to the Palace Gate, followed by a <U+017F>mall, but re<U+017F>olute Company of faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the Queen. The Prince<U+017F>s, who till then had <U+017F>mothered her Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion for <hi>Zelidan</hi> in the narrow limits of her Brea<U+017F>t, de<U+017F>pairing of <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s again<U+017F>t a Rival, which Duty forbad her to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e; and <U+017F>eeing what <U+017F>he prized dearer then her <U+017F>oul, ha<U+017F>ting to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent death; took a Sword from the neare<U+017F>t Attendant, and followed <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidan,</hi> hoping <U+017F>ome Fatal Blow would in his <U+017F>ight end her hopele<U+017F>s Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, with her life. The brave Stranger
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:56550:63"/>
(for <U+017F>o his Acts declared him) that led on the Citizens, conquered all oppo<U+017F>ition; till <hi>Zelidans</hi> arrival put a cheque to his growing victory. With an undaunted Meen <U+017F>he met him, and by her re<U+017F>olute Action, gave proof of a Courage far above her <U+017F>trength; but the invincible <hi>Alcidalis</hi> (for he it was) who had before conquered her in her own Province of Love, found but <U+017F>mall danger from her Arms. He received her fir<U+017F>t charge on his Shield, and by <U+017F>everal marks taking her for <hi>Zelidan</hi> the famous Stranger, and as he thought pretender to his Crown; cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>If thou wilt be a King, go Reign among the <U+017F>hades! and boa<U+017F>t thou dyed<U+017F>t by the hand of</hi> Alcidalis. At the beloved name of <hi>Alcidalis, Zelidan</hi> endeavoured to retreat, and di<U+017F>cover her <U+017F>elf; but in vain, for with <U+017F>uch fierce Blows he pur<U+017F>ued his Speech, that <U+017F>he fell Breathle<U+017F>s at his Feet. The unhappy amorous Prince<U+017F>s, <U+017F>triving with her feeble Arms to defend the fallen <hi>Zelidan,</hi> notwith<U+017F>tanding all <hi>Alcidalis</hi> could do to pre<U+017F>erve her, fell a deplorable Sacrifice to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen<U+017F>ed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56550:64"/>
Rabble, and dyed imbracing of <hi>Zelidan.</hi> The Queen, who from a Window beheld all this Action, at fir<U+017F>t lamented not the death of her Daughter; but con<U+017F>idering her as a Rival, Sacrificed all <U+017F>entiments of Nature to the <U+017F>atisfaction of her jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lou<U+017F>y. But <U+017F>eeing her beloved <hi>Zelidan</hi> Bleeding on the ground, extremity of Grief made her <U+017F>o in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther con<U+017F>iderations, that <U+017F>he was about to precipitate her <U+017F>elf from the Window: But hope, which is the la<U+017F>t thing that leaves the unfortunate, made her <U+017F>till think it not impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to recover him. She was running out to that purpo<U+017F>e, when <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> now a compleat Victor, was entring the Pallace: with all the <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of a Pious Son, he met her; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>He would take all for Enemies, that failed to render her the Honour due to the Widow, and Mother of their King.</hi> Without <U+017F>taying, or an<U+017F>wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him at all; but with an upbraiding look, (where Rage and Compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion <U+017F>trove for Superiority) which <U+017F>eemed to call him a thou<U+017F>and Cruel Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reres;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:56550:64"/>
<U+017F>he abandoned her <U+017F>elf whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the impul<U+017F>e of her Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, and ca<U+017F>ting her body on tho<U+017F>e of <hi>Zelidan</hi> and the Prince<U+017F>s her Daughter, <U+017F>he divided her Ki<U+017F><U+017F>es and Lamentations between them: 'Till exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive <U+017F>orrow, like a Tyrannical U<U+017F>urper, <U+017F>eized and oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed all her Vitals: By its <U+017F>ad weight reducing her to a <U+017F>tate as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, and void of life, as theirs whom <U+017F>he grieved for. Never had Love and Grief a greater Sacrifice then here, nor mi<U+017F>ery more powerful Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to gain compa<U+017F><U+017F>ion from the mo<U+017F>t obdurate hearts: (here is a large Field for the Author to expatiate on the vici<U+017F><U+017F>itude of humane things; but the Gentle Reader would think him very inhumane, nay in my Con<U+017F>cience acce<U+017F><U+017F>ary to their Murthers, if he <U+017F>uffered three of the mo<U+017F>t Illu<U+017F>trious Per<U+017F>ons in the World, to lye neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the ground, and dye for want of careful attendance, while he was <U+017F>hewing his Common-place Wit; therefore he ha<U+017F>tens to their relief, with re<U+017F>olution to <U+017F>ave them all if he can:) <hi>Alcidalis</hi> took the Queen in his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:56550:65"/>
Arms, while others performed the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ervice to the Prince<U+017F>s and <hi>Zeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan;</hi> conveying them to their <U+017F>everal apartments; the uncertain Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that <U+017F>ome few Minutes before breathed nothing but death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation again<U+017F>t them; now followed them Houling and Groaning. All the Arts and <U+017F>trength of Phy<U+017F>ick were diligently applyed, which re<U+017F>tored <U+017F>ome weak <U+017F>ymptoms of life in <hi>Zelidan;</hi> and tho<U+017F>e were carefully Cheri<U+017F>hed; but the unfortunate Prince<U+017F>s was irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocably dead. The Queens Swouning being only the effect of a vehement <U+017F>urprizing Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion, death <U+017F>oon was beaten off, and his pale <U+017F>preading En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igns rufled up by her returning Sen<U+017F>es: But life came accompanied with all tho<U+017F>e killing Griefs that wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on its exile, which like the envyed Favourites of <U+017F>ome weak unhappy Prince (for forrows <U+017F>oon in<U+017F>inuate them<U+017F>elves into the hearts affection) rai<U+017F>ed new Commotions among the <U+017F>ouls di<U+017F>contented faculties, and the oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Sen<U+017F>es, (tho<U+017F>e nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and <U+017F>upport of Life) which were
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:56550:65"/>
like to prove as fatal as the former; had not the News of <hi>Zelidans</hi> hopeful Recovery repre<U+017F><U+017F>ed their Violence, by the removal of the cau<U+017F>e.—Weak as <U+017F>he was, <U+017F>he cau<U+017F>ed her <U+017F>elf to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to his apartment.—But, Gods! what a univer<U+017F>al amazement <U+017F>eized the Queen, and all the Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, to find their Champion was a Woman? For <U+017F>o her <U+017F>welling Brea<U+017F>ts declared, which by undre<U+017F><U+017F>ing her, the better to apyly their nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary aid, were di<U+017F>covered. Her Sen<U+017F>es in a little time<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> were perfectly re<U+017F>tored; and 'twas difficult for the mo<U+017F>t curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erver to determine, whether the Queen or <hi>Zelinda</hi> (for <U+017F>o we mu<U+017F>t call her, now <U+017F>hes di<U+017F>covered) was in the greate<U+017F>t confu<U+017F>ion; after they had a long time gazed upon each other, the Queen finding in the transformed <hi>Zelidan,</hi> the well known Beauty and Meen of the per<U+017F>ecuted <hi>Zelinda;</hi> lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her eyes to Heaven cryed out; <hi>I yeild! ju<U+017F>t Gods, I yeild to my inexorable de<U+017F>tiny! Ab</hi> Zelinda! <hi>thy injuries have been too well revenged.</hi>—Having <U+017F>aid this, e'r <hi>Zelinda</hi> could an<U+017F>wer, <U+017F>he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56550:66"/>
Love being now wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extinct, Nature re<U+017F>umed her power, and carried her to the apartment of the Prince<U+017F>s, where with <U+017F>uch moving pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion <U+017F>he deplored her lo<U+017F>s, that the mo<U+017F>t in<U+017F><U+017F>ible were forced to <U+017F>ympathize with her. The News of <hi>Zelidans</hi> Transformation, flew <U+017F>traight through the Pallace, and the extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of the change, rai<U+017F>ed a<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Curio<U+017F>ity in <hi>Alcidalis</hi> to behold her, for he had not heard that it was <hi>Zelinda.</hi> The Me<U+017F><U+017F>engrr he <U+017F>ent to obtain that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, entered her Chamber, ju<U+017F>t as one was going from her to entreat the favour which he <U+017F>ought. The Prince full of <U+017F>hame for his Victory over a Woman, ha<U+017F>tened to beg her pardon; When he entered, his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants re<U+017F>pectively withdrew to the furthe<U+017F>t part of the Room. Neither the Palene<U+017F>s her lo<U+017F>s of Blood had planted on her Cheeks, nor their long <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, could hinder the di<U+017F>covery of the true <hi>Zelinda</hi> at fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ight:—So perfectly had love engraven her Image in his heart. What Pen can de<U+017F>cribe the Violence of their differnt Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:56550:66"/>
which then Tyrannized in this Princes Brea<U+017F>t? Shame and grief for wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her he prized above his Life, and joy that <U+017F>he <U+017F>urvived, and was in a place where he was now <U+017F>ole Ma<U+017F>ter<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> and able to give and receive the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t proofs of a mutual, unalterable Love, (like meeting Tydes, who<U+017F>e oppo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forces change <U+017F>wift running<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Streams a while into a fixed Calme) reduced him to a <U+017F>tate of in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibility:—With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Speech or motion, he beheld her<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Such exta<U+017F>ies are the u<U+017F>ual effects of <U+017F>udden Joys or Grief; the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <U+017F>urprized, and oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with unexpected Events, all the Vital Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits croud <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t to its a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, that they often cau<U+017F>e that ruine Nature <U+017F>ends them to prevent. As <U+017F>ome, who<U+017F>e Animal Spirits are ob<U+017F>tructed, and as it were <U+017F>mothered by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dige<U+017F>ted Vapours, which from the Stomach fume into the Brain, and a while deprive them of the benefits of Life, (as interpo<U+017F>ing Clouds ob<U+017F>cure the Suns lu<U+017F>tre) retain their Sen<U+017F>es, but want power to imploy them; <U+017F>uch the pre<U+017F>ent State of <hi>Alcidalis</hi> was,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56550:67"/>
he knew what he ought to <U+017F>peak, and act, but the greatne<U+017F>s of his Love, and violence of his de<U+017F>ires, took from him all ability of utterance; till <hi>Zelinda,</hi> who<U+017F>e condition much re<U+017F>embled his, fearing his <U+017F>ilence proceeded from <U+017F>ome change in his affection, thus began.—</p>
            <q>Is this the kind reception <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalis</hi> gives the unfortunate <hi>Zelinda?</hi> do all the dangers I have pa<U+017F>t, and all my con<U+017F>tant Love, merit this cold return? Great Gods! have you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erved me from <U+017F>o many various Deaths, to peri<U+017F>h here? here in the only Haven, where I had depo<U+017F>ited my la<U+017F>t hopes of a<U+017F><U+017F>ured <U+017F>afety? Oh <hi>Alcidalis!</hi> let thy Sword give me a <U+017F>peedy and more welcome death then thy di<U+017F>dain!—</q>
            <p>Here ca<U+017F>ting him<U+017F>elf on the Bed, and imbracing her, he could get out no more but, <hi>Oh my deare<U+017F>t</hi> Zelinda! and was relap<U+017F>ing again into his former exta<U+017F>ie; which overcoming, with much difficulty he proceeded.—</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:56550:67"/>Your <U+017F>afety and your love (my ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zelinda!</hi>) are ble<U+017F><U+017F>ings too great to be received at once, with le<U+017F>s concern: Since your lo<U+017F>s, in blindne<U+017F>s to all other objects of delight, I have wandred ore the World; pardon me, if I could not meet the fir<U+017F>t appearance of my Glorious Sun, without amazement. Give me, ye Divine Powers! pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned <U+017F>trength to bear my Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, le<U+017F>t like a <U+017F>tarving man, while I too greedily receive it, that ha<U+017F>tens my death which only can re<U+017F>tore my fainting life.—</q>
            <q>Then do you yet love me? (cryed the overjoyed Prince<U+017F>s;) and will the King, keep tho<U+017F>e vowes which <hi>Alcidalis</hi> made to the then Happy <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda?</hi>—</q>
            <q>For ever! for ever! (an<U+017F>wered the tran<U+017F>ported <hi>Alcidalis</hi>) the enjoyment of my adored <hi>Zelinda,</hi> is more then ten thou<U+017F>and Empires.—</q>
            <q>Ah Sir, (<U+017F>aid <U+017F>he) but intere<U+017F>t of State.—</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:56550:68"/>
               <q>State! (cryed <hi>Alcidalis</hi>) my <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> is all all to me, I would not thank the Gods for a Crown, but to lay it at her Feet.</q> Then turning to the Attendants which had now filled the Room, (impatience of beholding their long lo<U+017F>t Prince, bringing them thither from all parts) rai<U+017F>ing his voice, he cryed out: <q>He is a Traytor, and the Mortal Enemy of <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> that will not kneel and Petition the excellent <hi>Zelinda</hi> to be his Queen; who<U+017F>e Beauty and Virtues, merit the Empire of the Univer<U+017F>e. The Gods (to whom I pay all reverence) <U+017F>hall never, but by death, Divorce me from thy Arms.—Were I Racked to ten thou<U+017F>and peices, as every part of a broken Mirrour pre<U+017F>ents an entire face, in every part of <hi>Alcidalis,</hi> would appear the bright Image of my adored <hi>Zelinda.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Then they renewed their Embraces and mutual Vows; asking and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wearing twenty <U+017F>everal Que<U+017F>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at once. She related all her Adventures from her departure from <hi>Barcelona</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56550:68"/>
till that in<U+017F>tant: which <hi>Alcidalis</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited with his Story, how he <U+017F>ought her in <hi>Italy,</hi> (but omitted his intrigue with the Dutche<U+017F>s of <hi>Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>) and at <hi>Sardignia,</hi> where meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the News of his Fathers death, the pre<U+017F>ervation of his Crown ha<U+017F>tened him to <hi>Spain;</hi> But with a re<U+017F>olute deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to imploy all his new power, in <U+017F>earch of <hi>Zelinda:</hi> How, near <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<U+017F>a,</hi> by <U+017F>ome faithful Nobility to whom he made him<U+017F>elf known, and who received him with marks of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exepre<U+017F><U+017F>ible <U+017F>atisfaction, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Actions of <hi>Zelidan,</hi> his intere<U+017F>t with the Queen, and his <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>ed de<U+017F>ign of Marrying her, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urping the Crown. This gave Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a while the preheminence of Love, and led him in the Head of tho<U+017F>e Friends the <U+017F>hortne<U+017F>s of the time could get together, to this mi<U+017F>taken Revenge, and real Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s.—</p>
            <p>The Queen<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> notwith<U+017F>tanding all the <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ive importunity of <hi>Alcidalis<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </hi> and all the a<U+017F><U+017F>urances of Power and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:56550:69"/>
Honour he could give her, would not be diverted from a re<U+017F>olution <U+017F>he had made, of retiring to a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hou<U+017F>e, there to pa<U+017F>s the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of her now hated life.</p>
            <p>After the Funeral of the Prince<U+017F>s her Daughter was with all Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious, Pomp celebrated <U+017F>he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed her Vow, and was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied to the place of her retirememt, with a Magnificence becoming that Solemn occa<U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p>To that <U+017F>olemnity immediatly <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Coronation, and Marriag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Alcidalis</hi> and <hi>Zelinda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day with all imaginable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<U+017F>tances of an univer<U+017F>al joy was fini<U+017F>hed.</p>
            <p>After which, Gentle Reader! (I may <U+017F>afely call you <U+017F>o now, for I am <U+017F>ure you are tyr'd as well as I) you may <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e the long-wi<U+017F>hed night are riv'd, though very lazily in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the King and Queen: And you
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56550:69"/>
may <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e their impatient Love ha<U+017F>tened them to Bed; And what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, you may <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e too, if you plea<U+017F>e; for I have more Civility then to <U+017F>peak what I think: but as the mo<U+017F>t Ingenious Sir <hi>John Suckling</hi> <U+017F>aid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>What is this, who can tell?</l>
               <l>But I believe it was no more,</l>
               <l>Then thou and I have done before.</l>
               <l>With <hi>Bridget</hi> and with <hi>Nell.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I have naturally <U+017F>o much kindne<U+017F>s for Lovers, that I will without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther di<U+017F>turbance leave them to their private Banquet; and if no other Pen rai<U+017F>es them, they <U+017F>hall lye there till Dooms, day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:70"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56550:70"/>
            <head>Books Printed and Sold by <hi>James Magnes,</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>ell-Street,</hi> near the <hi>Piazza's.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>GOds Revenge again<U+017F>t Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bacons</hi> Natural Hi<U+017F>tory, <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nostra damus</hi> Prophe<U+017F>ies, <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hou<U+017F>e of Mourning, <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fodinae Regalis, Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plato's</hi> Apology of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Pheodo,</hi> or of the Soul, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Burnt Child dreads the Fire, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Natural Hi<U+017F>tory of the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:56550:71"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Garden</hi> Drollery, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>angers</hi> Letters, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip<U+017F>ious</hi> of Con<U+017F>tancy, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Taylors</hi> P<U+017F>alter, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Bi<U+017F>hop <hi>Andrews</hi> Devotions, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colets</hi> Devotions, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas a Kempis,</hi> in 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Plays<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tartuffe,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Puritan.</item>
               <item>Forced Marriage, or the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Bridegroom.</item>
               <item>All Mi<U+017F>taken, or the Mad Couple:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engli<U+017F>h Mon<U+017F>ieur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Andromicha.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Tragedy of <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Calisto,</hi> or the Cha<U+017F>te Nymph, a Ma<U+017F>que at Court Acted by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons of the Highe<U+017F>t Quality, frequently.</item>
               <item>The Mi<U+017F>taken Husband.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hannibal's</hi> Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>

