<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deliramenta catarrhi: or, The incongruities, impossibilities, and absurdities couched under the vulgar opinion of defluxions. The author, that great philosopher, by fire, Joh. Bapt. Van Helmont, &amp;c. The translator and paraphrast Dr. Charleton, physician to the late King.</title>
            <author>Helmont, Jean Baptiste van, 1577-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E601_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202434</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E601[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deliramenta catarrhi: or, The incongruities, impossibilities, and absurdities couched under the vulgar opinion of defluxions. The author, that great philosopher, by fire, Joh. Bapt. Van Helmont, &amp;c. The translator and paraphrast Dr. Charleton, physician to the late King.</title>
                  <author>Helmont, Jean Baptiste van, 1577-1644.</author>
                  <author>Charleton, Walter, 1619-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.G. for William Lee at the signe of the Turks-head in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Catarrhi deliramenta.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 18.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catarrh --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114890:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114890:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Deliramenta Catarrhi: OR, THE INCONGRUITIES, IMPOSSIBILITIES, and ABSURDITIES Couched under the Vulgar Opinion of DEFLUXIONS.</head>
            <p>The Author, That great Philo<U+017F>opher, by Fire, <hi>Joh. Bapt. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>an Helmont, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tran<U+017F>lator and Paraphra<U+017F>t D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. CHARLETON, Phy<U+017F>ician to the late KING.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>.</p> 
               <bibl>¶. Ari<U+017F>t. de Caelo. 1. cap. 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>William Lee</hi> at the <U+017F>igne of the Turks-head in <hi>Fleet-<U+017F>treet.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114890:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114890:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Tran<U+017F>lator to the Judicious and</hi> (therefore) <hi>unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O malevolent, <U+017F>evere, and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable have the Cen<U+017F>ures of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (yet <U+017F>uch onely, I conceive, who<U+017F>e <hi>parcel-literature,</hi> and incapacity of the more <U+017F>olid and weighty <hi>Notions</hi> of <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophy,</hi> delivered in mo<U+017F>t <hi>proper</hi> and <hi><U+017F>ignificant language,</hi> have depraved their <hi>Appetite</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and made them fit to dige<U+017F>t nothing, but crude <hi>Sallads</hi> gathered in the <hi>Poets Elizium,</hi> and <U+017F>oft <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> oyled with the effeminate <hi>Extracts</hi> of the <hi>Stage,</hi> and <U+017F>piced with <U+017F>ome new <hi>French-Engli<U+017F>h</hi> idioms) been of my precedent <hi>exerci<U+017F>e;</hi> that the <hi>World</hi> might expect from me rather a <hi>Vindication</hi> of that, then the <hi>Publication</hi> of a <U+017F>econd, of the <U+017F>ame kind. But as I ever level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my endeavors at a far nobler <hi>end,</hi> then the
<pb facs="tcp:114890:3"/>
nothing of vulgar <hi>Applaus:</hi> <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o have I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the temper of my <hi>Genius</hi> to be too <hi>Stoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> to feel the weak a<U+017F><U+017F>aults of that cowardly Pygmie, <hi>detraction;</hi> whom han<U+017F>omly to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,</hi> is to <hi><U+017F>corne.</hi> For common ob<U+017F>ervation will ju<U+017F>tifie, that no man ever entered the li<U+017F>ts with that ignorant <hi>Bug-bear,</hi> but lo<U+017F>t much by the encounter: his <hi>judgement</hi> inevitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <U+017F>uch <hi>VVounds,</hi> as the reputation of his <hi>Courage</hi> could never cure, or compen<U+017F>ate.</p>
            <p>Nor <U+017F>hall I at all recede from this <hi>Maxime,</hi> though I here adventure to profe<U+017F><U+017F>e, that next to the di<U+017F>charge of that duty, which, as a <hi>Scholer,</hi> I owe unto the Publique, in the <hi>Explanation, Improvement,</hi> and <hi>Communication</hi> of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cure <hi>Truths;</hi> the mo<U+017F>t forcible <hi>motive,</hi> that incited me to be<U+017F>tow a few recreative houres on the <hi>Tran<U+017F>lation,</hi> and <hi>marginal Paraphra<U+017F>e</hi> of this piece of <hi>Helmont,</hi> was to have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of letting the<U+017F>e <hi>Semi-criticks</hi> know: that though they have <hi>privately accu<U+017F>ed,</hi> yet would it have <U+017F>tood more with their Honour <hi>publickly</hi> to have <hi>convicted</hi> me of <U+017F>uch <hi>improprieties</hi> of expre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, or unnatural <hi>perver<U+017F>ions</hi> of my <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, as might make me alter any thing of moment in the former, or change my <U+017F>tile in the pre<U+017F>ent di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:114890:3"/>
For though I am <U+017F>ufficiently con<U+017F>cious to my <U+017F>elf of more <hi>defects,</hi> and greater <hi>unevenne<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> of my <hi>Pen,</hi> then the acute<U+017F>t of my <hi>Calumniators</hi> can di<U+017F>cover; and do account it more noble to detect my own, then others Frailties: yet I dare appeal to the <U+017F>ober Deci<U+017F>ion of any, who<U+017F>e <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> hold any proportion with the <hi>Subject,</hi> (and <U+017F>uch onely can I allow for competent <hi>Judges)</hi> whether <hi>the fine and my<U+017F>terious nature of many things, treated of in that di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e, might not have <U+017F>uffered a gro<U+017F><U+017F>e Eclip<U+017F>e, if dre<U+017F>t in a meer-Engli<U+017F>h veil?</hi> Whether it be a Crime in me to trace the foot<U+017F>teps of tho<U+017F>e Worthies, who have infinitely botb enriched and ennobled our Language, by admitting and naturalizing thou<U+017F>ands of forraigne Words, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently brought home from the <hi>Greek, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Italian,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Oratories; which, though in the untraveld ears of our <hi>Fathers</hi> they would have <U+017F>ounded as har<U+017F>h, as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ineffabilia verba. 2. Cor. 12. c. ver. 4.</note>; yet have a few years made <U+017F>o familiar unto us, that now even <hi>Children</hi> <U+017F>peak much of <hi>Latine,</hi> before they can well read a word of <hi>Engli<U+017F>h?</hi> And to draw in to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <U+017F>candal, whether <hi>I</hi> have merited the Epithite of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Qui venu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tatem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum, non <U+017F>en<U+017F>uum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumen in<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur.</note> of one that praefers
<pb facs="tcp:114890:4"/>
the noveltie, or affected elegance of the <hi>Phra<U+017F>e,</hi> to the nerves and importance of the <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e;</hi> meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becau<U+017F>e I rendered <U+017F>ome <hi>Phy<U+017F>ical Notions</hi> in <hi>terms</hi> mo<U+017F>t amply and adequately exhibiting their <hi>qualities;</hi> and tho<U+017F>e no other, but <U+017F>uch as are mo<U+017F>t frequent in the <hi>Schools:</hi> and attempted to paint the <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Helmonts</hi> <U+017F>pruce <hi>Conceptions,</hi> in <hi>Colours</hi> mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>trong and natural; though borrowed from the more praeci<U+017F>e, di<U+017F>tinctive, and emphatical <hi>Tinctures</hi> of forreigne <hi>Arti<U+017F>ts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can not but applaud the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and happy <hi>Phan<U+017F>ie</hi> of this <hi>Tetra<U+017F>tick,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Legi<U+017F>ti no<U+017F>tros? ri<U+017F>i<U+017F>ti, <hi>Romule,</hi> libros? <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ca<U+017F>p. Hof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus</hi> in praefatione <U+017F>ua ad <hi>lib. de Generat. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi> ¶</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ut vidi, ut ri<U+017F>i, <hi>Romule Dive,</hi> tuos.</l>
                  <l>Quae Cau<U+017F>a effectus paris in tam di<U+017F>pare cau<U+017F>a?</l>
                  <l>Ri<U+017F>i<U+017F>ti <hi>ingenium</hi> tute, ego <hi><U+017F>tultitiam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
And when any of the tribe of <hi>Zoilus</hi> <U+017F>hall <U+017F>hew us <U+017F>omething of their own, I may perchance be furni<U+017F>hed with an opportunity of <hi>Applying</hi> them.</p>
            <p>But le<U+017F>t I fall upon a <hi>Parergie,</hi> and loo<U+017F>ly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate into that <U+017F>ini<U+017F>ter path, which my re<U+017F>oluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons abhor; I return directly to my duty, which is to give the impartial <hi>Reader</hi> the <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> which per<U+017F>waded me to exhibite my <hi>Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114890:4"/>
of <hi>Helmonts</hi> unfrequent, and new coyned, or new-applied <hi>Termes</hi> of Art, in <hi>Latine.</hi> In a word, I conceived that the <hi>Quality</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> intimated by each of tho<U+017F>e paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Appellatives,</hi> being <U+017F>uch as falls under the comprehen<U+017F>ion of none, but the leading part of learning, and chiefly tho<U+017F>e, who have more then looked into the my<U+017F>terious Temple of <hi>Ae<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius,</hi> did nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily require it: and that no <hi>Engli<U+017F>h,</hi> how plain <U+017F>oever, could have dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their ample meaning into tho<U+017F>e skulls, which are <U+017F>o thick, as not to admit it in <hi>Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As concerning the <hi>Verity</hi> of the<U+017F>e <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes,</hi> in<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed upon the en<U+017F>uing <hi>Treati<U+017F>e,</hi> though I have formerly declared my Aver<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to attempt any <hi>Commentary</hi> on, or deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ive <hi>A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion</hi> of any of his <hi>Innovations;</hi> in regard I ever found his rea<U+017F>on <U+017F>tronger at <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moli<U+017F>hing</hi> the Doctrines of the Antient Pillars of our Art, then <hi>Erecting</hi> a more <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantial and durable <hi>Structure</hi> of his own, his <hi>Witt</hi> more acute and active at <hi>Contradiction,</hi> then his <hi>judgement</hi> profound and authentick at <hi>Probation:</hi> yet <U+017F>hall I u<U+017F>urp the liberty to <U+017F>ay, that many of the <hi>Grounds</hi> of his quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t the <hi>Schools,</hi> in this particular of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhs,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114890:5"/>
are <U+017F>ufficiently ju<U+017F>tifiable; and that if any member in the whole body of <hi>Phy<U+017F>ick</hi> needs to have its errors purged, <U+017F>tupidity corrected, di<U+017F>tortions rectified, and leanne<U+017F><U+017F>e reformed, doubtle<U+017F><U+017F>e this Capitall one of <hi>Defluxions</hi> may chiefly de<U+017F>erve the indu<U+017F>try of the pre<U+017F>ent, and gratefull improvement of the future Age. Nor <U+017F>hould I have onely <U+017F>aid it, had not my <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation,</hi> that <U+017F>ome more judicious and elegant hand will <U+017F>hortly <U+017F>et about that <U+017F>o nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, charitable, and honourable task, whi<U+017F>pered me, that this difficult, and (therefore) infinitely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iderable piece of knowledge, would unavoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably have <U+017F>uffered irreparable <hi>detriment, di<U+017F>paragement,</hi> and <hi>ob<U+017F>curity</hi> from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of my unequall undertaking. And I am bold to promi<U+017F>e, that if any <U+017F>ober mind, imbued with that u<U+017F>efull Le<U+017F><U+017F>on of <hi>Ari<U+017F>totle,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Metaphy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; de</hi> Coelo <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>, <U+017F>hall come to the di<U+017F>pute, denudate of all intere<U+017F>t, and purged from all the dreggs of <hi>Adhaerence</hi> to either <U+017F>ide; he <U+017F>hall <U+017F>oon be convicted, that in all that long flux of time betwixt the daies of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and us, no one (at lea<U+017F>t that ever came to our view) among the numerous <U+017F>warm of
<pb facs="tcp:114890:5"/>
               <hi>Pathologi<U+017F>ts</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Writers on the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the body of man.</note>, hath di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>ed of the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>cau<U+017F>es</hi> of <U+017F>uch <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es</hi> as are in vulgar practice confidently referred unto the <hi>Di<U+017F>tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Rheums</hi> from the head upon parts of inferior <U+017F>ituation, with <U+017F>uch cleare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable rea<U+017F>ons, as not to have left very large gapps, for the ea<U+017F>ie illation of the<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> and <hi>objections</hi> rai<U+017F>ed by <hi>Helmont</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t them. In brief; whoever <U+017F>hall <U+017F>o far contribute towards the advance of his own knowledge, as to receive the <hi>Arguments</hi> here oppo<U+017F>ed to the traditional Theory of <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> with that equal ju<U+017F>tice of improving them to that height, with which they are offered; will, I doubt not, afford us his concurrent vote: that the chiefe impediment to their prevailing upon the beliefe of many di<U+017F><U+017F>enters, will be their <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. For hardly doe we part with tho<U+017F>e Doctrines, which in<U+017F>tilled into our tender and un wary yeers, have grown up together with our under<U+017F>tandings, and hold our credulities en<U+017F>laved to an implicite confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, by the tyrannous title of Prae<U+017F>crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> A deplorable <hi>remora</hi> to the timely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antlation of <hi>Truth,</hi> long <U+017F>ince di<U+017F>covered and complained of by the <hi>grave</hi> and yet mo<U+017F>t <hi>acute
<pb facs="tcp:114890:6"/>
Stagirite,</hi> in the<U+017F>e words: <note n="*" place="margin">Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ic. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Quemadmodum enim con<U+017F>uevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ita judicamus dici debere, &amp; quae praeter haec non apparent <U+017F>imilia; <U+017F>ed quia non con<U+017F>uevimus, ignotiora &amp; magis pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grina. Con<U+017F>ueta enim notiora <U+017F>unt.</hi> I <U+017F>hall here <U+017F>o far exerci<U+017F>e your <hi>Candor</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> as to tolerate a <U+017F>hort <hi>Digre<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> (though perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and material) concerning this Cardinal cau<U+017F>e of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Indocibility.</hi> The <hi>De<U+017F>crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of this vice of the minde, <U+017F>ince mo<U+017F>t ample and elegant, I <U+017F>hall borrow from that Noble <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer</hi> into <hi>Truth, Mr. Hobbs,</hi> in his ine<U+017F>tima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manual of <hi>Human Nature.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>If the minds of men (<U+017F>ays he) were all of white Paper, they would, for the mo<U+017F>t, be equally di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge what<U+017F>oever <U+017F>hould be in the right method, and right ratiocination, delivered unto them: but when men have once acquie<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in untrue opinions, and regi<U+017F>tred them as authenticall methods in their minds; it is no le<U+017F><U+017F>e impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to <U+017F>peak intelligibly to <U+017F>uch men, then to write legibly upon a peece of Paper already <U+017F>cribled over. The immediate</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114890:6"/>
cau<U+017F>e <hi>therefore of</hi> Indocibility, <hi>is</hi> Prejudice; <hi>and of prejudice, fal<U+017F>e</hi> opinion <hi>of our own knowledge.</hi>
               </q> The <hi>Naturall Rea<U+017F>on</hi> of it I <U+017F>hall adventure to deduce from the <U+017F>lender stock of my own <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophy.</hi> We judge of the <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>fal<U+017F>hood</hi> not onely of things <U+017F>ubject to the apprehen<U+017F>ion of <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> but al<U+017F>o of <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> opinions, as we have been accu<U+017F>tomed from the minority of our <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tandings: and although many times we are greatly deluded, yet cannot the arm of the <U+017F>tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>on bend us from our accu<U+017F>tomed judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The ground of this is, that not onely the <note place="margin">Cur <U+017F>olitae opiniones placeant: in<U+017F>olitae, et<U+017F>i firmioribus rationibus bus innixae, di<U+017F>pliceant.</note> 
               <hi>Images,</hi> or bare <hi>Ideas</hi> (I mean not tho<U+017F>e <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall <U+017F>pecies,</hi> <U+017F>o much talked of in common Philo<U+017F>ophy, for I believe I could prove that there are no <U+017F>uch in Nature) of tho<U+017F>e things have an exi<U+017F>tence in the brain; but certaine <hi>Notes</hi> or marks of <hi>Rejection</hi> or <hi>Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> are al<U+017F>o <U+017F>uperadded unto them, and deeply impre<U+017F><U+017F>ed upon the brain. The<U+017F>e <hi>Images</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being again offered unto the mind, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not only the things them<U+017F>elves; but at the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tant, even without any hae<U+017F>itancy or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate examination, yea though mo<U+017F>t convincing
<pb facs="tcp:114890:7"/>
and firme arguments are <U+017F>ometimes brought to the contrary, with great violence, we <hi>approve</hi> or <hi>reject</hi> them according to the <hi>conformity</hi> or <hi>di<U+017F>proportion</hi> of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Notes</hi> formerly regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tred. The remove of which ob<U+017F>truction <U+017F>hall be the con<U+017F>tant bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e not onely of my <U+017F>tudies, but al<U+017F>o of my earne<U+017F>t prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae in Schola &amp; Cathedra aliquando praeter tationem, plerumque ad acuenda ingenia juven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rutis, in</hi> theoria <hi>proponuntur, <U+017F>unt toleranda: quae vero in</hi> praxi <hi>in perniciem aegrorum prae<U+017F>cribun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, potius execranda &amp; damnanda, quam admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda e<U+017F><U+017F>e, exi<U+017F>timo.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid verum, atque decens curo, &amp; rogo, &amp; omn is in hoc <U+017F>um.</l>
               <l>Condo, &amp; compono quae mox depromere po<U+017F><U+017F>im.</l>
               <l>Ac ne forte roges, quo me duce, quo lare tuter?</l>
               <l>Nullius addictus jurare in verba magi<U+017F>tri,</l>
               <l>Quo me cunque rapit tempe<U+017F>t as, deferor ho<U+017F>pes.</l>
               <l>Nunc agilis fio, &amp; mer<U+017F>or civilibus undis,</l>
               <l>Virtutis verae cu<U+017F>tos, rigidu<U+017F>que <U+017F>atelles.</l>
               <l>Nunc in Ari<U+017F>tippi furtim praecepta relabor:</l>
               <l>Et mihi res, non me rebus <U+017F>ubjungere conor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Poeta Philo<U+017F>ophus ad vada Maeandri concinuit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VV. CHARLETON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114890:7"/>
            <head>The Errors of Phy<U+017F>icians Concerning DEFLVXIONS.</head>
            <div type="summary">
               <head>The Summary.</head>
               <p>1. WHo is the Lord paramont of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and Nature, 2. Some <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>itions, by way of premi<U+017F>es. 3. The conclu<U+017F>ion. 4. Proved from experiments. 5. The explication of the Po<U+017F>ition. 6. The Lungs the part which fir<U+017F>t dyes. 7. Why the Author de<U+017F>erted the Schools. 8. The forerunner of mi<U+017F>eries to old men. 9. Purging medicaments, why de<U+017F>tructive to old men. 10. The te<U+017F>timonies that Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians give of their own ignorance, Fatall: becau<U+017F>e too late. 11. That Axiome of Phy<U+017F>icians de<U+017F>umed from the u<U+017F>e of things beneficiall and hurtfull, worthy their blu<U+017F>hes. 12. Errors of Phy<U+017F>icians. 13. The ground of Paracel<U+017F>us his incon<U+017F>tancy. 14. The Generalogy of a Catarrh, or Rheume, like an old wives fable. 15. Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es imputed to Catarrhs. 16. How great calamity arifeth to mankinde from thence. 17. By what means they make the <U+017F>ick their perpetuall <U+017F>laves. 18. The ordinary <U+017F>ubter<U+017F>uge of the Schools. 19. Thirteen Po<U+017F>itions. 20 Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Conclu<U+017F>ions emergent from tho<U+017F>e Po<U+017F>itions. 21. By a <U+017F>ufficient enumeration of Parts. 22. A Dilemma. 23. Some Ab<U+017F>urdities. 24. Ignorance in the Schools, the <U+017F>ole Mother
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114890:8"/>
of Catarrhs. 25 The <U+017F>ame Ignorance, the fountain of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>urdities in their method of Cure. 26. Shame, the Cau<U+017F>e of the Schools in<U+017F>tability, 27. A deniail of principles granted in the Schools 28. Whence heat is de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ived to the Liver. 29, The proof from un<U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>efull remedies. 30. the Tooth-ach ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined. 31. The dige<U+017F>tion of the Tooth and Nails, different from the Dige<U+017F>tion of all other parts. 32. A Catarrh upon the inward parts, demon<U+017F>trated impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, 33. The Po<U+017F>e, or Cold in the head, de<U+017F>cribed. 34. Ab<U+017F>urdities dependent on the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a Catarrh falling upon the <U+017F>tomack. 35. An enquiry concerning the dropping of Rheume upon the Lungs. 36. What di<U+017F>tills from the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap>, in the beginning of a Cold, and what in the continuance. 37. An Argument <hi>ab im<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F><U+017F>i i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> again<U+017F>t the Cau<U+017F>e of the Cough, delivered by the Schools. 38. The ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of the matter cau<U+017F>ing affections of the Lungs, declared. 39 The vanity and infertility of remedies, from want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. 40. The decoctions of China, Zarza, &amp;c. neither dry up excrementitious humors, nor prevent their generation. 41. Some Ab<U+017F>urdities growing upon this root. 42. What s to be ob<U+017F>erved in Affections of the Lungs, 43. The doctrine of the Schools, concerning the motion of the Lungs, fal<U+017F>e. 44. The u<U+017F>e of he Lungs, not yet knowne to the Schools. 45. 21. Peremtory rea<U+017F>ons again<U+017F>t the vulgar opinion of the u<U+017F>e of the Lungs. 46. The error of the Schools, concerning the u<U+017F>e of the Midrife, confirmed by 8. Arguments 47. 7. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clu<U+017F>ions en<U+017F>uing thereon. 48. Why the remedies of Phy<U+017F>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are inefficacious and barren. 49 That the means vulgarly u<U+017F>ed for the prevention and re<U+017F>traint of Catarrhs, are meer fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, and dreams worthy onely the heads of old women. 50. <hi>Galen</hi> wholly ridiculous in his Books of the con<U+017F>ervation of health. 51. The Ignorance of the Schools, right worthy our pitty and tears. 52 The di<U+017F><U+017F>ection of a living Dog, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Schools. 53. A new Error, concerning Lohochs, or Lambativ medicaments. 54. They depend on the <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Fal<U+017F>ity. 55. Some probations. 56. Whence the delu<U+017F>ion of Catarrhs was fir<U+017F>t introduced. 57. The refutation of an unrea<U+017F>onable and wild per<U+017F>ua<U+017F>ion. 58 What that is, which impo<U+017F>eth upon our <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, under the delu<U+017F>ive di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e of a De<U+017F>tillation. 59. What the <U+017F>econd and <U+017F>ucceeding matter. 60. Mens ignorance of the <hi>Latex,</hi> or <hi>fountain o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>erous humors,</hi> hath been the ba<U+017F>is to the opinion of Catarrhs. 61. Preoccupation. 62. The torture of night. 63. The incon<U+017F>tancy of Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>us.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114890:8"/>
64. Tho<U+017F>e liquid parts, which are not yet made commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants of vitality in our bodies, hold no corre<U+017F>pondence with the <U+017F>tarrs. 65. The marrow not accountable among<U+017F>t the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid parts of the body. ¶</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ea<U+017F>onable it is for us, now to declare, that the large Catalogue of Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, imputed to a <hi>de<U+017F>tillation</hi> of <hi>Rheume,</hi> from the head even to the extremity of the toes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ob<U+017F>tacle impeding the de<U+017F>cent, is an old wives fable, invented by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>adver<U+017F>ary</hi> of mankind, on purpo<U+017F>e, le<U+017F>t the <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> of <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es</hi> being known, their <hi>Remedies</hi> might at the <U+017F>ame time be revealed. However it may be, yet at le<U+017F>t is it hence manife<U+017F>ted, that the Schooles are, even to this very day, <U+017F>educed by the errors of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in the point of the <hi>Generation</hi> of <hi>Rheume,</hi> its <hi>defluction, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, way, matter, means, places,</hi> and <hi>organs;</hi> as al<U+017F>o of its <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vul<U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>Remedies.</hi> For fal<U+017F>e and ab<U+017F>urd mu<U+017F>t that <U+017F>uper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructure be, which is founded on an ab<U+017F>urd and impo<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Principle. For which rea<U+017F>on, the vain and ridiculous hope, which is erected upon <hi>Cauteries</hi> and <hi>Fontanels,</hi> is in like manner <U+017F>taggered and ruined: as I <U+017F>hall, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient place, demon<U+017F>trate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> her<U+017F>elfe is the <U+017F>ole <hi>Ae<U+017F>culapius</hi> of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es: and the <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician</hi> no more but her <hi>Adjutant;</hi> according to that <note place="margin">1.</note> worthy Maxime of <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> But the <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates onely to <U+017F>uch di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which <hi>nature,</hi> by her own <U+017F>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle power, u<U+017F>ually cureth. But when <U+017F>he hath been <U+017F>o fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foyled, that <U+017F>he cannot by her own <U+017F>trength ari<U+017F>e again to maintain the conflict; the <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician,</hi> elected by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<U+017F>e benignity of the <hi>Almighty Lord of Nature,</hi> and in who<U+017F>e balance all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es carry the <U+017F>ame weight, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> are equaly curable (<U+017F>uch is he, who hath, among a multitude
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114890:9"/>
of others of the <U+017F>ame order, obtained <U+017F>ome one <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>niver<U+017F>al Medicine)</hi> remains no longer her <U+017F>ervant: but is become her <hi>Interpreter, Rector</hi> and very potent <hi>Lord.</hi> Let the name of my <hi>Lord Je<U+017F>u</hi> be exalted to eternity, who ever vouch<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth his munificence to <hi>Little ones,</hi> abjected in their own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility! For the Nature of a <U+017F>ick man being the chiefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of <hi>Morbifick impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions,</hi> and the <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>itive mover</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the contrary; the Patient mu<U+017F>t, then at lea<U+017F>t, when the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es entertained become prevalent, yield to their conquering <U+017F>word, or at be<U+017F>t, in the future, <hi>live a Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous death,</hi> unle<U+017F><U+017F>e he <U+017F>hall be relieved and re<U+017F>tored to his primitive integrity, by the <hi>auxiliary</hi> hand of the <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician.</hi> Yet is it not in the lot of every Phy<U+017F>ician, to arrive at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> to a<U+017F>cend to that excellent knowledge: but his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who hath the happy qualifications of a <hi>Vocation, Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Exercitation,</hi> and <hi>Commi<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</hi> For in the le<U+017F><U+017F>e accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli<U+017F>hed dayes of Hippocrates, the tran<U+017F>cendent virtues of <hi>Catholique medicines</hi> remained in the darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e of undi<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very (and in truth, even in our brighter dayes, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue but jejune, and eclip<U+017F>ed with prejudice and deri<U+017F>ion, among<U+017F>t vulgar Phy<U+017F>icians) upon which con<U+017F>ideration, he is de<U+017F>ervedly to be excu<U+017F>ed, in that he conceived the whole bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e of the conque<U+017F>t of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es to lye upon the <U+017F>houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Nature,</hi> as being the <U+017F>ole <hi>protectre<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> of <hi>life.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p>Again, I have el<U+017F>ewhere <U+017F>hewed, that, even from the fir<U+017F>t moment of the conception of an <hi>Embrion,</hi> there is a<U+017F><U+017F>igned <note place="margin">2.</note> to every peculiar member one <hi>Implantate</hi> or <hi>Originary Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as immediate pre<U+017F>ident and Governour thereof, and another <hi>Influent Spirit,</hi> deradiant from the heart, as the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieator</hi> and a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tant of the former; which yet is not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to perfection, nor individually di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ubdued to a qualification requi<U+017F>ite by the praeparatory power of the <hi>Implantate.</hi> I have al<U+017F>o taught, in another place, that every member enjoyes the capacity of <hi>Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> according to the virtue of its peculiar <hi>Ferment</hi> origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally inoculated into its principles; and that, for this rea<U+017F>on, there can be no expectance of any <hi>tran<U+017F>mutation,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114890:9"/>
conductive to a new <hi>generation,</hi> unle<U+017F><U+017F>e by the mediation of that <hi>Ferment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from hence, by naturall con<U+017F>equence, we may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<U+017F>tand, that <hi>all vegetation is made by the <U+017F>pirits;</hi> and that <U+017F>o all debility of dige<U+017F>tion in the members doth depend upon the diminution of the <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> and their peculiar <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> according to that in <U+017F>acred Writ: <hi>My <U+017F>pirit</hi> (the involucrum or con<U+017F>ervatory of the Ferment) <hi><U+017F>hall be attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and</hi> (therefore) <hi>my dayes <U+017F>hortned.</hi> So that a member, which in its integrity affords no vi<U+017F>ible excrement, mu<U+017F>t produce a large and con<U+017F>tant <U+017F>ource of unnatural humor, when once wounded, injured, dimini<U+017F>hed, or impeded in the vigour of its appropriate Ferment. And, finally, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from hence, that according to the degrees of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and variety of Cau<U+017F>es inferring that injury; there mu<U+017F>t be generated a difformity and di<U+017F><U+017F>imilitude of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments re<U+017F>pectively. ¶</p>
               <p>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, therefore, have their origine, not from one fountain, particularly from the Head (from whence the <note place="margin">3.</note> Schools wildly imagine all <hi>Catarrhs</hi> to drop down) but from a <U+017F>ingle <hi>Idiopathy,</hi> or proper indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of every part, <U+017F>uperinduced upon the <hi>topicall</hi> or dome<U+017F>tick <hi>Ferments.</hi> Thus, to example, <hi>Wounds,</hi> long after their <U+017F>anation, break <note place="margin">4.</note> forth again, and frequently introduce durable <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers,</hi> and <hi>Apo<U+017F>tems:</hi> and upon change of <hi>Weather,</hi> many years after their perfect con<U+017F>olidation, fall into a reincrude<U+017F>cence, and fre<U+017F>hly renew their torture. Thus <hi>Coughs, Pleuri<U+017F>ies, Spittings of blood,</hi> and <hi>Eri<U+017F>ypelous tumors,</hi> or inflammations, have their <U+017F>et vici<U+017F><U+017F>itudes, and, after con<U+017F>iderable intermi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions, reinvade. For <U+017F>ome exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive montain <hi>Cold,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Damp</hi> <U+017F>uddenly <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ing, the nightly <hi>Aer,</hi> mari<U+017F>h or uliginous <hi>Fog,</hi> or malignant <hi>Fume</hi> belched from the acide bowels of <hi>Mines,</hi> doth frequently, with one a<U+017F><U+017F>ault, <U+017F>o vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and ruine the <hi>Ferments</hi> of the <hi>brain,</hi> or <hi>Lungs,</hi> that from thenceforward, during the whole after-life, they become the too fertil <hi>magazines</hi> of various <hi>excrements.</hi> After this manner al<U+017F>o in the eyes, ears, teeth, jaws, &amp;c. Excrements
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114890:10"/>
(not <U+017F>uch as the mucous or <U+017F>limy excretions of the brain) are ordinarily occa<U+017F>ioned by the irregularity or diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Ferments peculiar to tho<U+017F>e parts. So <hi>Coughs</hi> and <hi>A<U+017F>thmas,</hi> or difficulties of re<U+017F>piration fir<U+017F>t begin: and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ever by a continued Ferment. Not, in <U+017F>ooth, by rea<U+017F>on of <note place="margin">5.</note> a vi<U+017F>cid Phlegme dropping continually from the head; but engendered in the womb of the Lungs, by a violation of their dome<U+017F>tick Ferment. For the Lungs more ea<U+017F>ily <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the inva<U+017F>ion of any forraigne injury, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the body: in regard, <hi>the Lungs is of all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the fir<U+017F>t that grows old, decayed, and dies.</hi> As is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t <note place="margin">6.</note> from the Cough generally infe<U+017F>ting old men, and from the rattling in the throats of all dying men, though they peri<U+017F>h by any other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and not by affections of the Lungs. For this is proper to the Lungs, in this re<U+017F>pect, that they continually <U+017F>uck in crude Aer, and being neer to the heart oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, lavi<U+017F>hly expend their own <U+017F>trength, and by rea<U+017F>on of that exhau<U+017F>tion, decay much the <U+017F>ooner. ¶</p>
               <p>In the fir<U+017F>t place I di<U+017F><U+017F>ent from the Schools, becau<U+017F>e I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well know this kind of vitio<U+017F>ity in nature to belong to <note place="margin">7.</note> the parts <hi>containing,</hi> and not to the humors <hi>contained.</hi> For excrementitious humors of this kind contained, are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain productions, which are begotten by the <hi>Archeus,</hi> or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall pre<U+017F>ident of the particular parts, depraved by <U+017F>ome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious inquination precedent.</p>
               <p>In the <U+017F>econd, I di<U+017F><U+017F>ent from them al<U+017F>o in this point, <note place="margin">8.</note> that I <U+017F>tand a<U+017F><U+017F>ured, that this evill is <hi>topicall</hi> and <hi>primary,</hi> and not communicated by <hi>Deuteropathy</hi> or <hi>con<U+017F>ent</hi> with the head. For the Coughs of old men, which for the plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity di<U+017F>courage all hopes of re<U+017F>tauration, ari<U+017F>e from this root; that in the lowe<U+017F>t and <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t branches of the <hi>Re<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory Artery,</hi> or pipe of the Lungs, there doth con<U+017F>tantly re<U+017F>ide <U+017F>uch a quantity of excrement, generated in the Lungs, which doth not onely ob<U+017F>truct the tubes or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duicts: but al<U+017F>o, by the contagion of its pre<U+017F>ence, deprave and dimini<U+017F>h the <hi>Local Ferment;</hi> whereupon there is hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produced a new <U+017F>ource or <U+017F>upply of excrements, as the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114890:10"/>
plentifull maintainance of Coughs, which in men once entered the calamitous confines of old age, are hardly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by remedies known to vulgar heads: in regard <U+017F>uch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies neither <hi>arrive</hi> at the <hi>part affected,</hi> nor, in troth, are they endowed with any <hi>re<U+017F>tauratory faculty.</hi> The<U+017F>e kinds of excrementitious humors, therefore, are no other but <hi>topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call defects</hi> of the parts mi<U+017F>affected: and every particular part hath its particular debility, whether innate or acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ite, from a diminution of its <hi>vegetative Ferment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus it is evident, that the various <U+017F>treams of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note place="margin">9.</note> flowing from the various parts of the body, are all derived from this one fountain. ¶</p>
               <p>On the<U+017F>e firm grounds I apprehend, fir<U+017F>t, <hi>That all repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Purgations, in the<U+017F>e affections, are fru<U+017F>traneous and hurtfull:</hi> in re<U+017F>pect, they levell their power onely again<U+017F>t the productions, or <hi>Effects,</hi> and not again<U+017F>t the <hi>Cau<U+017F>es;</hi> and chiefly becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>uch vi<U+017F>cid excrements, <U+017F>eated remotely from the <U+017F>tomack, are too <U+017F>tubborn and refractory to yield to the laxative operation of <hi>Purgers.</hi> You may pleas to adde, that although <hi>Laxatives</hi> may <U+017F>eem to have afforded ea<U+017F>e and relief, for a day or two after their u<U+017F>e; in<U+017F>omuch as the ma<U+017F><U+017F>e of crude and inconfected blood in the mezara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick veins being voided by <U+017F>tool, there mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the more <U+017F>paring di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ation of blood through the body, and penury of nouri<U+017F>hment in the Lungs, and by con<U+017F>equence a le<U+017F><U+017F>e quantity of excrement be rejected: yet do they, by <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tracting from the nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary aliment of the whole, and by leaving behind them an evill tincture in the in<U+017F>truments of common dige<U+017F>tion, every day more and more infringe the univer<U+017F>all oeconomy of the body, and impugne the con<U+017F>erving vigour of nature.</p>
               <p>This when Phy<U+017F>icians darkly, as through a veile, di<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <note place="margin">10</note> and remain ignorant, that they have afforded no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to their Patients, by the exhau<U+017F>tion of the laudable ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the body, and the diminution of naturall vigour; they at length remit them to the <U+017F>ober rules of <hi>Diet,</hi> and <hi>kitchen phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> as the onely hopefull means of their reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114890:11"/>
and <U+017F>o leave them, by the painfull u<U+017F>e of <hi>Fontanels,</hi> and reiterated moderate <hi>Purges,</hi> to run out their remaining <U+017F>ands, <hi>medicaly</hi> (i. e.) <hi>mi<U+017F>erably.</hi> By which Conce<U+017F><U+017F>ion, fir<U+017F>t, they in<U+017F>inuate that whole<U+017F>ome and moderate diet is to be preferred to mo<U+017F>t of tho<U+017F>e unfaithfull medicaments of the <U+017F>hops: and upon the te<U+017F>timony of their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy experience, conclude, that the Patient ought to ab<U+017F>tain from them, as hurtfull, and at be<U+017F>t but rarely to be u<U+017F>ed. Our wi<U+017F>h is, that now, after <U+017F>o many de<U+017F>tructive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hau<U+017F>tions of <U+017F>ick mens <U+017F>trength, they would <U+017F>it down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and in the future no more attempt, by the <U+017F>ame fruitle<U+017F><U+017F>e means, to dreigne the hopes, bodies, veins, <U+017F>trength, and pur<U+017F>es of the <U+017F>ick. At le<U+017F>t, I wi<U+017F>h, that they would be mindfull of their own Axiome, wherein they unanimou<U+017F>ly con<U+017F>ent, <hi>That the chiefe<U+017F>t indication of the cure, is to be de<U+017F>umed from the benefit or harme which things already u<U+017F>ed have introduced.</hi> Which rule, although it be worthy the blu<U+017F>hes of learned men, and onely fit for the conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">11.</note> of Empyricks: yet, it may be wi<U+017F>hed, that, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truction thereof, they would be reclaimed from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of their former errors, and no longer in Coughs and Con<U+017F>umptions return to tho<U+017F>e inefficacious remedies, which they have ob<U+017F>erved, never to have been beneficiall to any. For then would all <hi>Purgatives, Phlebotomy, Errhines,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Errhinum <hi>e<U+017F>t medicamentum, quod naribus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum, ex cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro, <U+017F>ine <U+017F>ternu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione, humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; prae<U+017F>ertim pituitam eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Apophlegmati<U+017F>mes,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Apophleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati<U+017F>mi <hi><U+017F>unt remedia, quae in ore aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu detenta, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ju<U+017F>que cavum leniter ferientia, per emi<U+017F><U+017F>aria palati, capio<U+017F>am pituitam è cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bro deducunt; quae<U+017F>en<U+017F>impo<U+017F>tea frequenti <U+017F>puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione facilè ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluditur.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lambatives, drinks of China, Zarza, Sa<U+017F><U+017F>afras, Cauteries</hi> in the Coronal <U+017F>uture, and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull remedies of the <U+017F>ame order, be wholly layed a<U+017F>ide, which are brought into u<U+017F>e by Phy<U+017F>icians, that they might not appeare to have received their fees for nothing. It is al<U+017F>o to be wi<U+017F>hed, they had <U+017F>uffered them<U+017F>elves to be in<U+017F>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from their own practice, that while they pointed their endeavours directly again<U+017F>t the <hi>Ablation, Revul<U+017F>ion, Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and <hi>precaution</hi> of <U+017F>ecundary <hi>Effects,</hi> viz. the <hi>Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> wept from the injured <hi>Archeus</hi> of the particular part: they at the <U+017F>ame time tacitely confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed, that they neither under<U+017F>tood their originals, nor <U+017F>et about the Cure of them, according to the ju<U+017F>t method of beginning at the remove
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114890:11"/>
of their <hi>primary Cau<U+017F>es.</hi> And they had farther di<U+017F>covered, that a medical Cour<U+017F>e of Diet, is but a wild, languid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid and indeed de<U+017F>perate kind of remedy; and <hi>Kitchen A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phori<U+017F>mes</hi> too contemptible a <hi>militia</hi> to encounter <U+017F>o formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable an Adver<U+017F>ary, already entered upon the borders of life, and ready to di<U+017F><U+017F>olve the <hi>di<U+017F>cordant Harmony</hi> of the whole Compo<U+017F>ition, by the generall diffu<U+017F>ion of its tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. No wonder therefore, if the Common people, ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the vanity of <U+017F>uch Cures, have taken occa<U+017F>ion to create this proverbe, <hi>The be<U+017F>t phy<U+017F>ick, is to take no phy<U+017F>ick.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p>More then once have I lamented, out of a deep Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>eration <note place="margin">12.</note> of the hard Condition of man, while I read over whole Centuries of the Councels of Phy<U+017F>icians, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Commentaries on the 9. <hi>Rha<U+017F>. ad Alman<U+017F>orem,</hi> where they run over all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the body, from the Crowne of the head to the <U+017F>ole of the foot; that digging into the Center of each di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e (as they believe and glory) and there exploring the Grandfather, or procatarctick Cau<U+017F>e thereof, they ever and anon lay the blame on <U+017F>ome one <hi><U+017F>ingular di<U+017F>temper,</hi> either naturall or acquired: but yet with <U+017F>uch a re<U+017F>erve of uncertainty, that they dare not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<U+017F>ely determine, whether they ought to account that <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temper</hi> for the <hi>di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e,</hi> or onely for the <hi>Antecedent Cau<U+017F>e</hi> of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, about which they Con<U+017F>ult. But to prevent mi<U+017F>take, and to be <U+017F>ure of the right, generally in all infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities they accu<U+017F>e both <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>cold.</hi> For example, in mo<U+017F>t, they cry out upon a <hi>Frigidity</hi> of the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> either <U+017F>olitary, or combined with an exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Liver;</hi> whence they foretell <hi>Catarrhs</hi> to be engendered, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies of tho<U+017F>e parts, upon which <U+017F>uch rheumes <U+017F>hall be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe: and this hint they pur<U+017F>ue unto the explora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the nature not onely of very many <hi>Internall,</hi> but al<U+017F>o of mo<U+017F>t <hi>Externall</hi> and Cutany defects. And with <U+017F>uch <hi>Theorical</hi> and <hi>Practical</hi> decretals do the <U+017F>chools <U+017F>ea<U+017F>on the brains of their Di<U+017F>ciples. For thus are infirmities of the eyes, ears jawes, tongue, teeth, che<U+017F>t, arms, loyns, and thighs, charged upon the account of Catarrhs. Thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114890:12"/>
have Coughs, Con<U+017F>umtions, difficulties of re<U+017F>piration, Pleuri<U+017F>ies, Inflammations of the Lungs, Apoplexies, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ies, <U+017F>uddain Deaths, Impo<U+017F>tumes, Spittings of blood, found their pedigrees deduced from Di<U+017F>tillations. Thus finally, is the <U+017F>tomack infe<U+017F>ted with Vomiting, Nau<U+017F>eou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e, dejection of Appetite, and debility of Concoction: as al<U+017F>o the Liver and Spleen become mi<U+017F>affected. For crude and indige<U+017F>tible Phlegme being dropped downe from the retort of the Head, Ob<U+017F>tructions, Hardne<U+017F><U+017F>es, Drop<U+017F>ies, Apo<U+017F>tems, Schirrous tumors, Fevers, torments of the bowels, &amp;c. are li<U+017F>ted under the conduct of Catarrhs.</p>
               <p>To which Epidemick tradition of Catarrhs, <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us,</hi> though otherwi<U+017F>e above mode<U+017F>ty triumphing in his inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">13.</note> of <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the 3 fir<U+017F>t <hi>Hypo<U+017F>taticall Principles,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Princ pia Hypo<U+017F>tatic a <hi><U+017F>unt, quae majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri v<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ac effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia prae reliquis pollent; unde in Schola Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticaCheironia virilia, virtuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a dicuntur, <U+017F>unt<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> Sulphur, Mercurius, <hi>&amp;</hi> Sal. Sal <hi>e<U+017F>t prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipium hypo<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum, cum vi fermentandi &amp; coagulandi. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus <U+017F>ignatura e<U+017F>t, ut intrin<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus <U+017F>it fu<U+017F>il<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, metallorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tar &amp; fixus: ex trin<U+017F>ecus autem combu<U+017F>tibilis et incinerabilis.</hi> Sulphur <hi>principium e<U+017F>t hypo<U+017F>taticum, cum vi maturandi, tingendi, homogenea attrahendi, heterogenea repellendi, tendendi a centro ad circumferentiam, &amp; vici<U+017F><U+017F>im. Hujus <U+017F>ignatura e<U+017F>t, ut intra <U+017F>it fixum, oleagino<U+017F>um <U+017F>ive pingue: extra inflammabile e<U+017F><U+017F>e &amp; fugitivum.</hi> Flamma quippe <hi>e<U+017F>t</hi> Sulphur volatile. Mercurius <hi>e<U+017F>t principium hypo<U+017F>taticum, cum vi vegetativa et in<U+017F>taurativa. Hujus <U+017F>ignatura interna e<U+017F>t <U+017F>overe ignem potentem: externa vero e<U+017F>t liquidum, glutino<U+017F>um, incombu<U+017F>tibile &amp; frigidum e<U+017F><U+017F>e.</hi> Joh. Raicus tract. de podagra.</note> doth <note place="margin">14.</note> frequently <U+017F>ub<U+017F>cribe, and alwayes openly acknowledge the name of Defluxion <hi>(flu<U+017F><U+017F>en)</hi> <U+017F>taggering into <U+017F>elf-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, under the drunken guidance of that great Lady, <hi>Incertitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this fabulous <U+017F>cene of Defluxions, which indeed is very well worth our <U+017F>erious tears, do the Schools <U+017F>o poli<U+017F>h and trim up, and deliver from hand to hand down to po<U+017F>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; that it now dares plead pre<U+017F>cription, and u<U+017F>urpe the <U+017F>acred dignity of truth: yea common Idiots, by their own infirmities made <hi>pa<U+017F><U+017F>ive Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> tire my ears with a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lecture of their Catarrhs. Whereupon, <U+017F>ince it is a taske extremly difficult, and <U+017F>uch as my Genius abhorrs, to root out a cu<U+017F>tomary doctrine from the minds of men unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with more rationall wayes of learning, and in the place thereof, implant the <U+017F>eeds of <U+017F>olid truth; chiefly when vulgar heads are of that temper, that, like new ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114890:12"/>
hardly part with that odour, wherewith they were fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>oned: it is my cu<U+017F>tome, even among per<U+017F>ons of honour, to affect <U+017F>ilence, not to preach upon the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, or its Cau<U+017F>es, <U+017F>everal kinds, and remedies; but quietly concealing my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<U+017F>tation of the ea<U+017F>ie theory of the Schools, and di<U+017F><U+017F>embling an ignorance of all, go away as con<U+017F>enting to whatever hath been <U+017F>aid. Yet, in <U+017F>ome places, I adventure to leave a hint, that I am otherwi<U+017F>e in<U+017F>tructed, that Fools are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tellated to a capacity of medicinal Principles, nor my <U+017F>elfe to be their Paedagog. At be<U+017F>t, I cannot but admire, that no man hath hitherto, after <U+017F>o long a revolution of time, ever di<U+017F>covered, and made animadver<U+017F>ions on the palpable and <U+017F>uperlative ignorance of Phy<U+017F>icians: but that the grey-haired dreams of the Grecians have drawne the whole Chri<U+017F>tian World after them, into a <U+017F>ervitude. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vocabulum hic ab authore u<U+017F>urpatum, e<U+017F>t</hi> Latria; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>autem exprimit nedum</hi> cultum divinum, <hi>quo <U+017F>en<U+017F>u legitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Job. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. cap.</hi> 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>a<U+017F>t etiam</hi> <U+017F>ervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem, <hi><U+017F>uxta illud Sophoc. in Ajace,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>&amp; illud prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium Phocylid.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>tempori <U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vire.</hi>
                  </note> that is ridiculous, lying, and pernicious to humane <U+017F>ociety. To particular; they generally conclude that the head from whence their <hi>Nilus</hi> of <hi>Defluxions</hi> doth originally <U+017F>pring, is a <hi>Cold Di<U+017F>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> and an <hi>hot di<U+017F>temper</hi> of the <hi>Liver:</hi> and that the greate<U+017F>t part of mankinde is in <U+017F>ubjection to this tyranny. The manner of its generation they deliver thus; <hi>That the <U+017F>tomack, ince<U+017F><U+017F>antly, during the whole act of Concoction, receiving an acce<U+017F><U+017F>e of immoderate heat from the Liver, mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, all that while, <U+017F>end up whole clouds of vapours into the braine: and that by rea<U+017F>on the brain is, by its native temperament Cold, and <U+017F>et, like a cover over a boyling pot, or the head of an Alembick, in the highe<U+017F>t region of the body; all tho<U+017F>e vapours that a<U+017F>cend into it, are againe conden<U+017F>ed into Water; Which, <U+017F>ince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the propen<U+017F>ity of its nature, it mu<U+017F>t tend downwards, doth afford an ample <U+017F>ource to di<U+017F>tillations, and a generall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance to mo<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. That if this torrent fall down upon the eyes, ears, palate, teeth, &amp;c. tho<U+017F>e parts have very good rea<U+017F>on to bewaile, and with plenty of rheume lament their unkinde de<U+017F>tiny, in being <U+017F>o neer neighbours unto, and lying within reach of this tyrant, the Brain: but if upon the Lungs, it is quickly the inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">15.</note> 
                  <hi>occa<U+017F>ion of Coughs, Difficulties of re<U+017F>piration, and in fine of Con<U+017F>umtions, of palpitations or tremblings of the heart, and <U+017F>o of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114890:13"/>
immature death. But if the <U+017F>tream be turned upon the <U+017F>tomack, then doth the <U+017F>tomack <U+017F>uffer the ju<U+017F>t puni<U+017F>hment of its former di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temper, by admitting debility of Concoction, Crudities, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, Orexies</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>cibi appetentia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie dicitur; quo <U+017F>en<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u et</hi> Juvenal. <hi>u<U+017F>urpavit pro vehementi eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di aviditate, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidam facturus orexim.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>or in<U+017F>atiate Appetites, Swounings, fainting Pains of the mouth of the <U+017F>tomack, Ob<U+017F>tructions, Laskes, durable Fluxes of the belly, violent ejections of Choler upward and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, fits of the Colick, Atrophies, or univer<U+017F>all leane<U+017F><U+017F>e from decay of Nutrition, Drop<U+017F>ies, Schirrous tumors, and all other defects of the in<U+017F>truments officiall to common Dige<U+017F>tion: yea Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Putrefactions of the blood in the veins, as al<U+017F>o <U+017F>tones of the Spleen,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Calculi <hi>enim quando<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ene reperiuntur, materiâ hac</hi> tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tareâ <hi>longa die in e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dem coacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatâ, &amp; ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne interni &amp;</hi> nativi coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pij, <hi>in lapideam induratâ duriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em. Hi autem ante mortens vix deprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur, et me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinam <U+017F>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Kidneys, and Bladder, have their ordinary materials from the <U+017F>lime of this Defluxion. That if the<U+017F>e rivulets creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inmo<U+017F>t clo<U+017F>ets of the brain, then <U+017F>uddain death, Apoplexies, and Pal<U+017F>ies immediately en<U+017F>ue: but if in the hinder part of the head, by the neck they chanee to wander into the Nerves, Arteries, and Mu<U+017F>cles, then mu<U+017F>t Gouts, Pal<U+017F>ies, Pleure<U+017F>ies, and Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions of the receiving parts, unavoidably be introduced: yea all Chirurgicall defects, as Pains, Apo<U+017F>tems, and the numerous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers, do they father upon Catarrhs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That if this deluge be not evacuated and dreigned by <U+017F>ome of the forementioned <U+017F>luices, but becomes a <U+017F>tanding pond, from who<U+017F>e oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion the brain is not able to deliver it <U+017F>elf, neither by the Aquaeducts of the no<U+017F>trils, nor the laborious pump of Coughs: Oh! then in<U+017F>tantly follows, a <U+017F>tupid drou<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e, an inexpugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble propen<U+017F>ity to out <U+017F>leep Endymion,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>remitte ocu'os ad pag.</hi> 68. în tract. de mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netica vulner. curat. <hi>&amp; ibi fu<U+017F>è explicatum invenies, quid apud medicos de<U+017F>ignatur per</hi> Catochen.</note> 
                  <hi>Catoches, a Lethargy, Verti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, Apoplexy, lo<U+017F><U+017F>e of Memory, and perdition of Sences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For be<U+017F>ides the<U+017F>e forementioned <hi>di<U+017F>tempers</hi> of <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Cold,</hi> and <hi>Defluxions</hi> nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily re<U+017F>ulting from thence; the Books, Orations, Councels, Conver<U+017F>ations, Chairs and Practices of Phy<U+017F>icians <U+017F>ound of nothing: and <U+017F>o the whole bulk of the <hi>Art of healing,</hi> <U+017F>eems, now a dayes, to be moved upon the <U+017F>lender hinges of <hi>Purgations, Phlebotomy, Scarifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Baths, Sweatings, Cauteries,</hi> and, in <U+017F>hort, upon no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the <hi>diminutions</hi> of <U+017F>trength, and emaciations of the body, or ex<U+017F>iccations of <hi>Rheumes.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To which end, they impo<U+017F>e upon their Patients, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions of the roots of <hi>China, Zarza,</hi> and the wood of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114890:13"/>
                  <hi>Sa<U+017F><U+017F>afras,</hi> brought from the <hi>Ea<U+017F>t-Indies,</hi> upon de<U+017F>igne of drying up the luxuriant moy<U+017F>ture of the brain: for the mo<U+017F>t part mea<U+017F>uring the extent of the <hi>Pharmaceuticall</hi> and <hi>Diateticall Theory,</hi> by the rule of <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Cold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by this means, they never relea<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ick out of their hands: but perpetually oblige them, like purcha<U+017F>ed <note place="margin">17.</note> 
                  <hi>Bond<U+017F>laves,</hi> to the irk<U+017F>ome ob<U+017F>ervance of their Precepts; though with manife<U+017F>t de<U+017F>pair. In regard, while Phy<U+017F>icians remain ignorant of the fundamentals and <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, and by the light of their own un<U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sfulne<U+017F><U+017F>e read the vanity of their <hi>Operations,</hi> they mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>tand convicted of the impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of the <hi>Sanation:</hi> upon this ground, that the naturall <hi>Frigidity</hi> of the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> doth <hi>Antipractically,</hi> or by Counter violence, impugne the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Liver;</hi> and <U+017F>o tho<U+017F>e remedies which would be <hi>beneficiall</hi> to the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> mu<U+017F>t prove <hi>offen<U+017F>ive</hi> and dangerous to the <hi>Liver,</hi> and <U+017F>o tran<U+017F>po<U+017F>itively.</p>
               <p>All which impo<U+017F>tures, <U+017F>ince they con<U+017F>pire to the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the race of <hi>Adam,</hi> to the de<U+017F>olation of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, <note place="margin">18.</note> and utter oblivion of familyes; I could not but think it my duty (what in me lay) wholly to <U+017F>ubvert and di<U+017F>mantle this ex<U+017F>ecrable here<U+017F>ie of medical Doctrine: and <U+017F>o much the more compul<U+017F>ion had I upon my con<U+017F>cience to attempt it, in con<U+017F>ideration that this Pe<U+017F>tilence hath po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed the heads of our <hi>Europeans,</hi> ever <U+017F>ince the dayes of <hi>Galen,</hi> untill now. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Proprio dida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctro, inquit</hi> Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montius; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>enim <U+017F>onat idem, quod</hi> minerval <hi>latine, five prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium doctrinae.</hi>
                  </note> For <hi>rich</hi> men learn this Doctrine from the co<U+017F>tly dictates of their <hi>Pur<U+017F>es,</hi> and what they have learnt, they <U+017F>oon communicate to others: and thus all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es have their <U+017F>tories written in the mon<U+017F>trous Romance of <hi>Defluxions.</hi> Again<U+017F>t which I <U+017F>hall declare, by <hi>Po<U+017F>itions</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Schools. ¶</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi><U+017F>tomack</hi> of man, during life, is actually <hi>Warme,</hi> and its interior membrane or Coate bedewed with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <note place="margin">19.</note> 
                  <hi>moy<U+017F>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible it is, that any <hi>aquous humidity</hi> <U+017F>hould be actually <U+017F>eething in the body, and not at the <U+017F>ame time <U+017F>end forth plenty of <hi>Vapours</hi> from it <U+017F>elf.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114890:14"/>
3. The <U+017F>uperiour way from the <U+017F>tomack, is the <hi>Gullet,</hi> or <hi>oe<U+017F>ophagus,</hi> being a membrane round long and hollow, as a Pipe or Cane, extended from the <U+017F>tomack even up unto the jawes, and in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance the <U+017F>ame with the interior Coate of the <U+017F>tomack.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Gullet, by the privilege of its native con<U+017F>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is ever actually <hi>moy<U+017F>t,</hi> and con<U+017F>tantly (except at times of <U+017F>wallowing) actually <hi><U+017F>hut</hi> (otherwi<U+017F>e, di<U+017F>torted in avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> it would laterally fall together, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwi<U+017F>e then a bladder that wants <U+017F>ome gue<U+017F>t to fill its Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity:) and the <U+017F>ides thereof mutually meet and touch each the other, by the compul<U+017F>ion of that nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of Nature, which forbids a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>acuity.</hi> For the Gullet containg in it, neither meat, drink, nor aer, would of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity be empty, <U+017F>hould it remain open. But that it is not open, is evident from this, that otherwi<U+017F>e, at the <U+017F>wallowing downe of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mor<U+017F>ell of our Diet the Aer, which would be beneath the mor<U+017F>ell, and oppo<U+017F>e the de<U+017F>cent thereof, were the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ell proportionate in gravity to the <hi>renitency</hi> of the <hi>Aer,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be rammed downe into the cavity of the <U+017F>tomack; and <U+017F>o there mu<U+017F>t follow for every mor<U+017F>ell <U+017F>wallowed a <hi>Belch,</hi> or redi<U+017F>charge of that aer, by the <U+017F>uperior outlet of the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack. Finally, <U+017F>ince the membrane of this Gullet is always moy<U+017F>t, the <U+017F>ides thereof would of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity fall together, if not di<U+017F>tended by <U+017F>ome force: which is never ob<U+017F>erved in the di<U+017F><U+017F>ections of <hi>dead,</hi> nor could be of any u<U+017F>e in <hi>living bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The mouth of the <U+017F>tomack is <U+017F>hut up by a <hi>Natural</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not by a <hi>Voluntary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. And <hi>Anatomy</hi> affords no other knowledge of the Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, more then that it is narrow, lockt up beneath by the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorus</hi> or inferior orifice of the <U+017F>tomack, and in the neck of man on all <U+017F>ides compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed by very many ve<U+017F><U+017F>els circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Gullet</hi> neither <U+017F>ucks in, nor containes any Aer: for by rea<U+017F>on of its proper motion, naturall to it as a moy<U+017F>t membrane, and want of any body to di<U+017F>tend it from within, it falls together on all <U+017F>ides.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114890:14"/>
8. The <hi>Gullet</hi> is not opened longwayes, but during the de<U+017F>cent of Aliment. Which if very dry, makes a <U+017F>tand in the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, nor ea<U+017F>ily de<U+017F>cends, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e driven down by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor <U+017F>uperadded: which could not be, if the <hi>Gullet</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aer beneath the mor<U+017F>ell, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e there followed a <hi>Belch</hi> upon the deglutition of each mor<U+017F>ell. Yet the top of the <hi>Gullet,</hi> about the <hi>Larinx</hi> or head of the wind-pipe, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly open.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The lower end of the Gullet is contracted by an aliene power, and is therefore never opened but by the violence of <U+017F>ome aliment or other tenent, either entering into, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pul<U+017F>ed from the <U+017F>tomack: Or upon the knocking of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> it may be unlocked by a <hi><U+017F>trange key,</hi> i. e. not by its own motion, <U+017F>ince the <hi>humidity</hi> of its <U+017F>ides naturally di<U+017F>po<U+017F>eth them to <hi>Concidence,</hi> or falling together.</p>
               <p n="10">10. No <hi>Aer,</hi> and much le<U+017F><U+017F>e <hi>Vapour,</hi> ari<U+017F>eth out of the <U+017F>tomack, and a<U+017F>cends, without giving the loud report of a <hi>Belch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Though that heat, which is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to the <U+017F>tomack, immediately cau<U+017F>eth the exhalation of vapours: yet it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not, that the <U+017F>ame heat <U+017F>hould protrude tho<U+017F>e vapours upward, with <U+017F>o great violence as is required to break open the dore of the <U+017F>tomack, being fa<U+017F>t lockt, and di<U+017F>tend the Gullet, <U+017F>ince any one of the<U+017F>e contradictory <hi>The<U+017F>es</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, it will be a genuine <hi>inference,</hi> that every man mu<U+017F>t be troubled with continuall belchings.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In the <U+017F>tomack, as in all other ve<U+017F><U+017F>els moderately hot, every watery vapour doth <U+017F>ooner, upon the le<U+017F>t compre<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, return to its primitive con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, and unite again in drops; then to be of power <U+017F>ufficient to elevate and di<U+017F>tend a clo<U+017F>ely compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed membrane of con<U+017F>iderable magnitude. Where we ob<U+017F>erve, by the by, That <hi>Vapours are not the Cau<U+017F>e of Belchings:</hi> but onely the <hi>Gas <U+017F>ilve<U+017F>tre,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gas <hi>bifurca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ab</hi> Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montio <hi>no<U+017F>tro fabricatum inveni: primum <U+017F>cilicet</hi> Aquae, <hi><U+017F>ive</hi> Meteoron; <hi><U+017F>ecundum</hi> <U+017F>ylve<U+017F>tre. Ga. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teoron <hi>de<U+017F>ignat</hi> Aquam, <hi>in vaporem, per geniale aeris frigus (ubi omnia eo <U+017F>emel deducta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umuntur, &amp; in pri<U+017F>tinum aquae elementum retrocedunt) re<U+017F>olutam. Quinam vapor alterius <hi>utique <U+017F>ortis e<U+017F>t, quàm vapor per</hi> Calorem <hi><U+017F>u<U+017F>citatus: eo itaque re<U+017F>pectu, paradoxi licentia, in nominis magè convenientis ege<U+017F>tate, halitum illum</hi> Gas <hi>nominavit Author, non longe â</hi> Chao <hi>veterum <U+017F>ecretum.</hi> Gas <hi>autem</hi> <U+017F>ylve<U+017F>tre, <hi>e<U+017F>t <U+017F>piritus quidam naturae hominis planè ho<U+017F>tilis, atque á prunoribus nondum cognitus; qui nee va<U+017F>i<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cogi, nec in corpus vi<U+017F>ibile reduci, ni<U+017F>i extincto prius <U+017F>emine, pote<U+017F>t. Corpora enim continent hunc <U+017F>piritum, &amp; quandoque tota in eju<U+017F>modi forum halitum ab<U+017F>cedunt: non quidem quod actu in<U+017F>it ip<U+017F>is (<U+017F>iquidem detineri non po<U+017F><U+017F>et, imò totum concretum avolaret) <U+017F>ed e<U+017F>t <U+017F>piritus concretus, &amp; more corporis coagulatus, excitaturque acqui<U+017F>ito</hi> Fermento, <hi>ut in vino fermentante, omphacio, pane, hydromellite, itemque ruber ille ex Chry<U+017F>ulca operante eructatus: vel</hi> additamento peregrino, <hi>ut ex auro, adjecto <U+017F>ale Armeniaco: vel tandem per aliquam</hi> Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itionem Alterativam, <hi>qualis e<U+017F>t A<U+017F><U+017F>atio, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pectu pomi. Hujus autem ignoti ho<U+017F>pitis tum</hi> ortus, <hi>tum</hi> ho<U+017F>tilitatis <hi>atque implacabilli ferociae, quae nobis in<U+017F>idiatur capitaliter, exege<U+017F>i ulterius paulò inhaerendum: eâ poti<U+017F><U+017F>imum relatione, ut nedum</hi> Quidditas <hi>atque</hi> Nativitas <hi>hujus</hi> Gas <hi>innote<U+017F>cant ijs, quibus contigerit nondum omnia</hi> Helmontij <hi>my<U+017F>teria perlu<U+017F>trare; <U+017F>ed etiam ut i<U+017F>tud</hi> epitheton (<U+017F>ylve<U+017F>tre) <hi>non incongruenter illi appen<U+017F>um common<U+017F>tretur. Primò itaque quoad</hi> e<U+017F><U+017F>entiam <hi>ejus quidditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam; meditare, turpiter admodum e<U+017F><U+017F>e delu<U+017F>os qui credidêre</hi> Gas uvarum e<U+017F>t vini <U+017F>piritum <hi>in mu<U+017F>to.</hi> Gas <hi>enim uvarum &amp; mu<U+017F>ti, ex fermento ebullitionis concept<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> excitatum, e<U+017F>t tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in via ad vinum; non autem Vini, in <U+017F>uajam dignitate con<U+017F>tituti <U+017F>piritus. Intercedens enim inter utruneque</hi> Fermentalis Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>itio, <hi>rem praecedentem di<U+017F>ponit in <U+017F>ui tran<U+017F>mutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ut inde aliud</hi> ens <hi>fiat. Siquidem extra dubitationis aleam e<U+017F>t,</hi> omnem tran<U+017F>mutationem formalem prae<U+017F>upponere Fermentum corruptivum. <hi>Secundò, quoad</hi> Nativitatem Gas <hi>in uva; nota. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ua ill<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap><U+017F>a a<U+017F><U+017F>ervatur &amp; ex<U+017F>iccatur: <U+017F>i vero pellis ejus <U+017F>emel fuerit di<U+017F>rupta, &amp; vulnerata, illa mox fermentum ebullitionis concipit, hincque tran<U+017F>mutationis initium. Vina ergo <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>varum, pomorum, baccarum, mellis, itemque <U+017F>tores &amp; <U+017F>rondes <U+017F>emel di<U+017F>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta atque contu<U+017F>a, fermento arrepto, bullire ac ferve e incipiunt; unde</hi> Gas. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ltimò, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad ejus</hi> Malitiam <hi>ac feritatem attinet, oenopoli <U+017F>ciant, vinorum</hi> Gas, <hi><U+017F>i multa vi intra cados coerceatur, vina furio<U+017F>a, mala atque n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>civa reddere. Quapropter &amp; morbidum</hi> Gas, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vâ affatim come<U+017F>tâ, pluries aegritudines anxias c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncitavit. Siquidem</hi> Fermenti <hi><U+017F>piritus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuantur, &amp; cum dige<U+017F>tioni no<U+017F>trae <U+017F>int inobedientes, <U+017F>piritui Vitali <U+017F>e per vim a<U+017F><U+017F>ociant, imò <U+017F>i quid <U+017F>udore tenus excerni <U+017F>it paratum, id <U+017F>ua fermeati aciditate grume<U+017F>cunt, atque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ignes pariunt moleflias, tormina, diarrhaeas, dy<U+017F>enterias. Sed Etymi</hi> Gas <hi>explicationi <U+017F>atis <U+017F>uperque hactenus in<U+017F>udatum.</hi>
                  </note> or a certain <hi>Wilde <U+017F>pirit</hi> exhaling from <U+017F>ome aliment.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114890:15"/>
13. That granting a <hi>Natural <U+017F>pirit</hi> of the yet imperfect blood in the Liver, all the veins, by rea<U+017F>on of their con<U+017F>tant heat, would either about the parts of the Liver, or in their capillary branches, generate Catarrhs, which the Schools have baulked in their hunting of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. ¶</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusions">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114890:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Conclu<U+017F>ions erected on the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed Conce<U+017F><U+017F>ions.</hi> ¶</head>
               <p>FRom the<U+017F>e <hi>Po<U+017F>itions,</hi> confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed by generall <hi>Con<U+017F>ent,</hi> and demon<U+017F>trated by the ocular evidence of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally follows, in the fir<U+017F>t place</p>
               <p n="1">1. That no vapour can a<U+017F>cend from the <U+017F>tomack to the head; and the materiall Cau<U+017F>e of Catarrhs, vulgarly belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, mu<U+017F>t faile, and the very groundwork of the doctrine of Defluxions be demoli<U+017F>hed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <U+017F>o great a mi<U+017F>t of <hi>ignorance</hi> hath <U+017F>urrounded the world in things <hi>manife<U+017F>t</hi> and <hi>obvious</hi> to the ob<U+017F>ervation of <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e:</hi> what Cimmerian blindne<U+017F><U+017F>e may not be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected, in the common theory of <U+017F>uch things as lye more <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tru<U+017F>e,</hi> and therefore have their <hi>Cau<U+017F>alites</hi> onely di<U+017F>cernable by the opticks of the mo<U+017F>t acute <hi>Rea<U+017F>on?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That <U+017F>ubmitting our beliefe to the doctrine of the Schools, a <hi>healthy</hi> and <hi>hot <U+017F>tomack</hi> would generate more and greater <U+017F>howers of Catarrhs, then an <hi>unhealthy, weak</hi> and <hi>cold</hi> one; which is point blanck contratry to the opinion commonly embraced.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That, in order to the <hi>Cure of Defluxions,</hi> according to the con<U+017F>equence of their theory, we ought to endeavour the <hi>Refrigeration,</hi> rather then the <hi>Calefaction</hi> of the <U+017F>tomack.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That all men would of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity be equaly obnoxious to Catarrhs, and <U+017F>o continually infirme.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Upon this ground, that all men have their <hi>Gullet, Brain,</hi> and <hi>Stomack</hi> actually hot, equaly moy<U+017F>t, and con<U+017F>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <U+017F>ame <hi>Figure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That every man would naturally, like <U+017F>wine, belch at every <U+017F>tep he treads: <U+017F>ince the inde<U+017F>inent <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>moy<U+017F>ture</hi> mu<U+017F>t unavoydably tran<U+017F>mit continuall Clouds of vapours from the <U+017F>tomack.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That although we <U+017F>hould de<U+017F>cend to allow, that a vapour exhaled from the <U+017F>tomack might be of force <U+017F>uffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114890:16"/>
to di<U+017F>tend the Gullet; yea and be evaporated without ructation: yet would it remain of exceeding difficulty to infer an apprehen<U+017F>ion, that this vapour would not <U+017F>ooner be di<U+017F>charged by the annexed and open tubes of the mouth and no<U+017F>trils, then make a long and difficult progre<U+017F><U+017F>e up to the brain, by the narrow Meanders and blockt up avenews of a membrane. That this Vapour, <U+017F>teaming up from the furnace of the <U+017F>tomack, would nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily carry along with it a ful<U+017F>ome <hi>Hautgou<U+017F>t</hi> of the meat then <U+017F>uffering the act of Concoction, by the variety of ungratefull <hi>odours</hi> acquaint the no<U+017F>e with the un<U+017F>avoury <U+017F>tory of its various mutations, and be horridly offen<U+017F>ive both to our <U+017F>elves and company: and thus if all tho<U+017F>e frequent belches were thus <U+017F>trongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed by Corruption, our very <hi>breath</hi> al<U+017F>o, continually bla<U+017F>ted with them, would <U+017F>ave us the trouble of forreigne poy<U+017F>ons, di<U+017F>parage the fatall emi<U+017F>lions of the Ba<U+017F>ili<U+017F>ck, and be as dangerous to Conver<U+017F>ation, as the fumes of the <hi>Lago di Tripergola</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Avernus, Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, quo nullae aves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt, ob te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ejus odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem: propter quam graveo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam, etiam hîc de<U+017F>cen<U+017F>us ad inferos olim e<U+017F><U+017F>e credebatur. Gas <U+017F>ylve<U+017F>tre.</note> in Campania, or the <U+017F>ulphureous farts of our <hi>Grandmother,</hi> when delivered from the <hi>Colick,</hi> by the Cri<U+017F>is of an <hi>Earthquake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. That <U+017F>ince the <hi>Materiall cau<U+017F>e</hi> of belching is a nimble <hi>Wild <U+017F>pirit,</hi> ari<U+017F>ing for our <hi>Aliment,</hi> and far more <U+017F>ubtil then a <hi>vapour;</hi> but yet doth never invade the Brain, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e, upon <U+017F>hutting the mouth, it chance to advance to the forepart of the head, through the funnell of the palat, and be thence exploded by the no<U+017F>trils: a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly, much le<U+017F><U+017F>e can <hi>vapours,</hi> that are more gro<U+017F><U+017F>e and corporeal, a<U+017F>cend <U+017F>o high as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>inuate them<U+017F>elves into all the narrow creeks and intricate Cells of the brain.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That the<U+017F>e <hi>volatile</hi> and <hi>fugitive <U+017F>pirits,</hi> the cau<U+017F>ers of <hi>ructation,</hi> are never carried in a <hi>direct</hi> path, up to the region of the brain; but in an <hi>oblique,</hi> leading through the <hi>organ</hi> of <hi><U+017F>melling:</hi> and therefore they never afford an <hi>odour,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <U+017F>ubject to the perception of the <hi>odoratory nerves,</hi> but when the mouth is <U+017F>hut, at the in<U+017F>tant of their eruption; much le<U+017F><U+017F>e can a vapour from the <U+017F>tomack, by its own <U+017F>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous motion, arrive at the remote<U+017F>t clo<U+017F>ets of the brain.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114890:16"/>
11. That though we condi<U+017F>cend, that <hi>Vapours,</hi> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial cau<U+017F>e of <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> may in <U+017F>ome degree ari<U+017F>e up to the head, at lea<U+017F>t to the organ of <U+017F>melling: yet can we not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that this can happen, but when the mouth is <U+017F>hut; and <U+017F>o whoever gapeth, can never be infected with <hi>Defluxions,</hi> and by inference, to keep the mouth open, at the time of ructation, is a mo<U+017F>t ea<U+017F>ie and infallible precaution of the generation of rheums.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That <U+017F>ince two bodies cannot <U+017F>o far rebell again<U+017F>t the con<U+017F>erving <hi>Laws of Nature,</hi> as mutually to penetrate each the others dimen<U+017F>ions, in one and the <U+017F>ame place; and <U+017F>ince the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age from the jawes up into the brain is exceeding narrow, oppleted (for there is no <hi>vacuity</hi> in tho<U+017F>e organs) barrocadoed above and <U+017F>o impervious (for our very breath, though violently compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed by <U+017F>topping of the mouth and no<U+017F>trils, cannot force open a way into the ca<U+017F>tle of the brain:) therefore cannot a vapour, ari<U+017F>ing from the <U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, approach the <hi>ba<U+017F>is</hi> of the brain. By example, a <hi>Cane</hi> or hollow <hi>Tube,</hi> that is clo<U+017F>ely luted in the upper orifice, held in an erect po<U+017F>ition over a <U+017F>team of hot vapours, doth not admit them to a<U+017F>cend through its perforation, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on of the Aer, wherewith it was before po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Granting, that a vapour may clime upwards; yet would it not meet with any <hi>Plane</hi> or <hi>Concave,</hi> upon which it might, by <hi>Conden<U+017F>ation,</hi> be reunited into drops: and much le<U+017F><U+017F>e any part of <U+017F>uch figure, which re<U+017F>embleth the head of an <hi>Alembick,</hi> or <hi>Pot-lid.</hi> But in the <hi>ba<U+017F>is</hi> of the brain, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we gratis allow a vapour to a<U+017F>cend, is a narrow place, called the <hi>Pelvis,</hi> or <hi>brain tunnell;</hi> which <U+017F>endeth two <U+017F>mall <hi>tubes,</hi> or outlets, toward the <hi>no<U+017F>trils,</hi> and as many back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward toward the <hi>neck.</hi> Which two <hi>po<U+017F>terior cavities</hi> onely could the a<U+017F>cendent vapour in<U+017F>inuate it <U+017F>elf into; and tho<U+017F>e two are ever repleted with a <hi>muccous</hi> or vi<U+017F>cid <hi>excrement,</hi> and perpetually, by a kind of guttulous di<U+017F>tillation, di<U+017F>charge it down into the <hi>Palat,</hi> as the proper <hi>Emunctories</hi> or dreignes of the brain, de<U+017F>tined to the evacuation of the <U+017F>limy redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant humors. And therefore albeit we concede, that a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114890:17"/>
can a<U+017F>cend <U+017F>o high: yet neverthele<U+017F><U+017F>e can we find no <hi>place</hi> for the <hi>Concretion</hi> of a <hi>Catarrh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Should a vapour, if the exhalation of any <U+017F>uch from the <U+017F>tomack be po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, a<U+017F>cend <U+017F>o high as this <U+017F>lender <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> of the brain; yea <U+017F>hould it, in <U+017F>o <U+017F>mall a place, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<U+017F>ed into <hi>rheume,</hi> and that rheume drop downe again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Muccus,</hi> or indigenary excrement: yet would it prove of much le<U+017F><U+017F>e offence or danger, then that <hi>muccus,</hi> the ordinary excrement of the brain. All which the <hi>Shools</hi> them<U+017F>elves have by <hi>Anatomy</hi> di<U+017F>covered, and may (pleas them to <U+017F>uffer the ea<U+017F>ie trouble of a <U+017F>erious pen<U+017F>itati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly know to be inevitable: but, alas! they have eyes, and <U+017F>ee not; they have ears, and, we may ju<U+017F>tly feare, they will not hear.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That although the <hi>materiall Cau<U+017F>e</hi> of <hi>Ructation</hi> be the <hi>Gas</hi> of our aliment, and impregnated with the particular <hi>odour</hi> thereof: yet the <hi>vapour</hi> of any meat whatever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into no other, then an <hi>in<U+017F>ipid</hi> and <hi>harmle<U+017F><U+017F>e Water.</hi> By example, let any <U+017F>limy juice, or <U+017F>pitle be artificially di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tilled, in any ve<U+017F><U+017F>el, by a mo<U+017F>t gentle heat, exactly propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the <U+017F>ame degree, which is in the <U+017F>tomack of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man: yet, undoubtedly, <U+017F>hall you draw off nothing, but an <hi>in<U+017F>ipid</hi> and <hi>thin Water,</hi> wholly devoyd of the lea<U+017F>t glutino<U+017F>ity; and le<U+017F><U+017F>e any <hi><U+017F>alt, acid,</hi> or <hi><U+017F>harp Catarrh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. That albeit the <hi>muccus,</hi> or phlegmatick excrement of the brain, fall down upon the jawes, and frequently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth various mi<U+017F>affections upon them, according to its various indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>itions or deflexions from its naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>titution: yet neither the <hi>matter,</hi> nor <hi>defluxion</hi> thereof can endure the rea<U+017F>on of a <hi>Catarrh;</hi> no more then the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine,</hi> drop by drop trickling down from the kidneys into the bladder, ought to be e<U+017F>teemed a <hi>Catarrh.</hi> Wherefore, if this <hi>muccus,</hi> whether <hi>in<U+017F>ipid, <U+017F>alt</hi> or <hi><U+017F>harp,</hi> whether <hi>fluid</hi> or <hi>thick,</hi> drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping down upon tho<U+017F>e parts, which, as peculiar <hi>Emunoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> are naturally ordained to the evacuation of it, may not be accounted a <hi>Catarrh,</hi> however evil <hi>Accidents</hi> it impre<U+017F><U+017F>e upon tho<U+017F>e parts; <U+017F>o neither the <hi>urine,</hi> though it deprave the integrity of the bladder.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114890:17"/>
17. How much le<U+017F><U+017F>e ought the defluxion of any <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>humor,</hi> or imaginary <hi>excrement,</hi> who<U+017F>e <hi>nativity</hi> and <hi>tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> are delivered to be by a <hi>manner, means, places,</hi> and <hi>voyages,</hi> naturally impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, to be accounted a <hi>Catarrh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. If the Brain, while it enjoyeth the influence and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiation of <hi>vital heat,</hi> be not actually <hi>cold:</hi> without doubt, the rea<U+017F>on of the <hi>Conden<U+017F>ation</hi> of <hi>vapours</hi> into <hi>rheume,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>taggered into an impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibility. But if it be, by <U+017F>ome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, <hi>le<U+017F><U+017F>e hot</hi> then the other parts of the body: mu<U+017F>t we then be driven upon this ab<U+017F>urdity, that a vapour doth, as if endowed with <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e</hi> and an arbitrary power of <hi>Election,</hi> enquire out and pitch upon the colde<U+017F>t part, as mo<U+017F>t accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate to its future reduction into a humor? becau<U+017F>e, by the dictates of naturall propen<U+017F>ity, it rather de<U+017F>ires by <hi>coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> to be <hi>returned</hi> into its <hi>primitive,</hi> then by <hi>re<U+017F>olution</hi> to <hi>continue</hi> in the <hi>pre<U+017F>en<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> condition?</p>
               <p n="19">19. Or is it driven on by the crowd of other vapours, and on all <U+017F>ides recoyled from the <hi>hotter parts</hi> of the body, up to the <hi>brain,</hi> as to the <hi>colde<U+017F>t?</hi> if <U+017F>o, there would be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall tempe<U+017F>t in the <U+017F>ounde<U+017F>t bodies, and nought but <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panto Gu<U+017F>ts,</hi> and Catarrhs in the be<U+017F>t temperd heads: which to believe, is a madne<U+017F><U+017F>e beyond the power of Hellebor, and a dotage too ab<U+017F>urd to be excu<U+017F>ed by the large<U+017F>t candor. ¶</p>
               <p n="20">20. But laying a<U+017F>ide the<U+017F>e <hi>Po<U+017F>itions</hi> (which can, upon no nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of nature, be verified) as worthy onely a <U+017F>hort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation; we come now to prove, that <U+017F>hould all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the <U+017F>chools, hitherto mentioned, be freely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them: yet could they be of no advantage, as to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nife<U+017F>tation of the <hi>Cardinal</hi> point in controver<U+017F>ie, viz. the manner, rea<U+017F>ons, and wayes of the <hi>Defluxion of Catarrhs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. For fir<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e rivulets of rheume cannot make their progre<U+017F><U+017F>e to the <hi>outward</hi> parts of the head, betwixt the <hi>skull</hi> and <hi>skin:</hi> <U+017F>ince, indeed the Schools them<U+017F>elves declare, that <hi>Vapours,</hi> the <hi>Antecedent matter</hi> of <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> do mount up from the Stomack to the <hi>Ba<U+017F>is,</hi> or lowe<U+017F>t part of the brain, and there fix upon a <hi>Plane</hi> (imaginary, nor ever yet di<U+017F>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by any Anatomi<U+017F>t) in who<U+017F>e lower <U+017F>uperficies they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114890:18"/>
in<U+017F>tantly enterprize <hi>conden<U+017F>ation,</hi> and then, immediately after concretion, be rained down, like a malignant mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, upon the members <U+017F>ubjacent. Far di<U+017F>tant, in <U+017F>ober truth, from this, that this forreigne adver<U+017F>ary, this meer excrement, an ob<U+017F>cure alien to the brain, and <U+017F>ole occa<U+017F>ion of <U+017F>o many and incorrigible infirmities, having in the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t <hi>Plane</hi> of the brain transformed it <U+017F>elf into <hi>Water;</hi> <U+017F>hould thence either penetrate through the very <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the brain, in the gro<U+017F><U+017F>e di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e of <hi>Water:</hi> or at length return again to inve<U+017F>t it <U+017F>elf in the thinner dre<U+017F><U+017F>e of a vapour, and wantonly take up quarters in the forementioned <hi>Plane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. Not in the form of a vapour; for if a vapour flying up from the <U+017F>tomack, arive at the bottome of the brain, and by the native <hi>cold</hi> of that part be <hi>concreted</hi> (as they <U+017F>ay) into <hi>Water:</hi> beyond all di<U+017F>pute, by rea<U+017F>on of the <U+017F>ame opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>cold,</hi> it will continue <hi>Water,</hi> nor ever in that place be reduced back into a <hi>vapour</hi> again; untill <hi>Nature</hi> her <U+017F>elf run mad, and fall upon contradictory operations, <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>hall out do the confu<U+017F>ion of her primitive <hi>Chaos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. If therefore, this Vapour be once changed into Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by the inevitable activity of local Cold, it is too hard for the mo<U+017F>t incircum<U+017F>pect credulity to be per<U+017F>waded, that this <hi>Water,</hi> of knowne ho<U+017F>tility again<U+017F>t the native oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the head, <U+017F>hould be kindly invited, nay gredily drawne into the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>ecret and otherwi<U+017F>e inacce<U+017F><U+017F>ible clo<U+017F>ets thereof: much le<U+017F><U+017F>e that it can attaine <U+017F>o great thinne<U+017F><U+017F>e and <hi><U+017F>ubtility,</hi> as, notwith<U+017F>tanding the re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance and compre<U+017F><U+017F>ive endeavours of non admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion made by the parts invaded, to pierce through the very body of the <hi>Brain,</hi> its <hi>Membranes, Sutures, Skull,</hi> and <hi>Perio<U+017F>tion,</hi> or coate environing the skull; then <U+017F>top at the weaker counter<U+017F>carfe of the <hi>skin,</hi> and there begin its <hi>defluxion.</hi> And, be<U+017F>ide many other inevitable ab<U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, this Water can be at mo<U+017F>t but a kinde of <hi>Rain-water;</hi> and therefore wholly unfit to be made a <U+017F>ource of <hi>vi<U+017F>cid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhs,</hi> who<U+017F>e duration depends on their <hi>glutino<U+017F>ity:</hi> yea Catarrhs ari<U+017F>ing from this aqueous originall, would, upon the fir<U+017F>t acce<U+017F><U+017F>e of heat, vani<U+017F>h by tran<U+017F>piration, <U+017F>ooner then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114890:18"/>
the thinne<U+017F>t <U+017F>weat; unle<U+017F><U+017F>e the <hi>Galeni<U+017F>ts</hi> can <U+017F>hew, how wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made of vapours exhaled from the <U+017F>tomack, doth for ever after become <hi>fixed;</hi> as al<U+017F>o, that by touching onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a certain <hi>Plane</hi> (which the di<U+017F><U+017F>ecting knife hath never yet lighted upon) in the head, it doth acquire a <hi><U+017F>alt</hi> and <hi><U+017F>harp</hi> tincture. Again, the <hi>skin</hi> <U+017F>urrounding the skull, being far more <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>porous</hi> then the skull (through which it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e, by <hi>tran<U+017F>udation)</hi> mu<U+017F>t, according to the rules of probability, give way to the extermination of this water, either by in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible <hi>tran<U+017F>piration,</hi> or by <hi><U+017F>weat,</hi> much <U+017F>ooner, then impri<U+017F>on it <U+017F>o clo<U+017F>ely, as to force it, by <U+017F>eek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other vents, to introduce tho<U+017F>e various maladies vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly imputed thereunto. To which we may adde, that the skin obtended upon the skull, doth mo<U+017F>t clo<U+017F>ely and <hi>tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciou<U+017F>ly</hi> adhere unto it; nor can the <U+017F>ingle <hi>declivity</hi> of the place <U+017F>uffice to the <hi>diffu<U+017F>ion</hi> of the rheume, and the violent <hi>avul<U+017F>ion</hi> of the skin from the bone. Moreover this Water, generated of vapours <U+017F>teaming from the <U+017F>tomack, ought, of unexcu<U+017F>able nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, to have <U+017F>ome internall <hi>Pul<U+017F>or,</hi> or <hi>Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> to ram it through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the brain, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, skull, and perio<U+017F>tion. But this <hi>driver</hi> mu<U+017F>t not be <hi>heat;</hi> for then would it cea<U+017F>e to be Water, and in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, re-a<U+017F><U+017F>ume the con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of a vapour: which is wildly imagined to be conden<U+017F>ed into water, by the frigidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the brain. Further, Catarrhs are ob<U+017F>erved to be mo<U+017F>t frequent in <hi>old</hi> and infirm bodies, and Climates mo<U+017F>t infected with <hi>Cold:</hi> Wherefore this <hi>driver,</hi> in all probability, mu<U+017F>t be <hi>Cold,</hi> (which <U+017F>ober Philo<U+017F>ophy affirmes to cau<U+017F>e a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>triction</hi> and fa<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e in the parts) who<U+017F>e bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude this water through the brain, and in <U+017F>ooth in the gro<U+017F><U+017F>e form of Water; contrary to the ordinary energy of naturall qualities. And this impul<U+017F>ive force mu<U+017F>t be either in the <hi>Water,</hi> bred of meer vapours fuming from the <U+017F>tomack; or in the <hi>brain,</hi> by which it is compelled, together with its membranes and skull, to open at the advent of this Water. Finally, <U+017F>ince this kind of rain-water, made out of conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed vapours, is conceived to hang in pendulous manner on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114890:19"/>
the Iowe<U+017F>t <U+017F>uperficies of the ba<U+017F>is of the brain; nor can be there deteined in any quantity above a drop or twain, at mo<U+017F>t (for the narrowne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the Cavity forbids the admi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion of more) it mu<U+017F>t nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily, either immediately fall downward in <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drops: or the brain mu<U+017F>t con<U+017F>tantly play the <U+017F>pung, and <hi>imhibe</hi> it drop after drop, <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t as it is conden<U+017F>ed. Moreover, this excrementitious Water ought to have, be<U+017F>ides the forementioned <hi>Driver,</hi> a <hi>Conductor,</hi> which may di<U+017F>tend the skin, and in order to the generation of the Pleuri<U+017F>ie cau<U+017F>e an avul<U+017F>ion of the membrane lining the che<U+017F>t from the ribs, as an Harbinger to prepare a lodging for it: and as well this Conductor, as Driver, ought to be of far more power then our own indigenary <hi>Bla<U+017F>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. I <U+017F>hall at length expo<U+017F>e at any rate, to common <U+017F>ale, the<U+017F>e impo<U+017F>tures and delu<U+017F>ive dreams of the Schools: that no man may<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> the vizard of vulgar credulity being at the <U+017F>ame time detected, longer <U+017F>uffer by the unfortunate purcha<U+017F>e of fal<U+017F>e wares. Nor could I hitherto <U+017F>ufficiently admire, how the world could be <U+017F>o gro<U+017F><U+017F>ely cincumvented by the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Catarrhs:</hi> in a bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e, I <U+017F>ay, <U+017F>o fooli<U+017F>h, vain, and altogether impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, that <hi>men,</hi> the Charter of who<U+017F>e Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth entitle them to <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> <U+017F>hould thus pro<U+017F>titute their credultities to a Legend of <hi>Ab<U+017F>urdities,</hi> nay ab<U+017F>olute <hi>Impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibilities,</hi> and forfeit the dignity of their tran<U+017F>cendent endowment upon the <U+017F>ingle <U+017F>eduction of onely one idle fault, namely <hi>Ignorance.</hi> That they upon their lazy and indirect di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions, not finding any Cau<U+017F>e, on which to charge their large account of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, have impo<U+017F>ed upon the implicite beliefe of vulgar heads, drowned in a deluge of <U+017F>tupidity, the<U+017F>e ridiculous fictions of Catarrhs.</p>
               <p n="25">25. But the <hi><U+017F>weat,</hi> at lea<U+017F>t, is impregnated with a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t <hi><U+017F>altne<U+017F><U+017F>e;</hi> upon which hint, the <note n="*" place="margin">Latex, <hi>apud</hi> Helmontium, <hi>qui</hi> humorum quaternarium <hi>adnihilare peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>s contendit, e<U+017F>t idem aquo us li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, quem <U+017F>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guini ubique per omne veno<U+017F>um genus arcti<U+017F><U+017F>imè a<U+017F><U+017F>ociatum, <U+017F>cholae nominarunt</hi> Serum; <hi>illumque tam</hi> urinae, <hi>quàm</hi> <U+017F>udoris <hi>pariter atque</hi> lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum <hi>communem <U+017F>ecere materiam. De hoc pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarem, et no<U+017F>tro quidem judicio <U+017F>ufficientem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum, cui in<U+017F>criptio</hi> Latex Humor neglectus, <hi>panxit</hi> Helmont: <hi>quo planè o<U+017F>tendit, ingens ab ip<U+017F>a etiam natura po<U+017F>itum e<U+017F><U+017F>e, inter</hi> urinam <hi>&amp;</hi> laticem, <hi>quem frequenter extravenato <U+017F>anguini innatare cernimus, di<U+017F>crimen; tam quoad materiae e<U+017F><U+017F>entiam, quam</hi> u<U+017F>us <hi>utriu<U+017F>que <U+017F>ive de<U+017F>tinationes.</hi> Scopos <hi>autem <U+017F>ive fines, quibus in<U+017F>ervire voluit</hi> Laticem, <hi>brevi verborum <U+017F>erie <U+017F>ic comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> 1. <hi>Latex, ex <U+017F>ua natura pene in<U+017F>ipidus, pro primo <U+017F>copo habet, ut contemperet cruoris</hi> aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatem, <hi>eandemque arceat; et poti<U+017F><U+017F>imum po<U+017F>t labores, a<U+017F>tus, <U+017F>udo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es perfu<U+017F>os, balnea, &amp;c. nam in tanta per<U+017F>pirabilitate cruor valde conden<U+017F>aretur, ni<U+017F>i haberet aqueam partem admixtam pro <U+017F>udore.</hi> 2. <hi>Cum in omni crudiori chylo, cremore, &amp; cruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <U+017F>it aliquid excrementum; &amp; cruor <U+017F>ub dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo <U+017F>alem excrementitium re<U+017F>ervet, etiam dum in purum alimentum convertitur: e<U+017F>t ip<U+017F>i pr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in Latex opportunus <U+017F>ocius, qui in <U+017F>e recipiat hunc <U+017F>alem, eumque everrat.</hi> 3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t materialiter cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>et, ne ullum den<U+017F>ioris compaginis re<U+017F>iduum, in ultima alimoniae evaporatione remaneat: Sed <U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul per Diapnaeam explodatur, ratione Fermenti arterialis (ut</hi> Helmont in Blas Humano) <hi>vel ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione <U+017F>udoris eluatur. Sudor namque materialiter, nil ni<U+017F>i Latex e<U+017F>t, cui acce<U+017F><U+017F>it Sal <U+017F>uperfluus.</hi> 4. <hi>Cum oculus liquore opus haberet, ut ejus palpebra inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuè moveretur, &amp; lingua<U+017F>alivâ eguit, ut ma<U+017F>tica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos cibos madore temperaret; ab<U+017F>urdumque foret, totum cibum è ma<U+017F><U+017F>a cruoris humectari: idcirco per venas Latex delatus e<U+017F>t, unde <U+017F>aliva, lacryma, &amp;c. fierent. Nam dum in Anginis, &amp; infami Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij <U+017F>alivatione, plus ju<U+017F>to <U+017F>aliva profluit, alvus con<U+017F>ueto <U+017F>iccior evadit. Latex ergo in cruoris ma<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>a innoxius vagatur, ad loca opportuna defertur, di<U+017F>tributivae facultati promptè au<U+017F>cultans.</hi> 5. <hi>Quod <U+017F>uo madore compe<U+017F>cat, ne pulmo de hi<U+017F>cat, <U+017F>iccitate aeris attracti. Ad ip<U+017F>ius autem Authoris libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum recurrent <U+017F>tudio<U+017F>i, ubi omnium de hoc the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate uberiorem doctrinam habebunt.</hi> ¶</note> 
                  <hi>Latex,</hi> or <hi>Fountain of <U+017F>erous <U+017F>treams</hi> in the body, might with much more plau<U+017F>ible rea<U+017F>on have been adopted to the generation of Rheume, as being a very convenient mother to own <U+017F>uch a production: then an imaginary vapour, which requires to be conducted through <U+017F>o many in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ible ambages, and blind Meanders,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114890:19"/>
and who<U+017F>e po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of exi<U+017F>tence cannot be a<U+017F><U+017F>erted, without the joynt conce<U+017F><U+017F>ion of a thou<U+017F>and ab<U+017F>urdities, and bold violations of the unalterable decrees of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the accu<U+017F>tomed <hi><U+017F>altne<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> of the <hi>latex,</hi> may bear the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being the <hi>Cau<U+017F>e</hi> of <hi>Pains</hi> and other erratick accidents, with neerer relation to veri<U+017F>imility; then an <hi>in<U+017F>ipid Water,</hi> tran<U+017F>mitted upwards from vapours<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> which have no real Idea, but in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tracted imaginations of either the Contrivers, or Abettors of this Fable. Again, when this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath travelled through the Brain, Membranes, Skull, and Perio<U+017F>tion, doth it then grow weary, feeble, and unable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue on its progre<U+017F><U+017F>e, and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the ea<U+017F>ier perforations of the skin? or hath the former labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pilgrimage <U+017F>o refracted its power of tran<U+017F>udation, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired its memory, that it hath forgotten the way? Why doth the skin, which by rea<U+017F>on of its numerous evaporatories, or capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary poro<U+017F>ities, is ordained to tran<U+017F>mit the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er matter of <U+017F>weat, re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the tenuity of that Water, which hath <U+017F>o nimbly run through the impervious skull? But <U+017F>hould this Water be once colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into a pond, under the <hi><U+017F>calp;</hi> then would it either there <U+017F>well
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114890:20"/>
into a tumid Cataract, or be dreigned downward in a <U+017F>len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thread of <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drops: or were the collection about the temples, it would <U+017F>oon become <U+017F>ubject to the di<U+017F>covery of our touch: and <U+017F>hould it be rained down, yet could it not avoid to infer a manife<U+017F>t <hi>Tumor</hi> of in<U+017F>ipid water, upon the <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> or part <hi>recipient.</hi> And if in <U+017F>mall quantity, it would <U+017F>oon be di<U+017F>cu<U+017F><U+017F>ed by <U+017F>weat. However, it can never fall down upon, nor be congregate amid<U+017F>t the <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles;</hi> <U+017F>ince each of them is <U+017F>trongly guarded by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of a particular cro<U+017F><U+017F>e membrane, wherewith their <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance is immediately covered. Be<U+017F>ides, there is neither <hi>way</hi> for its defluxion from the head, betwixt the skin and perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tion; nor <hi>place</hi> to entertain it among<U+017F>t the interco<U+017F>tall <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles,</hi> in order to the generation of a <hi>Pleuri<U+017F>ie.</hi> For can that <hi>in<U+017F>ipid Water,</hi> which occa<U+017F>ioned no <hi>pain</hi> or mole<U+017F>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while it remained under the skin and hair of the head, within few minuts after its arrivall at the interco<U+017F>tall Mu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, kindle a violent <hi>Pleuri<U+017F>ie,</hi> together with <U+017F>uch intolerable <hi>torments;</hi> and onely by its <hi>de<U+017F>cent</hi> and <U+017F>ingle <hi>gravity</hi> avell the <hi>Pleura,</hi> or lining of the thorax, from the ribs, which is firmly annexed and immediately adheres unto them by the mediatory ligation of numerous <U+017F>olid <hi>Fibers?</hi> Certainly, that <hi>immanity</hi> and tincture of implacable tyranny mu<U+017F>t be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from no other impregnation, then what may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew unto it during its <hi>Defluxion.</hi> To proceed, no Catarrh can de<U+017F>cend upon the <hi>Teeth,</hi> or impeach their <hi>Nerves;</hi> which on either <U+017F>ide from the ba<U+017F>is of the brain are implanted into the mandible: <U+017F>ince they are <U+017F>o exactly proportioned to the diameter of their receptacles, and <U+017F>o entirely fill them up, that there can remain none the <U+017F>male<U+017F>t cranny for the intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion of one drop of rheume; and much the le<U+017F><U+017F>e for this, that <hi>Water cannot enter any <U+017F>mall perforation, that is <U+017F>hut be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</hi> If <U+017F>o, unfeignedly, we have no weighty engagement lies upon our rea<U+017F>on, to enforce a<U+017F><U+017F>ent; that this rheume <U+017F>hould cu<U+017F>tomarily fall foule and infe<U+017F>t one <hi><U+017F>ingle tooth,</hi> and <U+017F>uch onely as is <hi>Carious,</hi> or hollowed by putrefaction. We <U+017F>hall add, that a Catarrh collected into a <U+017F>howre underneath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114890:20"/>
the <U+017F>calp, <U+017F>hould, according to the <hi>vieinity</hi> and <hi>rectitude</hi> of conveyances, rather <U+017F>tream down upon the <hi>Cheeks,</hi> then the bottome of the <hi>Gums,</hi> through their fle<U+017F>hy Contexture, and per<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting non-incorporate to the blood, trace the impervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous paths of the nerves, through the mandible, untill it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <U+017F>ome one particular tooth. Yea though this phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tick deluge might be allowed to drop down from above, and <U+017F>o be thought the cau<U+017F>e of pain, in the <hi>upper</hi> jawe: yet no man can <U+017F>wallow <U+017F>o un<U+017F>avory an ab<U+017F>urdity, as that Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not at all participant of vitality, can by any means, or at any time, infe<U+017F>t the <hi>lower.</hi> What if this vagabond rheume chance to decline towards the <hi>eyes,</hi> or <hi>ears?</hi> in<U+017F>ooth, the malitious matter thereof mu<U+017F>t, from the conceited <hi>Plane</hi> of of the brain, fir<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>e through the chief <hi>Ventricle</hi> thereof: and <U+017F>o in that royall place become a <U+017F>econd and more fatall cataract; yea occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>uddain <hi>Death</hi> more probably, then an <hi>Ophthalmy,</hi> or bare inflammation of the eyes. Again, I <note place="margin">Ophthalmia <hi>e<U+017F>t annatae oculi tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicae inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, â <U+017F>anguine acri, venulas ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ius di<U+017F>tendente, exorta. Con<U+017F>ule practic<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</hi>
                  </note> well remember, that the <hi><U+017F>eat</hi> of a <hi>Pleuri<U+017F>ie</hi> is not betwixt the <hi>skin,</hi> or externall membrane univer<U+017F>ally <U+017F>wathing the body, and the <hi>interco<U+017F>tall mu<U+017F>cles</hi> (whither, notwith<U+017F>tanding, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxion might more directly <U+017F>tream down from the perio<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then toward the internall parts) but either in the very <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the <hi>oblique mu<U+017F>cles;</hi> or between tho<U+017F>e and the <hi>Pleura</hi> immediately en<U+017F>hrouding the Che<U+017F>t, from which part the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e hath de<U+017F>umed its denomination. By what <U+017F>luces therefore can a defluxion be derived from the head unto this place? I grant, indeed, by way of <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ition, that a certain <hi>Muccus,</hi> or phlegmatick and glutinous excrement, doth, even in Children and men of the <U+017F>ounde<U+017F>t con<U+017F>titutions, <U+017F>lide down by the palat into the <U+017F>tomack: yet this <U+017F>tands in no relation at all to a <hi>Catarrb;</hi> nor is that muccus bred from that cried up <hi>vapour</hi> of the fir<U+017F>t concoction; but is an unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>Excrement,</hi> begotten à <hi>Cu<U+017F>tode errante,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Inaudita pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Helmotij <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Paradoxa, <hi>ex profe<U+017F><U+017F>o ut e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>entiae, Cau<U+017F>ae, modique fiendi morborum, novis ejus in</hi> Phy<U+017F>iologia <hi>theorematis melius accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modarentur, fabricata, haud infimum tenet locum hocce, de</hi> Cu<U+017F>tode Errante, <hi>ingenium. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>i<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>autem quàm brevi<U+017F><U+017F>imè, &amp; pro captu marginis, quid <U+017F>ibi voluit per</hi> Cu<U+017F>todem, <hi>et quid per eundem</hi> errantem, <hi>explicemus; animadvertendum e<U+017F>t, quod Author, cum in<U+017F>ignem aquae cataractane è naribus, in principio</hi> Coryze (Frigus <hi>nuacuparunt ru<U+017F>tici) ordinariò effluxi<U+017F><U+017F>e cerneret; et uberrimum pariter</hi> Mucci <hi>proventum a pulmonibus tu<U+017F><U+017F>iendo explo<U+017F>um: ut anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatam, de</hi> Catarrho <hi>ex vaporibus in planum Cerebri delatis, eodem in loco rur<U+017F>um concretis, atque dein tandem guttulatim, partim per nervos olfactorios antror<U+017F>um, partim retror<U+017F>um per laryngem in exiles pulmonum tubos delabente, doctrinam pe<U+017F><U+017F>umdaret;</hi> Cu<U+017F>todes duos, <hi>unum in</hi> Cerebro, <hi>alterum in</hi> Larynge, <hi>â <U+017F>apiente reram Parente con<U+017F>titutos e<U+017F><U+017F>e, affirmare au<U+017F>us e<U+017F>t.</hi> Priori <hi>in provinciam delegatum e<U+017F>t, ut quoties Cerebrum ab externo aliquo malo lace<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum atque vitiatum fuerit, toties pote<U+017F>tate <U+017F>ua alterativa, <U+017F>ive tran<U+017F>mutationis energia, muci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagino<U+017F>um quoddam Excrementum, ex <U+017F>anguine in <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiam Cerebri mox ritè a<U+017F><U+017F>imilando, vel (ut</hi> Helmontij <hi>verbis utar) ex totalitate Alimenti, priu<U+017F>quam aleret, fabricet; quo, tanquam lorica, partes frigore percul<U+017F>ae circumtegantur &amp; ab immani ho<U+017F>te <U+017F>artae tectaeque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erventur. Atque hanc pote<U+017F>tatem,</hi> Mucci <hi>hujus</hi> effectricem, Cu<U+017F>todis <hi>etymo opportunè quadrare, con<U+017F>entaneum e<U+017F>t.</hi> Alteri, Laryngis <hi>nimirum</hi> Prae<U+017F>idi, <hi>munus fere idem e<U+017F>t; puta; ut quoties aeris inexcu<U+017F>abilis injuria partem utranque,</hi> i. e. <hi>Cerebrum &amp; Pulmonem adoriatur, toties è</hi> Latice <hi>&amp;</hi> Cruore <hi>crudiori, Muccum etiam quendam, tanquam ve<U+017F>tem, <U+017F>ive inter<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium objiciat; in quem aer ferociens, partim depo<U+017F>itâ primi ictus inclementiâ, mite<U+017F>cat. Quamdiu enim</hi> Cu<U+017F>tos <hi>rectè valet, atrocitatis aëris victrix <U+017F>uperat: dum verò ob perfractum robur, primae <U+017F>uae de<U+017F>tinationi ex voto <U+017F>atisfacere nequit; <U+017F>altem multum</hi> Mucci <hi>fabricat, ut conceptam eluat labem, quam primitùs non fuit <U+017F>eparando. Sed ah! ubi vel externa injuria major e<U+017F>t, quàm quae <U+017F>inat <U+017F>e <U+017F>ic deliniri; altiu<U+017F>ve ferit ip<U+017F>am laryngis aut pulmonum <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam: jam</hi> titubat Cu<U+017F>tos. <hi>Nec <U+017F>olum de<U+017F>umit auxilium abs</hi> Latice, <hi>Sed ip<U+017F>am</hi> proximi alimenti <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiam <hi>alienat, tran<U+017F>mutatque in mucco<U+017F>am collam; unde</hi> Phthi<U+017F>is <hi>mox <U+017F>equitur.</hi>
                  </note> by the <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> of the brain, <U+017F>educed into a perver<U+017F>ion of its office, as hath been clearly declared in convenient place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:114890:21"/>
I grant moreover, that in the <hi>Gout,</hi> and other con<U+017F>imilar di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, frequently the guilt may be imputed unto a certain <hi><U+017F>alt excrementitious <U+017F>tream,</hi> fretting the parts a<U+017F><U+017F>aulted: but of <U+017F>uch, onely the <hi>Latex,</hi> or <U+017F>ource of aqueous <U+017F>ero<U+017F>isy in the body, is the <hi>Mint, Caement,</hi> and <hi>Supply;</hi> and not an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cent of vapours from the <U+017F>tomack into the brain, not a mi<U+017F>celany of non-exi<U+017F>tent juices, nor a feigned <hi>Defluxion</hi> of <hi>Phlegme</hi> mixt with <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. For the Schools them<U+017F>elves, <U+017F>urrounded with <hi><U+017F>hame,</hi> that the <hi>Head,</hi> being on all <U+017F>ides brimfull of the brains, might be a <hi>Magazine</hi> for the collection of <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> and mo<U+017F>t <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es</hi> charged upon their <hi>Defluxion;</hi> have (alack, and alas for wo) unju<U+017F>tly accu<U+017F>ed the <hi><U+017F>tomack</hi> of continual <U+017F>moaking with vapours, and <U+017F>o contributing <hi>matter</hi> to their producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but finding the <U+017F>tomack not-guilty in healthy men, yet pre<U+017F>ently, in the <hi>Gout,</hi> they incriminate upon a <hi>Defluxion,</hi> and as benighted in a dark mi<U+017F>t of their <U+017F>hame, whi<U+017F>per out
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114890:21"/>
this fal<U+017F>e impeachment, nor adventure to <U+017F>peak it out, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged from the te<U+017F>timony of po<U+017F>itive <hi>knowledge.</hi> For they at fir<U+017F>t da<U+017F>h, <U+017F>teal the <hi>Que<U+017F>tion,</hi> borrow a kind of acrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Choler,</hi> and <hi><U+017F>alt Phlegme</hi> from the <U+017F>imple trea<U+017F>ury of the <hi>blood,</hi> and leave the controver<U+017F>ie undecided: whether tho<U+017F>e <hi>Humors</hi> are to be derived from the <hi>Liver,</hi> <U+017F>eparated, by a kind of <hi>Critical percolation</hi> in the veins, from the remaining laudible ma<U+017F><U+017F>e of blood, and <U+017F>o excluded and di<U+017F>charged upon the <hi>joynts;</hi> or whether a certain <hi>Water,</hi> tartareous <hi>Muccus,</hi> or other anonymous <hi>Excrement</hi> be tran<U+017F>mitted thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the head, underneath the skin. For yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unre<U+017F>olved; and are the more confounded in this, that they cannot manife<U+017F>t, what this cunning <hi>Separator,</hi> or Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nower of various humors, blended together in one form and con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence; or what that <hi>Conductor</hi> <U+017F>hould be, who <U+017F>hould tran<U+017F>port the<U+017F>e humors <U+017F>evered from the blood, incontami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with any alien tincture in <U+017F>o difficult a pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, where many more <U+017F>olid <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances are to be penetrated, onely to the <hi>Conjunctures</hi> and <hi>Articulations:</hi> and now <U+017F>elect and pitch upon this, and anon upon another determinate part: but leave unimpaired the more <hi>feeble</hi> and <hi><U+017F>upine,</hi> and every day make a fre<U+017F>h conque<U+017F>t and <U+017F>ubdue <U+017F>ome one new joynt; yea invade that member, which is become more capable of re<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance by <hi>Nodes</hi> and <hi>Oppilations.</hi> Whatever, therefore, the Schools dotingly pratle concerning vapours elevated from the <U+017F>tomack, and reconden<U+017F>ed in the brain, as the material Cau<U+017F>e of Catarrhs; let all pa<U+017F><U+017F>e for a Chri<U+017F>tma<U+017F><U+017F>e tale, or drunken Beldams dream. ¶</p>
               <p n="27">27. For the <hi><U+017F>tomack</hi> is never <hi>Cold</hi> below its native conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient temper; indeed the <hi>Dige<U+017F>tive Ferment</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Fermentum dige<U+017F>tivum, <hi>e<U+017F>t proprietas quaedam e<U+017F><U+017F>enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tens in</hi> vitali <hi>quadam</hi> Aciditate, <hi>ad tran<U+017F>mutationes ciborum in ventriculo potens; ideoque &amp; <U+017F>pecificae proprietatis. Non e<U+017F>t autem fermentum i<U+017F>tud dige<U+017F>tivum, in <U+017F>ola</hi> Aciditate <hi>aliquali fitum. Neque enim acetum, vel jus Citri farinam fermentat: imo nec farina fermentata proinde e<U+017F>t fermentum <U+017F>tomachicum; <U+017F>ed hoc e<U+017F>t</hi> Acidum e<U+017F>urinum, <U+017F>tomachicum, <U+017F>pecificum &amp; humanum; <hi>ita quidem per <U+017F>ingulas brutorum <U+017F>pecies</hi> Specificè <hi>di<U+017F>tinctum, quod ip<U+017F>is <U+017F>it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriatum. Mures namque, Glires, &amp; Sues citius fame pereunt, quàm Pha<U+017F>eolum edant. In</hi> homine <hi>verò plerumque ad</hi> Generis <hi>amplitudinem aspirat. Interim plures Ca<U+017F>eum horrent, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, lac, vel alia <U+017F>pernunt; quia non conficiunt. Ideoque quaecunque luctantur cum no<U+017F>tra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<U+017F>tione, obver<U+017F>antur</hi> Fermenti <hi>illius</hi> proprietati <U+017F>pecificae, <hi>fermentumque conculcare nituntur.</hi>
                  </note> (to which, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114890:22"/>
not to <hi>heat,</hi> the <hi>Faculty</hi> of <hi>Concoction</hi> ought immediately to be attributed; as we have in another tract concerning that particular Theme, to ample <U+017F>atisfaction evinced) may <U+017F>uffer <hi>Diminution:</hi> nor can the <hi>Liver</hi> a<U+017F>cend to an exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive <hi>Heat,</hi> above that con<U+017F>tant degree of <hi>Vital flame,</hi> which fir<U+017F>t entitled it to <hi>Animation;</hi> for in <U+017F>everity of truth, there is no other heat in our bodies, but what was fir<U+017F>t kindled in our heart by that Ve<U+017F>tal <U+017F>park, or <hi>vital light,</hi> which immediately and <U+017F>olely con<U+017F>tituteth the <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ence</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi> And this the rea<U+017F>on is, why every <hi>Carca<U+017F>e</hi> doth <U+017F>uddainly grow <hi>cold,</hi> as the heart of Winter, <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as the <hi>Vital flame</hi> is extingui<U+017F>hed. <note n="*" place="margin">Princium <hi>i<U+017F>tud</hi> Formale, <hi>cujus beneficio &amp; munere</hi> Animalium <hi>Corpora, alioqui frigida, concale<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, edendi<U+017F>que</hi> Vitae <hi>actionibus apta redduntur, non e<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> Calidum innatum, <hi><U+017F>ive</hi> Humidum primigenium <hi>in<U+017F>ito <U+017F>piritu &amp; calore undique perfu<U+017F>um, contra</hi> Ari<U+017F>totelem, <hi>eju<U+017F>que</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>acerrimè velitatur</hi> Author: <hi>tradens pa<U+017F><U+017F>im per <U+017F>uas lucubrationes, pro axiomate aeternae veritatis; quod in cunctis viventibus in<U+017F>it</hi> Lumen quoddam Vitale, <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatè &amp; fontalitèr â</hi> Patre Luminum (Formas <hi>enim rerum omnium immediate</hi> â Deo crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, <hi><U+017F>erio docet, in</hi> Lib. de Formarum ortu) <hi>dimanans, cordique, dum adhuc e<U+017F><U+017F>et in utero recens embryonatum, tanquam proprio conceptaculo implantatum, in quo</hi> Vita <hi>e<U+017F><U+017F>entialitèr con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tit, atque cujus marcor</hi> Senium, <hi>extinctio</hi> Mortem <hi>nece<U+017F><U+017F>ariò infert. Inquit enim, de</hi> Vita <hi><U+017F>olerter perorans; Vita e<U+017F>t lumen &amp; initium formale, quo res agit quod agere ju<U+017F><U+017F>a e<U+017F>t.</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>Hoc autem lumen, a Creatore rebus infu<U+017F>um, datur unico in<U+017F>tanti; prout â <U+017F>ilice ignis excutitur, <U+017F>ub formae identitate ac unitate clauditur, perque genera et <U+017F>pecies e<U+017F>t di<U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. Non e<U+017F>t autem lumen igneum, cumbu<U+017F>tivum, humidi radicalis con<U+017F>umptivum. Tam in pi<U+017F>ce vitale e<U+017F>t, quàm in Leone; tamque in papavere, quàm pipere. Nec etiam in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis deficit Calor, ob humidi radicalis con<U+017F>umptionem: nec vici<U+017F><U+017F>im humidum deficit, Calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris defectu; <U+017F>ed <U+017F>olâ duntaxat pote<U+017F>tatum Vitalium, adeoque et luminis diminutione &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctione. Fu<U+017F>iorem vero Argumenti hujus explicationem me legi<U+017F><U+017F>e memini, in tract.</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midum radicale <hi>nuncupato; quor<U+017F>um benevolos, avido<U+017F>que doctrinae Helmontij ex in<U+017F>tituto remittendos volui.</hi>
                     </q> ¶</note>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. But the offen<U+017F>ive <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Liver</hi> belongs to it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Accident.</hi> For example, let a <hi>cold Thorne</hi> or needle be pricked into any mans finger (an <hi>in<U+017F>tance</hi> frequently men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by me, and largely explained in my di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers)</hi> and thereupon <U+017F>hall in<U+017F>tantly en<U+017F>ue a violent <hi>Pul<U+017F>ation,</hi> occa<U+017F>ioned by the pain, an angry <hi>Incale<U+017F>cence,</hi> and <hi>Tumor</hi> of the <hi>part.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quicquid in <U+017F>anis edit acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones <U+017F>anas: id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ip<U+017F>um in morbis edit actiones vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatas. Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus enim i<U+017F>te ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefacit hominem naturaliter in <U+017F>anitate, idem qui in febribus ae<U+017F>tuat. per ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum. Spina querna digito infixa, actu et potentialiter frigida, mox in digito excitat calorem praeter naturam. Non qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, quod calidi humores affluant, qua<U+017F>i per <U+017F>pinam eò convocati, expecta<U+017F><U+017F>ent <U+017F>pinae vulnus, &amp; qui alia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>s <U+017F>uis <U+017F>edibus temperati <U+017F>edi<U+017F><U+017F>ent. Siquidem cruor vulneri proximus, primus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit, aditum venienti cruori praeripit. Et ip<U+017F>e per <U+017F>e quoque non calet: Sed ex gratia vitalis <U+017F>piritus. Itaque inflammatio, &amp; tumor cum pul<U+017F>a duro, dolore, &amp; calore, à <U+017F>olo <U+017F>piritu cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>alitèr; ab infixa verò <U+017F>pina occa<U+017F>ionaliter duntaxat procedunt.</hi> Helm. de Febr. cap. 1. ¶</note> Not becau<U+017F>e this <hi>Thorne</hi> is <hi>hot,</hi> nor that the <hi>blood</hi> then in vicinity to the wound had any immoderate <hi>offerve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> before the infixation of the thorne: but that exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive <hi>Ardor</hi> is kindled upon the entrance of the thorne into the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114890:22"/>
fle<U+017F>h. Now let the <U+017F>ame rea<U+017F>on hold good, as concerning the <hi>Liver;</hi> for if that at any time conceive an unnatural <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> it is cau<U+017F>ed by <U+017F>ome <hi>Thorne,</hi> or forreigne impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion which doth not indicate, in order to the extinction of that conflagration, any <hi>Refrigeration,</hi> but a totall <hi>Ablation</hi> or eradication of it. For <hi>Refrigeration</hi> of the <hi>Liver</hi> is <U+017F>o far from working even a bare palliative <hi>Cure</hi> of this <hi>Ardor,</hi> that indeed it renders the mi<U+017F>chief <hi>de<U+017F>perate,</hi> for the future.</p>
               <p n="29">29. And this, I earne<U+017F>tly wi<U+017F>h, the Schools may be plea<U+017F>ed <U+017F>oberly to ob<U+017F>erve; as al<U+017F>o their vain and impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible figment of the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Liver,</hi> and the manifold <hi>Errors</hi> in their <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>Sanation,</hi> all <U+017F>treaming from this fountain. May they <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ly ob<U+017F>erve al<U+017F>o, how barren and un<U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>eful all <U+017F>uch <hi>Remedies</hi> have proved, which have been directed (with grief I <U+017F>peak it) to the <hi>Head, Stomack,</hi> and <hi>Liver,</hi> for the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Catarrhs.</hi> Manife<U+017F>t therefore it is, that a <hi>Catarrh hath, in nature, neither Material Cau<U+017F>e for its Generatton, Place for its Conception, Conduiets for its Traduction, Receptaries for its cu<U+017F>tomary Admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion, nor <U+017F>ufficient activity to make good its Penetration through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the brain, Membranes, Skull, and Perio<U+017F>tion.</hi> For where in all this admirable Fabrick of the body can we find, that Nature (who<U+017F>e Providence can be found no way deficient) hath built any hou<U+017F>e of office, or <hi>clo<U+017F>e<U+017F>tool,</hi> meerly for the reception of <hi>Preternatural Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements:</hi> nor can it <U+017F>tand with the lawes of veri<U+017F>imility, that a <hi>meer excrement</hi> generated in any part, <U+017F>hould be endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> to tran<U+017F>plant it<U+017F>elfe at plea<U+017F>ure from one place to another. And upon the conce<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the doctrine of rheumes, the <hi>Trepan</hi> would every day, be of as much u<U+017F>e for the letting out of <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> as to give vent to the <hi>Purulent Effluxions</hi> of wounds in the head.</p>
               <p n="30">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:114890:23"/>
30. But why <U+017F>hould a Catarrh cea<U+017F>e <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>flow downwards, immediately after the Tooth, which aked, is pulled out? whither becau<U+017F>e it hath <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon forgotten its way thither? And if the matter thereof be originally tran<U+017F>mitted from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, whither, I be<U+017F>eech you, in relation to its natural Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, <U+017F>hould it then run? or upon what new part <U+017F>hall that ancient rivulet of rheume be diverted, which con<U+017F>tantly u<U+017F>ed to creep into the channel of the teeth, and in<U+017F>inuate it <U+017F>elfe through tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>lender perforations, which the <hi>Nerves,</hi> a<U+017F>well within, as without, above as below, entirely po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>e and fill up? Doth the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> for<U+017F>ooth, <hi>cea<U+017F>e,</hi> or not <hi>dare</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the exhalation of vapours, and the communication of the fuell for Catarrhs, after the drawing of a tooth? or doth the whole <U+017F>tore of rheume, yea <U+017F>uch as <U+017F>hall be generated in the future, flow forth together with the blood, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tant of the tooths evul<U+017F>ion? or upon the generation of fle<U+017F>h in the <hi>mortice</hi> of the drawn tooth, and <U+017F>o the cutting off all way of effu<U+017F>ion, doth the Catarrh dry up? But <U+017F>ure the Catarrh could not attempt a pa<U+017F><U+017F>age through the rocky and <hi>impenetrable <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance</hi> of the tooth? If not; what hindred it from <U+017F>welling, by re<U+017F>tagnation, into a nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary <hi>Apo<U+017F>tem</hi> in the parts adjacent? why doth it frequently, when <hi>one tooth</hi> is pulled out, find a new channel and drive again<U+017F>t <hi>another?</hi> Doth the evul<U+017F>ion of the <hi>first tooth</hi> turne the cour<U+017F>e of the <U+017F>tream upon the <hi><U+017F>econd?</hi> Doth the <hi>conductor</hi> of the rheum grow <hi>blind,</hi> and can no longer find its way to the remaining <hi>nerve</hi> of the drawn teeth, or at lea<U+017F>t to the <hi>carnous excre<U+017F>cence</hi> that <U+017F>ucceeds the tooth? or can it with more ea<U+017F>e drill a hole through a <U+017F>econd firme tooth, then pa<U+017F><U+017F>e the <U+017F>pongy fle<U+017F>h that ari<U+017F>eth upon the ejectment of the former? why can it not con<U+017F>tantly keep po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of that <hi>Current</hi> which it <U+017F>elf digged? And <U+017F>o con<U+017F>erve an outlet for it <U+017F>elfe, before the new tenant of fle<U+017F>h take livery and <U+017F>ei<U+017F>en? Mi<U+017F>erably, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ooth, is this rheum deluded by the Chirurgeon, which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, according to its cu<U+017F>tome, to invade <U+017F>ome one Tooth, and finding it removed, mu<U+017F>t be con<U+017F>trained to return back, by the <U+017F>ame way it came, and execute its malice upon <U+017F>ome
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114890:23"/>
more noble part; which it torments, in revenge of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front done by the Chirurgeon. <hi>No tooth, therefore, aketh by rea<U+017F>on of a Defluxion:</hi> but becau<U+017F>e, upon a detection of the Gum, it becomes <hi>too <U+017F>en<U+017F>ile;</hi> or that, in another ca<U+017F>e, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of its ultimate or mo<U+017F>t depurated <hi>Aliment,</hi> being defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively a<U+017F><U+017F>imilated, conceives <hi>putrefaction</hi> at the root of the tooth: and hence that intolerable <hi>Paine.</hi> 31. For the <hi>Dige<U+017F>tion</hi> of the <hi>Teeth</hi> and <hi>Nayls</hi> is di<U+017F>tinct from the Dige<U+017F>tion of all other parts, in this particular; that the Dige<U+017F>tion of <hi>tho<U+017F>e</hi> is performed in <hi>dome<U+017F>tick ve<U+017F><U+017F>els,</hi> or the very interior <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of each particular part; but of the<U+017F>e in <hi>ve<U+017F><U+017F>els</hi> onely <hi>contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to their <hi>roots.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p n="32">32. But that no Catarrh can fall down upon the <hi>Inwards,</hi> the Stomack, Lungs, Liver, Kidneys, &amp;c. is in part already manife<U+017F>ted, from that generall evidence alleaged again<U+017F>t the <hi>po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility</hi> of its <hi>materiall Cau<U+017F>e, waies</hi> of <hi>tran<U+017F>portation,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>production:</hi> and may, in part, be evinced from this, that nothing can fall down upon the <hi>Palat,</hi> much le<U+017F><U+017F>e into the <hi>Stomack,</hi> contrary to our will, but what may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tantly be ejected by <hi>ex<U+017F>creation.</hi> For we never <U+017F>wallow down the naturall <hi>Muccus<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </hi> ordinarily dropping from the head upon the root of the tongue; but <hi>unawares:</hi> nor is any Catarrh <U+017F>o far participant of the power of <hi>election,</hi> as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly to lie in ambu<U+017F>h, till we are lockt up in the arms of <U+017F>leep, and then a<U+017F><U+017F>ault us when we are unfit to endeavour its evacuation. May all <hi>Fables,</hi> and <hi>Dreams</hi> of impo<U+017F><U+017F>ibilities be henceforth utterly exiled from the Confines of the <U+017F>acred <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Healing.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p n="33">33. What<U+017F>oever, therefore, is di<U+017F>tilled from the head upon the jawes; is the <hi>Muccus,</hi> or ordinary excrement of the brain, either in its <hi>naturall</hi> and due con<U+017F>titution: or <hi>altered</hi> from it, into various <hi>irregularities,</hi> re<U+017F>pective to the indi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>itions of the <hi>Cu<U+017F>tos,</hi> or <hi>Prae<U+017F>ident</hi> of tho<U+017F>e parts. But this <hi>Muccus</hi> is, in totality of e<U+017F><U+017F>ence, di<U+017F>tinct from that <hi>Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> expectorated from the <hi>Lungs,</hi> by <hi>Cough.</hi> And then, what means this ra<U+017F>h inadvertency of the Schools, when they direct, that, by exact in<U+017F>pection, we examine the <U+017F>pitle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114890:24"/>
by Cough, whether it be <hi>watery, frothy, diaphanous, liquid, white, concreted, yellow, a<U+017F>h-coloured,</hi> or <hi>tawny?</hi> whether <hi>round, globular,</hi> of a con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence fit for <hi>impetuous defluxion?</hi> To what purpo<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ay I, doe they command us to make our augurie and explorations of the <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es</hi> of the <hi>Che<U+017F>t</hi> and <hi>Lungs;</hi> if, as them<U+017F>elves opinion, tho<U+017F>e excrements we <U+017F>pit up, be <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> and originally derived from the head? For <U+017F>o a rheum, following upon <U+017F>ome <hi>con<U+017F>tipation</hi> of the <hi>os Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moides,</hi> or <U+017F>pongy bone, by the <hi>Muccus</hi> ordinarily de<U+017F>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the no<U+017F>trils; would be diluted with a crude and aqueous <hi>Muccus;</hi> for this cau<U+017F>e, that provident <hi>Nature</hi> would hither <U+017F>end a plentifull torrent of the <hi>Latex</hi> for the <hi>ablution</hi> of that, who<U+017F>e thickne<U+017F><U+017F>e and vi<U+017F>cidity cau<U+017F>ed the ob<U+017F>truction. And if the <hi>materiall cau<U+017F>e</hi> hereof be primitively deduced from the <U+017F>tomack; why, when the <U+017F>pongy bone is ob<U+017F>tructed, doth the <U+017F>tomack of a man perfectly in health, grow outragious, play the tyrant, and oppre<U+017F><U+017F>e the brain with too great a charge of vapours? How can tho<U+017F>e vapors, when conden<U+017F>ed above the palate, arrive at the <hi>odoratorie Nerves,</hi> <U+017F>eated in the forehead, and there put on the form of a <hi><U+017F>alt water,</hi> to <hi>wa<U+017F>h</hi> and <hi>rince</hi> away the <hi>ob<U+017F>truction</hi> from the <hi><U+017F>pongie bone?</hi> From whence can vapours, of their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>in<U+017F>ipid</hi> and <hi>harmle<U+017F><U+017F>e;</hi> in their <U+017F>hort pa<U+017F><U+017F>age only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <U+017F>o much <hi><U+017F>alt;</hi> which they <U+017F>hould melt and precipitate downwards together with them<U+017F>elves, and, by this new <hi>acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious impraegnation,</hi> introduce frequent <hi><U+017F>quinancies,</hi> and other <hi>inflammations</hi> of the throat and jawes? ¶</p>
               <p n="34">34. Why doth this <hi>rheum,</hi> elevated formerly from the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> and by no other tran<U+017F>mutation, but only a bare <hi>Conden<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> into water (which is demon<U+017F>trated, by the mechanick experiments of <hi>Pyrotechny,</hi> to be nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily <hi>in<U+017F>ipid</hi> and <hi>gentle)</hi> changed from its primitive con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of a vapour; when once it falleth upon the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> occa<U+017F>ion <U+017F>o many and grievous mi<U+017F>chiefs therein: which yet not long before, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring its commixture with other parts of the <hi>Chyle,</hi> was <hi>gratefull</hi> and <hi>benefieiall</hi> to the <U+017F>ame? Whence can it obtain this <hi>Ho<U+017F>tility?</hi> What, from the <hi>Brain,</hi> one of the mo<U+017F>t noble
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114890:24"/>
parts of the body, and richly endowed with <hi>vitall principles?</hi> And if this <hi>Vapour</hi> hath only touched upon the lowe<U+017F>t <hi>Plane</hi> of the brain (as them<U+017F>elves affirme) and in<U+017F>tantly fall down from thence, <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon, as it multiplies up to the quantity of <hi>one <U+017F>ingle drop;</hi> and <U+017F>ince no third place can be found, to deteine each <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drop: therefore can this <hi>perver<U+017F>ity,</hi> or evill tincture, ari<U+017F>e unto this <hi>rheum,</hi> neither from the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany <U+017F>tay</hi> in the plane of the brain, nor from the <hi>Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> of any <hi>malignant part,</hi> nor finaly from any <hi><U+017F>eminality</hi> or infu<U+017F>ion of <hi>depravity</hi> received from thence. Unle<U+017F><U+017F>e, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, they <U+017F>hall be able to give in evidence, that, be<U+017F>ides the bare <hi>conden<U+017F>ation</hi> of the <hi>vapour</hi> into <hi>rheum,</hi> there interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <U+017F>ome <hi>Third cau<U+017F>ality,</hi> from which the <hi>Acrimony, <U+017F>altne<U+017F><U+017F>e,</hi> and <hi>virulency</hi> of the <hi>Defluxion</hi> was derived: which hitherto they have neglected to prove.</p>
               <p n="35">35. But <U+017F>ince the numerous <hi>Comments,</hi> concerning <hi>Catarrhs</hi> and <hi>Pulmonary</hi> maladies, have grown up into huge <hi>Volumes, Councels,</hi> and <hi>Di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>atories:</hi> I conceive it my proper bu<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e to declare, that no theory of the Schools was ever more full of <hi>negligence, ab<U+017F>urdity</hi> and <hi>danger,</hi> then this of Defluxions; on this account, that hitherto they have e<U+017F>tee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med no <U+017F>inne more veniall, then <hi>Homicide,</hi> committed out of incogicancy and circum<U+017F>pection; provided that the earth cover over their Crimes, and they become excu<U+017F>ed of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the allegation of <U+017F>ome <hi>Axiomes</hi> of vulgar tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And hence, amids my compa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate meditations, have I thought, that the Devil <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Con<U+017F>ule cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<U+017F><U+017F>imum <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                        </gap> illum, Dom. Selden, de dis Syris <U+017F>yntag.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Moloch</hi> fits Doctor of the Chair, and hath down to our daies infatuated the world with the whim<U+017F>ey of Catarrhs. Who<U+017F>e materiall Cau<U+017F>e, Nativity, Place of conception, Efficient, manner of Generation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptary, progre<U+017F><U+017F>e, and collection, are equally unwarrantable by truth, becau<U+017F>e ab<U+017F>olutely impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible in nature. The<U+017F>e ab<U+017F>urd doctrines therefore none hath broached and promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, but the <hi>old Serpent,</hi> the Father of lies; with de<U+017F>igne to depopulate <hi>Humanity.</hi> For whatever di<U+017F>tils from the head is the native <hi>Muccus</hi> and pure <hi>Excrement</hi> of the brain, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated within its proper confines; and no forreigner brought in from the <U+017F>tomack. ¶</p>
               <p n="36">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114890:25"/>
36. This Muccus, is con<U+017F>tantly <hi>white, thick, vi<U+017F>cid</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious;</hi> while the <hi>Cu<U+017F>tos,</hi> or Lord Pre<U+017F>ident of the head, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues <U+017F>ober, well di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed, and conformes its dominion to the whol<U+017F>ome Statutes of its primitive tru<U+017F>t: but when it degenerates into exorbitancies, and irregular operations, and the powers committed to its admini<U+017F>tration are perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into abu<U+017F>es; then doth the <hi>Muccus</hi> grow <hi>unnaturall, wild, watery, acute, <U+017F>alt, <U+017F>harp, yellow, tenacious,</hi> &amp;c. and like a virulent torrent, <U+017F>hower down upon the palate from the funnel of the brain, by the mo<U+017F>t convenient and obvious floodgate.</p>
               <p n="37">37. For that matter, which in the beginning of a <hi>cold,</hi> or po<U+017F>e in the head, trickles down in the form of a thin water, is not <U+017F>imply and meerly the <hi>muccus:</hi> but <hi><U+017F>alt Latex,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with nature endeavours to rince away that excrementitious <hi>Phlegme,</hi> which, as a forraine adver<U+017F>ary, hath encroached upon the <hi><U+017F>pongie bone,</hi> bordering upon the brain, and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tructed</hi> its <U+017F>luices; as I have already hinted. Nor is that matter, which comes <hi>yellow</hi> and <hi>vi<U+017F>cid,</hi> in the <hi>declination</hi> or exit of a Cold, the <U+017F>ame with the fir<U+017F>t <hi>Latex,</hi> nor any the <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t mea<U+017F>ure of time deteined and in<U+017F>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ated in the <U+017F>ame place; (as the Schools notwith<U+017F>tanding confidently teach) <U+017F>ince if <U+017F>o, the whole cavity of the skull, though all the brains were taken out, would not <U+017F>uffice to the reception of <U+017F>o va<U+017F>t a quantity of Excrement: but this new kind of <hi>Muc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> is fre<U+017F>hly created every <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive moment, and differs from the naturall and <hi>healthy Muccus,</hi> in diver<U+017F>ity of <hi>colour, <U+017F>tinke, vi<U+017F>cidity,</hi> and <hi>acrimony.</hi> Be<U+017F>ides, its ridiculous to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend this <hi>putrid Muccus,</hi> under the notion of an <hi>excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> well <hi>concocted</hi> and <hi>in<U+017F>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ated</hi> out of the former <hi>Latex;</hi> which is accidentally advenient, <hi>praeternaturall,</hi> and depends upon a forrein <hi>vitious cau<U+017F>ality.</hi> Now, that the <hi>Latex</hi> makes the fir<U+017F>t flood in a <hi>cold,</hi> is manife<U+017F>t from this ob<U+017F>ervation; that alwaies, for two daies, in every cold, the belly is more <U+017F>low in the exclu<U+017F>ion of its excrements, and the quantity of urine much dimini<U+017F>hed: which clearly evinceth that the <hi><U+017F>alt current</hi> is in part <hi>diverted</hi> upon the <hi>brain.</hi> Again, this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114890:25"/>
                  <hi>Latex</hi> evaporated in a convenient ve<U+017F><U+017F>ell, by a gentle heat, containeth nothing in its con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, that can be <hi>in<U+017F>pi<U+017F><U+017F>ated</hi> into a thickne<U+017F><U+017F>e equall to that of the <hi>Muccus:</hi> but how much of the <hi>Muccus,</hi> the <hi>Latex</hi> <U+017F>hall dilute, and rince away from the <U+017F>pongy bone, by its thinner <U+017F>tream; exactly <U+017F>o much, and no more of a <hi>mucilage,</hi> or glutinous <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, may be found in it. ¶</p>
               <p n="38">38. But however it be, and whatever that be which <U+017F>lides down from the Brain upon the Palate and root of the tongue: yet cannot the lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>ingle drop thereof enter into the Lungs, but before it de<U+017F>cend <U+017F>o low, it mu<U+017F>t endanger the life by <hi><U+017F>uffocation.</hi> For if one drop of liquor, <U+017F>lipping down the <hi>a<U+017F>pera Arteria</hi> or <hi>Wind-pipe</hi> unawares, whil<U+017F>t we are drinking, threaten the deplorable <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Anacraeon</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Had we <U+017F>aid <hi>cro<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> fate, the Epithite had been more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine, and had more clearly hinted the prepo<U+017F>terous rarity. For how unu<U+017F>uall and <hi>unnaturall</hi> an Accident was it, for the invincible <U+017F>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity of a <hi>Poet</hi> to flow from his <hi>inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> and a volatile <hi>mu<U+017F>e</hi> to be conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dulne<U+017F><U+017F>e, by the <U+017F>pright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruit of the <hi>Vine,</hi> the <U+017F>ame <hi>In<U+017F>pirer,</hi> who<U+017F>e active flames had <U+017F>o often warmed and exalted her to the <U+017F>ublimity of rapture?</note>: what would not <U+017F>o great a quantity of <hi>rheume,</hi> as is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected by Cough, even to the filling of <U+017F>everall ba<U+017F>ons in a very <U+017F>hort time, doe as to the inference of <hi><U+017F>uffocation?</hi> And far from the <U+017F>ober and rationall waies of <hi>Probability</hi> mu<U+017F>t his <hi>credulity</hi> wander, who can <U+017F>ubmit to a per<U+017F>wa<U+017F>ion, that the <hi><U+017F>leep</hi> of a few <U+017F>hort houres can in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly convey whole ba<U+017F>ons full of rheume into the Lungs; and that <U+017F>o impetuous a flood of <hi>Phlegme</hi> can run down through the narrow chink of the <hi>Epiglottis,</hi> or <hi>Flap</hi> of the <hi>Larinx,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the manife<U+017F>t hazzard of praefocation. In the daies of yore I ingeniou<U+017F>ly confe<U+017F><U+017F>e, being deluded by the <U+017F>ophi<U+017F>try of the <U+017F>chools, during my <hi>pedanti<U+017F>me</hi> and credulous pupil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, I di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed my patients, afflicted with affections of the Lungs, into <U+017F>uch a po<U+017F>ture, as that laying their faces <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> upon their pillows, they might <U+017F>leep in a <hi>prone po<U+017F>ition;</hi> with de<U+017F>igne, that the <hi>rheume</hi> (for<U+017F>ooth) might run out by the <hi>No<U+017F>trils,</hi> which would otherwi<U+017F>e have flowed into the <hi>Lungs:</hi> and upon this <U+017F>core, I promi<U+017F>ed immunity from the perill of <hi>Defluxions.</hi> But the following morne derided my ignorance and folly, with an argument borrowed from the con<U+017F>tant per<U+017F>everance of the <hi>Cough</hi> and <hi>ex<U+017F>creation</hi> of rheum. For then did I di<U+017F>cover, that an <hi>Orthopnaea,</hi> or extreame dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of <hi>Re<U+017F>piration,</hi> which con<U+017F>trains men to fetch their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114890:26"/>
breath in an <hi>erect po<U+017F>ture,</hi> put but a <U+017F>light valew upon the doctrine of Catarrhs, and amply convinced it as frivilous and incon<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent with truth. Since I ob<U+017F>erved many to be <U+017F>trangled in that prone and horizontall po<U+017F>ition; which yet was, with great gravity and confidence, pre<U+017F>cribed by the Schools, as the only barracado, or damm, to intercept the antecedent matter of the Catarrh. Upon which ob<U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation I fir<U+017F>t built this ju<U+017F>tifiable po<U+017F>ition; <hi>that every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular member of the body, once di<U+017F>affected, doth forge and coyne a very great quantity not onely of its naturall and ordinary excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but al<U+017F>o of new, alien, and adver<U+017F>e.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="39">39. Thus from the <hi>eyes,</hi> according to the variety of their di<U+017F>affections, trickle down continued rills of a <hi>purulent efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion,</hi> or of <hi><U+017F>alt</hi> and corro<U+017F>ive <hi>tears,</hi> let forth with out the key of <hi>pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion:</hi> and when the <hi>Throat</hi> is blockt up by a <hi><U+017F>quinaney,</hi> there continually hangs downe a rope of vi<U+017F>cid Phlegme from the tongue. And upon this root grew that branch of my judgement; that <hi>the Lungs are equally <U+017F>ubject to the <U+017F>ame law, with other members.</hi> So that as often as they are a<U+017F><U+017F>auled, irritated, injured, wounded, oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, or tainted by any inquination of the <hi>aer,</hi> or contagion of malignant <hi>vapours</hi> belched from the <U+017F>ulphureous and bituminous bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of <hi>Mines:</hi> <U+017F>o often mu<U+017F>t they produce various <hi>te<U+017F>timoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> of their pre<U+017F>ent <hi>langour,</hi> upon the credit of their own <hi>irregularities;</hi> and not that, upon any <U+017F>uch occa<U+017F>ion, tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>o de<U+017F>tructive and venenate <hi>excrements</hi> can fall in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly from the <hi>brain</hi> (who<U+017F>e integrity of con<U+017F>titution remains, for the mo<U+017F>t part, in <U+017F>uch Ca<U+017F>es, inviolate) and be received among<U+017F>t the <U+017F>lender Conduits of the <hi>Windpipe.</hi> And hence grew my <hi>Wonder</hi> al<U+017F>o, how the Schools could ob<U+017F>erve, that the <hi>matter</hi> running from the no<U+017F>trils, in a <hi>Cold,</hi> did in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination or <hi>Cata<U+017F>trophe</hi> much degenerate from what it was in the <hi>Prologue</hi> and fir<U+017F>t act; and imitate the proper and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary excrement of the brain: and yet, at the <U+017F>ame time, not di<U+017F>cover; that the <U+017F>ame <hi>perver<U+017F>ion</hi> or abu<U+017F>e of <hi>power</hi> lay in <hi>Common</hi> to the <hi>Lungs,</hi> a<U+017F>well as to other members of the body. According to their rule, whatever is avoyded from the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114890:26"/>
he <hi>Lungs,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be fathered upon the <hi>brain,</hi> mu<U+017F>t thence fall downe <hi>in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly</hi> (ridiculous) into the <hi>Windpipe,</hi> there, by a certain <hi>pepa<U+017F>mus,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, Maturatio: <hi>ita dicitur humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praeter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, morbos efficientium</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ique</hi> Alteratio <hi>in meliorem for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam; ut</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>e<U+017F>t naturalium concoctio<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> vide</hi> Hippocrat. &amp; Galen. in epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demiis. ¶</note> or <hi>maturation,</hi> be <U+017F>tewed into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>i<U+017F>tence more <U+017F>it for its future exantlation, and all that while be lodged in the <U+017F>mall-bored pipes of the Lungs, without cau<U+017F>ing any inten<U+017F>e <hi>Anhelation,</hi> or difficulty of breathing. When (alas) it can e<U+017F>cape the ob<U+017F>ervation of no man, that a far greater quantity of matter is frequently expectorated by Cough, in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Lungs, in the <U+017F>pace of one moneth, then the whole cavity of the Che<U+017F>t can conteine. Upon which con<U+017F>ideration, we are bold to affirme, <hi>That the yellow, a<U+017F>hcoloured, and ful<U+017F>om <U+017F>pittle of men in Con<U+017F>umtions, are errors of the</hi> Cu<U+017F>tos, <hi>or Pre<U+017F>ident of Vegetation in the Lungs, and materially the blood, degenerated into a white, yellow, <U+017F>tinking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement;</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Cu<U+017F>tos, <hi>qui laryngi &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bus prae<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, ubi <U+017F>emel</hi> in<U+017F>anit, <hi>rectoque ju<U+017F>titiae de tramite deviat, nedum</hi> humorem aquo<U+017F>um <hi>è v<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis advocat <U+017F>ui in auxilium; a<U+017F>t etiam</hi> ip<U+017F>am alimenti proximi <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantiam <hi>exhaurit, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpit, et in muccum infamem tran<U+017F>mutat: tantò viz. vi<U+017F>cerls alimento proximiorem, quantò altiùs ad colorem ex flavo rutilantem, &amp; rubedini vicinius acce<U+017F><U+017F>erit; reditque ab illo lap<U+017F>u in pri<U+017F>tinum, dum à rufo ad flavedinem paleae, atque inde demum ad albuminie o vi <U+017F>imilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem propriùs appropinquarit. Hinc vice ver<U+017F>a, in</hi> Hecticis <hi>cruentus evadit muccus, et cine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ob<U+017F>curorum colorem a<U+017F><U+017F>umit: dum ip<U+017F>amet alimenti <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantia ab<U+017F>cedit tran<U+017F>mutata, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientemque ibidem vitae integritatem pandit. Tunc nimirum faetidus cadaveris incipientis odor in anhelitu, deliquia prodit</hi> Archei Pulmonarij. <hi>Sed haec ad mentem Helmontij.</hi>
                  </note> which being thus exhau<U+017F>ted, there mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ity en<U+017F>ue an <hi>Atrophy,</hi> or univer<U+017F>al <hi>Famine</hi> in the body. ¶</p>
               <p n="40">40. Un<U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>efull, therefore, and deplorable are the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>criptions of <hi>Cephalick</hi> remedies, in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Lungs; vain are the drinks of cooling <hi>Pti<U+017F>ans,</hi> vain are <hi>Lambatives, Syrups,</hi> and whatever el<U+017F>e is <U+017F>wallowed down into the <hi><U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack:</hi> as <U+017F>uch that mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>uffer a <hi>Ca<U+017F>tration</hi> of their <hi>virtues</hi> in their tedious journey, and undergo many formal tran<U+017F>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, before they arrive at the <hi>part affected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">41. And what can <U+017F>mell more of the <hi>Fool,</hi> then to give <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions</hi> of the <hi>Indian Roots,</hi> to dry up rheums? for how can <hi>China, Zarza,</hi> or <hi>Guajacum</hi> conduce to <hi>ex<U+017F>iceation,</hi> when drank in a <hi>liquid</hi> forme? What can they dry up, which would not be more pernicious and de<U+017F>perate when dried up, then it could be in the more harmele<U+017F><U+017F>e con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence of a <hi>Liquor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="42">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:114890:27"/>
42. Why are <U+017F>uch things referred to <hi>Ex<U+017F>iccation;</hi> which, in the policy of rea<U+017F>on, want onely <U+017F>ome <hi>inhibitive Cour<U+017F>e</hi> to prevent their <hi>Cau<U+017F>ation:</hi> and when they are <U+017F>tolne into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<U+017F>tence, require not an <hi>evaporation</hi> of their liquid and fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive parts; but an entire <hi>ejection</hi> and eradication of their whole? Why do the Schools, in mo<U+017F>t of their di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions, look onely open the <hi>effects</hi> and obvious <hi>Exteriors:</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pur<U+017F>ue their <U+017F>earch back to the <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> and more remote <hi>Proto-principles?</hi> What though the<U+017F>e forreigne and barbarous <hi>drugs</hi> procure a general <hi><U+017F>weat,</hi> and <U+017F>o dimini<U+017F>h the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ite quantity of the <hi>Latex,</hi> to the great and almo<U+017F>t irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble detriment of the Patient: do they therefore <U+017F>trike at the <hi>root</hi> of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, and de<U+017F>troy the <hi>Cardinal efficient</hi> thereof? while by a <U+017F>pare <hi>diet,</hi> and plentifull <hi><U+017F>weats,</hi> they fir<U+017F>t dimini<U+017F>h the nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary mea<U+017F>ure of <hi>blood;</hi> and <U+017F>econdarily cau<U+017F>e an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoydable <hi>leanne<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> of the whole body. All which the Schools have drawne into practice, upon the de<U+017F>igne of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>iccation of <U+017F>uperfluities; wildly imagining to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, the <hi>competent quantity of blood, Generation</hi> of the exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Excrement,</hi> and ea<U+017F>ie <hi>Expul<U+017F>ion</hi> of the <U+017F>ame, under the <U+017F>ingle <U+017F>ynonyma of Ex<U+017F>iccation. But (alas) will the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition</hi> of the Lungs be hereby <hi>rectified?</hi> will the <hi>Transforming Vulcan,</hi> or <hi>Frantick Cu<U+017F>tos,</hi> which doth there coyne loath<U+017F>ome and con<U+017F>umptive <hi>Excrements</hi> out of the laudable <hi>blood,</hi> be by this ineffective means <U+017F>ubdued, lulled a<U+017F>leep, weakned, and reduced to its primitive <U+017F>obriety, and convenient admini<U+017F>tration of its power? which enraged Vulcan doth never, no not when the <U+017F>ick are emaciated to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving skeletons, remit or di<U+017F>continue the execution of its fury. Turne from us, oh thou <hi><U+017F>oul of goodne<U+017F><U+017F>e!</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Calamity, which the <U+017F>otti<U+017F>h <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> of <hi>Pagans,</hi> and herd of blind <hi>Doradoes,</hi> pretending to the <U+017F>acred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teries of <hi>Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> which more <U+017F>tudy their own gains, then the <U+017F>afety of their afflicted brother, have drawne upon all Chri<U+017F>tendom. ¶</p>
               <p n="43">43. The Cardinall point of the <hi>Cure</hi> lyes onely in this; that the irregular and erroneous <hi>impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> (which I call, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114890:27"/>
                  <hi>Factor</hi> of <hi>corruption,</hi> or <hi>Vulcan,</hi> re<U+017F>ident in the Lungs) be expunged and eradicated. For thats the only Publican, which by an un<U+017F>upportable Exci<U+017F>e, impoveri<U+017F>heth the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of the body, and makes nature bankrupt, by exhau<U+017F>ting the <U+017F>tock of aliment from the membranes, veines, Cartilages of the Windpipe, and all the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Lungs; and converting the <U+017F>ame into <U+017F>ordid and ulcerous excrements, which are continually pumpt up by Cough. But if there hath preceded an eruption of blood in any ve<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ell of the lungs, if the matter expectorated be <U+017F>anguine, and the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e hath proceeded to an ulcer; In <U+017F>uch a ca<U+017F>e, learn the right confection of <U+017F>uch admirable Medicaments, wherewith <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us</hi> was wont to cure the Con<U+017F>umption. For tho<U+017F>e, <U+017F>ince being taken inwardly they cure even a <hi>Cancer</hi> or any other <hi>corroding malignant <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcer,</hi> have more then a pretence to the cure of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers</hi> in the <hi>Lungs:</hi> And if any medicament drank down into the <U+017F>tomack, doe a cure of an ulcer in the <hi>thigh</hi> or <hi>foot:</hi> why <U+017F>hould it not doe the <U+017F>ame in the <hi>Lungs?</hi> But what will the Schools doe? they continue ignorant of the Cau<U+017F>es, ignorant of the Remedies, and wavering twixt negligence and uncertainty, <U+017F>u<U+017F>pend all further enquiry; and yet confidently cry down the u<U+017F>e of <hi>Mercury diaphoretick,</hi> fixed into a <U+017F>weetne<U+017F><U+017F>e equall to that of Hony; and the volatile Tincture of <hi>Lilium</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Lilium <hi>e<U+017F>t Tinctura Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel<U+017F>i ex <U+017F>tibio<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Nam alcool <U+017F>tibii in clau<U+017F>o reverberio detinebat per m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<U+017F>em, ut evaderet leve, &amp; volaticum, prime album, inde luteum, ex quo rubrum, &amp; tandem violaceum (quod</hi> Lilium Antiquorum <hi>alii nuncupant) ex quo, per vini <U+017F>piritus ad</hi> xx. <hi>digitos affu<U+017F>os, tincturam extrahebat, <U+017F>epara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toque po<U+017F>tliminio <U+017F>piritu,</hi> Nobili<U+017F><U+017F>imam Lilii E<U+017F><U+017F>entiam <hi>paratam e<U+017F><U+017F>e dicebat, in omni morbo prae<U+017F>tanti<U+017F><U+017F>imam. Arcani hujus praeparationem Paracel<U+017F>us haufi<U+017F><U+017F>e videtur ex libris Ba<U+017F>ilii Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentini Monachi, de Antimonio; qui extarunt ante plu<U+017F>quam</hi> 200 <hi>annus.</hi>
                  </note>: as al<U+017F>o the Milke or Element of Pearle <note n="b" place="margin">Lac <hi><U+017F>ive</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Perlarum <hi>fit, cum</hi> Margaritae <hi>in lacteum querdam cremorem (ex quo prius concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F><U+017F>e meritò credantur) repetitis mult<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ties <U+017F>olutionibus, liquoris <U+017F>olutivi evaporationibus, &amp; <U+017F>piritus vit<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ioli affu<U+017F>ione, di<U+017F><U+017F>olvuntur. Cum autem</hi> Helmontius, <hi>ne procis uniones projeci<U+017F><U+017F>e videatur, eju<U+017F>modi artificium coram mundo propalare recu<U+017F>et; l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ri, poti<U+017F><U+017F>imum cui</hi> Hermetis <hi>adyta intra<U+017F><U+017F>e nondum contigit gratum fore duximus, <U+017F>i rectum ac minimè laborto<U+017F>um conficiendi Lac Margaritarum modum, paginae hujus margini in<U+017F>eramus, parcâ verborum <U+017F>erie.</hi> Margari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, <hi>in porphyrite in farinam <U+017F>eu laeverem tritas, mitte in cucurbitam. Affunde men<U+017F>truum acutum <U+017F>olvens (puta <U+017F>uccum Limonum) ut duobus digitis excedat. Claude vitrom exactè. Colloca in cineres calentes, ut <U+017F>olvantur Perlae. Si una vice id non fit, muta men<U+017F>truum; donec tota <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantia delituerit. Solutiones di<U+017F>tilla ad <U+017F>iccum. Affunde aquam <U+017F>tillatitiam dulcem. Macera: di<U+017F>tilla; quod ter repete, aut donec acrimonia abierit. Calc<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> huic affunde optimum ex malvatico vino spiritum. Digere, di<U+017F>tilla blande. Redde alium: digere, di<U+017F>tilla, idque repete donec oleo<U+017F>itas <U+017F>piritus Perlas in oleum mutaverit. Quod cum novo <U+017F>piritu digerere, &amp; per alembicum extrahere queas, tandemque ab<U+017F>tracto <U+017F>piritu, per <U+017F>e dare. Si</hi> Tabulas <hi>vis cape quantum vis: affunde <U+017F>piritum Vitrioli, &amp; fiet</hi> Lac. <hi>Ex hoc <U+017F>ecedet Calx candida. Ab<U+017F>trahe humorem, &amp; cum <U+017F>acchari Chry<U+017F>tallini q <U+017F>. aqua ro<U+017F>acea <U+017F>oluti, fac</hi> Tabulas Perlatas.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:114890:28"/>
For unle<U+017F><U+017F>e the whole body throughout be tinged or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with <U+017F>ome <hi><U+017F>upereminent Bal<U+017F>am;</hi> <U+017F>eldome or never are <hi>internall ulcers</hi> brought to <hi>Con<U+017F>olidation.</hi> And the <hi>Lungs,</hi> being a part that fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>ubmitteth to old <hi>age</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> can very hardly make a <U+017F>afe retreat back to their primitive <U+017F>trength, when once a<U+017F><U+017F>aulted by any <U+017F>trong infirmity, the Forlorne-hope of Death: but having their forces once rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ea<U+017F>ily re<U+017F>igne to the tyranny of the Conqueror; and therefore <U+017F>eldom receive any recruit or a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon remedies. ¶</p>
               <p n="44">44. Upon the reputation of which rea<U+017F>on, hath the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique errour of the Schools (who, <U+017F>ooner then they will be brought to acknowledge any <hi>deficiency</hi> in their blew and invalid <hi>Medicaments,</hi> are ready to impeach <hi>Nature</hi> her<U+017F>elfe of imperfection, and transfer the blame upon the mo<U+017F>t <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Author of Nature,</hi> by implicit accu<U+017F>ing him of <hi>improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and drow<U+017F>ie <hi>omi<U+017F><U+017F>ion)</hi> <U+017F>ucceeded even down to our daies. They po<U+017F>itively affirm (for<U+017F>ooth) that the four <hi>lobes</hi> of the lungs are, during life, unce<U+017F><U+017F>antly <hi>expanded</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ed,</hi> by a <U+017F>hort vici<U+017F><U+017F>itude of contrary motions, like a paire of Bellows, for the u<U+017F>e of <hi>Re<U+017F>piration;</hi> <U+017F>o that the Aer in<U+017F>pired, is drawn only into the Lungs, but pa<U+017F><U+017F>eth no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t. Which opinion, truely, hath been of bloody di<U+017F>advantage in the method of healing: though at the <U+017F>ame time, it <U+017F>erved the Schools of Phy<U+017F>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for a weake <U+017F>anctuary, and childi<U+017F>h eva<U+017F>ion. For upon the ince<U+017F><U+017F>ant and inexcu<U+017F>able nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of the Dilatation and Con<U+017F>triction of the lungs, or perpetuall motion of their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, have they endeavoured to contrive an excu<U+017F>e for their practice: which leaves all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>leers</hi> of the <hi>lungs,</hi> all <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>umptions</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:114890:28"/>
&amp;c. as <hi>de<U+017F>perate,</hi> and beyond the art of <hi>Ae<U+017F>culapius.</hi> Well a day, as if they could cure an <hi>ulcerous</hi> inveterate <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> or quiet <hi>Fi<U+017F>tula</hi> of the <hi>Anus,</hi> or <hi>eyes,</hi> at plea<U+017F>ure! Which Error I thus encounter. ¶</p>
               <p n="45">45. In the Aer there perpetually <U+017F>aile up and down whole Clouds of du<U+017F>t atomized; and therefore, by a continuall nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, together with our breath we <U+017F>uck in whole <U+017F>warms of the<U+017F>e du<U+017F>ty atomes: and by con<U+017F>equence, the whole cavity of the Che<U+017F>t would in a very <U+017F>hort time be filled with dirt, if nature had not provided us of lungs, in who<U+017F>e narrow Meanders, and almo<U+017F>t impervious poro<U+017F>ities, the<U+017F>e Atomes of Du<U+017F>t might be <U+017F>topt and hindered from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advance. And in this relation, the Lungs have no other way of di<U+017F>charging their excrements, but by <hi>Ex<U+017F>creation;</hi> that the du<U+017F>t drawn in together with the Aer, might be pumpt out of the Pipes of the Lungs, at the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tant the ordinary excrements of the che<U+017F>t are avoyded. A <hi>u<U+017F>e,</hi> indeed, which hath hitherto layne ob<U+017F>cure and neglected by the Schools; who have unanimou<U+017F>ly denied the Lungs to be pervious. The haire, indeed, wherewith the no<U+017F>trils are fringed, like a net, catcheth all the <U+017F>mall fibres or threds of Atomes flying in the aer, and hinders their further ingre<U+017F><U+017F>e: and the numerous folds, and annulary Cartilages of the A<U+017F>pera Arteria, are like <U+017F>o many labyrinths to arre<U+017F>t and fix the finer du<U+017F>t, that it <U+017F>inke not to the bottome of the Lungs. In order to our proofe, That <hi>the Lungs are immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> we have a very <U+017F>ufficient argument from the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned u<U+017F>e of them: and not onely that, but further al<U+017F>o, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> that the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Lungs is uncapable of <hi>Expan<U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>Con<U+017F>triction.</hi> And therefore the Lungs of <hi>Birds</hi> (<U+017F>erving to the <U+017F>ame common u<U+017F>e of re<U+017F>piration, as well in them, as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> us) in regard they are, by many vi<U+017F>ible fibres, clo<U+017F>ely annexed and chained to the ribs, cannot by <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive or reciprocall <hi>Dilatation</hi> and <hi>Con<U+017F>triction,</hi> make up the compari<U+017F>on of a pair of bellows. Again, the whole fabrick of the Lungs con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> of three large ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, or tubes, equally di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed through the whole <hi>(viz.</hi> the <hi>Arteriall Vein,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>enall Artery,</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114890:29"/>
                  <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria,</hi> or Windpipe) of a <U+017F>anguine <hi>Parenchyma,</hi> or blood concreted into a <U+017F>olid ma<U+017F><U+017F>e; and a peculiar <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane,</hi> or <U+017F>carfe en<U+017F>hrowding all the re<U+017F>t. Now the three <hi>Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els</hi> are <hi>Canals</hi> or Conduits, equally divaricated and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tributed through their whole <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance; and the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are ever repleted with blood, and therefore ab<U+017F>olutely impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible it is <U+017F>or them to receive in any of the Aer drawn in by in<U+017F>piration: but the third is ever open, filled with Aer, and <U+017F>o incapable of any new in<U+017F>pired aer, untill the aer drawn in at the la<U+017F>t dilatation of the Che<U+017F>t, be fir<U+017F>t di<U+017F>charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down into the capacity of the Che<U+017F>t; for which rea<U+017F>on, undoubtedly the a<U+017F>pera arteria, as al<U+017F>o the Membrane en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hrowding the Lungs, are full of <U+017F>mall <hi>perforations.</hi> For this third Canale, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting al<U+017F>o of Cartilagineous or gri<U+017F>tly rings, made contiguous each to other, by the intervention of a horny membrane, is ever di<U+017F>tended and open; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e then the main trunk of the Windpipe. The fourth part of the Lungs, is their parenchymatick Fle<U+017F>h, altogether as incapable to admit the advenient Aer. To conclude, the fifth part is a membrane, <U+017F>erving as a Coat to inve<U+017F>t the whole <U+017F>tructure. This <U+017F>umm'd up and con<U+017F>idered, the re<U+017F>ult mu<U+017F>t be; <hi>that no part of the Lungs bath any room to entertaine any of the <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t parcell of the Aer brought in by in<U+017F>piration: and that no part of them can, without violence and the dilacera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, endure the reciprocall motion of Dilatation and Con<U+017F>triction.</hi> A miracle it is to me, I profe<U+017F><U+017F>e, that the Schools, notwith<U+017F>tanding the uncontroulable evidence of this verity, can yet <U+017F>nort in their inveterate Lethargy: that though they <U+017F>tand convinced, and allow of all our allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as true beyond all Scepticity; yet doe they not, even to this very day, cea<U+017F>e to preach up their ab<U+017F>urd opinion, that the Lungs are continually, by a reciprocation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary motions, like tho<U+017F>e of a paire of bellows, di<U+017F>tended and recompre<U+017F><U+017F>ed. Again, the third of the<U+017F>e ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Tubes (though we <U+017F>hould grant it not to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> continually repleted with aer, but an ab<U+017F>olute vacuity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed by any aer at all) in re<U+017F>piration (when yet it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114890:29"/>
open at all times, nor can the <U+017F>ides thereof meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>concidence,</hi> like a bladder, the cartilagineous rings forbidding it) can receive onely <U+017F>uch a <hi>proportion</hi> of new aer, as may re<U+017F>pond to its <hi>capacity;</hi> but <U+017F>ince at every in<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration we draw in <U+017F>o much aer, as mu<U+017F>t fill a larger capacity, then the dimen<U+017F>ions of the whole Lungs can be extended unto: it <U+017F>eems of undeniable nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, that the aer is not in<U+017F>pired onely into the pipes of the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria,</hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves uncapable of con<U+017F>triction and dilatation, but is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried further down, even into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t. For <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> a clo<U+017F>e, when any man hath received a wound with a dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or poyniard, through the interco<U+017F>tal mu<U+017F>cles; tis di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable with half an eye, whether or no the <U+017F>tab hath pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t: for if yea, then is the aer, upon con<U+017F>triction of the Che<U+017F>t, exploded by the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the wound in <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong a <U+017F>tream, that it will blow out the flame of a candle at con<U+017F>iderable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance; which could not <U+017F>tand with po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility, if the aer attracted by in<U+017F>piration did not pa<U+017F><U+017F>e through the Lungs into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equence of this is, that the <hi>Lungs have no motion at all.</hi> A principal Argument, for the illu<U+017F>tration of this <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox,</hi> is, that in the brea<U+017F>t is <U+017F>eated a double <hi>membrane,</hi> perpendicularly inter<U+017F>ecting the cavity thereof, from the neck down to the midrife, and therefore called the <hi>Media<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> or partition wall, provided by nature to guard the heart from the injuries of aer. This <hi>Media<U+017F>tinum</hi> divides the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t into a right and left. Now mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> it is, upon the conviction of the former experiment, that the aer <U+017F>uckt in by in<U+017F>piration, is drawne directly downe into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t; as al<U+017F>o that the <hi>Lungs</hi> are, for the <U+017F>ame rea<U+017F>on, devoyd of all motion. A <U+017F>econd <hi>Argument,</hi> no le<U+017F><U+017F>e obvious or <U+017F>atisfactory, may be collected from the <hi>purulent expectorations in Pleuri<U+017F>ies.</hi> For in the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are ever rejected by cough <U+017F>uch excrements, as were fir<U+017F>t generated of blood extravenated and putrified, in the parts adjacent to the ribs, and membrane en<U+017F>hrowding the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114890:30"/>
hollow of the Che<U+017F>t: and therefore it is of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, that the coat of the Lungs mu<U+017F>t be full of con<U+017F>iderable <hi>poro<U+017F>ities,</hi> or <hi>perforations,</hi> which <U+017F>uffice to the ea<U+017F>ie tran<U+017F>mi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of blood and thick purulent matter. All the<U+017F>e things the Schools <U+017F>ee, know, confe<U+017F><U+017F>e, and write of: and yet are <U+017F>o effronted by cu<U+017F>tome, that they adventure to deny, that the aerattra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by in<U+017F>piration, is carried through the Lungs down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hollow of the Che<U+017F>t; but affirme that the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Lungs is perpetually agitated, twixt expan<U+017F>ion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, like a pair of bellows. They concede, indeed, that the Lungs have many pores or <U+017F>mall perforations, through which the extravenated blood and apo<U+017F>temated matter in Pleuri<U+017F>ies are imbibed and <U+017F>pungd up: but will by no means grant, that the more <U+017F>ubtile and penetrative Aer can be tran<U+017F>mitted through tho<U+017F>e pores into the cavity of the Che<U+017F>t. Nor is there, why we <U+017F>hould wonder at this ob<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate infatuation; <U+017F>ince they <U+017F>peculate onely <hi>dead</hi> bodies, in which the pores of the membrane inve<U+017F>ting the Lungs are clo<U+017F>ed up by the conden<U+017F>ing hand of death: and the <U+017F>ame con<U+017F>tantly happens in the <hi>optick Nerves,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>pinal marrow, inter<U+017F>tice</hi> or midle partition of the <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>orifices</hi> of the <hi>me<U+017F>araick veins</hi> looking into the guts. The Lungs of any bea<U+017F>t float upon the water, while they are boyling whole, but minced into <U+017F>mall gobbets, they pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>ink to the bottom: the rea<U+017F>on belongs to the impletion of the A<U+017F>pera arteria with aer. And if boyling water (pardon us the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinency) cannot find acce<U+017F><U+017F>e into the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Lungs, while they are decocted; which way (we be<U+017F>eech you) can the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er matter of a frigid Catarrh hope to force an entrance into it, at plea<U+017F>ure? The <U+017F>ame is al<U+017F>o de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<U+017F>trable by an <hi>experiment,</hi> as ea<U+017F>ily made as mentioned. Let any man, by a <U+017F>trong <hi>efflation,</hi> breath out all the aer in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> his che<U+017F>t, as much as po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly he can; then with a ribon mea<U+017F>ure the <hi>circumference</hi> of his body, neer the point of the <hi><U+017F>wordlike Cartilage,</hi> above the pit of the <U+017F>tomack: and again, by as <U+017F>trong <hi>inflation,</hi> fill his brea<U+017F>t with aer, and mea<U+017F>ure it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> the <U+017F>econd time, and he <U+017F>hall find, by comparing the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114890:30"/>
mea<U+017F>ures, that more aer is attracted into the che<U+017F>t by in<U+017F>piration, then can be conteined in the dimen<U+017F>ions of the Lungs. And much more, when he <U+017F>hall allow for that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of aer which tending directly downwards, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>eth the <hi>midrife</hi> upon the <hi><U+017F>tomack.</hi> Try the <U+017F>ame expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, another way; draw in <U+017F>o much breath, as you can; then blow it immediately forth into a bladder, and you <U+017F>hall finde, as before, that the <hi>quantity of aer</hi> in<U+017F>pired doth by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees exceed the <hi>magnitude</hi> of the <hi>Lungs.</hi> But in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> mean time, be plea<U+017F>ed to remember, that all the <U+017F>maller tubes of the rough Arterie, as well as the upermo<U+017F>t large canale, remain con<U+017F>tantly wide open, as being di<U+017F>tended by their Annulary Catilages, and mu<U+017F>t therefore be repleted with Aer, <U+017F>ince <hi>nature and an ab<U+017F>olute vacuity are incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> No doubt, but the belly and brea<U+017F>t owe their <hi>intume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cence</hi> to the in<U+017F>piration of aer; if therefore the Lungs were capable of di<U+017F>ten<U+017F>ion (which yet <U+017F>eems to us impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible) yet could they not be di<U+017F>tended to a capacity <U+017F>ufficient to admit the tenth part of that aer, which the <hi>Thorax</hi> upon in<U+017F>pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth ordinarily receive; allowing for that aer, which doth depre<U+017F><U+017F>e the <hi>midrife</hi> downwards, and remain in the ever di<U+017F>tended pipes of the rough <hi>Arterie,</hi> in avoydance of <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity.</hi> By inference therefore, the motion of the Thorax doth argue the motion of the Lungs unnece<U+017F><U+017F>ary. Should <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> we grant, that the Lungs could fill the whole cavity of the che<U+017F>t (which the mo<U+017F>t impudent ignorance dares not a<U+017F><U+017F>ert) then would it <U+017F>ound concordant to rea<U+017F>on, that the eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ribs <U+017F>hould dilate the Lungs: but <U+017F>ince the <hi>aer,</hi> by the laws of its con<U+017F>titution, is <U+017F>ubject to <hi>Dilatation</hi> and <hi>Compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> (as common Philo<U+017F>ophy phra<U+017F>eth it) therefore could not the elevation of the ribs draw in a <U+017F>ufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of aer. Yea, <U+017F>ince that attraction cannot but be violent (as being a <hi><U+017F>hift</hi> Nature is put upon, for the prevention of a <hi>vacuum)</hi> i. e. è diametro adver<U+017F>e to naturall and vital mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: it follows, that the <hi>motion of the ribs is not ordeined nor conductive to the dilatation of the Lungs.</hi> And <U+017F>ince the Lungs have, neither in them<U+017F>elves, nor by in<U+017F>u<U+017F>ion from any other
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114890:31"/>
part, any principle or <hi>Cau<U+017F>alitie of peculiar Motion;</hi> other then that dependent on the motion of the ribs (according to the Schools:) it re<U+017F>ults a <U+017F>erene and irrefutable truth, that they have no motion at all; but from the fir<U+017F>t to the la<U+017F>t moment of Animation, continue quiet, without <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation</hi> of <hi>Figure,</hi> or <hi>enlargement</hi> and <hi>contraction</hi> of <hi>Dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions.</hi> What clearer manife<U+017F>t of folly and invincible do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> can there be, then to confe<U+017F><U+017F>e, that all the twigs, or <U+017F>maller Canals of the rough Arterie are con<U+017F>tantly wide open, as being nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily di<U+017F>tended by the contexture of the ringlike Cartilages: and yet at the <U+017F>ame time confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to maintain, that all the <U+017F>ame Canals, upon the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and explo<U+017F>ion of aer, in the reciprocal motions of Re<U+017F>piration, are dilated and compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed? Be<U+017F>ides all this, the Schools, in their lectures, deliver it for e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>ht <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> beyond di<U+017F>pute, that the <hi>Diaphragme</hi> or midrife doth, as <hi>prime</hi> and <hi><U+017F>ole Efficient,</hi> <U+017F>uffice to the ordinary u<U+017F>e of <hi>Re<U+017F>pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and yet anon they fall foul on their own maximes, and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>titute the <hi>interco<U+017F>tal mu<U+017F>cles,</hi> as <hi>Coadjutors,</hi> or Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries, to the performance of that office. Again, there frequently ari<U+017F>e out of the <U+017F>tomack <U+017F>uch <hi>belchings,</hi> as carry along with them the lively expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions of <hi>odours</hi> formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Lungs by in<U+017F>piration: therefore are the <hi>Lungs and midrife per<U+017F>pirable,</hi> that is drild full of <U+017F>mall poro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ities. In earne<U+017F>t, tis worthy our mo<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>ionate tears, that the Schools have, for <U+017F>o many ages together, unhapily mi<U+017F>pent their <U+017F>weat and oyle, in fripperies, childi<U+017F>h page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry, and compo<U+017F>ing Romances more wild then tho<U+017F>e of the Talmud or Ario<U+017F>to. I <U+017F>hall urge another ea<U+017F>ie and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar experiment; if, in a prone decumbency, that is lying with your face to the earth, you place one hand on your belly, and the other on your ribs, and at the <U+017F>ame time draw your breath at a moderate rate, you <U+017F>hall then plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the <hi>mu<U+017F>cles of the Abdomen are the onely operators in the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e of re<U+017F>piration:</hi> that the belly being lifted up, the midrife is drawn downward; and con<U+017F>equently that the cavity of the <hi>Abdomen</hi> is by <U+017F>o much enlarged, by how
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114890:31"/>
much the plane or <hi>diameter</hi> of the midrife (in it<U+017F>elf lax and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> undi<U+017F>tended) is le<U+017F><U+017F>e then its <hi><U+017F>emicircle,</hi> when it is drawne downward, and <U+017F>o much the larger, by how much the more lax the plane of the midrife is. Nay whats more, if you bind in your ribs with a <U+017F>treight girdle, and then fetch your breath very gently, you <U+017F>hall <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly perceive the belly to be reciprocally elevated and depre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, the ribs all the while remaining quiet, without any vi<U+017F>ible motion at all; and by con<U+017F>equence, that the Lungs in this ca<U+017F>e, <U+017F>hould we grant them to move at other times (which truth forbids) can remain quiet a whole day together, if the con<U+017F>triction la<U+017F>t <U+017F>o long. But in <hi><U+017F>ighing, o<U+017F>citation, <U+017F>ternutation,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<U+017F>e</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> 
                  <hi>re<U+017F>piration,</hi> or panting for breath (and in no other ca<U+017F>e) the <hi>mu<U+017F>cles</hi> of the <hi>Thorax,</hi> running along betwixt the <hi>ribs,</hi> are <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly perceived to officiate, and by a kind of <hi><U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>titute admini<U+017F>tration,</hi> concurre to the action of re<U+017F>piration. For the ribs are <hi><U+017F>emicircles</hi> propendent downward, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into a lateral convexity; to each of which is annexed one of the <hi>interco<U+017F>tal mu<U+017F>cles,</hi> which bend them upward, and by a kind of familar violence dimini<U+017F>h their convexity in the dilatation of the Che<U+017F>t. And as they become <hi>greater,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> as to their <hi>concave,</hi> when they are bent into a <hi>diminution</hi> of their <hi>convexity;</hi> in that relation al<U+017F>o do they become <hi>roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as to the figure of the che<U+017F>t; and <U+017F>o by con<U+017F>equence make the <hi>cavity</hi> of the thorax <hi>wider.</hi> Thus Orthopneuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> men, or <U+017F>uch as by extreme difficulty in re<U+017F>piration are con<U+017F>trained to keep their bodies in an upright po<U+017F>ture, heave up their <U+017F>houlders high, every time they re<U+017F>pire, by leaning their elbows or hands hard upon the pummels of their chairs; to the end, they may in <U+017F>ome part relieve them<U+017F>elves in that extremity, by the enlargement of the che<U+017F>t, and greater detru<U+017F>ion of the midrife. A certain ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, wife to <hi>Patritius,</hi> in hard travale (for the child came <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> forth prepo<U+017F>terou<U+017F>ly, with the buttocks forward) by a large in<U+017F>piration of acr, <U+017F>triving to promote her throws, and expedite the birth, broak the <hi>membrane</hi> environing her che<U+017F>t, betwixt the <U+017F>eventh and eighth ribs; yet without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nife<U+017F>t
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114890:32"/>
<U+017F>ence of <hi>pain</hi> (for a greater pain ever ob<U+017F>cures a le<U+017F><U+017F>e) any <hi>Apo<U+017F>teme,</hi> or other <hi>Accident</hi> ordinarily <U+017F>ub<U+017F>equent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wounds or dilaceration of that <U+017F>o <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible a part. Some few dayes after her childbed, as often as <U+017F>he held her breath long, or extended her che<U+017F>t, in <U+017F>inging, panting, &amp;c. <note n="*" place="margin">A<U+017F><U+017F>ellando <hi>(ob<U+017F>caenum <U+017F>ane vocabulum, et haud raro pro congre<U+017F><U+017F>u vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo apud</hi> Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alem, <hi>alio<U+017F>que la<U+017F>civiores au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thores u<U+017F>urpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum) hic mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tiori quidem metaphra<U+017F>i,</hi> Panting <hi>redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re placuit.</hi>
                  </note> <U+017F>he felt a very large <hi>tumor</hi> of <hi>wind</hi> bunch up betwixt her ribs; which <U+017F>unk down again, when <U+017F>he compre<U+017F><U+017F>ed it with her hand, and let her che<U+017F>t fall in again at the efflation of her breath. And from that time to her death, <U+017F>he never <U+017F>lept, but with a <U+017F>wath drawne hard upon that part of her brea<U+017F>t. Which in<U+017F>tance puts it among<U+017F>t truths mo<U+017F>t manife<U+017F>t, that the aer attracted by in<U+017F>piration is carried through the Lungs into the cavity of the che<U+017F>t. The <U+017F>ame have I ob<U+017F>erved al<U+017F>o in a very <hi>Noble Lady,</hi> who got this misfortune in her tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile; that whenever <U+017F>he held her breath, <U+017F>he had one <U+017F>ide of her throat blowne up, like a bladder di<U+017F>tended with aer, to <U+017F>uch a mon<U+017F>trous greatne<U+017F><U+017F>e, that no care or art could <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="T"/> conceal it from the <U+017F>tanders by. It makes very much al<U+017F>o to our pre<U+017F>ent purpo<U+017F>e, that I have, with mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>erious attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> con<U+017F>idered all <hi>Pulmoniacal</hi> and <hi>A<U+017F>thmatick</hi> Patients, and found, that, for the plurality, they <U+017F>leep with great ea<U+017F>e and quiet on one <U+017F>ide, and can hardly fetch their breath on the other. For we have no rea<U+017F>on to doubt, but this maladie is <hi>Idiopathical</hi> to the Lungs, <hi>i. e.</hi> not occa<U+017F>ioned by <hi>deuterapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> or con<U+017F>ent with any other mi<U+017F>affected part: as al<U+017F>o, that in that <U+017F>ide of the Lungs, which re<U+017F>pecteth the prone <U+017F>ide on which the <U+017F>ick man then lies, and which mu<U+017F>t in that prone po<U+017F>ition bob and fret again<U+017F>t the membrane lining the che<U+017F>t, tho<U+017F>e <hi>pores</hi> are <hi>con<U+017F>tipated</hi> or ob<U+017F>tructed, through which the aer u<U+017F>ed to be tran<U+017F>mitted into the cavity of the che<U+017F>t: and moreover, that the pores of either Lobe of the Lungs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon or facing the downward <U+017F>ide, are either all, or at le<U+017F>t the greate<U+017F>t part of them (which we may know by ob<U+017F>erving the degrees of extraordinary re<U+017F>piration; for the more or le<U+017F><U+017F>e difficulty of re<U+017F>piration, may be a certain rule to direct our compute of the greater or le<U+017F><U+017F>er number of pores ob<U+017F>tructed) by <U+017F>ome lap<U+017F>e of providence in di<U+017F>ordered
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114890:32"/>
nature, or forreigne contingency ob<U+017F>tructed. By which Argument it is manife<U+017F>t, that the <hi>Lungs</hi> are not <hi>Expanded</hi> and <hi>Contracted,</hi> like bellows, but <hi>pervious</hi> and tran<U+017F>pirable, by rea<U+017F>on of their numerous perforations: through which the aer <U+017F>moothly gliding into the hollow of the che<U+017F>t, doth con<U+017F>tantly hold an equal proportion to the magnitude thereof, as well in its <hi>diduction</hi> as <hi>contraction.</hi> And hence is it, that men <U+017F>ick of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in the Lungs draw their breath more ea<U+017F>ily when they <hi><U+017F>it up,</hi> then when they <hi>lye down:</hi> for the Lungs, when they hang directly downward in a free <hi>pendulous po<U+017F>ition,</hi> have on all <U+017F>ides tho<U+017F>e pores open and fit for the <hi>tran<U+017F>vection</hi> of <hi>aer,</hi> which have not yet <U+017F>ubmitted to the oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of <hi>ob<U+017F>tructions.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p n="48">48. Beyond all excu<U+017F>e therefore do the Schools erre, when they deliver, as an oraculous truth, that the <hi>midrife is the <U+017F>ole and prime Motor of the Lungs;</hi> and, in that relation, the <hi>proper and principiative efficient of Re<U+017F>piration.</hi> More particularly, that when the midrife doth <hi>contract</hi> it<U+017F>elf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its own <hi>Center,</hi> it then makes the <hi>Expiration;</hi> but when it relaxes toward the <hi>Circumference,</hi> the <hi>In<U+017F>piration:</hi> and <U+017F>o the quantity of aer in<U+017F>pired mu<U+017F>t in exact proportion re<U+017F>pond to the mea<U+017F>ure of the midrifes <hi>expan<U+017F>ion</hi> or relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Our rea<U+017F>ons the<U+017F>e, 1. Since all <hi>voluntary Motion</hi> is performed by a <hi>Mu<U+017F>cle,</hi> as the part <U+017F>olely and principally adapted by <hi>Nature</hi> to that action, by a <hi>retraction</hi> of the <hi>taile</hi> toward the <hi>head</hi> thereof; therefore, if their opinion <U+017F>tand allied to verity, mu<U+017F>t the <hi>midrife</hi> be a <hi>prime, heteroclite,</hi> and mo<U+017F>t <hi>principal Mu<U+017F>cle,</hi> and the <hi>head</hi> thereof <U+017F>eated in its <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 2. If the midrife be an organ primarily executive of motion; then, though the Mu<U+017F>cles both of the Abdomen and ribs cea<U+017F>e from all Contraction and relaxation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves, would the midrife maintain the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive motions of re<U+017F>piration, by its own <hi><U+017F>ingle power:</hi> Which experiment po<U+017F>itively denies. 3. Yea the mu<U+017F>cles of the Abdomen, which are ordinary mu<U+017F>cles, would have no motion proper to them<U+017F>elves, but be moved, at <U+017F>econd hand, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious motion of the midrife. 4. Vain and u<U+017F>ele<U+017F><U+017F>e would
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114890:33"/>
the contrivement of nature be, and her architecture imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in <U+017F>uperfluity, in making the abdominal mu<U+017F>cles; and the belly might have as conveniently been cloathed with the <U+017F>ingle coat of the Carnous Membrane, as with the bomba<U+017F>t and duplications of <U+017F>o many mu<U+017F>cles. 5. Since every organ of Voluntary motion doth execute its function by <hi>Traction,</hi> or drawing the part, into which its <hi>tendon</hi> is in<U+017F>erted, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it<U+017F>elf; the brea<U+017F>t, according to this error of the Schools, would be drawne very much inward by the <hi>Traction</hi> of the midrife, and the <hi>wa<U+017F>t</hi> convelled into the dwindling figure of an Houregla<U+017F><U+017F>e. <note n="*" place="margin">Clep<U+017F>ydra <hi>in archetypo: quaee<U+017F>t organum quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam artificiale, quo ex aqua, de vitro in vitrum deor<U+017F>um, per ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile foramen, gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatim de<U+017F>til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante, horas metiri <U+017F>olebant antiqui. Hodie vero, hominum ingeniis ad nobiliores machinationes feliciter provectis, exole<U+017F>cunt Clep<U+017F>ydrae; hi<U+017F>que <U+017F>uper venere</hi> Clep<U+017F>ammidia, <hi>quibus horas men<U+017F>uramus per <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffluxum Arenae: ut &amp;</hi> Horologia Automata, <hi>quorum orbiculi <U+017F>erratim dentati (graece</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ut</hi> Ari<U+017F>t. Mechanic.) <hi><U+017F>e<U+017F>e mutuò protrudentes, vel á chalybe arcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atim ten<U+017F>o, &amp; machinae infixo, vel ponderibus appen<U+017F>is circumgyrantur.</hi>
                  </note> 6. Further, the <hi>Expiration</hi> would not be a <hi>quiet</hi> or ce<U+017F><U+017F>ation from motion; but an ab<U+017F>olute <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the midrife contracted. 7. And <U+017F>o the <hi>Expiration</hi> would, even in mo<U+017F>t healthy men, be more difficult and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious then the <hi>In<U+017F>piration;</hi> 8. Since then the <hi>In<U+017F>piration</hi> would not be a <hi>motion,</hi> but a relaxion or <hi>quiet</hi> of the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife from its Contraction. ¶</p>
               <p n="49">49. Hence upon rationall deduction I conclude, 1. That the true and proper u<U+017F>e of the Midrife hath hitherto remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unknown. 2. That the u<U+017F>e of the Lungs hath never yet been met with, by the too lazy and jejune <U+017F>crutinies of the Schooles. 3. That the exact manner and rea<U+017F>on of Re<U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hath al<U+017F>o e<U+017F>caped the vulgar exploration of Anthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologi<U+017F>ts. 4. That Anatomi<U+017F>ts have never made a ju<U+017F>t and perfect di<U+017F>covery, which are the prime and principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>truments of re<U+017F>piration. 5. That the mu<U+017F>cles of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domen doe alone <U+017F>uffice to maintain ordinary and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate re<U+017F>piration. 6. That the Lungs are never moved by any naturall expan<U+017F>ion and Compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of their <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance; but <U+017F>erve onely as a <U+017F>ieve, or <hi>pecolatory,</hi> for the <U+017F>eque<U+017F>tration of the atomes of du<U+017F>t from the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>imple and pure aer, which is immediately tran<U+017F>mitted into the concave of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114890:33"/>
Che<U+017F>t. 7. That the deplorable difficulty of curing di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in the Lungs, e<U+017F>pecially where their <hi>Continuity</hi> is <hi>infringed,</hi> doth not ari<U+017F>e from this, that they are unce<U+017F><U+017F>antly agitated by a vici<U+017F><U+017F>itude of <hi>Compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>Expan<U+017F>ion,</hi> and in that re<U+017F>pect de<U+017F>titute of that re<U+017F>t and <hi>quiet,</hi> which is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to the <hi>con<U+017F>olidation</hi> of a <hi>di<U+017F>union</hi> (which hath ever been allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and admitted as an excu<U+017F>e for the languid and ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall operation of vulgar remedies) but from hence, that the <U+017F>mall <hi>apertures</hi> or extreme orifices of their perforations are blockt up by <hi>ob<U+017F>tructions,</hi> who<U+017F>e remove is a task too difficult for the infirme fingers of common pulmonary me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ments, and onely to be hoped for from the Herculean energy of <U+017F>ome <hi>Chymicall Panchre<U+017F>ton</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">An univer<U+017F>all Medicine.</note>. To which we may <U+017F>ubjoyn, that nothing, be<U+017F>ides <hi>aer,</hi> can arrive at the extreme pores of the Lungs, and that aer is, by rea<U+017F>on of the <hi>oppila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> there arre<U+017F>ted, and impri<U+017F>oned, and doth al<U+017F>o by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees <hi>ex<U+017F>iecare</hi> the ob<U+017F>tructing glutinous humors. From which depraved root there <U+017F>prings up a whole grove of preternaturall <hi>productions</hi> which in their maturity put on the de<U+017F>tructive blo<U+017F><U+017F>omes of <hi>Aridity, Acrimony,</hi> and <hi>Malignity:</hi> and in the <hi><U+017F>ummer</hi> or ripening of the<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>eeds</hi> of evill (which mu<U+017F>t, alas, be the <hi>autumne</hi> of <hi>life)</hi> there mu<U+017F>t grow a <hi>race<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> or bunch of de<U+017F>perate <hi>Accidents,</hi> <U+017F>uch as extreame anxiety in re<U+017F>piration, Apo<U+017F>tems of the Lungs, exe<U+017F>ion or corro<U+017F>ion of their ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, <U+017F>pitting of blood, ulceration, con<U+017F>umption, and in the cata<U+017F>trophe Death. For let us <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, that all the aer attracted by the expan<U+017F>ion of the Che<U+017F>t, is ordinarily tran<U+017F>mitted into the capacity thereof, through a <hi>thou<U+017F>and</hi> minute <hi>tubes</hi> or divarications of the <hi>A<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera Arteria;</hi> and that this ju<U+017F>t number of perforations in the Lungs is <U+017F>ufficient to the con<U+017F>ervation of health, as to the intere<U+017F>t of <hi>re<U+017F>piration:</hi> if therefore but a <hi>hundred</hi> of the<U+017F>e be <U+017F>topt up by <hi>ob<U+017F>tructions,</hi> then mu<U+017F>t the party <U+017F>uffering this con<U+017F>tipation, become, by one <hi>tenth part,</hi> more <U+017F>hortwinded, in long and inten<U+017F>e motion, or a<U+017F>cending up hill, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e he ought to be. ¶</p>
               <p n="50">50. From this advantage we have a cleare and un-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114890:34"/>
pro<U+017F>pect into the field of <hi>Pulmonary remedies,</hi> and may at fir<U+017F>t glance di<U+017F>cover, that <hi>Syrups, Lambatives, Loochs, &amp;c.</hi> are lame and de<U+017F>picable reliefes of nature; <U+017F>ince they never <hi>arrive at the parts di<U+017F>tre<U+017F><U+017F>ed,</hi> but are either <hi>diverted</hi> into the <U+017F>tomack, inte<U+017F>tines and other places wholy unconcerned in their operations; or <U+017F>o <hi>impaired</hi> in their <hi>activity</hi> by a tedious pilgrimage through many Concoctions and tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutations, that they lo<U+017F>e their primitive faculties, and grow too languid and evirate to encounter the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e. Nay what's more <U+017F>ad, that if they did arrive in the zenith of their <hi><U+017F>eminal</hi> powers and unrefracted qualities at the camp of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e: yet, like cowardly and treacherous <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> they would <hi>aggravate</hi> the charge of Nature, and <hi>ruine</hi> that part, who<U+017F>e <hi>a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance</hi> they pretend. Here al<U+017F>o our enquiry meets a han<U+017F>ome argument, why no one of the forementioned infirmities of the Lungs may hope a Cure from any Plant in the Phy<U+017F>icians garden, or Confection in the Apothecaries <U+017F>hop; unle<U+017F><U+017F>e <hi>Fire,</hi> di<U+017F>creetly governed by the learned hand of <hi>Chymi<U+017F>try,</hi> and blown into a temper <U+017F>uitable to that <hi>Ignis non lucens,</hi> or invi<U+017F>ible flame irradiating all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of frigid Clay, <U+017F>hall <hi>graduate</hi> <U+017F>ome medicament into a Noble <hi>Entelechie,</hi> and make its <hi>bal<U+017F>ame</hi> friendly and familiar to the principles of life, as natures own.</p>
               <p n="51">51. But as for tho<U+017F>e <hi>Precautions</hi> of <hi>Catarrbs,</hi> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne the u<U+017F>e of <hi>Coriander <U+017F>eed,</hi> and other <U+017F>uch vain foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, after <U+017F>upper, for the prevention of fumes ari<U+017F>ing out of the <U+017F>tomack; how much more worthily, in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <U+017F>ober rea<U+017F>on, doe they de<U+017F>erve our <hi>pitty,</hi> then our <hi>confidence?</hi> For if the <hi>generation</hi> of vapours, from their cau<U+017F>es <hi>(humidity</hi> as the <hi>material,</hi> and the innate <hi>heat</hi> of the <U+017F>tomack, the <hi>efficient)</hi> and their <hi>a<U+017F>cention</hi> be naturall; what can <hi>Coriander</hi> doe to hinder that the<U+017F>e naturall <hi>effects</hi> <U+017F>hould not follow on the neck of their <hi>cau<U+017F>es?</hi> Can <hi>Coriander</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>per<U+017F>ed upon boyling water in any <U+017F>mall neckt ve<U+017F><U+017F>ell, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede the exhalation or a<U+017F>cention of vapours out of the water? At the <U+017F>ame rate let us pri<U+017F>e tho<U+017F>e magnified trifles and <U+017F>erious nothings of the Schools, when they with great
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114890:34"/>
ceremony pre<U+017F>cribe, that the haire mu<U+017F>t not be kembed, nor the head rubbed at <hi>night,</hi> but <hi>morn</hi> (for<U+017F>ooth) not towards the <hi>forehead,</hi> but <hi>backward;</hi> le<U+017F>t Catarrhs, obeying the <hi>po<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional friction,</hi> be drawn forward. Nor doe we want ju<U+017F>t cau<U+017F>e for our complaint, that both Gates leading into the divine Temple of Ae<U+017F>culapius are blockt up by heaps of fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Chimaera's and the fabulous traditions of doting bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dames; <U+017F>ince the true and proxime <hi>cau<U+017F>es</hi> of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es have to this very day, remained lockt up in the dark of undi<U+017F>covery: nor have tho<U+017F>e <hi>Moles in Philo<U+017F>ophy</hi> ever digged deep enough into the Center of their <hi>Seminalities</hi> and fir<U+017F>t <hi>principles,</hi> or <U+017F>weat <U+017F>ufficiently in their exantlation.</p>
               <p n="52">52. For how frivolous is the doctrine of <hi>Galen,</hi> through all his five books of the <hi>Con<U+017F>ervation of health?</hi> In all which long and hollow tract you <U+017F>hall hear of nothing, but the echo's of <hi>Baths, Frictions,</hi> and <hi>Apotherapia</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Apoteraxia <hi>in<U+017F>cribitur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplari Elzevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranio; <U+017F>ed vel ex Helmontii calamo ad alia ocyùs fe<U+017F>tinante, vel compo<U+017F>itoris incuria, hoc vitium <U+017F>uam duxi<U+017F><U+017F>e origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem con<U+017F>enta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum e<U+017F>t. Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum enim vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulum tale (quod <U+017F>ciam) apud Galenum reperire<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> e<U+017F>t:</hi> Apotherapia <hi>autem quam plurimu in locis eju<U+017F>dem</hi> lib. de Con<U+017F>. <U+017F>anit. u<U+017F>urpatur, <hi>cujus proprius <U+017F>copus e<U+017F>t, ut la<U+017F><U+017F>itudinem, quae immodico exercitio <U+017F>uccedere <U+017F>olet, admoto oleo, <U+017F>ubmoveat atque prohibeat.</hi> Con<U+017F>ul. Galen. lib. de <U+017F>an. tuend. 2. cap. 6. &amp; 3. cap. 2.</note>, or Unction after violent and athletick exerci<U+017F>e. And though I have with commi<U+017F>eration ob<U+017F>erved the poverty and barrenne<U+017F><U+017F>e of <hi>Galen</hi> generally diffu<U+017F>ed through all his longwinded di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>es; yet in no one piece of his voluminous workes have I more manife<U+017F>tly taken the altitude of his <hi>wit,</hi> then where with extreme <U+017F>eriou<U+017F>ne<U+017F><U+017F>e, he pre<U+017F>cribes the <U+017F>everall di<U+017F>tinctions of <hi>po<U+017F>itionall Frictions</hi> to be u<U+017F>ed (for<U+017F>ooth) <hi>longwaies, tran<U+017F>ver<U+017F>e, oblique,</hi> and <hi>circular;</hi> and the<U+017F>e, like the ridiculous Ceremonics of <hi>Necromancers,</hi> to be ob<U+017F>erved with punctual and <U+017F>trict obedience, under no le<U+017F><U+017F>e then capitall penalty. For <hi>Rome</hi> was infe<U+017F>ted with fewer di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and tho<U+017F>e more gentle and benigne, and warmed her<U+017F>elfe at fewer funeral fires, in her fir<U+017F>t five innocent and growing Centuries; then after <U+017F>he had triumphed over conquered <hi>Greece,</hi> and among other Trophies brought home the <U+017F>atall and infectious <hi>Libraries</hi> of <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians.</hi> And all <hi>Europaeans,</hi> who harbour few or no Phy<U+017F>icians, will, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy to their experience, confirme the <U+017F>ame.</p>
               <p n="53">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:114890:35"/>
53. The Schools with <U+017F>erious gravity wonder, that <U+017F>o va<U+017F>t a quantity of <hi>Muccus,</hi> or glutinous gelly, <U+017F>hould ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily be avoyded by <U+017F>tool, upon the operation of <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida;</hi> and yet that the quantity of <hi>expectorations</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of the Lung, <U+017F>hould be thereby no whit dimini<U+017F>hed: and <U+017F>o while with in<U+017F>olent o<U+017F>tentation, they glory that they have found out the <hi>Antecedent cau<U+017F>e of Defluxions;</hi> at the <U+017F>ame time enchanted by the effects of <hi>Purgatives,</hi> they will by no force of argument be brought to confe<U+017F><U+017F>e the fal<U+017F>ity of their <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> axioms. Now <hi>Coloquintida, Seammony, Elaterium, &amp;c. dry</hi> the body more in one day, then the <hi>Decoction</hi> of <hi>China</hi> can in three moneths. What benefit then can, in rea<U+017F>on, be hoped from <hi>China,</hi> where more ex<U+017F>iccating <hi>Purgatives</hi> confe<U+017F><U+017F>e their invalidity: and their u<U+017F>e mu<U+017F>t needs be <hi>horrid?</hi> From this, who <U+017F>o purblind in his under<U+017F>tanding, as not to <U+017F>ee, that the paedantick Schools, adhering to the doctrines of their <hi>Ance<U+017F>tors,</hi> have <U+017F>et up their re<U+017F>t in this, that <hi>the writings of the antient Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks ought to be their Ne ultra in Philo<U+017F>ophy;</hi> that they are not obliged to any deeper di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions, or further explorations, but onely to order their Cures, according to the antique and thredbare <hi>Theorems</hi> of <hi>Phy<U+017F>ick.</hi> And though they cannot but ob<U+017F>erve their <hi>Practice</hi> <U+017F>hame their <hi>confidence,</hi> and the <hi><U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> fall <U+017F>hort of what their <U+017F>pecious <hi>Canons</hi> promi<U+017F>e: yet doe they not blu<U+017F>h to veile over their bloody ignorance, nor feel compunction at their inhumane re<U+017F>olve, that they had rather their afflicted Patients <U+017F>hould <U+017F>till remain <U+017F>u<U+017F>pended betwixt the calamities of the <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e,</hi> on one <U+017F>ide, and the more murderous tortures of their <hi>Purgers,</hi> on the other; then take the pains to <U+017F>tudy and explore any more rational and probable means of their redre<U+017F><U+017F>e. And, <U+017F>ober truth makes me confe<U+017F><U+017F>e it, <U+017F>o many Myriads of <hi>Incogitancies</hi> and <hi>Ab<U+017F>urdities,</hi> could never have thus long continued in the Schools, con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of men <U+017F>o acute, judicious, prudent, and experienced (among whom I as willingly as ju<U+017F>tly confe<U+017F><U+017F>e my <U+017F>elfe the mo<U+017F>t de<U+017F>picable and unworthy) had they been plea<U+017F>ed to abate any thing of their implicite <hi><U+017F>ub<U+017F>cription,</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:114890:35"/>
and recede the le<U+017F>t <U+017F>tep from the <hi>Axioms</hi> of <hi>Pagans.</hi> But, alas, they are clo<U+017F>ely be<U+017F>ieged by the grand <hi>enemy</hi> of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive truth; who holds them captived to the tyranny of his <hi>Delu<U+017F>ions,</hi> by the chain either of <hi>Arrogancy, Incircum<U+017F>pecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Cruelty, Avarice, Lazine<U+017F><U+017F>e, Stupidity,</hi> or, in fine, of <hi><U+017F>hame</hi> to be reformed. Good Je<U+017F>u! when wilt thou be plea<U+017F>ed to ca<U+017F>t this devil out of the Schools? when will the mea<U+017F>ure of the<U+017F>e fatall evils be full, and the Vintage of the<U+017F>e <U+017F>oure Grapes come; that, at length, by the comfortable <U+017F>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hine of thy truth, this Aegyptian night may be exhaled, and this mi<U+017F>t of horrid calamities that <U+017F>its heavy on the heads of all the wretched <U+017F>onnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> be di<U+017F>pelled? Thy an<U+017F>wer is, there can be no remedy for his blindne<U+017F><U+017F>e, who wilfully and <U+017F>tubbornly <U+017F>huts his eyes again<U+017F>t the light of a confe<U+017F><U+017F>ed verity. Therefore,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ju<U+017F>t God!</hi> all things are ju<U+017F>t, thou do<U+017F>t approve;</l>
                  <l>Thou unmov'd <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Font</hi> of <hi>Love!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <U+017F>ince we <U+017F>corn'd thy wi<U+017F>er <hi>Lawes</hi> t'obey</l>
                  <l>Wee'r made to <hi>Fools</hi> a <hi>Scorn,</hi> to <hi>Quacks</hi> a <hi>Prey.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p n="54">54. Some <hi>Anatomi<U+017F>ts</hi> there are who have di<U+017F><U+017F>ected a living Dog; and when they came to the <hi>Larynx,</hi> drenched him with milke, or other broth, tinged with <hi>Saffron</hi> or <hi>Bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniack,</hi> to the end they might perceive whether any part of the liquor entered the lungs: and found that a very <U+017F>mall quantity thereof gave a tincture to the <U+017F>ides of the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria.</hi> On this they cried out, that there mu<U+017F>t be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>en<U+017F>ible and ordinary de<U+017F>cent of excrements from the brain into the Lungs; and enacted for an e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>ht truth, that <hi>Lambatives,</hi> <U+017F>ince they are carried immediately into the <hi>Larynx,</hi> and thence <U+017F>lide down into all the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>lender and remote <hi>tubes</hi> of the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be the <U+017F>ole and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme remedy of <hi>Con<U+017F>umtions,</hi> and the mo<U+017F>t prevalent means to Con<U+017F>olidate <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers</hi> in the Lungs. An experiment, in troth, of very much <hi>cruelty</hi> to the <hi>Dogge;</hi> but of farre more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and unhappy con<U+017F>equence to <hi>Man:</hi> <U+017F>ince, at the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>wa<U+017F>ion hereof, the Schools have delivered it from hand
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114890:36"/>
to hand <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hic Author proculdubio al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<U+017F>it ad</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Antiquorum, â</hi> Pau<U+017F>an. <hi><U+017F>ic de<U+017F>criptam. In Academia Promethei ara e<U+017F>t: unde homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in urbem accen<U+017F>as lampadas ferentes decurrunt. Sequiturque victoria eum qui facem accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>am con<U+017F>ervarit; nam <U+017F>i extincta fuerit, alteri <U+017F>uccedenti ea traditur: eademque ratione tertio <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ori, <U+017F>i <U+017F>ecundus non pervenerit ad metam, cum lampade accen<U+017F>a. Quod <U+017F>i nemini ardentem deferre licuerit, palma in medio relinquitur.</hi>
                  </note> down to po<U+017F>terity, as an impraegnable verity; and making erroneous and unju<U+017F>ti<U+017F>iable inductions upon mi<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and onely imaginary po<U+017F>itions, have <U+017F>ub<U+017F>cribed unto fopperies <U+017F>o pernicious.</p>
               <p>For, Fir<U+017F>t, what can they expect that <hi>Syrups</hi> and <hi>Lamba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> <U+017F>hould doe, in the <U+017F>lender branches or divarications of the <hi>A<U+017F>pera Arteria,</hi> more then inevitably introduce the mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe of <hi>ob<U+017F>tructions?</hi> To what end, therefore, <U+017F>hould the<U+017F>e ful<U+017F>ome <hi>Loochs</hi> naturally and ordinarily affect that way of de<U+017F>cent into the lungs, or be tran<U+017F>mitted thither, or there entertained? <U+017F>ince in that place they can neither be dige<U+017F>ted, nor changed into good and nutritive or bal<U+017F>amicall juyce; nor yet conduce to the cure of either the purulent effluxions from ulcers, or vi<U+017F>cid Muccus expectorated. And further, if <U+017F>ome part of our liquor <U+017F>hould ordinarily drop into the lungs, then would the ordinary <hi><U+017F>pitle</hi> of healthy men <hi><U+017F>avour</hi> of the <hi>broths</hi> eaten, or <hi><U+017F>yrups</hi> lickt down. And although our fir<U+017F>t <hi><U+017F>pitle</hi> <U+017F>ometimes reli<U+017F>h of the <hi><U+017F>yrups,</hi> or other liquid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, newly <U+017F>wallowed down; yet <U+017F>uch ari<U+017F>eth not from the <hi>Lungs,</hi> but <hi>Palate</hi> and other parts <U+017F>eated in vicinity to the jawes: nor doe the <U+017F>ucceeding <U+017F>alivous rejections, for that rea<U+017F>on, confe<U+017F><U+017F>e an inquination or tincture of <U+017F>uch <hi>Lambatives,</hi> as in another ca<U+017F>e the <U+017F>ucceeding <U+017F>pitle returns fuliginous exhalations or <hi>fumes,</hi> received into the Lungs, a good while after their fir<U+017F>t admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion. Again, were this fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zible, then would any man, who <U+017F>hould lick up <U+017F>everall ounces of Syrup, in one evening, be, ere many minuts, reduced to the bo<U+017F>ome of his cold grandmother, by the inevitable de<U+017F>truction not onely of an <hi>A<U+017F>thma,</hi> but even of <hi><U+017F>uffocation</hi> en<U+017F>uing; for a part of tho<U+017F>e Syrups mu<U+017F>t fill up and choak the great pipe or cavity of the rough arterie. Seriou<U+017F>ly, our wonder may be excu<U+017F>ed, if we <U+017F>tand amazed,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114890:36"/>
how the Schools, <U+017F>educed by <U+017F>o blew and dull an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Dogge, have baulked the ob<U+017F>ervation, that this coloured broth, or Milk died with Saffron, was rapt down in the Larynx, not by the ordinary way of Deglutition; but <hi>unawares</hi> and <hi>preposterou<U+017F>ly,</hi> the poore di<U+017F>tracted animal howling amids his torments, and <U+017F>o opening the <hi>Epiglottis.</hi> Not that the <U+017F>ame is done of cu<U+017F>tome in <hi>healthy,</hi> or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ob<U+017F>erved in <hi>rheumatick</hi> per<U+017F>ons. For preci<U+017F>ely, if a man in an extreme fit of the <hi><U+017F>tone,</hi> endeavouring to make water, doth chance unwittingly to open the porthole of his ar<U+017F>e, and confront an Iri<U+017F>h man; mu<U+017F>t it therefore be the proper function of the <hi>Sphincter</hi> of the bladder, when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxeth it <U+017F>elfe, and gives way to the efflux of the urine, ordinarily al<U+017F>o to unlock the <U+017F>phincter of the <hi>port Ae<U+017F>quiline?</hi> For tis no rarity, for parts of the body, when their oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is infringed and di<U+017F>turbed into tumult and confu<U+017F>ion, by exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive <hi>pain</hi> and torture, to perform their functions <hi>depravedly;</hi> and draw other parts al<U+017F>o, to which they are allied by vicinity of <U+017F>ituation, or connexion, into the <U+017F>ame <hi>di<U+017F>order</hi> and irregularity. Their beliefe had been more <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely placed upon that <hi>Hi<U+017F>tory</hi> of one <U+017F>uffocated with a <U+017F>mall <hi>fether,</hi> and of another with a <hi>haire,</hi> unfortunately <U+017F>lipping into the rough arterie. For <U+017F>o had they <U+017F>tood confirmed, without di<U+017F>pute or hae<U+017F>itancy, that <hi>the Lungs can never admit any forraigne intru<U+017F>ion,</hi> or receive the <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t grain, without con<U+017F>iderable dammage and hazardous anx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iety; nay that <U+017F>uch as are afflicted with <hi>difficulty</hi> of <hi>re<U+017F>pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> can by no means endure <U+017F>o much as <hi>fragrant <U+017F>uffumiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> for rea<U+017F>ons alledged by us, in our di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e <hi>de Blas humano</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Blas <hi>importat vim</hi> Motus, <hi>tum</hi> Localis, <hi>tum</hi> Alterativi; <hi>idque nedum</hi> <U+017F>uperis, <hi>e<U+017F>t eti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</hi> inferis. Blas Humanum <hi>verò duplex con<U+017F>tituitur apud</hi> Helmontium <hi>no<U+017F>trum. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>num nempe</hi> Naturale, <hi>quod <U+017F>ingulis vi<U+017F>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, prima ex conformatione, implantatum radicaliter, per energiam radialem, vel effluvium incorporeum, in partes <U+017F>ui regimini conf<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gnatas, agit <U+017F>treu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>è &amp; monarchialiter: hoc e<U+017F>t, pote<U+017F>tate ab<U+017F>oluta, independenti, non locorum vicmitati, connexion<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, aut <U+017F>upinitati obligata, &amp; quolibet corporis <U+017F>itu aequè truculentèr. Per exemplum. In Foemina hy<U+017F>terica, ex utero (cujus <U+017F>ceptro univer<U+017F>am <U+017F>oeminei <U+017F>exus oeconomiam, ab<U+017F>olute <U+017F>ubditam, <U+017F>eriò contendit</hi> Helmont) <hi>in<U+017F>piratur</hi> blas pote<U+017F>tativ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in reliqua vi<U+017F>cerum, quod <U+017F>itum eorundem primigeneum, figuram, officiae, imò &amp; cra<U+017F>in etiam nativam mutet penitus, alienetque pro <U+017F>ui arbitrio. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nde huic utiqu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> radiali</hi> Regiminis actioni, <hi>nequaquam autem putaticiis <U+017F>cholarum vaporibus, humorumve reverà non-entium exhalationibus, quocunque etiam mia<U+017F>mate contagio<U+017F>o impraegnatis, ritè condonan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das decrevit qua<U+017F>libet uteri exorbitationes atque indignationes. Alio<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> perinde huju<U+017F>cemodi</hi> Blas Humani Naturalis <hi>effectus, nobis evidenter <U+017F>atis con<U+017F>piciendos exhibuit ip<U+017F>a Natura, in <U+017F>ingulis</hi> Dige<U+017F>tionum <hi>officinis. E<U+017F>t namque con<U+017F>tans Authoris dogma,</hi> Fel <hi>&amp;</hi> jecur <hi><U+017F>ua per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere munia, non quidem corporali contactu, congre<U+017F><U+017F>u, aut commi<U+017F>tione <U+017F>ui; nec denique am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectendo &amp; recipiendo <U+017F>uum intra gremium: a<U+017F>t per</hi> Aporrhaeas incorporeas, <hi>influxum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialem, <U+017F>ive</hi> Fermentum in<U+017F>piratum. <hi>Fel enim dimittit fermentale blas in inte<U+017F>tina: &amp; jecur <U+017F>uum in venas me<U+017F>enterii. Alterum</hi> Voluntarium: <hi>quod per internum velle <U+017F>ibi motor exi<U+017F>tit, <U+017F>ive quod voluntate animalium ad motum localem dirigitur. Huic autem the<U+017F>i, <U+017F>at firmo tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam fundamini,</hi> Helmont <hi><U+017F>uper<U+017F>truxit <U+017F>uum ariem, ad i<U+017F>tud <U+017F>cholarum axioma diruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, quo incautae admodum docuere;</hi> In omni motu locali <U+017F>tatuendum de nece<U+017F><U+017F>itate pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum motorem immobilem<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
                     <hi>In <U+017F>uo namque tramite, cui titulus</hi> Blas Humanum, <hi>ab illo <U+017F>at demon<U+017F>tratum exi<U+017F>timo, aliquid e<U+017F><U+017F>e in <U+017F>ublunaribus, quod <U+017F>eip<U+017F>um localiter &amp; alterative moveat, ab que Coelorum Blas, &amp; motore immobili naturali.</hi> Voluntas <hi>enim primum e<U+017F>t eju<U+017F>modi movens. movetque <U+017F>eip<U+017F>um quoque</hi> Ens Seminale, <hi>tam in <U+017F>eminibus, quam horum con<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis. Hinc in<U+017F>uper quaecunque In<U+017F>en<U+017F>itiva moventur, per quandam veluti Naturae</hi> Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem <hi>moventur, habentque <U+017F>aas naturales nece<U+017F><U+017F>itates &amp; fines. Fu<U+017F>ior hujus paradoxi expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio petatur ab ip<U+017F>o Authore.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:114890:37"/>
If therefore <hi>Suffumigations</hi> and <hi>aromatick exhalations,</hi> <U+017F>uch as promi<U+017F>e a gratefull <U+017F>uccour to the Lungs in their oppre<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions, be injurious and burden<U+017F>ome; what will not gro<U+017F><U+017F>er and <hi><U+017F>limy Lambatives</hi> do, though we grant them to arrive at the lower ve<U+017F><U+017F>els of the lungs, with all their vertue and efficacy about them? No man, that ever <U+017F>aw but one di<U+017F><U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, will deny, that when ever any thing is <U+017F>wallowed down into the <U+017F>tomack, at the <U+017F>ame in<U+017F>tant the <hi>Larynx</hi> is <U+017F>hut clo<U+017F>e by the <hi>Epiglottis,</hi> or trap doore, that carries the figure of an <hi>Ivy-leafe;</hi> <U+017F>o that not the <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t atome can <U+017F>lip into the Lungs. And I have known <U+017F>ome men <hi><U+017F>trangled,</hi> who had their Epiglottis not <U+017F>hut <U+017F>ufficiently clo<U+017F>e but on one <U+017F>ide, by rea<U+017F>on of a <hi>Convul<U+017F>ion</hi> of one part, and a re<U+017F>olu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or <hi>Pal<U+017F>ie</hi> of the other. ¶</p>
               <p n="55">55. And here we are falne upon the detection of another collateral Error of the Schools; in particular, their unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>ed A<U+017F><U+017F>ertion, that <hi>Lambatives <U+017F>wallowed down gently and by degrees, the head being at the <U+017F>ame time reflected into a po<U+017F>ition looking above the horizon, de<U+017F>cend into the Lungs; but not tho<U+017F>e, that are <U+017F>wallowed down greedily, and at once.</hi> If <U+017F>o, I demand,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114890:37"/>
whether the dog under the di<U+017F><U+017F>ecting knife, did <hi>lick</hi> and <hi>by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> <U+017F>wallow downe the coloured liquor; or <hi>chop</hi> it down <hi>at once?</hi> To what purpo<U+017F>e did the Anatomi<U+017F>ts poure it into his throat to be drank at one <U+017F>wallow or gulp, if they knew before hand, that it could not fall into the Lungs, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e lickt down gently? But letting this <hi>Hypothe<U+017F>is</hi> <U+017F>tand, that the Lungs ab<U+017F>olutely abhor the admi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of all external things, meer Aer and <U+017F>uch as is not incorporated to Fumes and Exhalations onely excepted: and then it will nece<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow, that whether any thing be lickt down gently, or drank down ravenou<U+017F>ly at once; yet <U+017F>till the <hi>Pre<U+017F>ident</hi> of the <hi>Epiglottis,</hi> or <hi>janitor</hi> of the Lungs attends the execution of his function, and ob<U+017F>erves the <hi>Clau<U+017F>ure</hi> of the <hi>Larynx;</hi> <U+017F>ince thereupon depends no le<U+017F><U+017F>e then the hazard of life. This, I conceive, may make it indubious to the mo<U+017F>t preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, that <hi>Lambatives and <U+017F>yrups,</hi> though they may, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing an <hi>unctuous <U+017F>urface</hi> upon the parts, make them more <hi><U+017F>mooth,</hi> <U+017F>lippery, and <U+017F>o more fit for the rejection of vi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid excrements flowing from the palate and other parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent; yet are they of no <U+017F>mall <hi>detriment</hi> to the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> nor can, in the le<U+017F>t degree, or large<U+017F>t latitude of intention, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford ea<U+017F>e or benefit in affections of the <hi>Lungs.</hi> But the Schools reply, that the <U+017F>alivous rheume or defluxion, doth <hi>in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly,</hi> and by its own <hi><U+017F>pontaneous laps,</hi> or natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, di<U+017F>till into the <hi>Larynx;</hi> and that, in this relation, <hi>Lambatives</hi> mu<U+017F>t be beneficial and <U+017F>anative.</p>
               <p n="56">56. But neither of the<U+017F>e articles can <U+017F>tand; <U+017F>ince into what po<U+017F>ition <U+017F>oever the neck be di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed, or however in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, yet the <U+017F>ame care and warine<U+017F><U+017F>e of <hi>Nature</hi> to praevent that nothing drop or in<U+017F>inuate into the Lungs, is con<U+017F>tant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continued. I beheld a <hi>Tumbler,</hi> not long <U+017F>ince, <U+017F>tand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head, his hands and feet inverted, and in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture drink a gla<U+017F><U+017F>e of wine. I appeal to <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly <U+017F>ubmit my hand to the ferula.</p>
               <p n="57">57. Many there are, out of who<U+017F>e mouthes, while they <U+017F>leep, run whole torrents of <U+017F>pitle; who if they chance to <U+017F>leep in a <U+017F>upine po<U+017F>ture, that is on their backs, it in<U+017F>tantly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114890:38"/>
happens, that they mu<U+017F>t turn them<U+017F>elves on one <U+017F>ide, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and <U+017F>it up, <hi>nature</hi> being affrighted by the terror of the <hi>danger</hi> imminent: and if any of the <U+017F>pitle fall accidentally and unawares into the Larynx; thenceforward, untill all be again exploded, they cough unce<U+017F><U+017F>antly. But, to come home to the center of the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F><U+017F>e; what comfort or <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour can <hi><U+017F>ugar,</hi> mixt with the cadaverous <hi>Lungs</hi> of a <hi>Fox,</hi> or imbued with the juice of <hi>Coltsfoot,</hi> adfer to the Lungs; when they utterly abhor the intru<U+017F>ion of any forreigner, admit nothing but Aer unle<U+017F><U+017F>e by accident and <hi>ex improvi<U+017F>o,</hi> and when any thing is entred into their confines, immediately reject it with great anxiety and labour? Can <U+017F>uch a remedy <U+017F>uffice to the <hi>re<U+017F>tauration</hi> of the decayed <hi>Faculties?</hi> Can this cut up <hi>Catarrhs</hi> by the root, or expunge the <hi><U+017F>eminal mia<U+017F>me,</hi> or original impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion fixt upon the <hi>Archeus?</hi> I profe<U+017F><U+017F>e, on which hand <U+017F>oever I turn me, on what part <U+017F>oever I place my di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions, I cannot di<U+017F>cover, that the Schools war again<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, with any other weapons, but the wilde dreams of the Gentiles, or <U+017F>trike at any thing beyond their <hi>effects</hi> and <U+017F>econdary <hi>Productions,</hi> leaving the head and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal <hi>Cau<U+017F>alities</hi> una<U+017F><U+017F>aulted; and all this, by rea<U+017F>on of their ignorance of the <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ence</hi> and <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> of <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</hi> And hence hath the name of <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician</hi> falne under the facete reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion of <hi>Comedians,</hi> and this proverbial reproach, that Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>icians care not what they <U+017F>hould think, what do, or how order their meditations, in order to their obedience unto that <U+017F>trict Precept: <hi>Be ye merciful, as your Father which is in heaven, is merciful,</hi> grown into u<U+017F>e. And, as St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> concerning the <hi>Clergy</hi> feeding upon the <U+017F>ins of the people, in re<U+017F>pect they live upon no other revenews, but <hi>Almes;</hi> <U+017F>o I concerning <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians.</hi> For they con<U+017F>ider not, whether they di<U+017F>charge their duty to the <hi>Commandment,</hi> or <U+017F>atisfie the debt of <hi>Charity;</hi> who banquet and grow fat upon the defections, languors, and infirmities of the people. Often have I pondered, but di<U+017F>cover I cannot, how the<U+017F>e Plagues of Aegypt, the<U+017F>e clouds of palpable darkne<U+017F><U+017F>e, were intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced upon the Schools; unle<U+017F><U+017F>e from hence, that being
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114890:38"/>
<U+017F>ea<U+017F>oned with evil principles, and infected with unju<U+017F>tifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble traditions, they frequently met with <hi>Affections,</hi> which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their outward appearance, and without <U+017F>cruple or <U+017F>tricter indagation, they in<U+017F>tantly referred to the fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <U+017F>cene of <hi>Catarrhs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="58">58. For <hi>in<U+017F>tance,</hi> a certain <U+017F>ick per<U+017F>on, invaded with a head ach, <U+017F>oon after feels a dull and ponderous pain in the neck, a difficulty and indi<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition to motion; and the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den plummets of <hi>Morpheus</hi> are too light to draw down the curtains of his eyes; on the neck of the<U+017F>e Accidents en<U+017F>ues a manife<U+017F>t pain and imbecillity of the loyns, which <U+017F>eems to be traduced down to the thighs, and thence to make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<U+017F><U+017F>e to the legs and feet. Hereupon it is decreed, that <hi>Pain</hi> (<U+017F>ince an <hi>Accident</hi> of <hi>inhaerence) cannot tran<U+017F>migrate from one <U+017F>ubject to another;</hi> unle<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>omething <hi>Material,</hi> <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ively trickling down from the brain along the mu<U+017F>cles of the <U+017F>pine, and by a <U+017F>pontaneous motion ari<U+017F>ing from its own tendency to declivity, remove from a <hi><U+017F>uperior</hi> to an <hi>inferior</hi> part: which may very accommodately make out the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Appellation</hi> of a <hi>Catarrh.</hi> It mu<U+017F>t become our method of exploring <hi>verity,</hi> to examine and detect the dotage and improbability of this per<U+017F>wa<U+017F>ion concerning <hi>defluxions,</hi> by the judicial te<U+017F>t of <hi>Anatomy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="59">59. For if this <hi>dolorifick matter</hi> di<U+017F>till, by <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drops, from the brain by the neck; no man can doubt, but that it mu<U+017F>t be tran<U+017F>ported thither, either through the <hi>Ventricles</hi> of the brain, or through the <hi><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance</hi> and <hi>membranes</hi> of the brain, or betwixt the <hi>Pia</hi> and <hi>Dura mater,</hi> or betwixt the <hi>Dura mater</hi> and the <hi>Skull,</hi> or, in fine, betwixt the <hi>Skull</hi> and the <hi>Skin.</hi> For the Con<U+017F>equence is warrantable from a <U+017F>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient enumeration of the parts. But, fir<U+017F>t, not through the <hi>Ventricles</hi> of the brain; <U+017F>ince that could not come to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e without the inevitable introduction of an <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> or univer<U+017F>al <hi>Pal<U+017F>ie:</hi> if the doctrine of the Schools, concerning the origination of the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, <U+017F>tand firme. For if the matter of the Defluxion be excluded from the cavities in the fore part of the brain, and thence di<U+017F>charged upon the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114890:39"/>
fourth ventricle, and <U+017F>o carried into the <U+017F>pinal marrow <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively; it cannot but horridly offend tho<U+017F>e noble parts, and being an alien and acrimonious excrement, cau<U+017F>e de<U+017F>perate and invincible ob<U+017F>tructions, and by con<U+017F>equence an <hi>Apoplexy</hi> or <hi>Pal<U+017F>ie.</hi> Secondly, the matter of this Defluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot, <hi>per</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>, by <hi>tran<U+017F>udation</hi> through the <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance of the brain, be fir<U+017F>t accumulated between the brain and its thinner inve<U+017F>tment, the <hi>Pia mater,</hi> and thence delaps; <U+017F>o that both Coats may yet keep their continual di<U+017F>tance and <hi><U+017F>eparation</hi> from the very marrow of the <U+017F>pine: in regard the defluxion in its de<U+017F>cent cannot but commit a <hi>divul<U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi><U+017F>olution</hi> of <hi>unity,</hi> in the medullary roots of the nerves, according to their <hi>longitude;</hi> (i. e.) as they run out in their di<U+017F>tinct di<U+017F><U+017F>eminations. Which wanteth not a multitude of ab<U+017F>urdities. In like manner, <U+017F>hould the Catarrh be rained down betwixt the <hi>two membranes;</hi> each of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>lender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<U+017F>tments, provided by nature to envellop the <U+017F>pinal marrow, would be <hi>double:</hi> which Anatomical in<U+017F>pection could never yet ju<U+017F>tifie. And <U+017F>hould we allow it <U+017F>o to be, it would not onely impede the <hi>motion</hi> of the <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles;</hi> but al<U+017F>o excite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme <hi>torture,</hi> and <hi>convul<U+017F>ive retractions</hi> of the Nerves. So there lieth an <hi>Error</hi> in the <hi>The<U+017F>is;</hi> <U+017F>ince the <hi>Nerve,</hi> indeed, is the <hi>organ delative of the mandates of the Will,</hi> (i. e.) the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in<U+017F>trument by which the Will tran<U+017F>mits her <U+017F>piritual Mercuries on an errand to the mu<U+017F>cles: but not <hi>Executive of Voluntary motion,</hi> (i. e.) not the immediate executioner of the commands given out. More plainly thus; the Will is <hi>Queen Regent;</hi> the <hi>Animal <U+017F>pirits,</hi> the <hi>Nuncij,</hi> or Emba<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors; the <hi>Nerve,</hi> the in<U+017F>trument of their <hi>tran<U+017F>vection</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from the brain, or white-hall of the <U+017F>oul, to the member to be imployed; and the <hi>mu<U+017F>cle,</hi> the <hi>executioner</hi> of her de<U+017F>ignes. That a Nerve is not the executioner of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary motion, may be clearly argued from hence; that very few nerves, in <hi>thickne<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> exceeed a thread of double twi<U+017F>ted <U+017F>ilk. Now a Nerve, being in<U+017F>erted into the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal part of its peculiar mu<U+017F>cle, cannot probably convey the rheume down to the midle of the mu<U+017F>cle, without inferring
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114890:39"/>
a <hi>Pal<U+017F>ie</hi> of that part, from its own <hi>ob<U+017F>truction,</hi> or a <hi>convul<U+017F>ion</hi> from the <hi>aerimony</hi> and virulency of the <hi>Defluxion.</hi> Again, if they <U+017F>hall affirme, that the Catarrh doth trickle down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Dura mater</hi> and the <hi>Skull;</hi> I may appeal for deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion to <hi>Anatomy,</hi> which autoptically demon<U+017F>trateth, that the <hi>perforations</hi> of the <U+017F>pondils of the <U+017F>pine, through which the nerves are threaded in their elongations from their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, the <U+017F>pinal marrow, are <U+017F>o exactly fitted to their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, that not a hair can be thru<U+017F>t between, without a <U+017F>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible Compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the nerve; <U+017F>o that, by con<U+017F>equence, there can be no void <U+017F>pace left for the intru<U+017F>ion of a Catarrh into the mu<U+017F>cles, from the <U+017F>pinal marrow. We add, that though our Adver<U+017F>aries could find out a <hi>place;</hi> wherein this fictitious rheume may be <hi>congregated;</hi> or <hi>pa<U+017F><U+017F>age</hi> for its <hi>deflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion</hi> upon the <U+017F>pinal marrow, and <hi>diffu<U+017F>ion</hi> thence through the <hi>perforatiens</hi> of the <U+017F>pondils into the mu<U+017F>cles: yet, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, it would amu<U+017F>e their <U+017F>ophi<U+017F>try, to give a plau<U+017F>ible rea<U+017F>on of the <hi><U+017F>ucceeding progre<U+017F><U+017F>e</hi> thereof, and fully to make out, how a humor, once delap<U+017F>ed upon a nerve running out betwixt two <U+017F>pondils, can remigrate, or return back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to invade other nerves <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively one after the other. What, doth the wanton rheume grow weary of one nerve, and to <U+017F>atisfie its de<U+017F>ire of change, at plea<U+017F>ure remove to another? Tis a <hi>Quaere</hi> not unworthy a <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantial determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, how a deluge of <U+017F>alt rheume can <U+017F>tream along a tender and extremly <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible nerve, without cau<U+017F>ing a <hi><U+017F>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> or <hi>dull in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibility,</hi> in that member into which it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erted? Can it in<U+017F>inuate into the tendinous <hi>head,</hi> and thence creep along into the <hi>taile</hi> of a <hi>mu<U+017F>cle?</hi> Can it retreat thence again, to a<U+017F><U+017F>ault other mu<U+017F>cles <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively, as the <U+017F>ituation of the <U+017F>econd is more <hi>prone</hi> or <hi>declive</hi> then of the former, and that then the third, &amp;c? or, if there may be a new <U+017F>upply of the defluxion, con<U+017F>tantly <U+017F>ucceeding, imagined to flow from parts above, to fre<U+017F>h ones below; how comes it to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e, that the <U+017F>uperior parts, fir<U+017F>t invaded, obtain an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from the mi<U+017F>chiefe? For <U+017F>ince the rivulet of rheume doth <U+017F>pring from one <hi>fountain,</hi> the <hi>brain;</hi> and run in one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114890:40"/>
continued <hi>Chanel,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>pinal marrow:</hi> why <U+017F>hould it not rather follow the <hi>old</hi> tract, then wander into a <hi>new,</hi> and undergo the difficulties of forcing, and as it were mining out a fre<U+017F>h current? Why doth it, as if carried on by an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous uncon<U+017F>tancy, de<U+017F>ert its antiently accu<U+017F>tomed bed; and affect the embraces of a <hi>fre<U+017F>h,</hi> nay frequently a <hi>feeble</hi> part? Why doth it for<U+017F>ake its frequented quarters, and range in que<U+017F>t of <U+017F>trang and never yet frequented lodgings? Hath it <U+017F>uch an Appetite or malitious propen<U+017F>ity inherent, that goads it on to variety of objects, whereon to <U+017F>ate its ho<U+017F>tility? For conclu<U+017F>ion; that this Error can expect no <U+017F>anctuary, in the po<U+017F><U+017F>ibility of the rheums defluxions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>skull</hi> and the <hi>skin,</hi> and through the firme <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance of the <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles,</hi> each being inve<U+017F>ted with a tunicle <U+017F>ufficiently compact and thick: may be amply collected from our precedent di<U+017F>qui<U+017F>itions. ¶</p>
               <p n="60">60. All this being <U+017F>ummd up, by the impartial Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick of <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> and examined by mature <hi>judgement;</hi> the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Product</hi> mu<U+017F>t amount to this: that there can be no <hi>way, medium, connexion,</hi> or <hi>dependence,</hi> by which a <hi>Catarrh</hi> may <U+017F>ub<U+017F>i<U+017F>t, in verity. And <U+017F>ince no rheume or material princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can be found out to have de<U+017F>cended, even in any of tho<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, for who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ake chiefly the Schools fir<U+017F>t invented this Chimera of <hi>Catarrhs:</hi> Know all the friends of truth, that as often as any peregrine <hi>Aer</hi> or bla<U+017F>t, any offen<U+017F>ive <hi>odor,</hi> any putrefactive <hi>Ferment,</hi> or exotick <hi>Seminality</hi> is impre<U+017F><U+017F>ed upon, or conceived in the <hi>Influent <U+017F>pirit;</hi> <U+017F>o of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is that contaminate and degenerate <U+017F>pirit excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated from the participation of <hi>Vitality</hi> by the <U+017F>evere ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tice of the incen<U+017F>ed <hi>Archeus.</hi> And the <hi>Genius</hi> or di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition of this depraved <hi>Seminality</hi> conceived, is of no le<U+017F><U+017F>e power then this, that it can tran<U+017F>mit the <hi>Influent <U+017F>pirit,</hi> made an alien to its primitive purity by the a<U+017F><U+017F>umption of an <hi>exotick Ferment,</hi> rather to parts <U+017F>eated at di<U+017F>tance and in the <hi><U+017F>uburbs,</hi> then <U+017F>uch as are neighbours to the <hi>Bialto</hi> or palace of life. As we <U+017F>hall at large declare in our di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>es
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:114890:40"/>
of the <hi>Gout</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In tractatu</hi> (Volupe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventium mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus antiquitus putatus, <hi>nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato) ad quem</hi> Helmont. <hi><U+017F>uos hîc remittit le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores,</hi> Arthri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidis <hi>naturam, cau<U+017F>as, atque nativitatem, brevitèr ad hunc modum de<U+017F>crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas videre e<U+017F>t.</hi> Podagra <hi>(in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit) e<U+017F>t Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter morbidus, <U+017F>eminalitèr in <U+017F>piritu vitae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ertus, qui <U+017F>uae maturitatis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, fructum acidum fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem gignit, <U+017F>permaticis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus confermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilem. Non exi<U+017F>tit ergo Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagra in cruore; multoque minus in excrementis. Verum Podagrici primum agitantur in</hi> praecordijs, <hi>&amp; tom internas potuum atque ciborum, quam externas aeris vici<U+017F><U+017F>itudines <U+017F>entiunt; imò &amp; <U+017F>aepè has futuras prae<U+017F>agiunt. Quare patiuntur <U+017F>ebriles motus primum, circa officinam <U+017F>piritus Vitalis, ac quidem paroxy<U+017F>mi initiis. Etenim primi motus è praecordiis a<U+017F>cendunt, <U+017F>edem animae <U+017F>en<U+017F>itivae adoriuntur. Conceptus namque in praecordiis Character,</hi> Lunae <hi>atque</hi> Mercurij <hi>typos explicat: atque deinde in corde perficitur. Formatus antem <U+017F>ive maturatus Character, spiritum ibidem febrilem induit, quatenus inficit. Qui <U+017F>imul atque acorem <U+017F>ymboli vitae five <U+017F>ermentalem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, motu febrili abigitur <U+017F>quallens, &amp; ad loca de<U+017F>tinata (crudi viz. spermatis in <U+017F>ynenia Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulorum) febriliter defertor. Spiritus, inquam, <U+017F>ic infectus, et non humor (quod notandum) <U+017F>ynoniam in <U+017F>e tran<U+017F>parens, cum</hi> Aciditate fermentali <hi>coagulat in gr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mum opacum. Ad<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t prae ponticitatis conceptae gradu, calores, delores, tumore<U+017F>que pedagrae di<U+017F>tinguantur.</hi> Laticem <hi>verò advocari</hi> doforis <hi>buccina, &amp; per venas dimitti, ad eluend<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, certum e<U+017F>t. Itaque ron quod dolet, quod tumet, vel ardet, Podagra e<U+017F>t: <U+017F>ed hujus <U+017F>unt</hi> producta. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>que enim per pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam bombardae <U+017F>ublato pede, ablata e<U+017F>t <U+017F>imul podagra, <U+017F>ive Arthritis: <U+017F>iquidem in <U+017F>en<U+017F>atione per organum <U+017F>en<U+017F>us, fit tantum con<U+017F>en<U+017F>us partium, &amp;c. Sed horum <U+017F><gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>des e<U+017F>to penes Authorem,</hi> ¶</note>, of the <hi>duumvirate</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lege jus duumviratus Helmentij.</note>, and el<U+017F>ewherere. For thus <hi>Mercury,</hi> externally applied by Unction, <U+017F>ubtily runs through all the body and invades the throat, tongue and teeth. Farther, when this vitiated <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> arrives at the place, to which it was di<U+017F>patched; in<U+017F>tantly it there imbueth the <hi>nutriment</hi> of that part with its putrefactive <hi>Ferment,</hi> tran<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planteth and transformeth it into a conformity or analogy to the idea of the <hi>Seminality:</hi> and that nutriment thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinated, by <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ive expirations or <hi>Afflations,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions, doth di<U+017F>order and pervert the <U+017F>unctions of the <hi>dige<U+017F>tive Faculty;</hi> and by this means doth not onely generate a plentiful harve<U+017F>t of <hi>Excrements;</hi> but al<U+017F>o <U+017F>tigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, or impre<U+017F><U+017F>e this depravity<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> upon the <hi>Implantate <U+017F>pirit</hi> of that part, <U+017F>o deeply, that it can hardly be expunged during the whole after life. All which the Schools, like mendicants, precarious de<U+017F>ume from the brain; &amp; erroneou<U+017F>ly impute to their four imaginary <hi>Humors,</hi> and the defluxion of <hi>Rheums.</hi> On which Con<U+017F>ideration, my Theory <U+017F>tands point blanck in defiance to the doting tradition of Catarrhs; as po<U+017F>itive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denying and wholly <U+017F>ubverting their <hi>material Cau<U+017F>e,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptaries or <hi>places</hi> of <hi>concretion, efficient Cau<U+017F>e,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Generation</hi> and <hi>Defluxion:</hi> and <U+017F>eparating the true <hi>Cau<U+017F>es, Effects,</hi> and method of <hi>Sanation,</hi> far from the ridiculous fictions of a <hi>Catarrh.</hi> ¶</p>
               <p n="61">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:114890:41"/>
61. By this time, we believe, it is plain and unque<U+017F>tion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that no <U+017F>alt, acid, <U+017F>harp, phlegmatick, or Cholerick humor can di<U+017F>til from the brain; but that, whenever the <hi>Influent</hi> <U+017F>pirit, polluted with <U+017F>ome alien and putrefactive <hi>impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion,</hi> doth arrive at any part of the body; then doth nature, without delay, <U+017F>end thither the <hi>Latex,</hi> or <U+017F>our<U+017F>e of <U+017F>erous humidity, to <hi>expung</hi> this impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, or at lea<U+017F>t rin<U+017F>e away the <hi>Excrements,</hi> there growing from the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the <hi>dige<U+017F>tive Faculty.</hi> For the <hi>Spirit,</hi> once vitiated by any forreigne <hi>Contagion,</hi> wildly rangeth at plea<U+017F>ure through the <hi>nerves, arteries,</hi> yea and the very <hi>habit</hi> of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; whereupon, the <U+017F>ick <U+017F>eeming to feel as it were the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxion, or trickling down of a cold rheume, the <hi>brain</hi> is immediately accu<U+017F>ed as treacherous, and the grand author of this ryot and irregularity in nature. Now <U+017F>ince the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex</hi> is <U+017F>ent to the part newly invaded by this malignant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, not as the primitive <hi>Cau<U+017F>e</hi> of the evill (though fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, by accident, it doth <hi>foment</hi> and aggravate the mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and <U+017F>o make the vitio<U+017F>ity more durable) but as a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> or <U+017F>tream to wa<U+017F>h away the impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion: hereupon have the Schools, to this day, remained doubtful, and dur<U+017F>t ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go <U+017F>o far as po<U+017F>itively to determine; whether in the <hi>Gout</hi> the <hi>Catarrb</hi> is derived from the <hi>head,</hi> by the <hi>Nerves:</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tran<U+017F>mitted from the <hi>Liver</hi> onely, by the <hi>Veins.</hi> And thus evident it is, that the Phlegme and Choler of the Schools flow not from one fountain, or Cataract; as though the <hi>brain</hi> were the <hi>Common <U+017F>ewer</hi> of all the<U+017F>e impurities. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as for the la<U+017F>t refuge, whereunto the Schools flye, for protection of their impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible dream of Catarrhs; namely the <hi>Declivity</hi> or downwardne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the <U+017F>ituation of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as in relation to the brain, and the facility of the pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ages: it may ea<U+017F>ily appear to be too rotten and fragile to afford them <U+017F>helter. Since as in dead bodies there are none of the<U+017F>e <hi>re<U+017F>pective <U+017F>ituations,</hi> but onely in living; <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o all motion of humors in the body is immediately cau<U+017F>ed by the <hi>Influent <U+017F>pirit,</hi> as the onely <hi>impetum faciens,</hi> and mediately derived from the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>vitality</hi> in who<U+017F>e occonomy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114890:41"/>
the <hi>A<U+017F>cent</hi> of humors is of no more difficulty then the <hi>de<U+017F>cent.</hi> For in living bodies, no humor oweth its motion down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to the declive tendency of its <hi>Gravity:</hi> but, in impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial truth, to the aim or direction of that <hi>mi<U+017F><U+017F>ive power,</hi> which levelled it at this or that determinate part. Hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> of an <hi>External</hi> depravity upon the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluent <U+017F>pirit:</hi> it follows that we declare the probability and manner how the <U+017F>ame <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> may <hi>conceive,</hi> and as it were <hi>batch</hi> an <hi>internal</hi> Character, or dome<U+017F>tick tincture of corruption. It comes to pa<U+017F><U+017F>e not <U+017F>eldome, that the <hi>Latex</hi> contaminated by the admixture of <U+017F>ome forreine <hi>Salt,</hi> doth therewith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the <hi>Influent Spirit,</hi> <U+017F>o that it in<U+017F>tantly becomes degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from its requi<U+017F>ite <U+017F>implicity and purity; though not by rea<U+017F>on of any external injury of the <hi>aer,</hi> offen<U+017F>ive <hi>odor,</hi> <U+017F>ulphureous <hi>Fume,</hi> &amp;c. but from a <hi>breath</hi> or bla<U+017F>t of <hi>Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> conceived <hi>in the part affected:</hi> yea that taking a di<U+017F>like or abhorrence from the <hi>Latex</hi> (as being polluted, and <U+017F>o uncapable of its vital irradiation) it grows enraged and forgeth within it<U+017F>elf a <hi>character</hi> of <hi>anger</hi> and <hi>reuenge.</hi> After this the uncivil <hi>Latex,</hi> like a rude <U+017F>ouldier that intrudes him<U+017F>elfe into quarters again<U+017F>t the will of the Landlord, forceth it<U+017F>elf into the <U+017F>ociety of the offended <hi>Influent <U+017F>pirit;</hi> and though unfit for its conver<U+017F>ation, as well in regard of its <hi>Acidity,</hi> as immoderate <hi>quantity,</hi> yet it <U+017F>till followeth and hangs upon its skirts. In which relation, the mo<U+017F>t hopefull remedies for mo<U+017F>t of the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es which cau<U+017F>e <hi>erratick</hi> paines, as al<U+017F>o for <hi>internall Ulcers,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be <hi>Baths, Sudaries,</hi> and <hi>Stoves</hi> or <hi>Hot-hou<U+017F>es:</hi> for by procuring liberall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>weats,</hi> and by that means <hi>exhau<U+017F>ting</hi> the <hi>Latex,</hi> as the <hi><U+017F>econdary</hi> and <hi>fomenting materiall Cau<U+017F>e,</hi> they <U+017F>eem more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly perpendicular to health, and conducible to the pacification of <hi>Archeus</hi> his wor<U+017F>hip; then the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall and languid <hi>Solutives</hi> and <hi>Ex<U+017F>iccatives</hi> of the Schools. ¶.</p>
               <p>Vaine, therefore, is the <U+017F>tory of a <hi>Catarrhs</hi> ari<U+017F>ing ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally from the <U+017F>tomack into the head: and its <hi>Conden<U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Concretion,</hi> and <hi>Congregation</hi> in the ventricles of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114890:42"/>
the brain. Vaine are the de<U+017F>criptions of its <hi>Defluxion,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the coats of the <hi><U+017F>pinal marrow,</hi> or between the <hi>skull</hi> and <hi>skin,</hi> upon the <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles.</hi> And, of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, vain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>uch <hi>Remedies</hi> be, as are admini<U+017F>tred when the <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are wholy unknown. Vain al<U+017F>o are <hi>Cauteries</hi> and <hi>Fontanels,</hi> for the <hi>Revul<U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>Exhau<U+017F>tion</hi> of <hi>Humors,</hi> that have no real exi<U+017F>tence in nature. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, vain are the <hi>Decoctions of China, Guajacum, Sa<U+017F><U+017F>afras,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ex<U+017F>iccating Drinks;</hi> <U+017F>ince the evill ari<U+017F>eth, at lea<U+017F>t is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ionally aggravated by tbe <hi>Latex,</hi> and mu<U+017F>t be fomented by any immoderate quantity of humidity. From whence we have a faire opportunity to collect, that <U+017F>ober and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>imonious <hi>drinking</hi> doth very much conduce to health; nay to the cure of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers</hi> in the Lungs, as al<U+017F>o of the <hi>Goute.</hi> Since the <hi>Latex,</hi> which according to the Primitive in<U+017F>titution of nature ought to be <hi>in<U+017F>ipid,</hi> upon the exce<U+017F><U+017F>ive drinking of eager Wines, <U+017F>uch are <hi>French, Rheni<U+017F>h,</hi> and <hi>Sherry,</hi> doth acquire a manife<U+017F>t <hi>Acidity,</hi> or <U+017F>owerne<U+017F><U+017F>e, and in<U+017F>tantly communicate the <U+017F>ame to the blood; from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Corro<U+017F>ions,</hi> <U+017F>harpe <hi>Spa<U+017F>mes</hi> and <hi>Convul<U+017F>ions, errat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick paines,</hi> and chiefly the <hi>Gout.</hi> But of the hi<U+017F>tory and nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of this <hi>Latex,</hi> we have written a particular Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e. ¶</p>
               <p n="62">62. You may plea<U+017F>e to remember, that the <hi>primitive Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of all concreted <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances, is onely Water</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De rerum naturalium pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordiis, per Mechanica Pyrotechniae experimenta, <U+017F>uo de more, inquirens Author, in</hi> tract. de Elementis; <hi>duo duntaxat reperit</hi> Primitiva Elementa: Aerem <hi><U+017F>cilicei &amp;</hi> Aquam. (Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem <hi>namque Ens Anomalon, &amp; adnihilationis ordinariò capax:</hi> Terram <hi>vero, <U+017F>ecundarium tantùm elementum, <U+017F>ive fructum ex Aqua, virtute <U+017F>eminum, concretum, eò quod tandem cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertibilis <U+017F>it in aquam, per privationem <U+017F>uae e<U+017F><U+017F>entiae, e<U+017F><U+017F>e exi<U+017F>timat.) In hanc autem <U+017F>ententiam <U+017F>e incidi<U+017F><U+017F>e fa<U+017F><U+017F>us e<U+017F>t, exinde quod per Hermetis ignem didici<U+017F><U+017F>et, omne corpus vi<U+017F>ibile, puta <U+017F>axum, lapidem, gemmam, <U+017F>ilicem, arenam, marcha<U+017F>itam, argillam, terram, vitrum, calcem, <U+017F>ulphur, &amp;c. tran<U+017F>mutari in</hi> Salem <hi>actualem: &amp; quod Sal i<U+017F>te, aliquoties cum</hi> Sale Circulato Paracel<U+017F>i <hi>cogobatus, <U+017F>uam omninò fixitatem amittat, tandem tran<U+017F>mutetur in aquam in<U+017F>ipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; &amp; quod aqua i<U+017F>ta aequiponderet <U+017F>ali <U+017F>uo, unde manavit. Nec in contrarium valet, quod imperitus aliquis for<U+017F>an objiciet;</hi> Vitrum <hi>e<U+017F><U+017F>e ultimum artis <U+017F>ubjectum, quodque nec igne nec arte deleri, aut in aquam re<U+017F>olvi unquam po<U+017F><U+017F>it. Erudietur enim, <U+017F>i Vitri pollinem pluri Alchali colliquaverit, ac humido loco exp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uerit; mox totum vitrum reduci in aquam limpidi<U+017F><U+017F>imam: Cui <U+017F>i affundatur Chry<U+017F>ulca, add<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o quantum <U+017F>aturando Alchali <U+017F>ufficiat, inveniet <U+017F>tatim in <U+017F>undo arenam <U+017F>idere, eodem pondere, quo prius faciundo vitro aptabatur. Idem etiam sperari po<U+017F><U+017F>it effectus ex <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>niver<U+017F>ali illo Men<U+017F>truo,</hi> Liquore A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hahe<U+017F>t; <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> omnia totius univer<U+017F>i corpora tangibilia perfectè reducit in aquam diaphanam, ab<U+017F>que ulla <U+017F>ui mutatione</hi> (i. e. <hi>quoad Formam e<U+017F><U+017F>entialem, <U+017F>ive nativam <U+017F>eminis dotem) viriumvè diminutione. Hujus autem <U+017F>iupendi <U+017F>ane Magnal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s praeparationem, â</hi> Paracel<U+017F>o, <hi>vel</hi> Ba<U+017F>ilio Valentino Monacho <hi>olim inventam, &amp; ab</hi> Helmontio, <hi>veluti</hi> Arcanum <hi>nemini, ni<U+017F>i dato prius Sacramenti pig<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ore, revelandum, <U+017F>ubdolè defo<U+017F><U+017F>am; me aliquando, ubi dabitur occa<U+017F>io, coram mundo liberè promulgaturum, <U+017F>pondeo.</hi> ¶</note>: and all <hi>fruits</hi> or productions of mixt bodies ari<U+017F>e from the <U+017F>ame principle.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114890:42"/>
Let us therefore grant, that the <hi>Latex,</hi> being naturally <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ipid,</hi> doth, upon the acce<U+017F><U+017F>e and fermentation of any <hi><U+017F>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality,</hi> or fructifying tincture, in<U+017F>tantly grow <hi>Acide.</hi> By example, in the beginning of the Spring, if you make an inci<U+017F>ion in the rind of a <hi>Vine</hi> or <hi>Birch</hi> tree, neer the <hi>root,</hi> there will di<U+017F>till forth a very great quantity of thin <hi>in<U+017F>ipid</hi> liquor, which is nothing but the water fre<U+017F>hly attracted out of the earth: but if the inci<U+017F>ion be made higher in the <U+017F>tock or branches, then will the liquor be a little Acid. The rea<U+017F>on is the <U+017F>ame in the <hi>Latex,</hi> which being naturally in<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, doth, if contaminated by the contagion of any ferment admixed, acquire a <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible Acidity, and inherit any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine quality, or tincture devolved from the vitio<U+017F>ity of our aliment. This <hi>Latex</hi> the Schools have wholy neglected, and indeed becau<U+017F>e they confounded it with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine.</hi> Tis a blind and rude method of exploring the <U+017F>ecrets of nature, to make no di<U+017F>tinction betwixt the <hi>Generatum,</hi> or producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the <hi>Materia ex qua,</hi> or materiall cau<U+017F>e thereof; no difference betwixt the <hi>Mother</hi> and the <hi>Daughter;</hi> as if the <hi>Muccus</hi> ordinarily dropping from the brain by the no<U+017F>trils, the <hi><U+017F>alivous humidity</hi> of the jawes and tongue, the <hi>Water</hi> effu<U+017F>ed betwixt the omentum, mu<U+017F>cles of the belly and the skin, in the drop<U+017F>ie, and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine,</hi> were all one and the <U+017F>ame matter, namely the <hi>liquor</hi> we ordinarily drink. The <hi>Liver</hi> therefore being mi<U+017F>affected, and invaded by any ho<U+017F>tile impre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, if it <U+017F>ound a retreat to the <hi>Latex,</hi> and call back the <U+017F>treams thereof to its own a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance; doth not convert it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114890:43"/>
into <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rine,</hi> but makes it the <hi>material</hi> cau<U+017F>e of <hi>oedematous</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ab</hi> Hippocrat. lib. de natura hominis, <hi>appellantur tumores 'laxi, molles, indolentes, ad digiti compre<U+017F><U+017F>ionem cedentes, à pituita tenui, <U+017F>eu frigidtore &amp; humidore parte ma<U+017F><U+017F>ae <U+017F>anguineae ortum ducentes.</hi> ¶</note> 
                  <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors,</hi> or an <hi>Ana<U+017F>arca</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ana<U+017F>arca <hi>e<U+017F>t tertia</hi> hydropis <hi><U+017F>pecies; quam quod univer<U+017F>a corporu moles aqua lenta &amp; concreta <U+017F>uffundatur,</hi> Ana<U+017F>arcam <hi>&amp;</hi> Leucophlegmatiam <hi>(turpiter enim hallucinatur</hi> Aretaeus, in 2. de diuturn. affect. cap. 1. <hi>dum di<U+017F>crimen quoddam inter Ana<U+017F>arcam &amp; Leuco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlegmatiam imaeginatur) Graeci nuncuparunt. Illius autem originem &amp; naturam fu<U+017F>e aperiit</hi> Hipocrat. lib. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                     </gap>. ¶</note>.</p>
               <p n="63">63. I am not a per<U+017F>on <U+017F>ubject to <U+017F>uch extravagancies and wild <U+017F>ingularities, as to affirme, that the <hi>Pleuri<U+017F>ie, Tooth-ache,</hi> and other <U+017F>uch maladies, who<U+017F>e tortures were in<U+017F>ufferable, were they not in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ort moderated by their <hi>acutene<U+017F><U+017F>e,</hi> or brevity of duration, are no <hi>real Entities.</hi> For I too well know, and lament their tyranny over us. I admit them as <hi>Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es:</hi> but oppo<U+017F>e the vulgar tradition of the <hi>cau<U+017F>es, maner, means, waies, end</hi> or de<U+017F>tinations of <hi>Catarrhs.</hi> Tho<U+017F>e fictitious and incon<U+017F>i<U+017F>tent cau<U+017F>es I deny, and explore other more reall and probable; in who<U+017F>e remove, the direct way to the re<U+017F>tauration of <hi>heath</hi> doth con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t. I acknowledge that any man, upon the rupture of an <hi>Apo<U+017F>teme</hi> in the Lungs, may die <U+017F>uddenly: yet I po<U+017F>itively deny, that a <hi>Catarrh</hi> is the <hi>cau<U+017F>e</hi> of this <hi>Apo<U+017F>teme,</hi> or that <hi>death</hi> is u<U+017F>hered in by a <hi>Defluxion.</hi> And with much more earne<U+017F>tne<U+017F><U+017F>e I deny, that an <hi>Apo<U+017F>teme</hi> in the Lungs can be generated from <hi>vapours</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled from the <hi><U+017F>tomack,</hi> and reconden<U+017F>ed in the brain. For which rea<U+017F>on I account not a <hi>Con<U+017F>umption</hi> the daughter of a <hi>Defluxion</hi> of rheume upon the Lungs; but the genuine i<U+017F><U+017F>ue of their own <hi>Archeus</hi> <U+017F>educed into irregularity, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved execution of the power delegated to his admini<U+017F>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I conced that the <hi>Gout</hi> may be prae<U+017F>aged a day or two before the inva<U+017F>ion of its paroxy<U+017F>me from the <U+017F>en<U+017F>ation of the motion of the <hi><U+017F>alt matter</hi> which runs to the joynts like a drop of <U+017F>calding liquor: but cannot allow a <hi>Catarrh</hi> to be the cau<U+017F>e thereof, <U+017F>ince I know a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly that its material principles, manner of generation, waies of di<U+017F>tillation and places of concretion and collection, are prodigious
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:114890:43"/>
figments, irreconcilable to truth. But the <hi>Latex,</hi> ordained by nature to wa<U+017F>h away the impurities from all parts official to concoction (like the river Alpheus brought by <hi>Hercules</hi> to clean<U+017F>e the <U+017F>table of Augeas) is of it<U+017F>elf <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ipid:</hi> but in its cour<U+017F>e meeting with the pollutions of <hi><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line tinctures,</hi> re<U+017F>ulting from impure and inconvenient ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it <U+017F>oon degenerates into <hi>hurtfull</hi> and <hi>acrimonious,</hi> and breeds <hi>Apo<U+017F>temes, <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lcers,</hi> and <hi>pruriginous maladies,</hi> as the <hi>Itch, Scabbs,</hi> &amp;c. I cannot fool my own credulity <U+017F>o far, as to apprehend any probability in the common opinion, that vapours can a<U+017F>cend out of the <U+017F>tomack into the plane of the brain, be there conden<U+017F>ed into water, where is a con<U+017F>tant <hi>actual heat;</hi> and thence penetrate through the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and double inve<U+017F>tment of the brain. Nor can I <U+017F>hake hands with that impertinent here<U+017F>ie of <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us,</hi> that the aer drawn in by in<U+017F>piration is carried down directly to the <U+017F>tomack, and other <hi>vi<U+017F>cera</hi> of the lower belly: but allow that a very <U+017F>mall quantity thereof is in<U+017F>en<U+017F>ibly <U+017F>trained through the capillary perforations of the midrife. For in long compre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the breath, neither any con<U+017F>iderable intume<U+017F>cence of the Abdomen can be ob<U+017F>erved; nor doth the breath, upon its efflation, <U+017F>mell of any thing conteined in the parts below the Midrife. In like manner can no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of Wine or other inebriative liquor, ari<U+017F>e up to the head, unle<U+017F><U+017F>e by the Arteries <note n="*" place="margin">See Doctor <hi>Browne</hi> in the <U+017F>econd book of vulgar er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. cap. 6. <U+017F>ect. 7. 1 edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>. For whatever procureth vertigoes or giddine<U+017F><U+017F>e in the head, <U+017F>woonings and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicating Accidents, belongs to another Common-wealth, then that Eutopia of vapours. Nor from the <hi>Wembe</hi> can vapours be tran<U+017F>mitted into the head; however vulgar <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologie</hi> affirmes, that wild and durable <hi>perturbations</hi> of the <hi>Animall Faculties,</hi> and a <U+017F>trong <hi>con<U+017F><gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pition</hi> of <hi>rea<U+017F>on,</hi> are derivatory from <hi>malignant and narcotiall exhalations</hi> ari<U+017F>ing out of tbe wombe. For tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>urious motions and actions of the <hi>matrix</hi> are not to be a<U+017F>cribed to any <hi><U+017F>ympathy</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity of <hi>Per<U+017F>pirability;</hi> but to the <hi>mon<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>machy</hi> or civil war of that peculiar Monarchy of the wombe, wherein women <U+017F>eem to be <U+017F>trangled by an a<U+017F>cention of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114890:44"/>
<U+017F>ome certain globular body, or lump, up to their throat. This action is a commotion or tumult of the offended <U+017F>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits re<U+017F>iding in that part, or an error in the government of the <hi>Archeus,</hi> or <hi>uterine Pre<U+017F>ident</hi> enraged, to who<U+017F>e arbitary power all parts of the body mu<U+017F>t doe hon age and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: as I have amply explained in my Treati<U+017F>e called <hi>Ignota actio Regiminis.</hi> For the dominion of which the <hi>Womb</hi> hath over all parts of the body, is no le<U+017F><U+017F>e ab<U+017F>olute or diffu<U+017F>ive, then that whereby the <hi>Testicles</hi> di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h a Cocke from a Capon, a Bull from an Ox, and a man from an Eunuch; as wil in the Figure of the body, as the blood, fle<U+017F>h, skin, and animo<U+017F>ity. ¶</p>
               <p n="64">64. But in regard all tho<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e conceived to proceed from Catarrhs, the contaminated <hi>Latex</hi> hath obtained a peculiar <U+017F>uperintendency or domination over the other humors of the body, and re<U+017F>ponds to the nature of <hi>Water:</hi> therefore doe all <hi>Accidents</hi> accompanying <U+017F>uch infirmities ob<U+017F>erve their periodicall <hi>exacerbations</hi> mo<U+017F>t toward night; the influence of the <hi>Moone, queen regent of all humane <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tances,</hi> operating tho<U+017F>e vici<U+017F><U+017F>itudes, or cau<U+017F>ing ebullitions in us at tho<U+017F>e houres. And the<U+017F>e Accidents di<U+017F>play their ho<U+017F>tility mo<U+017F>t upon the <hi>brain,</hi> weakned by any native or acquired di<U+017F>temper praeceding: as al<U+017F>o upon the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Membranes,</hi> as parts who<U+017F>e <U+017F>mall <U+017F>tock of <hi>Vitall heat</hi> makes them le<U+017F><U+017F>e able to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t or <U+017F>ubdue the impre<U+017F><U+017F>ions of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Cold.</hi> And hence is it, that <hi>Con<U+017F>umptive, Hydropick, Gouty</hi> and <hi>decaying,</hi> bodies carry an infallible Almanack in their bones, pre<U+017F>age change of weather, and by the Augurie of their pains are <U+017F>orewarned of en<U+017F>uing tempe<U+017F>ts: which I have, for that rea<U+017F>on, Chri<U+017F>tned <hi>Tortura Noctis,</hi> the torture of night. It is my <U+017F>erious <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inam,</hi> and may be many others, that this way of progno<U+017F>tication had not co<U+017F>t us <U+017F>o deare, as the <U+017F>ufferance of <U+017F>uch intolerable angui<U+017F>h and anxiety. For almo<U+017F>t every week ob<U+017F>erves unto us, that men once inured to weare the fetters of the <hi>Gout,</hi> or tainted with any imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the <hi>lungs,</hi> yea <U+017F>uch as are onely troubled with <hi>cornes</hi> on their feet, are <U+017F>uddainly awakened out of their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:114890:44"/>
Profounde<U+017F>t <U+017F>leep, by the twinges and cruell mementoes of their infirmities, again<U+017F>t change of weather: and by this <U+017F>mart adverti<U+017F>ement can at midnight tell, that <hi>Juno</hi> hath put on her <U+017F>able weed of Clouds, and that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<U+017F>tant <hi>winds</hi> are tackt about to another point of the Compa<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
               <p n="65">65. <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us</hi> was plea<U+017F>ed to opinion, that <hi>Mercury</hi> was Lord Paramont, or <hi>Pre<U+017F>ident</hi> over the <hi>Alimentary liquor,</hi> through the whole body: and for that rea<U+017F>on, in another place <hi>(de morbis miner alibus)</hi> both in name and reality, he confounds this <hi>Planet</hi> with the <hi>terre<U+017F>trial Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="66">66 But we, on more <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantial and preci<U+017F>e grounds, <U+017F>tand a<U+017F><U+017F>ured, that each <hi>nutritive humor</hi> of the body doth conform to the regiment, and obey the <hi>alterative influence</hi> of that <hi><U+017F>eminall part,</hi> unto which it is proximly to be <hi>a<U+017F><U+017F>imilated:</hi> nor doe the <hi>liquid <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tances</hi> in the body hold any <hi>corre<U+017F>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> with the <hi>Stars,</hi> <U+017F>o long as they are not radically inocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into the <U+017F>tock of <hi>Vitality,</hi> i.e. untill, by the irradia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>internal Sol,</hi> or <hi>vital Spirit,</hi> they are rarified and exalted into a finene<U+017F><U+017F>e requi<U+017F>ite to their <hi>participation of lif<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Which is a convincing argument, that the <hi>Marrow in the bones is an homogeneous part of the body; but no alimentary or liquid <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance:</hi> <U+017F>ince it is evidently <U+017F>ubordinate to the <hi>Moon;</hi> and the brain, to who<U+017F>e influential power the <hi>bones</hi> are <U+017F>ubject. And thus all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es conceived to tyrannize over man, under the mi<U+017F>taken name of <hi>Defluxions,</hi> as al<U+017F>o the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>eneral Contagion,</hi> or <hi>French Pox, Contractions</hi> of the <U+017F>inews, <hi>torments</hi> of the <hi>joynts,</hi> &amp;c. fall under this one generall title or denomination, <hi>Tortura Noctis:</hi> in this intere<U+017F>t, that their <hi>Paroxy<U+017F>mes</hi> or periodicall inva<U+017F>ions depend upon the <hi>motions</hi> or <hi>ebullitions</hi> of the <hi>Latex,</hi> are regulated by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of our <hi>Moon,</hi> and ob<U+017F>erve their tides or vici<U+017F><U+017F>itudes in exact conformity to the various <hi>motions, po<U+017F>itions,</hi> and <hi>configurations</hi> or reciprocal <hi>A<U+017F>pects</hi> of the <hi>Planets.</hi> ¶</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

