<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new method of Rosie Crucian physick: wherein is shewed the cause; and therewith their experienced medicines for the cure of all diseases, theoparadota; freely given to the inspired Christians, by Ton aggelon presbytaton, ton archaggelon, logon, archon, onoma theo. And in obedience fitted for the understanding of mean capacities by the adorer, and the most unworthy of their love, John Heydon, a servant of God, and secretary of nature.</title>
            <author>Heydon, John, b. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-10">2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E946_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866645</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A86278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 141:E946[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new method of Rosie Crucian physick: wherein is shewed the cause; and therewith their experienced medicines for the cure of all diseases, theoparadota; freely given to the inspired Christians, by Ton aggelon presbytaton, ton archaggelon, logon, archon, onoma theo. And in obedience fitted for the understanding of mean capacities by the adorer, and the most unworthy of their love, John Heydon, a servant of God, and secretary of nature.</title>
                  <author>Heydon, John, b. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Lock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Portions of title, "Theoparadota" and "Ton aggelon .. theo," transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>With an errata leaf facing the titlepage.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 22"; "May 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosicrucians --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118922:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW METHOD OF Rosie Crucian phy<U+017F>ick: Wherein is <U+017F>hewed the Cau<U+017F>e; and therewith their experienced Medicines for the Cure of all <hi>DISEASES,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>; Freely given to the in<U+017F>pired <hi>CHRISTIANS,</hi> BY <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And in obedience fitted for the under<U+017F>tanding of mean capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities by the Adorer, and the mo<U+017F>t unworthy of their LOVE, <hi>John Heydon,</hi> a Servant of God, and Secretary of Nature.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Penes nos unda Tagi.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Lock,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118922:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118922:2"/>
            <head>An Apologue for an Epilogue.</head>
            <p>I Shall here tel you what <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> are, and that <hi>Mo<U+017F>es</hi> was their <hi>Father,</hi> and he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>; <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay they were of the order of <hi>Elias,</hi> <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay the Di<U+017F>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> others define them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap>; <hi>i.e.</hi> The Officers of the <hi>Generali<U+017F><U+017F>imo</hi> of the world, that are as the eyes and cares of the great King, <U+017F>eeing &amp; hearing all things; they are Seraphically illuminated, as <hi>Mo<U+017F>es</hi> was according to this order of the <hi>Elements,</hi> earth refin'd to water, water to air, air to fire; <U+017F>o of a man to be one of the <hi>Heroes</hi> of a <hi>Heros,</hi> a <hi>Daemon,</hi> or good ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, of a <hi>genius,</hi> a partaker of Divine things, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of the holy company of unbodied <U+017F>ouls and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Angels, and according to their <hi>vehicles,</hi> a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>atile life, turning them<U+017F>elves <hi>Proteus</hi>-like into any <U+017F>hape.</p>
            <p>But there is yet arguments to procure <hi>Mr. Walfoord,</hi> and <hi>T. Williams, Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> by election, and that is the miracles that were done by them, in any <U+017F>ight; for it <U+017F>hould <U+017F>eeme <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> were not only initiated into the Mo<U+017F>aicall Theory, but have arrived al<U+017F>o to the power of working miracles as <hi>Mo<U+017F>es, Elias, Ezekiel</hi> and the <U+017F>ucceeding Prophets did, as being tran<U+017F>ported where they plea<U+017F>e, as <hi>Habakkuk</hi> was from <hi>Jewry</hi> to <hi>Babylon</hi> or as <hi>Philip</hi> after he had baptized the <hi>Enuch</hi> to <hi>Arotus,</hi> and one of the<U+017F>e went from me to a friend of mine in <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hire,</hi> and came and brought me an an<U+017F>wer to <hi>London</hi> the <U+017F>ame day, which is four dayes journey, they taught
<pb facs="tcp:118922:3"/>
me excellent predictions of A<U+017F>trologie, and earthquakes; they <U+017F>lack the plague in Cityes; they <U+017F>ilence the violent winds and tempe<U+017F>ts; they calme the rage of the Sea and rivers; they walk in the Air, they fru<U+017F>trate the Malicious a<U+017F>pect of Witches; they cure all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; I de<U+017F>ired one of the<U+017F>e to tell me whether my complexion were capable of the <U+017F>ociety of my good <hi>Genius?</hi> when I <U+017F>ee you again, <U+017F>aid he, I will tell you (which is) (when he plea<U+017F>es to come to me, for I know not where to go to him) when I <U+017F>aw him then he <U+017F>aid Ye <U+017F>hould pray to God, for a good and holy man can offer no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor more acceptable <U+017F>acrifice to God, then the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him<U+017F>elf, his <U+017F>oul.</p>
            <p>He <U+017F>aid al<U+017F>o that the good <hi>Genii</hi> are as the benigne eyes of God, running to and fro in the world, with love and pitty beholding the innocent endeavours of harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s and <U+017F>ingle hearted men, ever ready to do them good, and to help them; and at his going away he bid me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of my <U+017F>eeming friends who would do me all the hurt they could, and cau<U+017F>e the Governors of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be angry with me, and <U+017F>et bounds to my liberty, which truly hapned to me, as they did indeed: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things more he told me before we parted, but I <U+017F>hall not name them here.</p>
            <p>For this <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> Phy<U+017F>ick or Medicines, I happily and unexpectedly light upon in <hi>Arabia,</hi> which will prove a re<U+017F>tauration of health to all that are afflicted w<hi rend="sup">h</hi> that <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, which we ordinarily cal natural, &amp; all other di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, as the Gour, Drop<U+017F>ie, Lepro<U+017F>ie and falling <U+017F>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s; and the<U+017F>e men may be <U+017F>aid to have no <U+017F>mall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ight in the body, and that <hi>Walfoord, Williams,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Fraternity now living, may bear up in the <U+017F>ame likely Equipage, with tho<U+017F>e noble Divine <U+017F>pirits their predece<U+017F>sors, though the unskilfullne<U+017F>s in men commonly acknowledge more of <U+017F>upernaturall a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance
<pb facs="tcp:118922:3"/>
in hot un<U+017F>etled fancies, and perplexed melancholy, then in the calme and di<U+017F>tinct u<U+017F>e of rea<U+017F>on; yet for mine own part, but not without <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>ion to better judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I looke upon the<U+017F>e <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> above all men truly in<U+017F>pired, and more than any that profe<U+017F><U+017F>ed or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>o, this <U+017F>ixteen hundred yeares, and I am ravi<U+017F>hed with admiration of their miracles and tran<U+017F>cendent mechanicall inventions, for the <U+017F>alving the Phaenomena in the world; I may without offence therefore compare them with <hi>Bezaliel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> tho<U+017F>e skilfull and cunning workers of the tabernacle, who, as <hi>Mo<U+017F>es</hi> te<U+017F>tifies, were filled with the <U+017F>pirit of God, and therefore were of an excellent under<U+017F>tanding to find out all manner of curious work.</p>
            <p>Nor is it any more argument, that the<U+017F>e <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are not in<U+017F>pired, becau<U+017F>e they do not <U+017F>ay they are; then that others are in<U+017F>pired, becau<U+017F>e they <U+017F>ay they are; which to me is no argument at all; but the <U+017F>uppre<U+017F><U+017F>ion of what <U+017F>o hapned, would argue much more <U+017F>obriety &amp; mode<U+017F>ty; whenas the profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion of it with <U+017F>ober men, would be <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected of <U+017F>ome peice of melancholy and di<U+017F>traction, e<U+017F>pecially in the<U+017F>e things, where the grand plea<U+017F>ure is the evidence and exerci<U+017F>e of rea<U+017F>on, not a bare beliefe, or an ineffable <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of life, in re<U+017F>pect whereof there is no true chri<U+017F>tian but he is in<U+017F>pired; but if any more zealous pretender to prudence and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, wanting either lea<U+017F>ure or ability to examine the<U+017F>e <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> Medicines to the bottom <U+017F>hall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<U+017F>tanding either condemn them or admire them; he hath unbecommingly and indi<U+017F>creetly vetered out of his own <U+017F>phere, and <hi>I</hi> cannot acquit him of inju<U+017F>tice or folly: Nor am I a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian,</hi> nor do I <U+017F>peake of <U+017F>pite, or hope of gain, or for any <U+017F>uch matter; there is no cau<U+017F>e, God knows, I envie no man, be he what he will be, <hi>I</hi> am no phy<U+017F>itian, never was, nor never mean to be: what <hi>I</hi> am it
<pb facs="tcp:118922:4"/>
makes no matter as to my profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion.</p>
            <p>La<U+017F>tly, the<U+017F>e holy and good men would have me know that the greate<U+017F>t <U+017F>weet and perfection of a vertuous <U+017F>oul, is the kindly accompli<U+017F>hment of her own nature, in true wi<U+017F>dom and divine love; and the<U+017F>e miraculus things that are done by them are, that that worth and knowledge that is in them may be taken notice of, and that God thereby may be glorified who<U+017F>e witne<U+017F><U+017F>es they are; but no other happine<U+017F>s accrues to them from this, but that hereby they may be in a better capacity of makeing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers happy,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my hou<U+017F>e in <hi>Spittle</hi> fields next door to the red Lyon <date>this 10. of <hi>May,</hi> 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Iohn Heydon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118922:4"/>
            <head>A New METHOD OF <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Phy<U+017F>ick.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Accurate Structure of Mans body.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Admire the goodne<U+017F>s of God towards us in the frame and <U+017F>tructure of our bodies, the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Artifice whereof, <hi>Galen, though a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali<U+017F>t,</hi> was <U+017F>o taken with, that he could not but adjudge the honor of a hymn to the wi<U+017F>e Creator of it. The continuance of the whole, and every particular, is <U+017F>o evident an Argument of exqui<U+017F>ite skill in the Maker, that if I <U+017F>hould pur<U+017F>ue all that <U+017F>utes to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, it would amount to too large (yet an entire) Volume. I <U+017F>hall therefore write all that is needful to be known by all men, leaving the re<U+017F>t to be <U+017F>upply'd by <hi>Anatomists:</hi> And I think there is no man that hath any skill in that Art, but will confe<U+017F>s, the more diligently and accurately the frame of our body is examined, it is found the more exqui<U+017F>itely conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our Rea<U+017F>on, Judgement, and De<U+017F>ire; <U+017F>o that <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118922:5"/>
the <U+017F>ame matter that our bodies are made of, if it had been in our own power to have made our <U+017F>elves, we <U+017F>hould have fram'd our <U+017F>elves no otherwi<U+017F>e then we are: To in<U+017F>tance in <U+017F>ome particulars; <hi>As in our Eyes,</hi> the <hi>Number,</hi> the <hi>Scituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of them is <U+017F>uch, that we can excogitate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be added thereto, or to be altered, either for their <hi>beauty, <U+017F>afety,</hi> or <hi>u<U+017F>efulne<U+017F>s;</hi> but as for their beauty, I have trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted largely of it in my youthful merry Poems, &amp; now am not minded to tran<U+017F>cribe my tender nice <U+017F>ubject, and couple it with my <U+017F>everer <U+017F>tile; I will onely note how <U+017F>afely they are <hi>guarded,</hi> and <hi>fitly framed</hi> out for the u<U+017F>e they are intended: The Brow and the No<U+017F>e <U+017F>aves them from harder <U+017F>trokes; but <U+017F>uch a curious part as the <hi>Eye</hi> being nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily liable to mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief from <U+017F>malle<U+017F>t matters, the <U+017F>weat of the Forehead is fenced off by tho<U+017F>e two Wreaths of Hair which we call the Eye-brows; and the Eye-lids are fortified with little <U+017F>tiff bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tles, as with Palli<U+017F>adoes, again<U+017F>t the a<U+017F><U+017F>ault of Flyes and Gnats, and <U+017F>uch-like bold <hi>Animalcula;</hi> be<U+017F>ides, the upper-lid pre<U+017F>ently claps down, and is as good a Fence as a Port-Cullis again<U+017F>t the importunity of the Enemy; which is done al<U+017F>o e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night, whether there be any pre<U+017F>ent a<U+017F><U+017F>ault or no, as if nature kept Garri<U+017F>on in this <hi>Acropolis</hi> of mans body, the <hi>Head,</hi> and look'd that <U+017F>uch Laws <U+017F>hould be duly ob<U+017F>erved, as were mo<U+017F>t for his <U+017F>afety.</p>
               <p>And now for the u<U+017F>e of the Eye, which is <U+017F>ight, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that this Organ is <U+017F>o exqui<U+017F>itely framed for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e, that not the lea<U+017F>t curio<U+017F>ity can be added: For fir<U+017F>t, the <hi>Humor</hi> and <hi>Tunicles</hi> are purely <hi>tran<U+017F>parent</hi> to let in light, and colours unfould, and un<U+017F>ophi<U+017F>ticated by any inward tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. And then again, the parts of the Eye are made <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vex,</hi> that there might be a direction of many raies coming from one point of the object, unto one point an<U+017F>werable in the bottom of the eye; to which purpo<U+017F>e the <hi>Chry<U+017F>talline hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor</hi> is of great moment, and without which, the <U+017F>ight would be very ob<U+017F>cure and weak. Thirdly, The <hi>Tunica uvea</hi> hath a <hi>Mu<U+017F>culous Power,</hi> and can dilate and contract that round hole in it which is called the Pupil of the <hi>Eye,</hi> for the better moderating the tran<U+017F>mi<U+017F><U+017F>ion of light. Fourthly, The in<U+017F>ide
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118922:5"/>
of the <hi>uvea is blacked</hi> like the Wall of a Tennis-Court, the raies falling upon the <hi>Retina</hi> again; for <U+017F>uch a repercu<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would make the <U+017F>ight more confu<U+017F>ed. Fifthly, The <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica Arachnoides,</hi> which invellops the <hi>Chry<U+017F>talline Humour,</hi> by vertue of its <hi>Proce<U+017F><U+017F>us Ciliaros,</hi> can thru<U+017F>t forward, or draw back that precious u<U+017F>eful part of the Eye, as the nearne<U+017F>s or di<U+017F>tance of the objects <U+017F>hall require. Sixthly and la<U+017F>tly, The <hi>Tunica Retina</hi> is <hi>white,</hi> for the better and more true recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <U+017F>pecies of things, (as they ordinarily call them) as white paper is fitte<U+017F>t to receive tho<U+017F>e Images into a dark room; and the eye is already <U+017F>o perfect, that I believe it is not needful to <U+017F>peak any more thereof; we being able to move our head upwards and downwards, and on every <U+017F>ide, might have unawares thought our <U+017F>elves <U+017F>ufficiently well provided for; but Nature hath added Mu<U+017F>cles al<U+017F>o to the Eyes, that no perfection might be wanting; for we have oft occa<U+017F>ion to move our Eyes, our Heads being unmoved, as in reading, and viewing more particularly any object <U+017F>et be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; and that this may be done with more ea<U+017F>e and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curacy, <U+017F>he hath furni<U+017F>hed that Organ with no le<U+017F><U+017F>e then <hi><U+017F>ix <U+017F>everal Mu<U+017F>cles;</hi> and indeed, this framing of Mu<U+017F>cles, not onely in the Eye, but in the whole body, is admirable; for is it not a wonder that even all our fle<U+017F>h <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>o hand<U+017F>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formed and contrived into di<U+017F>tinct pieces, who<U+017F>e ri<U+017F>e and in<U+017F>ertions <U+017F>hould be with <U+017F>uch advantage that they do <U+017F>erve to move <U+017F>ome part of the body or other? and that the parts of our body are not moved onely <U+017F>o conveniently as wil <U+017F>erve us to walk and <U+017F>ub<U+017F>i<U+017F>t by, but that they are able to move e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way imaginable that will advantage us; for we can fling out Legs and Arms upwards and downwards, backwards, forwards, and round, as they that <U+017F>pin, or would <U+017F>pread a Mole-hill with their feet. To <U+017F>ay nothing of <hi>Re<U+017F>piration,</hi> the con<U+017F>triction of the <hi>Diaphragme</hi> for the keeping down the Guts, and <U+017F>o enlarging the <hi>Thorax,</hi> that the Lungs may have play, and the a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of the inward <hi>interco<U+017F>tal Mu<U+017F>cles</hi> in deep <U+017F>u<U+017F>pirations, when we take more large gulps of <hi>air</hi> to cool our heart over-charged with love or <U+017F>orrow; nor of the curious Fabrick of the Lainix, <U+017F>o well fitted with Mu<U+017F>cles for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118922:6"/>
the modulation of the Voice, tunable <U+017F>peech, and delicious <hi><U+017F>inging:</hi> You may adde to the<U+017F>e the notable contrivance of the <hi>Heart,</hi> its two <hi>ventricles,</hi> and its many <hi>valvulae,</hi> <U+017F>o fram'd and <U+017F>cituated, as is mo<U+017F>t fit for the reception and tran<U+017F>mi<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood, and it's <U+017F>ent thence away warm to comfort and cheri<U+017F>h the re<U+017F>t of the body; for which purpo<U+017F>e al<U+017F>o the <hi>valvulae</hi> in the veins are made.</p>
               <p>But we <U+017F>ee by experience that <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>grief</hi> proceed not in all men from the <U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>es, and that men differ very much in the con<U+017F>titution of the body, whereby that which help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and furthereth vital con<U+017F>titution in one, and is therefore delightful, hindereth &amp; cro<U+017F><U+017F>eth it in another, and therefore cau<U+017F>eth <hi>grief.</hi> The difference therefore of <hi>Wits,</hi> hath its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal from the different pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, &amp; from the ends to which the appetite leadeth them. As for that difference which ari<U+017F>eth from <hi><U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s,</hi> and <U+017F>uch accidental di<U+017F>tempers, I have appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for the <U+017F>econd Part of this Book, and therefore I omit the <U+017F>ame as impertinent to this place, and con<U+017F>ider it onely in <U+017F>uch as have their health, perfection of body, and Organs well di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the perfection of the Body, and then of the Nature of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es; of Delight, Pain, Love, Hatred, <U+017F>en<U+017F>ual Delight, and Pains of the Body, Joy, and Grief.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OTher things I have to <U+017F>ay, but I will rather in<U+017F>i<U+017F>t upon <U+017F>uch things as are ea<U+017F>ie ahd intelligible even to <hi>Idiots,</hi> or <U+017F>uch <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> that are no wi<U+017F>er, who if they can but tell the Joints of their hands, or know the u<U+017F>e of their teeth, they may ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>cover it was Coun<U+017F>el, not Chance, that created them; and if they but under<U+017F>tand the<U+017F>e natural Medecines I have prepared in this Book for their example, they will know that they <U+017F>hall be cured of all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es without pain, or any great co<U+017F>t; and <hi>Love,</hi> not <hi>Money,</hi> was it that made me under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this Task. Now of the well-fram'd parts of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118922:6"/>
I would know why we have three joints in our Legs and Arms, as al<U+017F>o in our fingers, but that it was much better then having but two or four? And why are our <hi>fore-teeth <U+017F>harp,</hi> like Chizzels, to cut, but our <hi>inward teeth broad, to grind?</hi> but this is more exqui<U+017F>ite then having them all <U+017F>harp, or all broad, or the fore-teeth broad, and the other <U+017F>harp; but we might have made a hard <U+017F>hift to have lived, though in that wor<U+017F>er condition. Again, Why are the Teeth <U+017F>o luckily pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? or rather, Why are there not Teeth in <hi>other bones</hi> as well as in the Jaw-bones, for they might have been as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the<U+017F>e. But the rea<U+017F>on is, Nothing is done fooll<U+017F>hly, nor in vain. I will <U+017F>hew you <hi>how to prolong life,</hi> and to <hi>return from age to youth;</hi> and <hi>how to change, alter, and amend the state of the body;</hi> but that I intend in a Treati<U+017F>e entituled <hi>The Wi<U+017F>e Mans Crown:</hi> To keep the body in perfect <hi>health</hi> is my pre<U+017F>ent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign, <hi>and to cure all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es without reward;</hi> for there is a <hi>Divine Providence</hi> that orders all things. Again, (to <U+017F>ay nothing of the inward curio<U+017F>ity of the <hi>Ear</hi>) Why is that outward frame of it, but that it is certainly known that it's for the better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>hearing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might add, That <hi>Nature</hi> hath made the <hi>hind-mo<U+017F>t parts</hi> of our <hi>body</hi> (which we <U+017F>it upon) mo<U+017F>t <hi>fle<U+017F>hy,</hi> as providing for our ea<U+017F>e, making us a <hi>Natural Cu<U+017F>hion,</hi> as well as for <hi>In<U+017F>truments of Motion</hi> for our <hi>Thighs</hi> and <hi>Legs;</hi> <U+017F>he hath made the hinder part of the <hi>Head</hi> more <U+017F>trong, as being otherwi<U+017F>e unfenced again<U+017F>t falls and other ca<U+017F>ualties. She hath made the <hi>Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> of <U+017F>everal <hi>Vertebrae,</hi> as being more fit to bend, more tough, and le<U+017F>s in danger of breaking then if they were all one intire bone, without tho<U+017F>e gri<U+017F>tly Junctures. She hath <U+017F>trengthened our <hi>fingers</hi> and <hi>toes</hi> with <hi>Nailes,</hi> whereas <U+017F>he might have <U+017F>ent out that <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance at the end of the fir<U+017F>t and <U+017F>econd Joints, which had not been <U+017F>o hand<U+017F>om and u<U+017F>eful, nay, rather <U+017F>omewhat trouble<U+017F>ome and hurtful. And la<U+017F>tly, She hath made all bones devoid of <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e,</hi> becau<U+017F>e they were to bear the weight of them<U+017F>elves, and of the whole body; and therefore if they had had <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, our life had been painful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and dolorous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118922:7"/>And now I have con<U+017F>idered the fitne<U+017F>s of the parts of mans bodie for the good of the whole, let me but con<U+017F>ider briefly his <U+017F>ences and his nature, and then I intend more <U+017F>olidly to demon<U+017F>trate the cau<U+017F>e of all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and with that the Cure, becau<U+017F>e I intend a Method of <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed <hi>in my way to Bli<U+017F><U+017F>e.</hi> By our <U+017F>everal Organs, we have <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Conceptions of <U+017F>everal qualities in the objects; for by <U+017F>ight we have a conception or image compo<U+017F>ed of colour and figure, which is all the notice and knowledge the object im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth to us of its nature, by the excellency of the eye. By <hi>Hearing</hi> we have a conception called <hi>Sound,</hi> which is all the knowledge we have of the quality of the object from the Ear: And <U+017F>o the re<U+017F>t of the Sences are al<U+017F>o conceptions of <U+017F>everal qualities or natures of their objects.</p>
               <p>Becau<U+017F>e the Image in vi<U+017F>ion con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of colour and <U+017F>hape, is the knowledge we have of the qualities of the object of that Sence, it is no hard matter for a man to fall into this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, That the <U+017F>ame colour &amp; <U+017F>hape are the very qualities them<U+017F>elves; and for the <U+017F>ame cau<U+017F>e that <U+017F>ound &amp; noi<U+017F>e are the qualities of a piece of Canon or Culvering charged with <U+017F>ulphurous Powder, fired, or of the Air: And this opinion hath been <U+017F>o long received, that the contrary mu<U+017F>t needs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a great Paradox. The <U+017F>ame qualities are ea<U+017F>ier in a bell; and yet the introduction of <U+017F>pecies vi<U+017F>ible and intelligible, (which is nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for the maintenance of that opinion) pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing to and fro from the object, is wor<U+017F>e then any Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, as being a plain impo<U+017F>sibility. I <U+017F>hall therefore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to make plain the<U+017F>e points.</p>
               <p>That the <U+017F>ubject wherein colour and image are inherent; is not the object or thing <U+017F>een.</p>
               <p>That there is nothing (really) which we call an Image or Colour.</p>
               <p>That the <U+017F>aid Image, or Colour, is but an apparation unto us of the motion, agitation, or alteration, which the object worketh in the brain, or <U+017F>pirits, or <U+017F>ome internal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Head.</p>
               <p>That as in vi<U+017F>ion, <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o in conceptions that ari<U+017F>e from the other <U+017F>en<U+017F>es, the <U+017F>ubject of their inherence is not the object, but the continent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118922:7"/>That conceptions and apparitions are nothing really, but motion in <U+017F>ome internal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance of the Head; which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not <U+017F>topping there, of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity mu<U+017F>t there either help, or hinder the motion which is called Vital; when it helpeth it is called Delight, Contentment or Plea<U+017F>ure, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing really but <hi>motion about the heart,</hi> as <hi>conception</hi> is nothing but <hi>motion in the head;</hi> and the objects that cau<U+017F>e it are called <hi>Plea<U+017F>ant,</hi> or <hi>Delightful;</hi> and the <U+017F>ame Delight, with reference to the object is called <hi>Love;</hi> but when <U+017F>uch motion weakneth or hindreth the vital motion, then it is called <hi>Pain,</hi> and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that which cau<U+017F>eth it, <hi>Hatred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two <U+017F>orts of plea<U+017F>ures, whereof one <U+017F>eemeth to affect the corporeal Organ of the <U+017F>ence, and that I call <U+017F>en<U+017F>ual, the greate<U+017F>t part whereof is that by which we are invited to give continuance to our <hi><U+017F>pecies;</hi> and the next by which a man is invited to meat, for pre<U+017F>ervation of his indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual per<U+017F>on. The other <U+017F>ort of Delight is not particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any part of the body, and is called <hi>The Delight of the mind,</hi> &amp; is that which we call <hi>Joy.</hi> Likewi<U+017F>e of pains, <U+017F>ome affect the body, and are therefore called <hi>The pains of the body;</hi> and <U+017F>ome not, and tho<U+017F>e are called <hi>grief.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the nature of the Soul of Man, whether <U+017F>he be a meer Modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the body, or a Sub<U+017F>tance really di<U+017F>tinct; and then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corporeal, or incorporeal, and of the temper of the bodie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HEre I am forced to <U+017F>peak what I have in my <hi>Familiar Spirit,</hi> and it is not impertinent to my purpo<U+017F>e; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we <U+017F>ay that the <hi><U+017F>oul</hi> is a meer <hi>modification of the body,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>oul</hi> then is but one <hi>univer<U+017F>al faculty of the body,</hi> or a many faculties put together; and tho<U+017F>e operations which are u<U+017F>ually attributed unto the <hi><U+017F>oul,</hi> mu<U+017F>t of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity be attributed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>body:</hi> I demand therefore, To what in the body will you attribute <hi><U+017F>pontaneous motion?</hi> I under<U+017F>tand thereby a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118922:8"/>
in our <U+017F>elves of wagging, or holding <U+017F>till mo<U+017F>t of the parts of our <hi>body,</hi> as our <hi>hand</hi> <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, or <hi>little finger:</hi> If you will <U+017F>ay that it is nothing but the <hi>immi<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> of the <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> into <U+017F>uch and <U+017F>uch <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles,</hi> I would gladly know what does <hi>immit</hi> the<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>pirits,</hi> and direct them <U+017F>o curiou<U+017F>ly; is it them<U+017F>elves? or the <hi>brains?</hi> or that particular piece of the brain they call the <hi>Pine-Kernel?</hi> What ever it be, that which doth thus immit them, and direct them, mu<U+017F>t have <hi>Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ion;</hi> and the <U+017F>ame that hath <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ion,</hi> hath <hi>Memory and Rea<U+017F>on</hi> al<U+017F>o: Now I would know whether the <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves be capable of <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ion, Memory,</hi> and <hi>Rea<U+017F>on;</hi> for it indeed <U+017F>eems altogether impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible; for the<U+017F>e animal <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> are nothing el<U+017F>e but matter very thin and liquid, who<U+017F>e na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in this, that all the particles of it be in motion, and being loo<U+017F>e from one another, frigge and play up and down according to the mea<U+017F>ure and manner of agitation in them.</p>
               <p>I therefore demand which of the<U+017F>e <hi>particles</hi> in the<U+017F>e <U+017F>o ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loo<U+017F>ly moving one from another, hath <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ion</hi> in it? if you <U+017F>ay that they all put together have; I appeal to him that thus an<U+017F>wers, how unlikely it is that that <U+017F>hould have <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ion</hi> that is <U+017F>o utterly uncapable of <hi>Memory,</hi> and con<U+017F>equently, of <hi>Rea<U+017F>on;</hi> for it is impo<U+017F>sible to conceive memory competible to <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>ubject, as it is how to write <hi>Characters</hi> in the <hi>Water,</hi> or in the <hi>Wind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you <U+017F>ay the <hi>Brain</hi> immits and directs the<U+017F>e <U+017F>pirits; how can that <U+017F>o freely and <hi><U+017F>pontaneou<U+017F>ly</hi> move it <U+017F>elf, or another, that hath no <hi>Mu<U+017F>cles?</hi> Be<U+017F>ides <hi>Doctor Culpepper</hi> tells you that though the <hi>Brain</hi> be the in<U+017F>trument of <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> yet it hath no <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e</hi> at all of it <U+017F>elf; how then can that that hath no <hi><U+017F>ence</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thus <hi><U+017F>pontaneou<U+017F>ly</hi> and arbitrariou<U+017F>ly, the animal <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> in to any part of the body? an Act that plainly requires deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate <hi><U+017F>en<U+017F>e</hi> and <hi>perception:</hi> But let the <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> and <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<U+017F>ts</hi> conclude what they will, I <U+017F>hall, I think, little le<U+017F><U+017F>e then demon<U+017F>trate that the <hi>brains have no <U+017F>ence;</hi> for the <U+017F>ame in us that hath <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> hath likewi<U+017F>e <hi>animadver<U+017F>ion;</hi> and that which hath <hi>animadver<U+017F>ion in us,</hi> hath al<U+017F>o a faculty of free and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious <hi>Fancy and Rea<U+017F>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118922:8"/>Let us now con<U+017F>ider the nature of the <hi>brain,</hi> and <U+017F>ee how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible tho<U+017F>e alterations are to <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>ubject; verily if we take a right view of this <hi>Laxe pith or marrow</hi> in mans <hi>head,</hi> neither our <hi><U+017F>ence</hi> nor under<U+017F>tanding can di<U+017F>cover any thing more in this <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance that can pretend to <U+017F>uch noble operations, as free imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and <U+017F>agacious collections of <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> then we can di<U+017F>cern in a <hi>lump of fat,</hi> or a <hi>pot of honey;</hi> for this loo<U+017F>e <hi>pulpe</hi> that is thus wrapped up within our <hi>Cranium,</hi> is but a <U+017F>pongie and porous <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and pervious, not onely to the <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits,</hi> but al<U+017F>o to more Juice and Liquor; el<U+017F>e it could not well be nouri<U+017F>hed, at lea<U+017F>t it could not be <U+017F>o <U+017F>oft and moi<U+017F>tned by <hi>drunkenne<U+017F>s</hi> and exce<U+017F>s, as to make the under<U+017F>tanding inept and <U+017F>otti<U+017F>h in its operations. Wherefore I now demand, in this <U+017F>oft <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance which we call the <hi>brain,</hi> who<U+017F>e <U+017F>oftne<U+017F>s implies that it is in <U+017F>ome mea<U+017F>ure li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, and liquidity implies a <U+017F>everal motion of loo<U+017F>ened parts; in what part or parcel thereof does <hi>Fancy, Rea<U+017F>on, and Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>ion</hi> lie? In this laxe con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence <hi>that lies like a Net, all on heaps in the water; I demand, In what Knot, Loope, or Interval thereof, does this faculty of free Fancy, and active Rea<U+017F>on re<U+017F>ide?</hi> I believe not a <hi>Doctor in England,</hi> nay, not Dr. <hi>Culpepper</hi> him<U+017F>elf, were he alive, nor his men, <hi>Doctor Freeman,</hi> and the re<U+017F>t, can a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign me any; and if any will <U+017F>ay, in all together; they mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>ay that the whole <hi>brain</hi> is figured into this or that repre<U+017F>entation, which would cancel <hi>memory,</hi> and take away all capacity of there being any di<U+017F>tinct notes and places for the <U+017F>everal <U+017F>pecies of things there pre<U+017F>ented. But if they will <U+017F>ay there is in every part of the <hi>brain</hi> this <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>Fancy,</hi> they are to remember that the brain is in <U+017F>ome mea<U+017F>ure a <hi>liquid body,</hi> and we mu<U+017F>t enquire how the<U+017F>e loo<U+017F>e parts under<U+017F>tand one anothers <U+017F>everal <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ions</hi> and notions; and if they could (which is yet very unconceivable) yet if they could from hence do any thing toward the <hi>immi<U+017F><U+017F>ion</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> of the <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this or that part of the body, they mu<U+017F>t do it by knowing one anothers minds, and by a ioint contention of <U+017F>trength, as when many men at once, the word being given when they weigh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, put their <U+017F>trength together for the moving of that <hi>Ma<U+017F><U+017F>ie body,</hi> that the <U+017F>ingle <U+017F>trength of one could not deal with; but this is to make the <U+017F>everal particles of the <hi>brain</hi> <U+017F>o many indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118922:9"/>
per<U+017F>ons; a fitter object for laughter, then the lea<U+017F>t mea<U+017F>ure of belief.</p>
               <p>Be<U+017F>ides, how come the<U+017F>e many <hi>Animadver<U+017F>ions</hi> to <U+017F>eem but one to us, our mind being the<U+017F>e, as is <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed? Or why if the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration of one part of the <hi>brain</hi> be communicated to all the re<U+017F>t, does not the <U+017F>ame object <U+017F>eem <U+017F>ituated both behind us, and before us, above, and beneath, on the right hand and on the left; and every way as the impre<U+017F>s of the object is reflected again<U+017F>t all the parts of the <hi>brains?</hi> but there appearing to us but one animadver<U+017F>ion, and one <U+017F>ight of things, it is a <U+017F>ufficient Argument that there is but one; or if there be many, that they are not mutually communicated from the parts one to another, and therefore there can be no <U+017F>uch joint endeavor towards one de<U+017F>ign; whence it is manife<U+017F>t, that the <hi>brains</hi> cannot <hi>immit</hi> or <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect</hi> the<U+017F>e <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits</hi> into what part of the body they plea<U+017F>e.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Spontaneous Motion; of the External Phaenomena; of the nature of the E<U+017F><U+017F>ence of the Soul her <U+017F>elf, what it is, and whether it be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, or incorporeal.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW I mu<U+017F>t tell you, that the <hi>brain</hi> hath no <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot impre<U+017F>s <hi><U+017F>pontaneou<U+017F>ly</hi> any motion on the <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal <U+017F>pirits;</hi> it is no <U+017F>light Argument that <U+017F>ome being di<U+017F><U+017F>ected, have been found without <hi>brains;</hi> and this I <U+017F>aw, a <hi>Captain in Chri<U+017F>ley, in Arabia</hi> that was accidentally kill'd by an <hi>Alcade,</hi> and an <hi>Arabian,</hi> the <U+017F>tory is plea<U+017F>ant, but not pertinent to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e; but this man had nothing but a limpid water in his head in<U+017F>tead of <hi>brains,</hi> and the <hi>brains</hi> generally are ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F><U+017F>olvable into a watery con<U+017F>i<U+017F>tence, which agrees with what I intimated before. Now I appeal to any free Judge, how likely the<U+017F>e liquid particles are to approve them<U+017F>elves of that nature and power, as to be able by erecting and knitting them<U+017F>elves together for a moment of time, to bear them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>o, as with one joint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of <U+017F>trength, to cau<U+017F>e an arbitrarious obligation of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118922:9"/>
the <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> into this or that determinate part of the <hi>body;</hi> but the ab<U+017F>urdity of this I have <U+017F>ufficiently in<U+017F>inuated already.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Nerves,</hi> I mean the <hi>Marrow</hi> of them, which is of the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance with the <hi>brain,</hi> have no <U+017F>ence, as is demon<U+017F>trated from a <hi>Catalep<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> or <hi>Cat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chus;</hi> but I will not accumulate Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a matter <U+017F>o palpable. As for that little <U+017F>prunt piece of the <hi>brain</hi> which they call the <hi>Conacion,</hi> that this <U+017F>hould be the very <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, who<U+017F>e natural faculty it is to move it <U+017F>elf, and by its <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>nods</hi> to determine the cour<U+017F>e of the <hi><U+017F>pirits</hi> into this or that part of the body, <U+017F>eems to me no le<U+017F>s fooli<U+017F>h and fabulous then the Storie of this entituled <hi>Doctor Freeman,</hi> <U+017F>o much commended by ignorantly innocent people: If you heard but the magnificent <U+017F>torie that is told of the little lurking <hi>Mu<U+017F>hrome,</hi> how it does not onely <hi>hear</hi> and <hi><U+017F>ee,</hi> but <hi>imagines, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons, commands</hi> the whole <hi>fabrick</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> more dexterou<U+017F>ly then an <hi>Indian Boy</hi> does an <hi>Elephant:</hi> what an <hi>acute Logician, <U+017F>ubtile Geometrician, prudent State<U+017F>man, skilful Phy<U+017F>ician,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Philo<U+017F>opher</hi> he is! and then afterwards by di<U+017F><U+017F>ection you di<U+017F>cover this worker of miracles to be nothing but a poor <U+017F>illy <hi>contemptible Knob,</hi> or <hi>Protuberancy,</hi> con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting of a thin <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane,</hi> containing a little pulpous matter, much of the <U+017F>ame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>Brain,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Spectatum admi<U+017F>si ri<U+017F>um teneatis amici?</q>
               <p>Would you not <U+017F>ooner laugh at it, then go about to confute it? and truly I may the better laugh it now, having already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed it in what I have afore merrily argued concerning the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>Brain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I <U+017F>hall therefore make bold to conclude, That the impre<U+017F>s of <hi>Spontaneous Motion</hi> is neither from the animal <hi><U+017F>pirits,</hi> nor from the <hi>Brain, &amp;c.</hi> therefore that tho<U+017F>e operations that are u<U+017F>ually attributed unto the <hi><U+017F>oul,</hi> are really incompetible to any part of the <hi>body;</hi> and therefore, as in the la<U+017F>t Chapter I hinted, I <U+017F>ay, That the <U+017F>oul is not a meer <hi>modification</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> but a <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance di<U+017F>tinct therefrom.</p>
               <p>Now we are to enquire, Whether this <hi><U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance di<U+017F>tinct</hi> from what we ordinarily call the <hi>body,</hi> be al<U+017F>o it <U+017F>elf a <hi>Corporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tance,</hi> or whether it be <hi>incorporeal?</hi> If you <U+017F>ay that it is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, you can under<U+017F>tand no other then matter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118922:10"/>
more <U+017F>ubtile and tenuious then the animal <U+017F>pirits them<U+017F>elves, mingled with them, and di<U+017F>per<U+017F>ed through the ve<U+017F><U+017F>els and poro<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the body; for there can be no penetration of dimen<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But I need no new arguments to confute this fond conceit; for what I <U+017F>aid of the <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits</hi> before, is applicable with all ea<U+017F>e and fitne<U+017F>s to this pre<U+017F>ent ca<U+017F>e; and let it be <U+017F>ufficient that I adverti<U+017F>e you <U+017F>o much, and <U+017F>o be excu<U+017F>ed from the repeating of the <U+017F>ame things over again.</p>
               <p>It remains therefore that we conclude, That that which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<U+017F><U+017F>es <hi>Spontaneous Motion</hi> upon the body or more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits:</hi> That which imagines, remembers, and rea<U+017F>ons, is an immaterial <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, di<U+017F>tinct from the body, which u<U+017F>es the <hi>animal <U+017F>pirits</hi> and the <hi>brain</hi> for <hi>In<U+017F>truments</hi> in <U+017F>uch and <U+017F>uch operations. And thus we have found a <hi><U+017F>pirit</hi> in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per notion and <U+017F>ignification, that hath apparently the<U+017F>e facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in it, it can both under<U+017F>tand and move corporeal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>And now this prize that we have won will prove for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign in this new Method of Phy<U+017F>ick and Philo<U+017F>ophy of very great con<U+017F>equence; for it is obvious here to ob<U+017F>erve that the <U+017F>oul of man is as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>compendious <U+017F>tatue of the Deity;</hi> her <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance is a <U+017F>olid <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>igies</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and therefore as with ea<U+017F>e we con<U+017F>ider the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance and motion of the va<U+017F>t <hi>Heavens</hi> on a <hi>little Sphere, or Globe,</hi> <U+017F>o we may with like facility contemplate the <hi>nature</hi> of the Almighty in this little Model of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>oul</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> enlarging to Infinity what we ob<U+017F>erve in our <U+017F>elves when we transfer it unto God, as we do imagine the<U+017F>e Circles which we view on the <hi>Globe,</hi> to be va<U+017F>tly bigger while we fancy them as de<U+017F>cribed in the <hi>heavens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore we being a<U+017F><U+017F>ured of this, That there is a <U+017F>piritual <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance in our <U+017F>elves, in which both the<U+017F>e properties do re<U+017F>ide, <hi>viz.</hi> of the under<U+017F>tanding, and of moving the <hi>corporeal matter;</hi> let us but enlarge our minds <U+017F>o as to conceive as well as we can of a <U+017F>piritual <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance that is able to move &amp; actuate all matter what<U+017F>oever, never <U+017F>o far extended, and after what way &amp; manner <U+017F>oever it plea<U+017F>e, and that it hath not onely the knowledge of this or that particular thing, but a di<U+017F>tinct and plenary cognizance of all things; and we have indeed a very competent apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118922:10"/>
of the nature of the eternal and invi<U+017F>ible God, who like the <hi><U+017F>oul of man,</hi> does not indeed fall under <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> but does every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where operate <U+017F>o, that his per<U+017F>on is ea<U+017F>ily to be gathered from what is di<U+017F>covered by our outward <U+017F>ences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Plants; that the meer motion of the matter may do <U+017F>omething, yet it will not amount to the production of Plants. That it is no botch in Nature that <U+017F>ome Phaenomena be the re<U+017F>ults of Motion, others of <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tantial forms. That beauty is not a meer fancy, and that the beauty and vertue of Plants is an Argument that they are made for the u<U+017F>e of our bodies from an intellectual princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HOW weak is <hi>Man</hi> if you con<U+017F>ider his <hi>nature,</hi> what faculties he hath, and in what order he is in re<U+017F>pect of the re<U+017F>t of the <hi>creatures?</hi> And indeed, though his body be but weak and di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, yet his inward abilities of <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> and artificial contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, is admirable, both for finding out tho<U+017F>e <hi><U+017F>ecret Medicines</hi> which God prepared for the u<U+017F>e of <hi>Man</hi> in the <hi>Bowels of the Earth,</hi> of <hi>Plants</hi> and <hi>Minerals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And fir<U+017F>t of <hi>Vegetables,</hi> where I <U+017F>hall touch onely the<U+017F>e four heads, their <hi>form and beauty, their <U+017F>eed, their <U+017F>ignatures,</hi> and their <hi>great u<U+017F>e,</hi> as well for <hi>medicines</hi> as <hi><U+017F>u<U+017F>tenance;</hi> and that we may the better under<U+017F>tand the advantage we have in this clo<U+017F>er contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the works of nature, we are in the fir<U+017F>t place to take notice of the condition of the <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, which we call matter, how fluid and <U+017F>lippery, and undeterminate it is of it <U+017F>elf; or if it be hard, how unfit it is to be changed into any thing el<U+017F>e; and therefore all things rot into a moi<U+017F>ture before any thing can be generated of them, as we <U+017F>often the wax before we <U+017F>et on the <U+017F>eal.</p>
               <p>Now therefore, unle<U+017F>s we will be fooli<U+017F>h, as becau<U+017F>e the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form motion of the <hi>Air,</hi> or <U+017F>ome more <U+017F>ubtil <hi>corporeal Element,</hi> may <U+017F>o equally compre<U+017F>s or bear again<U+017F>t the parts of a little vaporous <hi>moi<U+017F>ture,</hi> as to form it into round drops (as we <U+017F>ee in the dew, and other experiments) and therefore becau<U+017F>e this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118922:11"/>
more rude and <hi>general</hi> motion can do <U+017F>omething, to conclude that it does all things; We mu<U+017F>t in all rea<U+017F>on confe<U+017F>s that there is an eternal <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> whereof the matter is thus u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully formed and changed.</p>
               <p>But meer rude and undirected <hi>motion,</hi> becau<U+017F>e naturally it will have <U+017F>ome kind of re<U+017F>ults, that therefore it will reach to <U+017F>uch as plainly imply a wi<U+017F>e contrivance of coun<U+017F>el, is <U+017F>o ridiculous a <hi>Sophi<U+017F>m,</hi> as I have already intimated, that it is more fit to impo<U+017F>e upon the incon<U+017F>iderate <hi><U+017F>ouls</hi> of <hi>fool</hi> &amp; <hi>children,</hi> then upon men of Mature Rea<U+017F>on, and well exerci<U+017F>ed in <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophy,</hi> or the <hi>grave</hi> and well <hi>practi<U+017F>ed, <U+017F>eraphically illuminated Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians.</hi> Admit that <hi>Rain,</hi> and <hi>Snow,</hi> and <hi>Wind,</hi> and <hi>Hail,</hi> and <hi>Ice,</hi> and <hi>Thunder,</hi> and <hi>Lightning,</hi> and a <hi>Star</hi> I mention for example, that may be let in among<U+017F>t Meteors, by <U+017F>ome called <hi>Hellens-<U+017F>tar,</hi> and is well known at Sea; I have <U+017F>een it <hi>melt Copper Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els</hi> a-board a <U+017F>hip; it cometh of an heap of <U+017F>uch vapors as are carryed by violent cro<U+017F>s Winds up from the Earth; and <U+017F>uch like <hi>Meteors</hi> may be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts of <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>cold,</hi> or of the motion and re<U+017F>t of certain <U+017F>mall particles of the matter; yet that the u<U+017F>eful and beautiful contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Branches, Flowers, and Fruits of Plants <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>o too, (to <U+017F>ay nothing yet of <hi>Minerals,</hi> and the bodies of men) is as ridiculous and <U+017F>upine a collection, as to infer, That becau<U+017F>e meer heat and cold does <U+017F>often and harden Wax, and puts it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <U+017F>ome <U+017F>hape or other, that therefore this meer heat and cold, or Motion and Re<U+017F>t, without any Art and Direction, made the <hi>Silver Seal</hi> too, and graved upon it <U+017F>o curiou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>ome Coate of Arms, or the <U+017F>hape of <U+017F>ome Bird or Bea<U+017F>t, as an Eagle, a Lyon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nay indeed this inference is more tolerable far then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the<U+017F>e effects of Art being more ea<U+017F>ie, and le<U+017F>s noble then tho<U+017F>e other of nature.</p>
               <p>Nor is it any deficiency at all in the Works of <hi>Nature,</hi> that <U+017F>ome particular <hi>Phaenomena</hi> be but the ea<U+017F>ie re<U+017F>ults of that general motion communicated unto the matter from <hi>God;</hi> others the effects of more curious contrivance, or of the <hi>Divine Ar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Rea<U+017F>on,</hi> (for <U+017F>uch are the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Rationes Seminales</hi>) incorporated in the Matter, e<U+017F>pecially the Matter it <U+017F>elf being in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ort vital, el<U+017F>e it would not continue the motion that it is put upon, when it is occa<U+017F>ionally this or the other way mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118922:11"/>
and be<U+017F>ides the Nature of <hi>God</hi> being the mo<U+017F>t perfect ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of life that is po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly conceiveable, it is very congruous that this outmo<U+017F>t and remote<U+017F>t <U+017F>hadow of him<U+017F>elf, be <U+017F>ome way, though but ob<U+017F>curely vital: Wherefore things falling off by degrees from the highe<U+017F>t perfection, it will be no uneven or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable <U+017F>tep, if de<U+017F>cending from the top of this utmo<U+017F>t Creation, <hi>Man,</hi> in whom there is a more fine conception, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexive Rea<U+017F>on, which hangs on, as every man hath <U+017F>o much experience as to have <U+017F>een the <hi>Sun,</hi> and other vi<U+017F>ible objects by reflexion in the Water and Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es; and this as yet <U+017F>hall be all I will <U+017F>ay for this rea<U+017F>on; I will give you more then I promi<U+017F>ed in the Contents, by four propo<U+017F>itions concerning the nature of conceptions, and they <U+017F>hall be proved; and al<U+017F>o of the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of <hi><U+017F>ence,</hi> that <hi>Colour</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> may be there where the thing <U+017F>een is not: But becau<U+017F>e it may be <U+017F>aid, That notwith<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Image</hi> in the <hi>Water</hi> be not in the object, but a thing meerly <hi>phanta<U+017F>tical,</hi> yet there may be colours really in the thing it <U+017F>elf, I will urge further this experience, That divers times men <U+017F>ee directly the <U+017F>ame object double, as two Candles for one, which may happen from di<U+017F>temper, or otherwi<U+017F>e without di<U+017F>temper if a man will; the <hi>Organs</hi> being either in their right temper, or equally di<U+017F>tempered, the <hi>colours</hi> and <hi>images</hi> in two <U+017F>uch <hi>characters</hi> of the <U+017F>ame thing, cannot be inherent therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e the thing <U+017F>een cannot be in two places.</p>
               <p>One of the<U+017F>e <hi>Images</hi> therefore is not inherent in the <hi>Object</hi> but the <U+017F>eeing, the <hi>Organs</hi> of the <U+017F>ight are then in equal temper or di<U+017F>temper, the one of them is no more inherent then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and con<U+017F>equently, neither of them both are in the <hi>Objects,</hi> which is the fir<U+017F>t propo<U+017F>ition mentioned in the precedent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the Image of any thing by reflexion in a gla<U+017F>s, or water, or the like, is not any thing in, or behind the gla<U+017F>s, or in, or under the Water, every man may grant to him<U+017F>elf; which is the <U+017F>econd propo<U+017F>ition of <hi>Des Cartes.</hi> For thirdly We are to con<U+017F>ider, fir<U+017F>t, That every great agitation or concu<U+017F><U+017F>ion of the brain (as it happeneth from a <U+017F>troke, e<U+017F>pecially if the <U+017F>troke be upon the eye) whereby the Optick Nerve <U+017F>uffereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great violence, there <hi>appeareth</hi> before the <hi>Eyes</hi> a certain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118922:12"/>
                  <hi>light,</hi> which light is nothing without, but an apparition onely; all that is real being the concu<U+017F><U+017F>ion or motion of the parts of the Nerve; from which experience we may conclude, That ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition of light is really nothing but motion within. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from Lucid bodies there can be derived motion, <U+017F>o as to affect the Optick Nerve in <U+017F>uch manner as is proper thereunto, there will follow an Image of light <U+017F>ome-where in that line by which the motion was la<U+017F>t derived to the eye, that is to <U+017F>ay, In the object, if we look directly on it, and in the Gla<U+017F>s or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when we look upon it in the line of reflexion, which in effect is the third propo<U+017F>ition, namely, That image and colour is but an apparition to us of that motion, agitation, or alteration, which the object worketh in the brain or <U+017F>pirits, or <U+017F>ome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance in the head.</p>
               <p>But that from all lucid, <U+017F>hining, and illuminate bodies, there is a motion produced to the eye, and thorow the eye, to the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Nerve</hi> and <U+017F>o into the <hi>Brain,</hi> by which the apparition of light or colour is effected, is not hard to prove. And fir<U+017F>t, it is evident that the Fire, the onely lucid body here upon Earth, worketh by motion equally every way, in<U+017F>omuch as the motion thereof <U+017F>topped or inclo<U+017F>ed, it is pre<U+017F>ently extingui<U+017F>hed, and no more fire. And further, That that motion whereby the fire worketh, is dilation and contraction of it <U+017F>elf alternately, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Scintillation, or glowing, is manife<U+017F>t al<U+017F>o by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; from <U+017F>uch motion in the fire mu<U+017F>t needs ari<U+017F>e a rejection, or ca<U+017F>ting from it <U+017F>elf off that part of the medium which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous to it, whereby that part al<U+017F>o rejecteth the next, and <U+017F>o <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively one part beateth back another to the very eye, and in the <U+017F>ame manner the exteriour part of the eye pre<U+017F><U+017F>eth the interiour, (the Laws of refraction <U+017F>till ob<U+017F>erved.) Now the interior coat of the eye is nothing el<U+017F>e but a piece of the Optick Nerve, and therefore the motion is <U+017F>till continued thereby into the <hi>Brain,</hi> and by re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance or re-action of the <hi>Brain,</hi> is al<U+017F>o a rebound into the Optick Nerve again, which we not conceiving as motion or rebound from within, do think it is without, and call it Light, as hath been already <U+017F>hewed by the experience of a <U+017F>troake: We have no rea<U+017F>on to doubt that the Fountain of Light, the Sun, worketh by any other ways then the <hi>Fire,</hi> at lea<U+017F>t
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118922:12"/>
in this matter; and thus all vi<U+017F>ion hath its original from <U+017F>uch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as is here de<U+017F>cribed; for where there is no light, there is no <U+017F>ight; and therefore colour mu<U+017F>t be the <U+017F>ame thing with light, as being the effect of the lucid bodies, their difference being one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, That when the light cometh directly from the Fountain to the eye, or indirectly by reflexion from clean and polite bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and <U+017F>uch as have not any polite bodies, and <U+017F>uch as have not any particular motion internal to alter it, we call it light; but when it cometh to the eye by reflexion from uneven, rough, and cour<U+017F>e bodies, or <U+017F>uch as are affected with internal motion of their own that may alter it, then we call it <hi>Colour;</hi> colour and light differing onely in this, that the one is pure, and the other perturbed light; by that which hath been <U+017F>aid, not onely the truth of the third propo<U+017F>ition, but al<U+017F>o the whole manner of producing light and colour, is apparent.</p>
               <p>As colour is not inherent in the object, but an effect thereof upon us, cau<U+017F>ed by <U+017F>uch motion in the object as hath been de<U+017F>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; <U+017F>o neither is <U+017F>ound in the thing we hear, but in our <U+017F>elves; one manife<U+017F>t <U+017F>ign thereof, is, That as man may <U+017F>ee, <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o he may hear double &amp; trebble by multiplication of Ecchoes, which Ecchoes are <U+017F>ounds as well as the Original; and not being in one and the <U+017F>ame place, cannot be inherent in the body that maketh them; nothing can make any thing which is not in it <U+017F>elf; the Clapper of a Bell hath no <U+017F>ound in it, but motion, and maketh motion in the internal parts of the Bell; <U+017F>o the Bell hath motion and not <U+017F>ound, that imparteth motion to the air; and the aire hath motion, but not <U+017F>ound; the air imparteth motion by the ear and nerve unto the <hi>Brain;</hi> and the Brain hath motion, but not <U+017F>ound; from the Brain it reboundeth back into the Nerves outward, and thence it becommeth an Apparition without, which we call <U+017F>ound; And to proceed to the re<U+017F>t of the <U+017F>ences, it is apparent enough, that the <U+017F>mell and ta<U+017F>te of the <U+017F>ame thing are not the <U+017F>ame to every man, and therefore are not in the thing <U+017F>melt or ta<U+017F>ted, but in the men; <U+017F>o likewi<U+017F>e the heat we feel from the fire is manife<U+017F>tly in us, and is quite different from the heat which is in the fire; for our heat is plea<U+017F>ure or pain, according as it is great or moderate; but in the cool there is no <U+017F>uch thing: By this the la<U+017F>t is proved, <hi>viz.</hi> that as in vi<U+017F>ion,
<pb facs="tcp:118922:13"/>
<U+017F>o al<U+017F>o in Conceptions that ari<U+017F>e from other <U+017F>en<U+017F>es, the <U+017F>ubject of their inherence is not in the object, but in the Sentinent; And from hence al<U+017F>o it followeth that what<U+017F>oever accidents or qualities our <U+017F>ences make us think there be in the world, they be not there, but are <U+017F>eeming and apparitions only; the things that really are in the world without us, are tho<U+017F>e motions by which the<U+017F>e <U+017F>eemings are cau<U+017F>ed; and this is the great deception of <U+017F>ence, which al<U+017F>o is to be by <U+017F>ence corrected: for as <U+017F>ence telleth me when I <U+017F>ee directly, that the colour <U+017F>eemeth to be in the object; <U+017F>o al<U+017F>o <U+017F>ence telleth me when I <U+017F>ee by reflection, that colour is in the object. But now I am out of the way from the outward Creation of Man, in whom there is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of more fine and reflexive rea<U+017F>on, which hangs on, though not in that manner, in the more perfect kinde of Brutes, as <U+017F>ence al<U+017F>o (loth to be curbed with too narrow compa<U+017F>s) layes hold upon <U+017F>ome kinde of plants, as in tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>undry <U+017F>orts of <hi>Zoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyta,</hi> but in the re<U+017F>t there are no further foot<U+017F>teps di<U+017F>covered of an animadver<U+017F>ive forme abiding in them; yet there be the effects of an inadvertent forme (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap>) of materiated or incorporated Art or <U+017F>eminal Rea<U+017F>on; I <U+017F>ay it is no uneven jot to pa<U+017F>s from the more faint and ob<U+017F>cure example of Sperma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical life, to the more Con<U+017F>iderable effects of general Motion in <hi>Mineralls, Metalls,</hi> nor yet to <U+017F>ay any thing of the Medicines extracted, mortified, fixt, di<U+017F><U+017F>olv'd and incorporated with their proper Veagles, becau<U+017F>e we have intended it our la<U+017F>t bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s to return to Mineralls, Mettals, and <U+017F>undry Meteors, who<U+017F>e ea<U+017F>ie and rude <U+017F>hapes have no need of any particular principle of life, or Spermatical form di<U+017F>tinct from the re<U+017F>t, or motion of the particles of the matter.</p>
               <p>But there is that curio<U+017F>ity of form and beauty in the more noble kinde of Plants, bearing <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>utablene<U+017F>s and harmony with the more refined <U+017F>ence and <U+017F>agacity of the <U+017F>oul of Man, that he cannot choo<U+017F>e (his intellectual touch being <U+017F>o <U+017F>weetly gratified by what it deprehends in <U+017F>uch like objects,) but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that <U+017F>ome hidden cau<U+017F>e much a-kin to his own nature that is intellectual, is the contriver and perfecter of the<U+017F>e <U+017F>o plea<U+017F>ant <U+017F>pectacles in the world.</p>
               <p>Nor is it at all to the purpo<U+017F>e to object that this bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118922:13"/>
                  <hi>Beauty</hi> and comeline<U+017F>s of proportion is but a conceit, becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome men acknowledge no <U+017F>uch thing, and all things are alike hand<U+017F>ome to them, who yet notwith<U+017F>tanding have the u<U+017F>e of their eyes as well as other folks; for I <U+017F>ay, this rather makes for what we aim at, that <hi>Pulchritudo</hi> is conveyed indeed by the outward <U+017F>ences unto the <U+017F>oul, but a more intellectual faculty is that which reli<U+017F>hes it; as an <hi>A<U+017F>trologicall,</hi> or better, a <hi>Geometricall Scheam</hi> is let in by the eyes, but the <hi>Demon<U+017F>tration</hi> is di<U+017F>cern'd by <hi>Rea<U+017F>on:</hi> And therefore it is more rational to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <U+017F>ome intellectual principle was the Author of this <hi>Pulchritude</hi> of things, then that they <U+017F>hould be thus fa<U+017F>hion'd without the help of that principle: And to <U+017F>ay there is no <U+017F>uch thing as <hi>Pulchritude,</hi> and <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay, there is no <hi>way to felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> The fir<U+017F>t, I an<U+017F>wer, is becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome mens <U+017F>ouls are <U+017F>o dull and <U+017F>tupid. And the <U+017F>econd is that they never knew <hi>The way to bli<U+017F>s,</hi> The fir<U+017F>t cannot reli<U+017F>h all objects alike in that re<U+017F>pect; The <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond knows not <hi>Happine<U+017F>s,</hi> nor the <hi>way to long life,</hi> nor the <hi>means to Health,</hi> nor how to <hi>return from Age to Youth, &amp;c.</hi> which is as ab<U+017F>urd and groundle<U+017F>s as to conclude there is no <U+017F>uch thing as <hi>Rea<U+017F>on</hi> and <hi>Demon<U+017F>tration,</hi> becau<U+017F>e a natural fool cannot reach unto it. But that there is <U+017F>uch a thing as <hi>The way to Bli<U+017F>s, Long life,</hi> and a certain way to <hi>Health,</hi> not as yet known in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I will demon<U+017F>trate in a Treati<U+017F>e by it <U+017F>elf; <hi>The way to Health</hi> I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>hew you anon in this book, the re<U+017F>t in another Part, as I promi<U+017F>ed you.</p>
               <p>Now that there is <U+017F>uch a thing as Beauty, and that it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the whole generations of men, to be in Trees, flowers and fruits, and the adorning of buildings in all Ages, is an example, and undenyable te<U+017F>timony; for what is more and ordinary with them then taking in flowers and fruitage for the garni<U+017F>hing of their work? Be<U+017F>ides I appeal to any man that is not <U+017F>unk into <U+017F>o forlorne a pitch of Degeneracy; that he is as <U+017F>tupid to the<U+017F>e things as the ba<U+017F>e<U+017F>t of Bea<U+017F>ts, whether for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a rightly cut <hi>Tetrae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum, cube</hi> or <hi>Ico<U+017F>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>drum,</hi> have no more pulchritude in them, then any rude <hi>broken <U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one</hi> lying in the field or high-wayes; Or to name other <U+017F>olid Figures which though they be not regular properly <U+017F>o called, yet have a <U+017F>etled Idea, &amp; Nature, as a <hi>Cone, Sphere,</hi> or <hi>Cylinder,</hi> whether the <U+017F>ight of the<U+017F>e
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118922:14"/>
do not gratifie the mindes of men more, and pretend to more elegancy of <U+017F>hape, then tho<U+017F>e rude cuttings or chippings of <hi>free-<U+017F>tone</hi> that fall from the Ma<U+017F>ons hands, and <U+017F>erve for nothing but to fill up the middle of the wall, and <U+017F>o to be hid from the eyes of Man for their ugline<U+017F>s: And it is ob<U+017F>ervable, That if Nature <U+017F>hape any thing neer this <hi>Geometrical</hi> accuracy, that we take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it with much content and plea<U+017F>ure, as if it be but exactly round, as there be abundance of <U+017F>uch <U+017F>tones upon <hi>Me<U+017F>que,</hi> a hill in <hi>Arabia,</hi> I have <U+017F>een them there, or ordinarily Quinquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, or have the <U+017F>ides but parallels, though the Angles be une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, as is <U+017F>een in <U+017F>ome little <U+017F>tones, and in a kinde of Alabla<U+017F>ter found here in <hi>England,</hi> and other pretty <U+017F>tones found upon <hi>Bulverton-hill</hi> neer <hi>Sidmouth</hi> in <hi>Devon<U+017F>hire;</hi> and neer <hi>Stratford</hi> upon <hi>Avon,</hi> and in <hi>Tyms Grove</hi> at <hi>Colton</hi> in <hi>Warwicke<U+017F>hire,</hi> are found <U+017F>uch <U+017F>tones that grow naturally carved with various works, <U+017F>ome with Ro<U+017F>es, others with Lyons, Eagles, and all manner of delightfull works; The<U+017F>e <U+017F>tones I <U+017F>ay, gratifie our <U+017F>ight, as having a nearer cognation with the <U+017F>oul of man that is rational and intellectual, and therefore is well plea<U+017F>ed when it meets with any outward object that fits and agrees with tho<U+017F>e congenite Ideas her own nature is furni<U+017F>hed with: For <hi>Symme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, Equality,</hi> and <hi>Corre<U+017F>pondency</hi> of parts, is the di<U+017F>cernment of Rea<U+017F>on, not the object of Sence, as I have in another place proved.</p>
               <p>Now therefore it being evident, that there is <U+017F>uch a thing as <hi>Beauty, Symmetry</hi> and <hi>Comeline<U+017F>s</hi> of proportion, (to <U+017F>ay nothing of the delightful mixture of colours, and that this is the proper object of the Under<U+017F>tanding and Rea<U+017F>on; for the<U+017F>e things be not taken notice of by the Bea<U+017F>ts) I think I may <U+017F>afely inferre, that what<U+017F>oever is the fir<U+017F>t and principal cau<U+017F>e of changing the fluid and undeterminated Matter into <U+017F>hapes <U+017F>o comely and <U+017F>ymmetrical, as we <U+017F>ee in flowers and trees, is an under<U+017F>tanding Principle, and knowes both the nature of man, and of tho<U+017F>e objects he offers to his <U+017F>ight in this outward and vi<U+017F>ible world, and would have man <U+017F>earch and finde out tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ecrets by the which he might keep his body in health many hundreds of years, and at la<U+017F>t find <hi>the way to Bli<U+017F>s;</hi> for the<U+017F>e things cannot come by chance, or by a Multiranious attempt of the parts of the matter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118922:14"/>
upon them<U+017F>elves, for then it were likely that the <U+017F>pecies of things though <U+017F>ome might hit right, yet mo<U+017F>t would be maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ridiculous; but now there is not any ineptitude in any thing which is a <U+017F>ign that the fluidne<U+017F><U+017F>e of the matter is guided and determined by the overpowering coun<U+017F>el of an eternall mind.</p>
               <p>If it were not needle<U+017F><U+017F>e, I might in<U+017F>tance in <U+017F>undry kinds of flowers herbs and trees; but the<U+017F>e objects being <U+017F>o obvious, and every mans fancy being brauched with the remembrance of <hi>Ro<U+017F>es, Marigolds, Gelliflowers, Pionies, Tulips, Pau<U+017F>ies, Primro<U+017F>es,</hi> the leaves and clu<U+017F>ters of the Vine &amp;c. Of all which you mu<U+017F>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>s that there is in them beauty and <U+017F>ymetry, and u<U+017F>e in Phy<U+017F>ick, and gratefull proportion; I hold it <U+017F>uperfluity to weary you with any longer induction, but <U+017F>hall pa<U+017F>s on to tho<U+017F>e con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions behind, of their <U+017F>eed, <U+017F>ignaure and u<U+017F>efullne<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>hall pa<U+017F>s through them very briefly, and then I <U+017F>hall come to minerall Medicines, the<U+017F>e ob<U+017F>ervables being very nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary fir<U+017F>t to be known by way of an Introduction, and as ordinary and ea<U+017F>ily Intelligible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118922:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Seeds and Signatures of Plants, and wherefore <hi>GOD</hi> made them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>EVery plant hath its <U+017F>eed; Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians therefore <U+017F>ay there are <U+017F>ecret My<U+017F>teries lye hidden in them, which <U+017F>hould be our delight to find out; for Divine Providence made all good for the u<U+017F>e of man: And this being no nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary re<U+017F>ult of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter, as the whole contrivance of the plant indeed is not; and it being of great con<U+017F>equence that they have Seed for the continuance of propagation of their whole Species, and for the gratifying of mans Art al<U+017F>o, indu<U+017F>try and nece<U+017F><U+017F>itie, (for much of Husbandry and Gardening lies in this) it cannot but be the Act of <hi>Coun<U+017F>el</hi> to furni<U+017F>h the <U+017F>everal kinds of Plants with their Seeds, e<U+017F>pecially the Earth being of <U+017F>uch a nature that though at fir<U+017F>t for a while it might bring forth all manner of <hi>Plantts,</hi> (as <U+017F>ome will have it al<U+017F>o to have brought forth all kinds of <hi>Animals</hi>) yet at la<U+017F>t it would grow <U+017F>o <U+017F>luggi<U+017F>h, that without the advantage of tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>mall compendious principles of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the Grain of Seed would yeild no <U+017F>uch births, no more then a Pump grown dry will yeild any Water, unle<U+017F>s you pour a little Water into it fir<U+017F>t, and then for <U+017F>o many Ba<U+017F>ons full, you may fetch up as many Tankards full.</p>
               <p>Nor is it material to object that <U+017F>tinking Weeds, and <hi>poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onous Plants</hi> bear <hi>Seed</hi> too, as well as the mo<U+017F>t plea<U+017F>ant and u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for even tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>tinking <hi>Weeds,</hi> and <hi>poy<U+017F>onous Plants</hi> have their u<U+017F>e in <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> as you <U+017F>hall know hereafter; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides our common Phy<U+017F>ick-Mongers often u<U+017F>e them as their Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy guides them, grounded upon no other rea<U+017F>on then woful and deadly experience; <U+017F>ometimes the indu<U+017F>try of man is exerci<U+017F>ed by them to weed them out where they are hurtful, which rea<U+017F>ons if they <U+017F>eeme fleight, let us but con<U+017F>ider, that if hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane indu<U+017F>try had nothing to conflict and <U+017F>truggle with, the fire of mans <U+017F>pirit would behalf extingui<U+017F>hed in the fle<U+017F>h, and then we <U+017F>hall acknowledge that that which I have alledged is not <U+017F>o contemptible nor invalid.</p>
               <p>But <U+017F>econdly, Who knows but it is <U+017F>o with poy<U+017F>onous <hi>Plants,</hi> as vulgarly is fancyed concerning Toads, and other poy<U+017F>onous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118922:15"/>
Serpents that lick the Venom from off the Earth? So poy<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Plants may well draw to them all the Maligne Juice and nouri<U+017F>hment, that the other may be more pure and defae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, as there are Recepticles in the body of man, and Emuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to drain them of <U+017F>uperfluous Choler and Melancholy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>La<U+017F>tly, It is very well known by them that know any thing in Nature and Phy<U+017F>ick, That tho<U+017F>e Herbs that the rude and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant would call <hi>Weeds,</hi> are the materials of very <hi><U+017F>overaign Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines,</hi> that <hi>Aconitum Hyemale,</hi> or <hi>Winter Wolfs bain,</hi> that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<U+017F>e is rank poy<U+017F>on, is reported to prevail mightily again<U+017F>t the biting of Vipers, Scorpions, and mad dogs, which Sir <hi>Chri<U+017F>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Heydon</hi> a<U+017F><U+017F>enteth unto; and that that plant that bears death in the very Name of it, <hi>Solanum Lethiferum,</hi> prevents death by procuring <U+017F>leep, if it be ayplyed in a Fever; nor are tho<U+017F>e things to be deemed uprofitable, <U+017F>ay the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> who<U+017F>e u<U+017F>e our heavy ignorance will not let us under<U+017F>tand; but they will teach us as followeth.</p>
               <p>We come now to the <U+017F>ignatures of plants, which indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pects us more properly and adaequately then the other, and is a Key (as <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> <U+017F>ay) to enter man into the knowledge and u<U+017F>e of the Trea<U+017F>ures of nature; I demand therefore, Whether it be not a very ea<U+017F>ie and Genuine inference from the ob<U+017F>erving that <U+017F>everal herbs are marked with <U+017F>ome mark or <U+017F>ign that intimates their vertue, what they are good for; and there being <U+017F>uch a creature as man in the World that can read &amp; under<U+017F>tand the<U+017F>e <U+017F>igns and characters, hence to collect that the Author both of man and them, knew the nature of them both; and be<U+017F>ides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence would onely initiate and enter mankind in the u<U+017F>eful knowledge of her Trea<U+017F>ures by the Seraphical illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians, leaving the re<U+017F>t to employ the vulgar that they might not be idle; for the Theater of the World is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erci<U+017F>e of mans wit, and therefore all things are in <U+017F>ome mea<U+017F>ure ob<U+017F>cure and intricate; that the <U+017F>edulity of that divine <U+017F>park, the <U+017F>oul of man, may have matter of conque<U+017F>t and triumph, when he hath done bravely by a <U+017F>uperadvenient a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of God.</p>
               <p>But that there be <U+017F>ome plants that bear a very evident <U+017F>igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their nature and u<U+017F>e, for example, <hi>Capillus veneris, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trichon,</hi> or <hi>Maiden-hair;</hi> the Lye in which it is <U+017F>odden or infus'd,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118922:16"/>
is good to wa<U+017F>h the head, and make the <hi>hair grow</hi> in tho<U+017F>e places that are <hi>bare;</hi> the <hi>decoction of Quinces,</hi> which are a downey and hairy Fruit, is accounted good for the <hi>fetching again hair</hi> that hath been fallen by the <hi>French Pox;</hi> the Leaf of <hi>Balm and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluia,</hi> or <hi>Wood-Sorrel,</hi> as al<U+017F>o the <hi>roots of Anthora,</hi> repre<U+017F>ent the heart in figure, and are <hi>Cordiacal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Walnuts</hi> beare the whole <hi><U+017F>ignature</hi> of the <hi>head;</hi> the outward green <hi>Cortex</hi> an<U+017F>wers to the <hi>Pericranium,</hi> and a Salt made of it is <U+017F>ingular good for Wounds in that part, as the <hi>Kernel</hi> is good for the <hi>Brains,</hi> which it re<U+017F>embles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vmbelicus Veneris</hi> is powerful to provoke <hi>lu<U+017F>t,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Culpep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> affirms; as al<U+017F>o your <U+017F>everal <U+017F>orts of <hi>Satyrions,</hi> which have the evident re<U+017F>emblance of the genetal parts upon them; <hi>Aron</hi> e<U+017F>pecially, and all your <hi>Orchi<U+017F><U+017F>es,</hi> that they have given Names unto, from <U+017F>ome bea<U+017F>t or other, as <hi>Cyno<U+017F>orchis, Orchis Miodes, Tragorchis, &amp;c.</hi> the la<U+017F>t whereof notoriorious for its Goati<U+017F>h <U+017F>mell, and Tufts not unlike the Beard of that Lecherous Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, is of all the re<U+017F>t the mo<U+017F>t powerful incentive to lu<U+017F>t.</p>
               <p>The Leaves of <hi>Hypericon</hi> are very thick pricked, or pointed with little holes, and it is a <U+017F>ingular good Wound-herb, as u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful al<U+017F>o for de-ob<U+017F>tructing the pores of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorpioides, Echium,</hi> or <hi>Scorpions gra<U+017F><U+017F>e,</hi> is like the crooked Tayle of a <hi>Scorpion;</hi> and <hi>Ophioglo<U+017F><U+017F>um,</hi> or <hi>Adders Tongue,</hi> hath a very plain and perfect re<U+017F>emblance of the Tongue of a Serpent; as al<U+017F>o <hi>Ophio<U+017F>corodon</hi> of the intire head and upper-parts of the body; and the<U+017F>e are all held very good again<U+017F>t poy<U+017F>on, and the biting of Serpents; and generally all <U+017F>uch plants as are <U+017F>peckled with <U+017F>pots like the Skins of Vipers, or other venemous creatures, are known to be good again<U+017F>t the <U+017F>tings or bitings of them, and are powerful objects again<U+017F>t poy<U+017F>on.</p>
               <p>Thus did divine providence by natural <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> read <U+017F>hort <hi>Lectures</hi> to the rude wit of vulgar man; others of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphically illuminated Fraternity,</hi> being entred, and <U+017F>ufficiently experienced of the<U+017F>e, found out the re<U+017F>t, it being very rea<U+017F>ona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that other herbs that had not <U+017F>uch <U+017F>ignatures, might be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for Medicinal u<U+017F>es, as well as they that had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> have quickned and actuated their Phlegmatick natures to more frequent and effectual <hi>venery;</hi> for their <hi>long
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118922:16"/>
lives health,</hi> &amp; <hi>youthfulne<U+017F>s,</hi> <U+017F>hews they were not very fiery, to <U+017F>ay nothing of their <hi>happine<U+017F><U+017F>e, riches, wi<U+017F>dom and vertue,</hi> becau<U+017F>e I have in my Treati<U+017F>e of <hi>The way to bli<U+017F><U+017F>e,</hi> <U+017F>poken of it largely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the u<U+017F>efulne<U+017F><U+017F>e of Plants, and of the Works of God.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>YOu <U+017F>hal now briefly take notice of the u<U+017F>efulnes &amp; profitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s of plants both for Phy<U+017F>ick and Food, and then pa<U+017F>s on to the con<U+017F>ideration of the in<U+017F>pired <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> what their Medicines are: As for the common u<U+017F>es of Plants, <hi>Herbals</hi> teach you <U+017F>omething; but I refer you to the <hi><U+017F>ingular Medicines of Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> in my Book of <hi>The way to bli<U+017F>s</hi> for the <U+017F>alvation of your health, Animals know as much by in<U+017F>tinct and nature; and that which is mo<U+017F>t ob<U+017F>ervable here, is this, That brute Bea<U+017F>ts know as much as many Phy<U+017F>icians do that are taught by Herbals onely; and the<U+017F>e deny the power of God in the Works of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the power of Nature in the skill of man, that it <U+017F>hould be impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to make <hi>Trees bear fruit in December, and Apple-trees to grow to blo<U+017F><U+017F>om, and bear Apples contrary to kind in March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bea<U+017F>ts have knowledge in the vertue of Plants as well as men, for the Toad being overcharged with the poy<U+017F>on of the Spider, (as is well known) hath recour<U+017F>e to the Plantane-Leaf. The Wea<U+017F>el when <U+017F>he is to encounter the Serpent, arms her <U+017F>elf with eating of Rue. The Dog when he is <U+017F>ick at the <U+017F>tomack, knows his cure, falls to his gra<U+017F>s, vomits, and is well. The Swallows make u<U+017F>e of <hi>Celandine,</hi> the Lennet of <hi>Euphragia</hi> for the repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their <U+017F>ight. And the A<U+017F>s when he is oppre<U+017F><U+017F>ed with melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, eats of the Herb <hi>A<U+017F>plenium,</hi> or <hi>Miltwa<U+017F>t</hi> &amp; <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>es him<U+017F>elf of the <U+017F>welling of the <U+017F>pleen. The Raven makes u<U+017F>e of <hi>Cinquefoyle</hi> for the prolongation of his life to <U+017F>omtimes <U+017F>ix or <U+017F>evenhundred years; and therefore I think it is that the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> pre<U+017F>cribe the oyle of <hi>Ravens, Swallows,</hi> and <hi>Harts</hi> for the u<U+017F>e of man to annoint him<U+017F>elf, to continue his fle<U+017F>h and well-complexioned body from wrinkles and lamene<U+017F>s; and <hi>Dictamnum Creten<U+017F>e</hi> is much u<U+017F>ed, as I told you in my <hi>Wi<U+017F>e mans Crown; Cretian Ditta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> cures Wounds of what nature <U+017F>oever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118922:17"/>Which thing I conceive no ob<U+017F>cure indigation of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; for they doing that by in<U+017F>tinct and Nature, which men who have free Rea<U+017F>on cannot but acknowledge to be very pertinent and fitting, nay <U+017F>uch that the skilfulle<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an will approve and allow; and the<U+017F>e creatures having no <U+017F>uch rea<U+017F>on and skill them<U+017F>elves as to turn Phy<U+017F>icians, it mu<U+017F>t needs be concluded by vertue of that principle that contrived them, and made them of that Nature they are, enabled them al<U+017F>o to do the<U+017F>e things.</p>
               <p>Let us now con<U+017F>ider the Fruits of the Trees, where I think it will appear very manife<U+017F>tly, That there was one <hi>worker of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and in<U+017F>pirer of Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians;</hi> I might now reach out to Exortick-Plants, <U+017F>uch as the <hi>Cinamon-Tree,</hi> the <hi>Bal<U+017F>ome-Tree,</hi> and the Tree that bears the Nutmeg, invelopped the Mace; as al<U+017F>o the famous Indian Nut-Tree, which at once (as the Ro<U+017F>ie Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians <U+017F>ay) affords almo<U+017F>t all the nece<U+017F><U+017F>aries of life; for if they cut but the Twigs at Evening, there is a plentiful and plea<U+017F>ant Juice comes out, which they receive into Bottles, and drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tead of Wine, and out of which they extract <U+017F>uch an Aquae Vitae as is very <U+017F>overaign again<U+017F>t all manner of <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>es, the branches and boughs they make their Hou<U+017F>es of, and the body of the tree being very <U+017F>pongy within, though hard without, they ea<U+017F>ily contrive into the frame and u<U+017F>e of their <hi>Canoes,</hi> or <hi>boats.</hi> the Kernel of the Nut <U+017F>erves them for bread and meat, and the Shells for Cups to drink in; and indeed they are not meer empty Cups, for there is found a delicious cooling milk in them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ides there is a kind of hemp that inclo<U+017F>es the Nut, of which they make Ropes and Cables, and of the fine<U+017F>t of it, Sayles for their <U+017F>hips; and the Leaves are <U+017F>o hard and <U+017F>harp pointed, that they ea<U+017F>ily make Needles or Bodkins of them for <U+017F>titching their Sayles, and for other nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary purpo<U+017F>es; and that Providence may <U+017F>hew her <U+017F>elf benigne as well as wi<U+017F>e, this <U+017F>o notable a Plant is not re<U+017F>train'd to one coa<U+017F>t of the World as the Ea<U+017F>t-Indies, but is found in <hi>Affrica, Arabia,</hi> and in all the I<U+017F>lands of the We<U+017F>t-Indies, as <hi>Hi<U+017F>paniola, Cuba,</hi> where our men are victorers; and <U+017F>everal other places of the new-found World.</p>
               <p>But I thought fit to in<U+017F>i<U+017F>t upon the<U+017F>e things by way of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, but to contain my <U+017F>elf within the compa<U+017F>s of <U+017F>uch
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118922:17"/>
objects as are nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for our knowledge, and familiarly and ordinarily before our eyes, that we may the better (the<U+017F>e things under<U+017F>tood) take occa<U+017F>ion from thence to demon<U+017F>trate the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ie Crucian way to health, and their ordinary Medicines which to us are not as yet known.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> way how to get health; The cau<U+017F>es why we eat food; Of the fir<U+017F>t nature of the World; A mea<U+017F>ure of raw and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate meat, and the cau<U+017F>e of the fiery, and <U+017F>oummy Gall and needle<U+017F>s muddy bowels the melt; nature carele<U+017F>s of making the reins of Urine drawers, drinkle<U+017F>s animals have none at all; how to clen<U+017F>e your <U+017F>elf from the<U+017F>e idle Bowels and avoid all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>DO you not con<U+017F>ider the weakne<U+017F><U+017F>e of man, what faculties he hath, and in what order he is in re<U+017F>pect of the re<U+017F>t of the creatures; <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> ob<U+017F>erve though his body be weake and di<U+017F>armed, yet his inward abilities of rea<U+017F>on, and artificiall contrivance is admirable; he is much given to <U+017F>earch out the <hi>Medicinall virtues</hi> of <hi>Plants, Wights,</hi> and <hi>Mineralls,</hi> and hath found out tho<U+017F>e that were of <U+017F>o pre<U+017F>ent and great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equence as to be Antidotes again<U+017F>t poy<U+017F>on that would <U+017F>o quickly have di<U+017F>patched mankind, it were good for us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<U+017F>trate the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Medicines,</hi> now our <hi>land is afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s called the new di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, of which all <U+017F>orts dye,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy, for none as yet have pre<U+017F>cribed a <hi>Medicine, for young men</hi> that de<U+017F>ire to live, and for old men that wi<U+017F>h for health, without which no life is <U+017F>weet and <U+017F>avory, then let us bend our <U+017F>elves to cure our brethren fir<U+017F>t, and endeavour to <U+017F>hew the means (be<U+017F>ides the commmon Collegian Doctors drenches, or <hi>Culpepers</hi> way, how every man may get and keep his health, that is <U+017F>omething <U+017F>trange but a vowed truth; the con<U+017F>ent &amp; equall (I mean agreeable to kind) temper &amp; dulling our four fir<U+017F>t beginnings, the <U+017F>taff of our bodies, for if this knot be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118922:18"/>
broken, &amp; they loo<U+017F> towards their former liberty, they wax proud and <U+017F>trong, and fight, for their nature is together by the ears, and put us to pain, and lets the rule of nature, and this they call the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>Then to handle one at once as our manner is, and will keep our cu<U+017F>tom <U+017F>till, to keep our health and body in temper, <U+017F>eems no <U+017F>uch matter to me as the world would make it, even plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, when I know all the wayes and entries to let in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and di<U+017F>tempers of the body, may by <U+017F>mall heed be <hi><U+017F>toped</hi> and <hi>fenced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee mu<U+017F>t needs draw breath and eat meat; for the cau<U+017F>e I <U+017F>hall <U+017F>peake of it in its place; and as this is not all clear and agreeable, <U+017F>o <hi>nature</hi> hath her leavings; and again <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>rest</hi> are <hi>needful,</hi> and perhaps we cannot chu<U+017F>e but be moved in mind with joy, greife, fear, hope, and <U+017F>uch like pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, though the <hi>Stoick</hi> deny nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity, <U+017F>aith <hi>Des Carte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <U+017F>o many wayes and gat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es may enter, if they be not well watced and looked unto, which may be done in rea<U+017F>on, and hath been done often, as they a<U+017F><U+017F>ure us that have lived long without all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e and <U+017F>ickne<U+017F><U+017F>es, as <hi>Iohn Harding</hi> relates of a Mini<U+017F>ter called <hi>Iohn Macklaine</hi> to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the<U+017F>e four<U+017F>core years la<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>t together in health, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his hair, teeth, eys &amp; fle<U+017F>h renued, &amp; became yong again, &amp; <U+017F>uch like <U+017F>tories are to be found enough if we might <U+017F>tay to <U+017F>eek them; <U+017F>ome are contented for all but air and meat, but the<U+017F>e <U+017F>ay they have often <U+017F>eeds of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es lye hid in them unable to be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>een or prevented, as we find tho<U+017F>e meats that make the fine<U+017F>t <U+017F>hew, (as Wine and Sugar) and <U+017F>uch enticeing baites, to have hid in them mo<U+017F>t hateful di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es and dregs in the bottom; <U+017F>o the air when it <U+017F>eems the be<U+017F>t and highe<U+017F>t, yet is <U+017F>ometimes infected and poy<U+017F>oned with venemous breath <U+017F>ent out and thru<U+017F>t into it either from below or from the <U+017F>cars of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and as the cau<U+017F>e is hidden and unknown to us, <U+017F>o the hurt impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be avoyed and prevented.</p>
               <p>If I li<U+017F>t to let my <U+017F>peech run at large, e<U+017F>pecialy in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens grounds, I could finde that that Divi<U+017F>ion is fal<U+017F>e, fir<U+017F>t, (to come to meat anon) and then if it were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118922:18"/>
true, yet the cau<U+017F>e of that infection not unable to be fore<U+017F>een and warded; but I am <U+017F>o <U+017F>orry for the fault above, that I can the better take heed hereafter; yet methinks it is a grief to hear the harmle<U+017F>s and glorious divine things above <U+017F>o defaced with <U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and no man makes an<U+017F>wer for them.</p>
               <p>Gentle Reader, be plea<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>tay a little; If the <hi>Stars</hi> have no light, and <U+017F>o no power but from the <hi>Sun,</hi> that mo<U+017F>t whol<U+017F>ome and pro<U+017F>perous creature, then they hurt him mo<U+017F>t wrongfully, and reprove them<U+017F>elves very rightly. And again, if they be but a piece of the finer part; and fir<U+017F>t nature, as it were, of the World, as I have <U+017F>hewed in my Book of the <hi>The Wi<U+017F>e Mans Crown,</hi> then they be the whol<U+017F>ome<U+017F>t things in the World; <U+017F>o far be they from poy<U+017F>oned <U+017F>lander: And <U+017F>o let their Lights be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <U+017F>o gro<U+017F>ly mingled in their meetings, and thereby that <U+017F>tate of the Weather changed <U+017F>uddenly, and from thence our bodie's troubled and turned into Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, becau<U+017F>e they were not prepared and made ready for it, yet the things are good and pro<U+017F>perous; and by knowledge of A<U+017F>trology, or influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Planets, and races of the <U+017F>tars, we may prepare our <U+017F>elves, and prevent all, if we cannot have that happine<U+017F>s to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>e with our <hi>Guardian Genius.</hi> Now for lower reflexion, it is not worth the an<U+017F>wering when there is <U+017F>o much wa<U+017F>te ground in the World; then let us pa<U+017F>s over to that other <hi>Breach;</hi> may we not <U+017F>hun the leaving baits in our Dyet, and take <U+017F>uch meat as is mo<U+017F>t temperate and near our Nature, and then dre<U+017F>s the <U+017F>ame after the mo<U+017F>t kindly and whol<U+017F>ome manner, <U+017F>ea<U+017F>oning it well with labour, mirth and <U+017F>leep?</p>
               <p>And to be plain, I have <U+017F>hewed in another Treati<U+017F>e of mine, entituled, <hi>The way to bli<U+017F><U+017F>e,</hi> <U+017F>o much noted by our Writers, what a jewel of health it were to u<U+017F>e all raw &amp; temperate meat, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F> we be wi<U+017F>e &amp; vertuous, and this Dyet would perhaps change our Nature of fire, but like <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophers,</hi> a quite contrary way; taking the be<U+017F>t, when as none is lo<U+017F>t, and leaving the wor<U+017F>t, which is that we now take, a Way I <U+017F>ay, to <U+017F>trip of all gro<U+017F>sne<U+017F>s and foulne<U+017F>s of bodies, the only hurt of them<U+017F>elves, and is the Food of all Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es.</p>
               <p>I will tell you another way which you will think <U+017F>trange, but you <U+017F>hall find it true; if the meat be temperate, as I bid you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118922:19"/>
chu<U+017F>e it, there is no hurt can come thereby, (if you keep mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure in your <U+017F>elves) <U+017F>ave from your leavings; the<U+017F>e in <U+017F>o clear a Dyet fir<U+017F>t will be very few; but if you would be ruled by my <hi>Coun<U+017F>el which Nature taught me,</hi> tho<U+017F>e few <U+017F>hould never hurt you.</p>
               <p>Of all the Leavings in the body, there are three which the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver maketh mo<U+017F>t trouble<U+017F>ome unto us, (for the re<U+017F>t are ea<U+017F>ily di<U+017F>patched) a light and ea<U+017F>ie, or rather a <hi>fiery</hi> (as <U+017F>ome call) <hi>Choller;</hi> a cold and heavy mud, called <hi>Melancholly;</hi> and the third is <hi>Vrine,</hi> which I wil treat of in the next Chapter but tho<U+017F>e two the wor<U+017F>er, and this fault is not in them<U+017F>elves, but all by rea<U+017F>on of the needle<U+017F>s and hurtful bowels in our bodies, (as the Seeds-man u<U+017F>eth to <U+017F>ow good and bad together) which being of the <U+017F>ame kind and quality with tho<U+017F>e humors, do draw and pul them <U+017F>til unto them (as all other parts and things do) for their Food and nouri<U+017F>hment and <U+017F>o by the narrow pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages to and fro, their greedine<U+017F>s in pulling and holding, and a hundred <U+017F>uch means, <U+017F>ubject to great mi<U+017F>chances, have brought in as many mi<U+017F>chiefs, whereas Nature the great expeller of her unlike, and Enemies, if <U+017F>he had free choice and liberty, would otherwi<U+017F>e with ca<U+017F>e, and without hurt, expel tho<U+017F>e Leavings, e<U+017F>pecially <U+017F>o <U+017F>mall a number of the better <U+017F>ort in <U+017F>o clean a Dyet; nay, <U+017F>et the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of tho<U+017F>e parts, (tho<U+017F>e parts are <hi>Melt-Gall,</hi> and <hi>Reins</hi>) if there be not <U+017F>ufficient <U+017F>tore of other <U+017F>oul meat at hand, like a poy<U+017F>oned or a purging Medicine, they u<U+017F>e to draw good Juices, and to make Food of them; what is not manife<U+017F>ted in this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <U+017F>hall methodically be demon<U+017F>trated in the en<U+017F>uing, for I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be <U+017F>erious in this part of my Book, and will <U+017F>hew you what Nature taught me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118922:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Medicines made plain by examples, and tho<U+017F>e are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove controlement; That the wet Sun-beams declare <U+017F>ome fine and forrain fatne<U+017F>s to nouri<U+017F>h mankind. How to live twenty yeers without Food, as many creatures do. V<U+017F>e and Cu<U+017F>tom a <U+017F>econd Nature: The Bird called Manuda Diaoa, and the <U+017F>inging Dog, and Camelian that never eat food. An experienced Medicine, and how to apply it, Paracel<U+017F>e, and the Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian new Art of Healing.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OF <hi>Ari<U+017F>totle</hi> it is reported, That he is the witty Spye of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as if he had been made in this matter, he <U+017F>hews the need and u<U+017F>e of the greater Entralls and Bowels of <hi>Wights,</hi> and <U+017F>aith very truly and wi<U+017F>ely, The Heart and Liver as the <U+017F>pring of Life and Food, to be needful for all <hi>VVights,</hi> adding to the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one, the <hi>Brain</hi> to <hi>cool,</hi> and the <hi>Lights</hi> to clen<U+017F>e the <hi>Heat,</hi> <U+017F>tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there as if he thought the other three unprofitable; nay for one of them in the <U+017F>ame Book, (I <U+017F>ay) telling the <U+017F>tories of the Hart and Camel, and giving the rea<U+017F>on why they be both <U+017F>o <U+017F>wift, healthful, long-liv'd and other good properties above the re<U+017F>t enfeoffed, vouched in plain tearms, the want of the fiery and <U+017F>cummy Gall, as a great Enemy to them, for the Melt that muddy Bowel, that it may be left out as needle<U+017F>s in the bodies of the better creatures. The Meadows near <hi>Cortinae</hi> and <hi>Mugga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> declare when by a <U+017F>trange and hidden vertue they bereave the Bea<U+017F>ts thereof that graze upon them of it; the Herb is called <hi>A<U+017F>plenium;</hi> as I told you in the preceding Chapters, nay, that the Milt is not onely idle, but hurtful, which all experience, even in our <U+017F>elves hath taught it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> light Footmen, (I <U+017F>ay, which I know not by what example unle<U+017F>s it were the want of the <U+017F>ame in the Camel, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Bea<U+017F>t able to travel an hundred miles a day, and <U+017F>o without drink fifteen dayes together) being in their childhood purged of their Milt, prove thereby the mo<U+017F>t light, <U+017F>wift, <U+017F>ound and la<U+017F>ting Footmen in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118922:20"/>As for the veins of Urine-drawers, as drinkle<U+017F>s creatures have none at all, <U+017F>o <U+017F>ome men have but one of them, as if nature pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed not to make any at all; if we could forbear our drink (as the<U+017F>e Bea<U+017F>ts do by kinde, and <U+017F>ome men by cu<U+017F>tom) we might the better <U+017F>pare them, and avoid many mi<U+017F>chiefs in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
               <p>Therefore the odd man, <hi>Paracel<U+017F>us,</hi> I know not by what light, if not of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Cro<U+017F>s,</hi> (ca<U+017F>t in I think from <U+017F>eraphical illumination) not onely <U+017F>ees the<U+017F>e faults, but al<U+017F>o finds wayes to amend them, and to cut the mi<U+017F>chiefs off all the<U+017F>e three noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome parts, not with any yeilding Craft, but with Ro<U+017F>ie Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an divine kind of Healing, with <hi>Aurum protabile, &amp;c.</hi> <U+017F>o that to avoid all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es that <U+017F>pring of the Leavings, take of <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> one ounce; one pound of the Oyle of Ravens; two pound of <hi>Miltwa<U+017F>t,</hi> or <hi>A<U+017F>plenium;</hi> a handful of <hi>Cinkefoyle,</hi> of <hi>Dictamnum Creten<U+017F>e, Ophioglo<U+017F>sum</hi> and <hi>Scorpioides, Echium,</hi> of each a like quantity, and ob<U+017F>erve the A<U+017F>cendent, and his Lord; and the Moon, and Lord of the <U+017F>ixt, at your di<U+017F>cretion, and take the quantity of a Walnut every night and morning, and anoynt the face &amp; hands, &amp; (if you wil) the re<U+017F>t of the body: Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ie Crucians have other healing and yeilding Medicines, you <U+017F>hall know them in their places; this is <U+017F>uch an experienced Medicine, that you know where to find it; I need not <U+017F>hew you to put out the <U+017F>way and power of the<U+017F>e idle bowels, or perhaps it <U+017F>hould not need, and in a <U+017F>tock that ea<U+017F>eth our clean Dyet Nature her <U+017F>elf as <U+017F>he doth in tho<U+017F>e Meadows by other creatures would al<U+017F>o quite raze and di<U+017F>patch them within a few generations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118922:20"/>But I will go further, Hear a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> new and unheard of opinion, and yet let not your judgement run, before you <U+017F>ee good rea<U+017F>on; <hi>What if we could fa<U+017F>t for ever, and live without all food?</hi> might not all hurt and danger of meat be then fore<U+017F>talled? if other <hi>Creatures,</hi> who<U+017F>e life hangeth upon the <U+017F>ame hold, by the <U+017F>ufferance, nay by the commandement <hi>of God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> do la<U+017F>t for ever, there is no <hi>Rea<U+017F>on</hi> but the <U+017F>ame <hi>common Nature</hi> will at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>uffer it in us; Let us <U+017F>ee. And to <U+017F>tep over the <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> becau<U+017F>e it is a <hi>Cold</hi> and <hi>bloodle<U+017F>s Creature;</hi> what <U+017F>ay we to a <hi>Bird,</hi> which is an hot and perfect one? <hi>a bird</hi> in the <hi>Molucco I<U+017F>lands, Manuda Diaca</hi> by name, that hath no feet at all, no more then an ordinary fi<U+017F>h, as Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> <U+017F>aith, and I have <U+017F>een her; the bigne<U+017F>s of her body and bill, as likewi<U+017F>e the form of them, is much what of a <hi>Swallows,</hi> but the <U+017F>preading out of her <hi>wings</hi> and <hi>Tail</hi> has no le<U+017F>s compa<U+017F>s then an <hi>Eagles;</hi> <U+017F>he <hi>lives</hi> and breeds in the <hi>Aire,</hi> born up by the force of <hi>wind</hi> with more ea<U+017F>e then <hi>Archytas</hi> his <hi>Dove,</hi> and comes not near the <hi>earth</hi> but for her <hi>Burial;</hi> for the largene<U+017F>s and lightne<U+017F>s of her wings and tail <U+017F>u<U+017F>tain her without La<U+017F><U+017F>itude, and the laying of her <hi>Egges</hi> and brooding of her young is upon the back of the <hi>Male,</hi> which is made hollow, as al<U+017F>o the brea<U+017F>t of the <hi>Female,</hi> for the more ea<U+017F>ie incubation, taking no other food, as alas how <U+017F>hould <U+017F>he? then there is found: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <U+017F>he lives meerly of the dew of <hi>Heaven,</hi> or of flies and <U+017F>uch like in<U+017F>ects, I leave to others to di<U+017F>pute.</p>
               <p>Nay, have you not heard of the <hi>Little Dog</hi> in the <hi>We<U+017F>t Indies,</hi> which <U+017F>ingeth <U+017F>o <U+017F>weetly all the night long, neither night nor day eating any thing? But there be examples in our kind as well, then it is certain above controlment: Sir <hi>Chri<U+017F>topher Heydon</hi> <U+017F>aith there is a <hi>Mouthle<U+017F>s and <U+017F>o a meatle<U+017F>s people or kind of men</hi> about the head of <hi>Ganges,</hi> which liveth by the breath of their <hi>No<U+017F>trils,</hi> except when they take a far journey, they mend their <hi>Diet</hi> with the <U+017F>mell of <hi>flowers:</hi> and le<U+017F>t you may think I lean upon bare Authorities without the <U+017F>tay of rea<U+017F>on, all the matter re<U+017F>ts upon this rea<U+017F>on I told you before, that our life lay in the hand (be<U+017F>ide a little exerci<U+017F>e) of two like meats, one for the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Natural heat</hi> which is within us, and the fine<U+017F>t and fir<U+017F>t moi<U+017F>ture in our body, the others is without any meat, of the <U+017F>ame Temper with our body as near as may be; to uphold the frame and building of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118922:21"/>
the <U+017F>ame which <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>aid to be a fine <hi>Aiery and Fiery flame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we are now grown <U+017F>o out of order, and <U+017F>o much e<U+017F>tranged from our <hi>Etherial</hi> fir<U+017F>t <hi>Moi<U+017F>ture</hi> and the life of <hi>God,</hi> that we creep downward towards the <hi>Earth</hi> through di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, before we can reach the <hi>Life of the Vehicle;</hi> within <U+017F>ix<U+017F>core years we dye, and are hidden from the <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible approch of renewing life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Nature and her medicines experienced by Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians, and of the occult virtue of My<U+017F>teries; of the healing and con<U+017F>uming medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines and of their u<U+017F>e; of the Gout, Lepro<U+017F>ie, Drop<U+017F>ie and Falling Sickne<U+017F>s, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW the <hi>Aire</hi> it <U+017F>elf, e<U+017F>pecially when it is ever more as the <hi>wet Sunbeams</hi> declare, <U+017F>o <U+017F>prinkled with <U+017F>ome <hi>Fine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign fatne<U+017F>s,</hi> may <U+017F>eem <U+017F>ufficient food to nouri<U+017F>h the finer part of our <hi>Frame,</hi> wherein the temper of <hi>mankind,</hi> and his <hi>life</hi> (touching that point) <U+017F>tandeth, which is as much as any meat can do to <hi>life,</hi> (for it is not fed by common food, as I <U+017F>aid above) though not enough for <U+017F>trength, becau<U+017F>e the gro<U+017F><U+017F>er, <U+017F>ounder, and tougher parts wherein the <U+017F>trength lyeth, <U+017F>hall want food in this <hi>Dyet,</hi> and fail no doubt greatly, <hi>yet life <U+017F>hall la<U+017F>t <U+017F>till,</hi> as long as <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>fir<U+017F>t moi<U+017F>ture</hi> holds, in my opinion: or if we think that <U+017F>o <U+017F>pare a Diet, we may mend it (as the <hi>mouthle<U+017F>s people do</hi>) with <U+017F>mell of <hi>Flowers:</hi> or rather, as we know <hi>Nature</hi> is able to draw <hi>Aire</hi> and other food which <U+017F>he de<U+017F>ireth through the skin into all places of the body; <U+017F>o if <U+017F>he had meat applyed to the <U+017F>tomach, <U+017F>he would no doubt <U+017F>atisfie her<U+017F>elf that way mo<U+017F>t finely, without the heap of hurts let in at the broad and common gates, as we <U+017F>ee by example for <hi>Drink,</hi> that all the while we <U+017F>it in <hi>Water</hi> we <U+017F>hall never thir<U+017F>t<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> And for meat, I have heard <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> <U+017F>ay, by applying of <hi>wine</hi> in this <U+017F>ort they fa<U+017F>ted without all hunger for two years together.</p>
               <p>And in like manner I have experienced this, and fa<U+017F>ted two dayes when I fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>tudied the nature of the <hi>Guardian Genii:</hi> But if that would not <U+017F>erve the turn, and we mu<U+017F>t needs receive in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118922:21"/>
meat at the common gate, yet we may let it pa<U+017F>s no further then the gate, and make the <U+017F>tomach in the mouth, which is the u<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> when they are <hi>Seraphically illuminated;</hi> and to provide enough for life and <U+017F>trength, and a great deal bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our health, then we do, becau<U+017F>e the clearer part alone <U+017F>hould be received, And moreover <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>ay, for the clear di<U+017F>patch of that our ordinary trouble and anoyance which your reverence will not <U+017F>uffer me to name, although <hi>I</hi> might among <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> but they know my meaning: But it <U+017F>hall not need to <U+017F>teal <U+017F>hifts and holds if you will believe the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> that we may ea<U+017F>ily fa<U+017F>t all our life (though it be <hi>three hundred years together</hi>) without all kind of meat, and <U+017F>o cut off all doubts and dangers of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es thereof <U+017F>pringing; and for my own part, I know <U+017F>ome that have fa<U+017F>ted and lived in the <hi>holy orders of the Fraternity</hi> without all food <hi>ten years</hi> <U+017F>pace together. What need we <U+017F>ay more? if you be both <U+017F>o hard of belief, and dull of <U+017F>ight, and reports of good Authors, nor my own experience will <U+017F>ink into you, nor yet can you <U+017F>ee the light of rea<U+017F>on <U+017F>hining before you, take here a few of ordinary matters in the <hi>life</hi> and u<U+017F>e of men, and weigh one with another; is it not as common in u<U+017F>e, and indeed needful, to <U+017F>pit, and avoid another namele<U+017F>s leaving? and to <hi>Drink</hi> but to <U+017F>leep e<U+017F>pecially? If <U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e, nay all may be <U+017F>pared, why not our meat al<U+017F>o? let us <U+017F>ee a little, and by example, becau<U+017F>e Rea<U+017F>on is both too long and too open to cavil.</p>
               <p>To leave drink, which many have all their lives left; <hi>Elizabeth Drewe, a Devon<U+017F>hire Gentlewoman, is reported never to have <U+017F>pat, nor the whole Indian Nation.</hi> Sr. <hi>Iohn Heydon</hi> <U+017F>aith, <hi>he knew one that kept the namele<U+017F>s matter forty daies together.</hi> And although this an<U+017F>wereth not the que<U+017F>tion, yet it <U+017F>heweth the truth of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Holy Story,</hi> for if in <U+017F>o foul and gro<U+017F>s a thing as dyet is, he could <U+017F>o long want it, why not the<U+017F>e men for ever, in <U+017F>o clear and fine adiet, almo<U+017F>t empty and void of all leavings? For the gro<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>er <U+017F>ort, which make up this foul and <U+017F>hameful one we left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as you heard, and the finer in the pa<U+017F><U+017F>age from the <hi>Stomach</hi> through the former Gates were drawn all away to the <hi>Liver,</hi> as the like is ever in us and voided otherwaies. To clo<U+017F>e up all, I was at Sea with one that <U+017F>lept not one wink for the<U+017F>e three years la<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>t, and Mr. <hi>Iohn Knotsford</hi> is a Witne<U+017F>s to this truth, and Capt. <hi>Wind<U+017F>or.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118922:22"/>And thus we <U+017F>ee the<U+017F>e <U+017F>trange things fall our in proof, but how I cannot <U+017F>tand to <U+017F>hew: Fir<U+017F>t, nature <U+017F>uffers them, then u<U+017F>e and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tome another Nature brings them in, yet we may well beleeve the like in this matter of meat we have in hand; For as the <hi>Bear</hi> (according to the gui<U+017F>e of many Bea<U+017F>ts that lurk in Winter) fa<U+017F>teth fourty daies, <U+017F>o <hi>Eugenius Theodidactus,</hi> the reported <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie-Crucian</hi> tells of a <hi>Scotti<U+017F>h young man, David Zeamons,</hi> that waited on him, that by u<U+017F>e brought him<U+017F>elf to fa<U+017F>t three daies together, which by u<U+017F>e might have been three hundred as well, if he had ordered him<U+017F>elf thereafter by <U+017F>low and creeping cu<U+017F>tome, as Captain <hi>Copeland</hi> calls it, and by <U+017F>uch means as <hi>I</hi> <U+017F>et down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>So we <U+017F>ee, I <U+017F>ay, great wordly wonders prove plain and ea<U+017F>ie truths in the <U+017F>ight of Wi<U+017F>dome: you have read of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Acourate Structure of mans Body,</hi> of his <hi>Soul,</hi> of his <hi>Sen<U+017F>es,</hi> of <hi>Plants,</hi> of <hi>Minerals;</hi> and <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian medicine</hi> <U+017F>hall be that which <hi>I</hi> will in<U+017F>i<U+017F>t upon, and that by the means afore<U+017F>aid (where are more than one, if this like them not, they may take another) it is po<U+017F><U+017F>ible for all men by kind and cu<U+017F>tome to keep their health for ever: Let us come to the next point, that is, a<U+017F>well to be recovered if it were lo<U+017F>t, and that all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es may be cured. This is a point much harder then the fir<U+017F>t, even <U+017F>o be<U+017F>et and <U+017F>topt with all kind of lets and incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that a man can <U+017F>carce tell which way to <U+017F>et his foot forwards. Fir<U+017F>t appears <hi>Ae<U+017F>culapius, Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> the chief among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> bearing in hand <U+017F>undry di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es of both kinds (both come by de<U+017F>cent, and gotten by purcha<U+017F>e) hopele<U+017F>s and pa<U+017F>t reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and giving over the men that owe them, for trouble<U+017F>ome to them<U+017F>elves and to the Commonwealth: Then you may <U+017F>ee <hi>Galen,</hi> and his <U+017F>oft and fine Company with him, and that follow the<U+017F>e are <hi>Gerard</hi> and <hi>Riverius,</hi> and <hi>Culpepper,</hi> and the<U+017F>e with a long train of <hi>hedge-Doctours;</hi> and among the<U+017F>e <U+017F>tands <hi>Freeman,</hi> with <hi>Caterers,</hi> and <hi>Cooks,</hi> laden after them with all kind of <hi>dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Druggs,</hi> <U+017F>tand forth and <hi>Cry,</hi> they have the<U+017F>e many ages de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured heaps of Books, and took endle<U+017F>s pains in <U+017F>earching out the <hi>Nature</hi> of <U+017F>ingle Medicines, and making mixtures of the <U+017F>ame, and yet could hardly cure <U+017F>ome <hi>Agues,</hi> and other le<U+017F>s di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; But for the four great di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, viz. the <hi>Gout, Lepro<U+017F>ie, Drop<U+017F>ie,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118922:22"/>
Falling Sickne<U+017F>s,</hi> they could never heal them, and have therefore for <hi>Oracles</hi> <U+017F>et them down incurable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That the knowledge and vertue of Medicines are <U+017F>ecretly hid from vulgar under<U+017F>tanding: how they may be gotten: and of what lies couched in the Oil of Bodies: of the u<U+017F>e, and how to fetch it out by Skill, the Haven of Medicine.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVHat is left to be done in this Matter? what <U+017F>hall we <U+017F>et again<U+017F>t the weight of <U+017F>o many great mens <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</hi> Equally put them in the <hi>Ballance,</hi> as we have done hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and weigh them with <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>rea<U+017F>on:</hi> But where <U+017F>hall we find it? <U+017F>ay they; As it is every where, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> <U+017F>aid, drowned in the deep, <U+017F>o in this matter it is <U+017F>cattered all about, and largely <U+017F>pread withall; for there be three things, and every one full of under-<hi>Branches,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Art and way of Healing; The fir<U+017F>t is knowledge of the Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, the <U+017F>econd the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies again<U+017F>t them, and the third of the Appliance of the remedies,</hi> all which <U+017F>hould be traver<U+017F>ed in this Methodical my<U+017F>terious Treati<U+017F>e: but it <U+017F>hall not need I hope, nay we mu<U+017F>t take heed how we enter into <U+017F>o long and large a race, in <U+017F>o <U+017F>hort and narrow a compa<U+017F>s of time appointed, e<U+017F>pecially being never run before by any man but our <U+017F>elf, not one of the wi<U+017F>e <hi>Egyptians,</hi> nor our <hi>Ance<U+017F>tours, the holy Company of Mo<U+017F>es and Elias,</hi> who<U+017F>e <U+017F>teps we <U+017F>trive to follow, and their <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ours; for when they have once hit the mark they have <U+017F>hot at, and gotten the great and general Medicine <hi>Caput mortuum A. P.</hi> curing with ea<U+017F>e all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, they think it <U+017F>traight enough, and an empty and needle<U+017F>s Labour, as it is indeed, to trouble <hi>them<U+017F>elves</hi> and their <hi>Children</hi> with large Rules about innumerable <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Cau<U+017F>es</hi> of infinite di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and about other <U+017F>mall particulars in appliance. Neither would I have you <U+017F>et <hi>Sendivogius, Paracel<U+017F>e,</hi> and their heirs upon me, and <U+017F>ay they have taken great and goodly pains in this field; you will then force me to <U+017F>peak my thoughts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118922:23"/>Though the<U+017F>e men, (to let <hi>Philalethes, Vaughan,</hi> and <hi>Culpepper, Varlet, Freeman,</hi> and other <hi>Pretenders, with <U+017F>ome Schollars goe, as too young and childi<U+017F>h yet,</hi>) by great light of Wit wherewith they flowed, and by long proling both with eies, ears, and hands, in the my<U+017F>teries of <hi>Egypt,</hi> <U+017F>aw and performed many of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> deep <U+017F>ecrets, yea and there got mo<U+017F>t of their worldly prai<U+017F>e, although I think a number feigned, yet <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e</hi> his new Art and Rules of Healing are not good in my opinion; For fir<U+017F>t, again<U+017F>t the example of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie crucians,</hi> from whom he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all things, and then in de<U+017F>pight and di<U+017F>grace of <hi>Galen,</hi> for mi<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling his Countrymen, as you have heard, but chiefly carryed away with a mad and raging de<U+017F>ire of <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> which <hi>Culpepper</hi> alwaies de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>ed, yet the <hi>Starres</hi> favoured him, when I a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>ted to <U+017F>et up that new, famous and <U+017F>trange work of <hi>Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> now well known and practi<U+017F>ed, which <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e</hi> when he took in hand, a man unfit to do it, to pull down and raze the old Work, and to <U+017F>et up our new experienced <U+017F>ecret, which he could never do all his life.</p>
               <p>Then we <U+017F>ee how it is performed, he <U+017F>ets down <U+017F>ome fal<U+017F>e rules, <U+017F>ome wa<U+017F>t, idle, and <U+017F>ome wanting, and all uncon<U+017F>tant, di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, and unlearned; when he doth well (as he doth <U+017F>ometime) he doth no more then was done before him, and brings in the <U+017F>ame thing di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>ed with new, odd, cro<U+017F>s, and unheard of names, <U+017F>uch as may move wonder at the fir<U+017F>t, but when they be <U+017F>canned, Laughter, as Mr. <hi>Moor</hi> <U+017F>aith of <hi>Eugenius Philalethes</hi> his like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F>es in his <hi>Aula Lucis Adamica Magica &amp; Euphrates,</hi> and others of his Welch Philo<U+017F>ophie. And that I doe not <U+017F>lander them where there is no cau<U+017F>e, I could prove, if this place would admit a Volume. Wherefore let us follow the true and right <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> as ea<U+017F>ily you may know them by their actions, if ever you fortune to <U+017F>ee them and be acquainted with them; and leave <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e,</hi> and the re<U+017F>t in this ill matter, and Light and Api<U+017F>h, as he makes it; and why <U+017F>hould we <U+017F>pend all our care and thought about a <U+017F>mall matter? you have a good <hi>Medicine</hi> and remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, when <hi>old wives</hi> in the Countrey, and <U+017F>ome good <hi>Women,</hi> among<U+017F>t other Dr. <hi>Culpeppers late wife,</hi> and <hi>Simple men,</hi> on our <U+017F>ide (I mean Simple in re<U+017F>pect of the <hi>Grecian</hi> <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties about nothing) when the<U+017F>e people have healed mo<U+017F>t, nay,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118922:23"/>
even all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and with which womani<U+017F>h Medicines indeed, the German Doctour (let us give him his due prai<U+017F>e) hath quite <U+017F>lain the <hi>Grecian Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> and here done much for mankind, by de<U+017F>cribing and di<U+017F>patching our clo<U+017F>e and <U+017F>ecret enemie, which under colour of friend<U+017F>hip and fighting again<U+017F>t our enemies hath this long time betrayed us and done us much mi<U+017F>chief; which thing one of their be<U+017F>t <hi>Captains</hi> of their State, <hi>Fernell</hi> by name, after he had been a while in <hi>Egypt,</hi> began to <U+017F>mell at la<U+017F>t, and began to repent him<U+017F>elf of all his former pains (which we know were great) be<U+017F>towed in that kind of <hi>Healing,</hi> <U+017F>aying it to be but words, and the whole force and weight of this <hi>Art</hi> to lean upon the knowledge and vertues of Medicines, <hi><U+017F>ecretly hid and couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the mid<U+017F>t and oyl of bodies,</hi> to be fetched out and gotten by the skilful means of <hi>Alchymi<U+017F>ts;</hi> even <U+017F>o of that Art, which is <U+017F>o much condemned of his fellows before and <U+017F>ince him, have fled and do daily flie from the daily toil and trouble of their <hi>fruitle<U+017F>s and barren dead Sea:</hi> Now let us <U+017F>hift our <hi>Sailes,</hi> and flie further too, I hope of wind and tide and all; which we have.</p>
               <p>But let us mount up to the <hi>main-ma<U+017F>t top</hi> of our Knowledge, and <U+017F>ee if we can de<U+017F>cribe the <hi>Haven of Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Medicines,</hi> and <U+017F>ee what marks it hath, and how it differs from other Creeks adjoining, le<U+017F>t at our journeys end we mi<U+017F>s, with more <U+017F>hame and grief, and <U+017F>uffer <U+017F>hipwrack. A <hi>medicine</hi> is that which kills the face of that which hurts us; and this it doth many waies, and yet al<U+017F>o to one end (which is is the end of all doing and working as I <U+017F>aid before) for his food and <U+017F>u<U+017F>tenance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118922:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Medicines again<U+017F>t Witchcraft, and to cure tho<U+017F>e that are afflicted thereby, although their bodies be po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed with evill <U+017F>pirits, that cau<U+017F>e them to vomit up Needles, Thimbles, Pots, Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es, Hair, and <U+017F>hreds of cloth, which by the Divil were conveyed into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. That Winds and Tempe<U+017F>ts are rai<U+017F>ed by Witches upon meer ceremonies of Medicines, and of poy<U+017F>ons; with the examples al<U+017F>o of other <U+017F>upernatural effects of unclean <U+017F>pirits, and of imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How to cure a Witch, and to take away her power.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>A <hi>Servant of God and Secretary of Nature,</hi> mu<U+017F>t be well advi<U+017F>ed of what he writes, e<U+017F>pecially in this age, and of this matter <hi>(viz.)</hi> of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> le<U+017F>t he <U+017F>hould, as I <U+017F>aid before, fail in this de<U+017F>ign, and <U+017F>o it may be a <U+017F>hame that he <U+017F>hould be reproved, by the pretenders to tho<U+017F>e wi<U+017F>e truths he alone hath opened to publick view; then let us come again and <U+017F>ort our <U+017F>peeches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Medicine heals us, and kills our enemie,</hi> either by dulling or con<U+017F>uming it; for when it meets with a contrary of even <U+017F>trength (as when oyl and poy<U+017F>on &amp;c. joyn) then in <U+017F>trength they neither eat up nor de<U+017F>troy one another, but both are dulled and weakned, and make one heavy thing which nature ca<U+017F>teth out for an unlike and unkindly dead thing, which they call an excrement, or (Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving;) but in ca<U+017F>e it be of more <U+017F>trength and power then our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, then it quite de<U+017F>troyes, devours, and turns him into his own nature. And this con<U+017F>umer is either like the thing that hurts us, in which <U+017F>ort even as every herb of <U+017F>undry qualities draws and feeds upon his own <hi>juice</hi> in a <hi>Garden;</hi> <U+017F>o one Poy<U+017F>on doth cure another, and all purging and drawing things do heal us, and all <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians hid</hi> and <hi>Divine properties</hi> do work by plain rea<U+017F>on; or el<U+017F>e it is unlike and contrary to their cu<U+017F>tome; after which manner as <hi>dry <U+017F>ticks, and Tow, and vinegar quench wild fire,</hi> or other <hi>Fat Fires,</hi> before <hi>water,</hi> who<U+017F>e fatne<U+017F>s feeds it, for the <U+017F>trong contrary quality quelling and eating up the weaker; <U+017F>o doth any cold and dry thing as <hi>Bolearminick, Terra Lemnia,</hi> &amp;c. cure a Rotten poy<U+017F>on: and <U+017F>o are a great number of cures done; which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118922:24"/>
onely cour<U+017F>e, in a word, the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> u<U+017F>e for <hi>Phy<U+017F>ick,</hi> and not indeed without good <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s; we heard even now of two hinderances of healing, which our common <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> did take unawares, and <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e</hi> pretends to have found out before me, gave any hint to the World of our experienced inventions, of <hi>Gold di<U+017F><U+017F>olved and made potable, being incorporated with its proper Veyle,</hi> which we now u<U+017F>e by the name of <hi>Aurum potabile;</hi> but <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e</hi> <U+017F>traieth much in the making of it, and knows it not no more than that <hi>tattered Doctor Freeman,</hi> <U+017F>o <U+017F>hamefully <hi>called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<U+017F>t Phy<U+017F>icians:</hi> Whither in their poi<U+017F>ons, on the other <U+017F>ide, when they think all cures thereby performed.</p>
               <p>Now when the Con<U+017F>uming Medicines have done their duties, Nature expells them for poi<U+017F>on and unlike <U+017F>trange things, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Axiomata,</hi> as well as the <hi>Grecian Rules,</hi> becau<U+017F>e all their Medicines were not approved by the Fraternity, and were by their confe<U+017F><U+017F>ion <U+017F>uch: But if they had either thought of the dulling nouri<U+017F>her, which as I told you, takes the nature of the leaving or excrement, or had known the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome <hi>Medicine,</hi> they would have made another reckoning; But let them go, and us <U+017F>ee out in time towards the <hi>Haven of Health,</hi> If the Art of Healing be nothing but de<U+017F>troying hurtful things, And their <U+017F>tronger enemies (but equality will <U+017F>ometimes <U+017F>erve the turn) or likes together; and the world be full of both the<U+017F>e kinds of Creatures, following the nature of their Parents of four beginnings, which are as we <U+017F>ee, <U+017F>ome like, and <U+017F>ome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary one to another.</p>
               <p>Then <U+017F>ure the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> Art of <hi>Healing</hi> is not (as <U+017F>ome may <U+017F>ay) impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible, truly it wanteth nothing, but a man well skilled in the Nature of things, <hi>A <U+017F>ervant of God, and Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Nature by name;</hi> for (I think) I need not put in a <hi>Phy<U+017F>ici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> to know what other part the Cau<U+017F>es of the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, which mu<U+017F>t be known and matched, becau<U+017F>e as Sr. <hi>Chri<U+017F>topher Heydon</hi> the <hi>Seraphically Illuminated Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian,</hi> and learned <hi>A<U+017F>trologer,</hi> well <U+017F>aith, He that knoweth the changes and chances of things in the <hi>great World,</hi> may <U+017F>oon find them in the <hi>Little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our nought-Healing Bill-men, that daub Medicines upon every Wall and Po<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>ome Leaches, will <U+017F>tep in, and <U+017F>ay, di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es are in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>o great, and in all <U+017F>o many, and mans wit is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118922:25"/>
<U+017F>o weak and <U+017F>hallow, and the Medicines <U+017F>o hid and drowned in the deep of Nature, that it is not po<U+017F><U+017F>ible to find them all; or if they were found, to apply them with <U+017F>uch di<U+017F>cretion as Nature might abide tho<U+017F>e poi<U+017F>oned Fraies and Battels within her. And again, admit all this untrue, yet there be <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>ent from <hi>Witchcraft and Sorcery,</hi> and other means which have their cau<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>o their Cure. I have read of <U+017F>om that have vomited uppieces of Cloth with Pins <U+017F>tuck in them, <hi>Nails, Needles,</hi> &amp; <U+017F>uch like <U+017F>tuff; and this is <hi>inge<U+017F>ted</hi> into the <hi>Stomach,</hi> by the <hi>pre<U+017F>tigious</hi> Sleights of <hi>Witches;</hi> Others I have <U+017F>een vomit up Hair, Gla<U+017F>s, Iron, and pieces of Wood with Pins <U+017F>tuck in it; anothers Corps was di<U+017F><U+017F>ected, and <hi>ripping up the Ventricle,</hi> there they found the Cau<U+017F>e of the di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>e, which was a <hi>round piece of Wood, four Knives,</hi> <U+017F>ome <hi>even and <U+017F>harp, others were indented like a Saw. Others do Miracles</hi> by ca<U+017F>ting <hi>Flint-<U+017F>tones behind their Backs</hi> towards the <hi>We<U+017F>t,</hi> or <U+017F>triking <hi>a River with Broom,</hi> or <hi>flinging of Sand in the Air,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>tirring of Urine in a hole in the ground,</hi> or <hi>boyling of Hogges Bri<U+017F>tles in a pot;</hi> <U+017F>ome by <hi>whi<U+017F>pering <U+017F>ome words in the Ear of an hor<U+017F>e or wild Stagg, could direct him a journey according to their own de<U+017F>ire.</hi> But what are the<U+017F>e things available? to gather <hi>Clouds,</hi> and to cover the <hi>Air</hi> with darkne<U+017F>s, and then to make the ground <U+017F>moke with peals of <hi>Hail</hi> and <hi>Rain,</hi> and make the <hi>Air</hi> terrible with frequent <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> and ratling Claps of <hi>Thunder:</hi> But this is from the power of the <hi>Divel</hi> (as <U+017F>ome fancy) which he hath in his Kingdome of the Air.</p>
               <p>For the Remedy of the<U+017F>e mi<U+017F>chiefs, I have <U+017F>een a man was pre<U+017F>ent, when <U+017F>ome have vomited up <hi>Needles, Thimbles, Shreds of Cloth, pieces of Pots, Gla<U+017F>s, Hair;</hi> another would <U+017F>uffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf for <hi>money</hi> to be <hi>run thorow</hi> with a <U+017F>word when I was not there, but it appeared to me a Fable. I have <U+017F>een a Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian cure the<U+017F>e afflicted People. But if you will <U+017F>ay, There is a touch<U+017F>tone whereby we may di<U+017F>cerne the truth of Metals, but that there is nothing whereby we may di<U+017F>cover the truth of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> recorded every where in Hi<U+017F>tory. But I an<U+017F>wer there is, and that is this:</p>
               <p>Fir<U+017F>t, If what is recorded was avouched by <U+017F>uch per<U+017F>ons, who had no end nor intere<U+017F>t in avouching <U+017F>uch things.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if there were many eye-witne<U+017F><U+017F>es of the <U+017F>ame matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118922:25"/>Thirdly and la<U+017F>tly, If the<U+017F>e things which are <U+017F>o <U+017F>trange and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous leave any <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible effects behind them; Though I will not acknowledge that all tho<U+017F>e Stories are fal<U+017F>e that want the<U+017F>e Conditions, yet I dare affirme that it is meer Humour and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenne<U+017F>s in a man to reject the <hi>Truth,</hi> of tho<U+017F>e that hear them: For it is to believe nothing but what he <U+017F>eeth him<U+017F>elf, from whence it will follow, That he is to read nothing of Hi<U+017F>tory, for there is neither Plea<U+017F>ure nor any u<U+017F>efulne<U+017F><U+017F>e, if it de<U+017F>erve no Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               <p>Another Remedy for the<U+017F>e <hi>Supernatural di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es,</hi> is, Let one watch the <hi>party Su<U+017F>pected,</hi> when they go home to their <hi>hou<U+017F>e,</hi> and pre<U+017F>ently after, before any body goe into the hou<U+017F>e after him or her, let one pull a handful of the <hi>Thatch,</hi> or a <hi>Tyle</hi> that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Door,</hi> and if it be a <hi>Tyle,</hi> make a good <hi>Fire,</hi> and heat it <hi>red hot</hi> therein, <U+017F>etting a <hi>Trivet</hi> over it; then take the parties <hi>Water,</hi> if it be a <hi>Man, Woman,</hi> or <hi>Child,</hi> and poure it upon the <hi>red hot Tyle,</hi> upon one <U+017F>ide fir<U+017F>t, and then on the other, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain put the Tyle into the Fire, and make it extremely hot, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ever and anon, and let no body come into the hou<U+017F>e in the mean time.</p>
               <p>If they be Cattle that are bewitched, take <U+017F>ome of the Hair of every one of them, and mix the Hair in fair water, or wet it well, and then lay it under the <hi>Tyle,</hi> the Trevet <U+017F>tanding over the Tyle, make a lu<U+017F>ty fire, turne your Tyle oft upon the Hair, and <U+017F>tir up the Hair ever and anon; after you have done this by the <U+017F>pace of a <hi>quarter of an hour;</hi> let the fire alone, and when the A<U+017F>hes are cold, bury them in the ground towards that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Heaven where the <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected Witch lives; this Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> <U+017F>aith he hath experienced.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Witch live</hi> where there is no <hi>Tyle,</hi> but <hi>Thatch,</hi> then take a great handful thereof, and wet it in the parties <hi>Water,</hi> or el<U+017F>e in common <hi>Water</hi> mixed with <U+017F>ome <hi>Salt,</hi> then lay it in the <hi>Fire,</hi> <U+017F>o that it may <hi>molter and <U+017F>mother</hi> by degrees, and in a long time: <U+017F>etting a Trivet over it. Or el<U+017F>e take <hi>two new Hor<U+017F>e-<U+017F>hooes,</hi> heat them red hot, and nail one of them on the <hi>Thre<U+017F>hold</hi> of the <hi>Door,</hi> but quench the other in the <hi>Urine</hi> of the party <U+017F>o <hi>bewitched,</hi> then <U+017F>et the <hi>Urine</hi> over the <hi>fire,</hi> and put the <hi>Hor<U+017F>e-<U+017F>hooe in it,</hi> <U+017F>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a <hi>Tryvet</hi> over the <hi>Pipkin</hi> or <hi>Pan</hi> wherein the Urine is; make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118922:26"/>
the urine boil with a little <U+017F>alt put into it, and the Hor<U+017F>e nailes, until its almo<U+017F>t con<U+017F>umed, viz. the <hi>Urine;</hi> what is not boiled fully away pour into the fire: <hi>Keep your Hor<U+017F>-<U+017F>hoe and Nails in a clean Cloth or Paper,</hi> and do likewi<U+017F>e three <U+017F>everal times; the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be far more effectual if you do the<U+017F>e things at the very <hi>change or full Moon,</hi> or at the very <hi>hour of the fir<U+017F>t or <U+017F>econd Quarter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they be Cattel, you mu<U+017F>t mix the hair of their Tails with the <hi>Thatch,</hi> and moi<U+017F>ten them being well bound together, and <U+017F>o let them be a long time in the fire con<U+017F>uming.</p>
               <p>You have heard the Cau<U+017F>e of <U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and have heard the Cure by <hi>Sympathie</hi> al<U+017F>o; but the<U+017F>e are without the compa<U+017F>s of Nature, and <U+017F>o let them pa<U+017F>s with our fickle <U+017F>tanding, which is daily and hourely <U+017F>o be<U+017F>et with de<U+017F>tinies, that a man can warrant nothing.</p>
               <p>Truly de<U+017F>tinies are <U+017F>o deep and bottomle<U+017F>s, (to return <U+017F>traight <hi>Homer</hi>-like upon them, and therefore it were be<U+017F>t indeed to let them goe, and the applying of the <hi>Medicines</hi> with them) The rather becau<U+017F>e the other, (I mean the former) is <U+017F>o <U+017F>light a matter to a di<U+017F>creet <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician,</hi> <U+017F>uch a one as is pointed out by their old and famous Leader <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> who both in this and all other duties of his Art made <U+017F>uch <U+017F>peed, and <U+017F>o far pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed all his fellowes (as none <U+017F>ince, which is a good time, could ever overtake him) no nor yet come <U+017F>o neer as to keep the <U+017F>ight of him, whom they had in cha<U+017F>e and followed.</p>
               <p>Then for tho<U+017F>e <hi>Supernatural cau<U+017F>es,</hi> which I <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>tand here to <U+017F>earch (for <U+017F>o they are called) if they flow from <hi>unclean and wicked Spirits</hi> (as <U+017F>ome think) they are not the Stuff of the things that hurt us, though <U+017F>omtimes they dwell in and po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s the body, but windy matters, much like unto tho<U+017F>e fierce and <U+017F>ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den changes of the Weather, proceeding from the Influences of the Planets and fixed Stars, and working the like effects in mens bodies, <U+017F>o that <U+017F>ith the neare<U+017F>t cau<U+017F>e is Natural, let the re<U+017F>t be what they will, and the Cure be done by Natural means, as we <U+017F>ee by experience among<U+017F>t us: And therefore <hi>E. A.</hi> that pretends this, and puts the fault in the Faith of the wicked, which is a thing as far <hi>above Nature,</hi> yet holds its Cure with a <hi>Natural Medicine,</hi> which we call a <hi>Quinte<U+017F><U+017F>ence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118922:26"/>Although I am not willing, that <U+017F>ometimes this <hi><U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s is <U+017F>uch</hi> as he bids us <U+017F>ometimes with<U+017F>tand it with another as <U+017F>trong a belief <U+017F>et again<U+017F>t it, but for my part, I cannot reach it with my conceit (let deeper heads then mine or the <hi>Vice-Chancellor of Oxford, Doctor Owen,</hi> think upon it) how the<U+017F>e beliefs and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and other parts and powers of the <U+017F>oul or mind of man, can <U+017F>o flye out of their own kingdome, and <hi>Reigne</hi> over <hi>a forraign body,</hi> when we know the <hi>Soul and minde</hi> is <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>t bound in <hi>the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy indurance,</hi> and <U+017F>o like to be, untill it be the great plea<U+017F>ure of the <hi>Omnipotent and the Omni<U+017F><U+017F>ent God,</hi> the <hi>chief good,</hi> who hath committed them, to let them loo<U+017F>e at once, and <U+017F>et them full at <hi>Liberty;</hi> and this may be di<U+017F>puted with <hi>Grace and knowledge</hi> on my part; Let this man therefore buzze again<U+017F>t my <hi>knowledge,</hi> which he would have to be more <hi>then Grace,</hi> I <hi>appeal</hi> to the <hi>Naturall faculties</hi> of any <hi>free judge, whether there be not as much Grace in me as there is hone<U+017F>ty in him:</hi> All men cen<U+017F>ure as they like of Stories; <U+017F>o let them pa<U+017F>s among<U+017F>t old wives tales for me, we will <U+017F>everely follow our task. That if the effect do not cea<U+017F>e which the object hath wrought upon the <hi>Brain,</hi> <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as ever by turning a<U+017F>ide of the <hi>Organs</hi> the <hi>object</hi> cea<U+017F>eth to work <hi>(viz.)</hi> though the <hi><U+017F>ence</hi> be pa<U+017F>t; As the <U+017F>troke of a <U+017F>tone, a bla<U+017F>t of wind, puts <U+017F>tanding water into Motion, and it doth not <hi>pre<U+017F>ently give over moving</hi> as <U+017F>oon as the <hi>wind cea<U+017F>eth,</hi> or the <hi>Stone <U+017F>etleth:</hi> <U+017F>o the <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Conception remaineth,</hi> but more ob<U+017F>cure, while <hi>we are awake,</hi> becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome object or other continually plyeth and <U+017F>olli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth our eyes and ears, keepeth the mind in a <U+017F>tronger Motion, whereby the weaker doth not ea<U+017F>ily appear. And this ob<U+017F>cure conception is that we call <hi>Phanta<U+017F>ie,</hi> or <hi>Imagination; Imagination</hi> being (to define it) <hi>conception remaining,</hi> and by little and little <hi>decaying from and after the act of <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, &amp;c.</hi> If <U+017F>ome of the<U+017F>e di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es <U+017F>pring, as Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> Doctor <hi>Culpeper,</hi> and <U+017F>ome others hold, and with good rea<U+017F>on, from neither of both the<U+017F>e two roots named, but from a foul and venomous breath, <U+017F>ent forth from a poy<U+017F>oned temper of the <hi>Witches body,</hi> through the <hi>windine<U+017F>s</hi> of <hi>hatefull eyes:</hi> For <hi>Thought fa<U+017F>hioneth</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> almo<U+017F>t at <hi>his plea<U+017F>ure;</hi> then all the cau<U+017F>es being ordinary, and agreeing to the cour<U+017F>e of Nature, they may be cured and put to flight by the <U+017F>ame cour<U+017F>e and means; which opinion, if you plea<U+017F>e to bear
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118922:27"/>
with my tarrying, it is worth the handling, taketh hold upon this rea<U+017F>on, becau<U+017F>e (as <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> do witne<U+017F>s) <U+017F>ome bea<U+017F>ts of ranker venome, do witch and hurt after the <U+017F>ame manner; as an old Toad by <U+017F>tedfa<U+017F>t view, not onely prevails, but benums a <hi>Wea<U+017F>ell,</hi> but kills a young child. And by the <U+017F>ame means the <hi>Bever</hi> hunts the little fi<U+017F>h, and takes his prey: But mo<U+017F>t fiercely and mi<U+017F>chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<U+017F>ly of all creatures in the world, the two mon<U+017F>ters in kind, the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> and <hi>Apoblepas:</hi> again, for that the eye of a men<U+017F>truous woman (as all report) doth <U+017F>pot the gla<U+017F>s which it beholdeth; and moreover <hi>Eugenius Theodidactus,</hi> in <hi>the wi<U+017F>emans Crown,</hi> telleth of many folk that through a poy<U+017F>oned prerogative, which a mon<U+017F>trous Mark of a double-<U+017F>ighted eye gave unto them, were able to <hi>bewitch to death</hi> all tho<U+017F>e upon whom that <hi>eye</hi> was <hi>angerly</hi> and <hi><U+017F>urely</hi> <U+017F>et and <hi>fa<U+017F>tned;</hi> but chiefly becau<U+017F>e we <U+017F>ee them that u<U+017F>e this wicked trade, to be by kind of a <hi>muddy</hi> and <hi>Earthlike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> and <hi>nature,</hi> brought by age, as they be mo<U+017F>t commonly <hi>long life,</hi> and <hi>gro<U+017F>s diet,</hi> to the <hi>pitch of melancholy,</hi> that is, to a cold and mo<U+017F>t dry nature in the world.</p>
               <p>For certain proof whereof, bring one of them out of that bea<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like life, brought unto merry company, and fed full with dainty <hi>Diet,</hi> and within <hi>twenty days,</hi> as hath by a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> been tried a truth, the whole <U+017F>tate and nature of her body will be <U+017F>o changed, as it <U+017F>hall not <U+017F>uffer her to bewitch and hurt again; as you may read in my <hi>Familiar Spirit</hi> or <hi>Guardian Genius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118922:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Naturall effects of Medicine: the force and power of mineralls in di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; with examples al<U+017F>o that every di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e-breeder hath the cure or remedy in it: examples that poy<U+017F>on prepared cures poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>oned people: Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Arts: the virtue and power of the Planets and heavenly Stars poured through the influence of the moon upon the Lower Creatures: of Hot Stomachs: of the Etherial fir<U+017F>t moi<U+017F>ture of of man: examples al<U+017F>o of Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Natural and <U+017F>upernaturall cures: of the under<U+017F>tanding of the<U+017F>e experienced truths by the wit of man: <hi>of Paracel<U+017F>us and Culpeper.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>LEt us come to the next and chiefe<U+017F>t point; And there we mu<U+017F>t not <U+017F>ay for <U+017F>hame, that the<U+017F>e helps and remedies lye hid in nature, too far for the wit of man to find, unle<U+017F>s we will accu<U+017F>e our own <U+017F>loth and dulne<U+017F>s: For <hi>nature</hi> hath brought them forth and laid them open a<U+017F>wel as the Poy<U+017F>ons and hurtful things, or el<U+017F>e <U+017F>he were very cro<U+017F>s and ill-willing to him for who<U+017F>e <U+017F>ake it <U+017F>eems <U+017F>he doth all things.</p>
               <p>Nay further (as Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> <U+017F>aith) her good will is <U+017F>uch, as <U+017F>he hath not only laid them open, but given us wayes to come by them, and means of <U+017F>peech, hands and wit al<U+017F>o, far above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther living creatures. And yet <U+017F>he hath not left us <U+017F>o, but le<U+017F>t by chance we might go wide and mi<U+017F>s them, to <U+017F>hew her mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love and affection towards us, <U+017F>he hath guided (as Mr. <hi>Moor</hi> <U+017F>aith) many witle<U+017F>s Bea<U+017F>ts, even by common <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, unto their <U+017F>peedy helps and remdies in their di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es: That we by the plainne<U+017F>s and <U+017F>hame of the example (as Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> wi<U+017F>ely <U+017F>aith) might be taught and moved to <U+017F>eek out the my<U+017F>terious truths of nature <hi>in Cele<U+017F>tial bodies,</hi> as wel as bea<U+017F>ts that <U+017F>eek and find us Medicines helpful in the like di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, for our <hi>Terre<U+017F>tial Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</hi> As to name a few not unworthy meaning; <U+017F>he maketh the bea<U+017F>t <hi>Hippotamus</hi> in time of his fulne<U+017F>s and fatne<U+017F>s to go to a reed, and by rubbing a vain to let him<U+017F>elf blood, and to <U+017F>top it again by laying mud upon it; A <U+017F>ick <hi>dog</hi> to <U+017F>eek an Herb and purge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf; and the <hi>bear</hi> to do the <U+017F>ame after his long fa<U+017F>t in <hi>Winter;</hi> <U+017F>he leads the <hi>Panther,</hi> when he is poy<U+017F>oned, to her foul and namele<U+017F>s
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118922:28"/>
leaving; and the <hi>Tortoy<U+017F>e,</hi> after he hath eat a Viper, to Summer Savery: And the Hedg-hog is <U+017F>o good a natural A<U+017F>tronomer, that he fortifies his hole again<U+017F>t foul weather; the Hog will gather Mo<U+017F>s and <U+017F>traw to cover him<U+017F>elf a little before it rains; The dog knows the influence of Mars when he doth <U+017F>leep by the fire, and will not go out a dores when he is in any evil po<U+017F>ition: and many <U+017F>uch like examples hath nature laid before us for our in<U+017F>truction; by which at la<U+017F>t wi<U+017F>e <hi>Plato, Philo, Apollonius, Pythagoras,</hi> and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men of <hi>Greece,</hi> as they them<U+017F>elves report, be they <hi>Elias or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<U+017F>ha,</hi> from whom the order of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Cro<U+017F>s</hi> came, (as <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay) or el<U+017F>e as others will have it, from <hi>Mo<U+017F>es, or Ezekiel,</hi> or who<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and by laying rea<U+017F>on and further proof together, fir<U+017F>t made the Art and rules of <hi>Healing,</hi> to know whence di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es came, and how to recover them. And then <U+017F>eeking all about for remedies to <U+017F>erve each turne, by little and little they matched the mo<U+017F>t part of the le<U+017F><U+017F>er rank with <U+017F>ingle Medicines, and the greater ones they doubled and coupled many together, in<U+017F>omuch as at la<U+017F>t, which was in <hi>Hippocrates</hi> time, they were able to heal all (<U+017F>aving four,) of the greate<U+017F>t and deepe<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, the <hi>Gout,</hi> the <hi>Drop<U+017F>ie,</hi> the <hi>Lepro<U+017F>ie,</hi> the <hi>Falling <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s;</hi> which are now healed by the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians onely.</hi> But this race is below the <hi>Seraphically illuminated Fraternity:</hi> now not a <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician</hi> that is lined with Plu<U+017F>h in <hi>England, Spain, Germany, or France;</hi> but holds that <hi>Long-life,</hi> Health, Youth, not attainable, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with one con<U+017F>ent, among<U+017F>t the other four, call them impo<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible.</p>
               <p>But to come to the point; what wrong this was both to <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>nature,</hi> they do ea<U+017F>ily <U+017F>ee and laugh at, which know that in this labour, they did not onely over<U+017F>ee and skip the <hi>Minerals,</hi> the <U+017F>toute<U+017F>t helps in the whole <U+017F>tore-hou<U+017F>e of <hi>Nature</hi> (although they could dig them out well enough to other and wor<U+017F>er u<U+017F>es) but al<U+017F>o, which is in all, did let the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> skill of preparing <hi>Medicines,</hi> whereby weak things are made almighty, quite e<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore to make up the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Art of healing,</hi> and to make it able (as they <U+017F>ay) to help and cure all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es came in, or rather went before them, into mans body; The <hi>Egyptians</hi> in great <U+017F>avour too with <hi>nature</hi> both for their <U+017F>oil and bringing up,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118922:28"/>
<U+017F>o notably commended above all <hi>nations,</hi> (having for example, to move and teach them even the great weight of the world as Sr. <hi>Iohn Heydon</hi> <U+017F>aith) for wits to devi<U+017F>e, and bodies to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<U+017F>e.</p>
               <p>Whereby in <U+017F>hort time they unfolded the knot why the <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> were of greate<U+017F>t force and power again<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; and <U+017F>oon after, which was a divine light, and in-<U+017F>ight, they perceived the huge labour of <U+017F>eeking <U+017F>uch a huge <U+017F>ort of <U+017F>ingles and mixtures to be vain and empty, and pittiful among wi<U+017F>emen.</p>
               <p>Becau<U+017F>e fir<U+017F>t, there is nothing hurtful and a breeder of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e, but it hath the heal and remedy for the <U+017F>ame about him: For the <hi>wings</hi> and <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>Cantharides,</hi> the <hi>Fruit</hi> of the <hi>Root Bezar,</hi> the A<U+017F>hes of Scorpions, Toads, and Vipers; and divers other <U+017F>tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger poy<U+017F>ons, both by nature and skill dre<U+017F>t and prepared, do cure and heal their own and all other Poy<U+017F>ons; nay as all <U+017F>tronger likes do cure their likes throughout the whole world of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, even <U+017F>o when a man hath found out the thing that hurts him, he may by ea<U+017F>ie skill mingle and break the temper of the <U+017F>ame further; that is, make it able to eat up and con<U+017F>ume it <U+017F>elf as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ily, without any further doubt, toil and labour; But e<U+017F>pecially becau<U+017F>e there is no one thing in the world, take what you will, that hath not the vertues of the <hi>Planets</hi> arre<U+017F>ted and fa<U+017F>tened upon it, and al<U+017F>o of the qualities thereof within it <U+017F>elf, that is not as good as all, and may <U+017F>erve in<U+017F>tead of all, and that is not able to cure all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es; which thing weighed, and with di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of wit and rea<U+017F>on fully reached, they went to practi<U+017F>e, and by the like <U+017F>harpne<U+017F>s of wit, they found out the kindly and ready way to dre<U+017F>s and make fit the<U+017F>e three kinds of Medicines afore<U+017F>aid, which contain all the Art of healing, all the re<U+017F>t are but wa<U+017F>t words and grievous toyl, to tire a world of wits about a bootle<U+017F>s matter, as <U+017F>aith <hi>Des Cartes.</hi> But e<U+017F>pecially they re<U+017F>ted in the la<U+017F>t, which is enough alone, and yet not without great foreca<U+017F>t, to chu<U+017F>e one of the be<U+017F>t, and that the very be<U+017F>t of all, for their ea<U+017F>e in dre<U+017F><U+017F>ing. Though Dr. <hi>Culpeper</hi> of late was not content with this, but ran through the re<U+017F>t, a<U+017F>well to <U+017F>pite his enemies, the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> as to make him<U+017F>elf famous in <hi>Taverns</hi> and <hi>Alehou<U+017F>es,</hi> as <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e</hi> in his time did<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> who<U+017F>e <U+017F>teps he <U+017F>trove to follow again<U+017F>t the rule of <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian wi<U+017F>dom and vertue;</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:118922:29"/>
and the example of his ance<U+017F>tors.</p>
               <p>But hath every thing all the vertues and influences taken from the <hi>Planets</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> by the <hi>Moon,</hi> to the earth; That is, all the curing and healing power of all the things in the world? very well you mu<U+017F>t remember that I proved above all the <hi>vertues</hi> and <hi>powers</hi> of <hi>heaven,</hi> poured down through the <hi>Influence</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> upon the<U+017F>e lower <hi>creatures,</hi> to be nothing el<U+017F>e (as <hi>Captain George Wharton</hi> truly <U+017F>aith) but one <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ame life and Soul, and <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> heat in all things, And again, that all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es flow from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>temper, and as it were di<U+017F>cord of the Natural con<U+017F>ent of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; then that thing which is endued with <U+017F>tore of life, and with exact and perfect temperatene<U+017F>s, <U+017F>eated upon both a <U+017F>ubtile and <U+017F>trong body, (which the thing in the bottom is) able alone by <U+017F>ubduing his weaker enemies, tho<U+017F>e di<U+017F>tempered di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, by <U+017F>trengthening his fellow life, <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> in our bodies. And la<U+017F>tly, by orderly binding together the frame that was <U+017F>lipt out of order, to do as much as all the powers and forces of all the <hi>Plants, Weights, and minerals</hi> in the world, that is, to put to flight all trouble of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and re<U+017F>tore the body to perfect health and quierne<U+017F>s.</p>
               <p>But how is all this done? we talk of high things, and huddle up too many great matters together. It were good for us to work them out di<U+017F>tinctly; when this <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> we <U+017F>peak of, and <U+017F>trong tempered <hi>medicines,</hi> <U+017F>lip into the <U+017F>tomach, it <U+017F>tayes no long dige<U+017F>tion, being already dige<U+017F>ted, nor look for any ordinary pa<U+017F><U+017F>ages to be opened unto it, but as <U+017F>oon as it is rai<U+017F>ed out of <U+017F>leep by his fellow, the natural heat, by and by he flyes our, and skowers about, as fa<U+017F>t as the <hi>Dolphine</hi> after his prey, or as nature her <U+017F>elf, whom Mr. <hi>Booker,</hi> as I take it (<U+017F>aith) to pierce bounds, and all to the purpo<U+017F>e, that is to <U+017F>eek his like food, and <U+017F>u<U+017F>tenance, whereby to pre<U+017F>erve his <U+017F>tate and being, which is the purpo<U+017F>e of all things in the world, as was <U+017F>aid above.</p>
               <p>Now there is nothing <U+017F>o like and neer a perfect temperature in the world, as the <hi>Etherial fir<U+017F>t moi<U+017F>ture</hi> in man; But what this is, you may read in my book entituled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ventus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is be<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t in the heart, the root of life, then thither it hyeth and preyeth upon that part fir<U+017F>t, and that is the cau<U+017F>e why
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118922:29"/>
it pre<U+017F>ently re<U+017F>toreth a man half dead, and as it were, pulls him out of the throat of <hi>death;</hi> then it runs to the re<U+017F>t all about, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crea<U+017F>ing by that means the natural heat, and fir<U+017F>t moi<U+017F>ture of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the body; when this is done, he turns upon the parts them<U+017F>elves, and by encountring with them in the <U+017F>ame <U+017F>ort, according to his might, feeds upon them, and brings them a certain way towards his own nature, even <U+017F>o far as we will by our u<U+017F>age <U+017F>uffer; for if we take it with mea<U+017F>ure and di<U+017F>cretion, it will bring our body to a middle mean and <U+017F>tate, between his own exact temperature and the di<U+017F>temper of di<U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es, even a better <U+017F>tate then ever it had before; if we u<U+017F>e it out of mea<U+017F>ure, it takes us up too high, and too near his own <hi>nature,</hi> and makes us unmeet for the deeds of the duties of an <hi>earthly life.</hi> But in the mean while in the mid<U+017F>t of this work, we mu<U+017F>t know that by his exceeding heat and <U+017F>ubtlene<U+017F>s which is gotten by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> skill, and which make up the <U+017F>trength above all things, it divides and <U+017F>catters, like <U+017F>moke before the wind, all di<U+017F>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and hurtful things, and if they cannot be reconciled and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to goodne<U+017F>s, nature throws them out as dead, and unfruitful leavings.</p>
               <p>But how do we talk, (as Mr <hi>William Tub</hi> the A<U+017F>trological <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> <U+017F>aith) <hi><U+017F>o much of exact and perfect temper,</hi> when by the <hi>verdict</hi> of all the <hi>Que<U+017F>t</hi> in the<U+017F>e ca<U+017F>es there is no <U+017F>uch thing found in <hi>nature,</hi> but in <hi>heaven onely?</hi> neither heard you me <U+017F>ay that it floated aloft, <hi>but was <U+017F>unk to the bottom of all nature;</hi> notwith<U+017F>tanding by a true and Holy <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> to be <U+017F>ounded and weighed up. For as heaven was once a gro<U+017F>s and di<U+017F>tempered lump (as I told you in my book <hi>of the nature and dignity of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>) by the divine art of God that ordered all things (as you have read in the Introductory part of this book,) refined and <U+017F>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred away round to the place and <hi>nature</hi> where it now <U+017F>tandeth; even <U+017F>o one of our gro<U+017F>s bodies here below, being <hi>a piece of the <U+017F>ame lump</hi> al<U+017F>o, and all one with that which Heaven once was, may by the like art and cunning be refined and parted from all his di<U+017F>tempered dro<U+017F>s and foul dro<U+017F><U+017F>ine<U+017F>s, and brought into a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly nature</hi> of the be<U+017F>t and goodlie<U+017F>t thing in <hi>Heaven:</hi> And yet you mu<U+017F>t not take me as though I would have <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc><…></desc>
                  </gap> wit of man, which is b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a <U+017F>park of the divine g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc><…></desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118922:30"/>
in my book called <hi>Ventus Ingens</hi>) to be able to reach the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his work, and to make <U+017F>o great perfection; if he do but <U+017F>hadow it, and make a Counterfeit, that is, if he reach not <U+017F>o far as to make all things, but to mend a few by this his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, all is well, it is as much as I can look for at the hand of any man that is not a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian.</hi> Now is the time to re<U+017F>t a little, and pray for the good u<U+017F>e and practice of tho<U+017F>e that <U+017F>hall read our writing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Sun, or Spiritual Oyl. Of the Divine Works of God not yet ob<U+017F>erved. How we make Aether. Examples of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian and Grecian. Of Poi<U+017F>on. Of the Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Miracles of the Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians, with obedience to Rea<U+017F>on. Another Medicine of Supernatural effect. Of the power and <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret skill of Nature. How to di<U+017F><U+017F>olve Minerals: And how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for Mens Bodies.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>EUgenius Theodidactus</hi> hath <U+017F>hewed you this <hi>Heaven,</hi> Nay this <hi>Sun</hi> of ours, which is nought el<U+017F>e, as I told you in one of my books of <hi>A<U+017F>trologie,</hi> but an <hi>Oyl full of heavenly Spirits,</hi> and yet in Quality of his body ju<U+017F>t, even and natural, fine and piercing, clo<U+017F>e and la<U+017F>ting, able as well to rule this little World, as Mr. <hi>Thomas Heydon</hi> <U+017F>aith, the great <hi>Sun</hi> is able to governe the great World.</p>
               <p>But what is he, <U+017F>aies Mr. <hi>Iohn Cleeveland,</hi> that can <U+017F>ee this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Art and Way, whereby God made his great and mighty work, viz: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                  </gap> as I <U+017F>hewed in my Book, intituled, <hi>Mo<U+017F>es <U+017F>peech to God,</hi> upon the <U+017F>econd chapter of <hi>Gene<U+017F>is?</hi> or if he <U+017F>aw it, learne and match it by imitation? I an<U+017F>wer, None but <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> to whom I am a friend, and they God hath enlightned and un<U+017F>eal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their eyes, they have found the way lying open in all places, and in all <hi>Natural changes,</hi> they <U+017F>ee them pa<U+017F>s and travel, I <U+017F>ay <U+017F>till, the cour<U+017F>e that <hi>Heydon</hi> calls <U+017F>oft and witty, that is, kindly <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and if he be not <U+017F>wift and ra<U+017F>h as many, <U+017F>uch as <hi>Thomas
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118922:30"/>
Vaughan</hi> and <hi>Street,</hi> but will have <U+017F>ober patience, his own skill and labour will be but little if he plea<U+017F>e; for Nature her <U+017F>elf very kindly will in her due time performe all, and even all that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly workman<U+017F>hip be ea<U+017F>ily performed; and yet I mean not <U+017F>o but that Art mu<U+017F>t accompany and attend upon Nature (though with no great pains and skill) both forward and backward in this Journey (Doctour <hi>French</hi> knows my meaning, <U+017F>o doth Doctour <hi>Owen,</hi> if his angry Cen<U+017F>ure will <U+017F>uffer his Natural judgement) until he come to his wi<U+017F>hed re<U+017F>t, and to the top of all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>If you perceive not, con<U+017F>ider the way whereby we made our <hi>Ether</hi> in our book abovenamed, and matched our own fir<U+017F>t moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture, a thing <hi>Etherial,</hi> I <U+017F>ay, and almo<U+017F>t Temperate; mark what I <U+017F>ay, there is a further end in the matter, hold on the <U+017F>ame means whereby you came <U+017F>o far through <hi>The wi<U+017F>e mans Crown,</hi> and are gone <U+017F>o far <hi>in the Way to bli<U+017F>s,</hi> which is that I <U+017F>pake of, and you may reach it.</p>
               <p>Then you <U+017F>ee the way to cure all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es by the third way of <hi>Egyptian healing,</hi> which they doe, and we may well call it the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians Heaven, and yet it is a way far beneath the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> Art of Healing, as we <U+017F>hall <U+017F>hew hereafter.</p>
               <p>But if they will not yeeld yet to rea<U+017F>on, but mutter <U+017F>til <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Street</hi>-like, that the<U+017F>e Heavenly Medicines of ours are very high for the reach of mens <U+017F>illy wits, here <U+017F>trowed below upon the ground for other le<U+017F><U+017F>er and ba<U+017F>er u<U+017F>es, and that no man <U+017F>ince the fir<U+017F>t man, or if I will <U+017F>ay <hi>Mo<U+017F>es,</hi> was the fir<U+017F>t, that fir<U+017F>t found out the<U+017F>e inventions as they call them, after <hi>Adam;</hi> and that none but the <hi><U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ors of Mo<U+017F>es</hi> have been ever yet known to have found and wrought the <U+017F>ame; I will not <U+017F>tand to beat rea<U+017F>on into <U+017F>uch giddy-braindmen, but go to the other two waies of healing, which the <hi>Egyptians</hi> found out and u<U+017F>ed, and called the fir<U+017F>t Mineral Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and the<U+017F>e <hi>Mo<U+017F>es</hi> taught the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>I<U+017F>rael</hi> in <hi>the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of mount Sinai, when he took the Golden Calf which he had made, and calcined it in the fire, and ground it to powder, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated it with a Solar Veagle, and made the children of I<U+017F>rael drink Aurum potabile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the next my<U+017F>teries and <U+017F>ecrets, as may appear by <hi>Riverius</hi> his <U+017F>peaking of <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Secrets,</hi> we fitly may call this <U+017F>econd,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118922:31"/>
kind, becau<U+017F>e that is too large a <hi>Name</hi> (if it be lawful for us as well as for all other <hi>Learned men,</hi> where a fit word wants to make a new) we may do well I <U+017F>ay to call it a <hi>Cure it <U+017F>elf,</hi> becau<U+017F>e it is by that way of healing, whereby every <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ame thing further broken may cure it <U+017F>elf; and this inward and hidden thing as they <U+017F>ay, the outward and apparent by the cour<U+017F>e of kind, whereby the <U+017F>tronger like eates up in triall and con<U+017F>umes the weaker.</p>
               <p>If this leave be once granted, we will borrow a little more for the other two likewi<U+017F>e, becau<U+017F>e their names, are not pertinent to our purpo<U+017F>e, and call that <hi>Heaven</hi> a <hi>Cure-all,</hi> for <U+017F>o it doth, and the next a <hi>Cure-the Great,</hi> becau<U+017F>e the <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> is alwayes to match the greater and more <U+017F>tubborn <U+017F>ort of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es with the Stout and <hi>mighty minerals,</hi> and the re<U+017F>t with tho<U+017F>e hidden <hi>cure-them<U+017F>elves,</hi> or at lea<U+017F>t in the lower rank of lighter di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, with their likes, onely raw, as the <hi>Grecians</hi> u<U+017F>e them, without any curious dre<U+017F><U+017F>ing.</p>
               <p>Let us draw nearer a conclu<U+017F>ion of the matter; becau<U+017F>e <hi>Grecians</hi> them<U+017F>elves are able, and our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> that learn of them, to cure the lighter <U+017F>ort of di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and to heal all but the four afore<U+017F>aid, we will leave the re<U+017F>t for them, and <U+017F>o let this <U+017F>econd kind of healing go called <hi>our hidden cure them<U+017F>elves,</hi> and bend all our batteries again<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e four which they call incurable, and <U+017F>ee how by force of our Mineral Medicines, they may be cured: we <U+017F>ee the Poy<U+017F>oned <U+017F>pirits and breaths of venomous things, with what force they work upon our bodies, things in <hi>Nature</hi> <U+017F>et again<U+017F>t them, and how they con<U+017F>ume them; If you do not <U+017F>ee by imagination, rea<U+017F>on with your <U+017F>elves, if not remember tho<U+017F>e above named, that killed with their <U+017F>ight; Hear one or two more that work the <U+017F>ame by touch as violently. The <hi>Hare-fi<U+017F>h,</hi> a mo<U+017F>t cold and dry <hi>creature</hi> (to omit that <U+017F>he maketh a mans head ake by <U+017F>ight) if you touch her aloof onely with a <U+017F>taffe, that her veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous breath may go <U+017F>traight and round unto you, you die pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ently. The root <hi>Baazam</hi> in <hi>Pale<U+017F>tine,</hi> as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> writes, kills the man that handleth it, and therefore they u<U+017F>ed to make a dog pull it up (as <hi>Ben. Iohn<U+017F>on</hi> <U+017F>aith) who thereby died imediately. To come into the body; that <hi>co<U+017F>tly poy<U+017F>on</hi> Mr. <hi>Linacre</hi> talks of, that is in <hi>Nubia,</hi> and one grain kills a man out of hand yet <U+017F>tay but a quarter of an hours working, and that one grain divided will
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118922:31"/>
overcome ten men; I hope you doubt not but the<U+017F>e mighty poy<U+017F>ons if they were like in <hi>Nature</hi> to the four great di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, and by little and little to be born by Nature, and <U+017F>et upon them, would be able ea<U+017F>ily, by their great <U+017F>trength to devour and con<U+017F>ume them; or el<U+017F>e <U+017F>ure <U+017F>uch heaps of poy<U+017F>on as the <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> give us would not dwell <U+017F>o long within us, but would put out life in a moment. Now what are the<U+017F>e poy<U+017F>oned <hi>Vapours,</hi> but mo<U+017F>t cold and dry bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, wrought and broken up by naturall mingling, unto great finene<U+017F>s and <U+017F>ubtilene<U+017F>s, by this peircing <U+017F>wiftly all about, and by the<U+017F>e contrary qualities overcoming? Then let us take the <U+017F>tout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<U+017F>t <hi>Minerals,</hi> <U+017F>uch as are called <hi>Middle Minerals</hi> by <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> or hard juices by Mr. <hi>Berkenhead</hi> (to leave the Metals for a better purpo<U+017F>e) be they poy<U+017F>ons, as <hi>G. Agricola</hi> <U+017F>aith, but what they be <hi>I</hi> care not, and after we have by meer working, clean<U+017F>ed them and <U+017F>tripped them of their cloggs and hinderances, broken and rai<U+017F>ed them to a fine <U+017F>ub<U+017F>tance, then match them with their likes, the hurtfull things in our bodies, <U+017F>hall they not let all the re<U+017F>t alone, and <U+017F>traightway cleave to their fellows, as well as a purging <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,</hi> and <U+017F>o devour and draw them out by little and little? If there be no likes, I grant they will as well as that, fall upon their enemies, or good juices, and feed upon them.</p>
               <p>Then what do you doubt is not a Mineral body far better? And therefore if it be rai<U+017F>ed to as great a finene<U+017F>s, much <U+017F>tronger in working then the gentle and loo<U+017F>e temper of a <hi>wight</hi> or <hi>plant:</hi> wherefore the<U+017F>e our Mineral Medicines, and <U+017F>ome other fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Medicines, and <hi>cure the great,</hi> as we call them, <U+017F>hall in any rea<U+017F>on, work more violently upon their likes, then the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>poy<U+017F>ons</hi> of <hi>Wights</hi> and <hi>Plants</hi> do upon their contraries, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e the like doth more ea<U+017F>ily yield then the contrary, and for that the lighter here is the <U+017F>tronger.</p>
               <p>But if you cannot <U+017F>ee the<U+017F>e things by the light of mind, open your eyes, and ca<U+017F>t them a little into the School of <hi>Alchimy,</hi> into the le<U+017F><U+017F>er and lower <U+017F>chool, I mean of <hi>Germans,</hi> and you <U+017F>hall <U+017F>ee the Schollars, e<U+017F>pecially the ma<U+017F>ters, by <U+017F>tripping the Minerals, and lifting up their properties, but a few degrees, to work wonders; as to name three or four, by quenching the <hi>Load<U+017F>tone</hi> in the oyl of Iron, his proper food, they make him ten times <U+017F>tronger, able to pull a nail out of a po<U+017F>t, &amp;c. And by this natural pattern they make
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118922:32"/>
Artificial drawers, not for Iron onely, but for all other things, yea and <U+017F>ome <U+017F>o mighty, as they will lift up an Ox from the ground, and rent the arm of a Tree from the body, as Mr. <hi>Comer</hi> doth witne<U+017F>s; who reporteth again that he <U+017F>aw a fle<U+017F>h-drawer, that pulled up 100 weight of fle<U+017F>h, and a mans eye out of his head, and his Lights up into his <hi>Throat and choaked him.</hi> They make <hi>binders</hi> al<U+017F>o to <hi>glew two pieces of Iron together,</hi> as fa<U+017F>t as the <hi>Smith</hi> can joyn them To be <U+017F>hort they make <hi>eaters</hi> al<U+017F>o, that will con<U+017F>ume <hi>Iron <U+017F>tones</hi> or any <hi>hard thing</hi> to nought in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they <hi>di<U+017F><U+017F>olve Gold</hi> into an <hi>oyle;</hi> they <hi>Fix Mercury</hi> with the <hi><U+017F>moke of Brim<U+017F>tone,</hi> and make many rare devi<U+017F>es of it; And all the<U+017F>e wonders and many more they do by certain rea<U+017F>on: I could tell you, if I could <U+017F>tand about it. In the mean time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ider, if the<U+017F>e or any other <U+017F>uch like Minerals were rai<U+017F>ed higher, and led to the top of their finene<U+017F>s and <U+017F>ubtlene<U+017F>s, and matched with their like companions, or with their contraries, if you will, tho<U+017F>e great di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in our bodies, what <U+017F>tirrs they would make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, how ea<U+017F>ily they would hew them, pierce, divide, wa<U+017F>te, and con<U+017F>ume them? But you mu<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alwayes have a <U+017F>pecial regard, that the Medicines be not liker our natures, then the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing that hurts us; for then they would fir<U+017F>t fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and let the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es alone, which heed is ea<U+017F>ily taken in <hi>minerals,</hi> things very far off our <hi>nature,</hi> <U+017F>aith <hi>Des Cartes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And with the<U+017F>e experience the wonderful vertue of the <hi>oyl</hi> and <hi>water of Tobacco</hi> wi<U+017F>e men I have known do miracles with it.</p>
               <p>What is to be <U+017F>aid more in the<U+017F>e matters? I think nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s through the countenance of an idle opinion that reigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, they dare flye to the la<U+017F>t, and of all other the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>lender <U+017F>helter, and deny our ability to break, tame and handle as we li<U+017F>t, <U+017F>uch <U+017F>tout and <U+017F>tubborn bodies: (what) becau<U+017F>e you know not how to do it, will you fa<U+017F>hion all men by your mould? wi<U+017F>e men would fir<U+017F>t look into the power and <U+017F>trength of skill and nature, and <U+017F>ee what they can do and mea<U+017F>ure it thereby, and not by their own weakne<U+017F>s; there <U+017F>hall you under<U+017F>tand, that there is nothing in nature <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong and <U+017F>tubborn, but it hath its match at lea<U+017F>t, if not his overmatch in <hi>Nature,</hi> <U+017F>uch is the nature of <hi>mans body,</hi> of his <hi>Soul</hi> of <hi><U+017F>ignatures</hi> of <hi>Plants,</hi> of <hi>mettals,</hi> and <hi>minerals,</hi> and other things al<U+017F>o.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:118922:32"/>But admit <U+017F>omewhat weaker as <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Plants,</hi> &amp;c. yet this, if he get the help of a wi<U+017F>emans Art unto him, <U+017F>hall quickly wax great and mend in <U+017F>trength and be able ea<U+017F>ily to overcome, that other; mark how the <hi>dregs</hi> of <hi>Vinegar,</hi> a thing <U+017F>prung out from a weak beginning, and it <U+017F>elf as weak as water, is able if it be but once <hi>di<U+017F>tilled,</hi> to make <U+017F>touter things then <hi>minerals</hi> even <hi>mettals them<U+017F>elves,</hi> all but <hi><U+017F>ilver and gold,</hi> to yield and melt down to his own <hi>wateri<U+017F>h nature,</hi> nay which is more then <hi>Mild-dew</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cooks the Vicar</hi> calls it, wrought fir<U+017F>t by the <hi>Bee</hi> that cunning bea<U+017F>t, and then, twice or thrice by the di<U+017F>tiller, di<U+017F>tilled will do the <U+017F>ame, you may judge with your <U+017F>elf, what not onely the<U+017F>e, but other fiercer and <U+017F>harper things, as Salts, &amp;c. more like to do upon Minerals; and by the way con<U+017F>ider, if <U+017F>uch mild things as wine and honey, <U+017F>o meanly prepared, are able to <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due in that <U+017F>ort the mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>tiffe and tough things in the world, <U+017F>o minerals cheaper then <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> in their highe<U+017F>t degree of dignity would cure the <U+017F>toute<U+017F>t di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e (being prepared fitly) that can grow in our bodies. Now let us <U+017F>it and take our re<U+017F>t a little and then we will conclude our Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Medicines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118922:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians make a Chirurgeons in<U+017F>trument; that it <U+017F>hall pierce through any part of the whole body, without <U+017F>en<U+017F>e or feeling, and <U+017F>ound the depth of a wound. The difference of Common Phy<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians Raw, Blunt, and herby medicines, and Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians: What a Phy<U+017F>ician ought to be, what they ought to learn, and what they ought to practi<U+017F>e, and then I <U+017F>hall love them of the order of the Ro<U+017F>ie Cro<U+017F>s.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUt I wear away time in vain, to <U+017F>peak <U+017F>o much about tis matter; and yet <U+017F>ith all are not of like Capacity, I will adde one yet familiar example; when a <hi>Surgeon</hi> goeth about to <U+017F>earch a wound that is deep, if he thru<U+017F>t at it with a <hi>Butchers prick</hi> he would move <hi>Laughter;</hi> let him take a <hi>Thorwe,</hi> and it wil pierce <U+017F>omewhat prettily; but to do it throughly, and at his plea<U+017F>ure he will u<U+017F>e, (though to the great grief of his <hi>Patient</hi>) a fine and long in<U+017F>trument of Mettal. But a right <hi>Surgeon</hi> the common ones are but Butchers, <U+017F>uch a one as is a <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician,</hi> and <hi>A<U+017F>trologer,</hi> nay a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> al<U+017F>o, would touch his <hi>In<U+017F>trument,</hi> with a <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tone,</hi> that is commonly found, to make it pierce throughout the body without all <U+017F>en<U+017F>e or feeling; Even <U+017F>o good <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> <U+017F>uch an one, as the <hi>Lord Marques of Worce<U+017F>ter</hi> had, whom he taught many fine inventions: he told me of a <hi>Golden</hi> ball that this Lord made, that let him throw it into a River or Pool, it would ari<U+017F>e a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again from the bottom at what hour he plea<U+017F>ed. This <hi>noble Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> <U+017F>hewed me a key of the lock, that would tell him who touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. Nay if it fortuned to be pickt he could know who did it, and what was taken away (before their faces) and many rare things I have <U+017F>een this princely Philo<U+017F>opher do, which his excellency was plea<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>hew me; <U+017F>uch as the<U+017F>e are hard to be found in this <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> where none of the<U+017F>e can live without great envie. If one of the<U+017F>e <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> be to encounter with our greate<U+017F>t ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the<U+017F>e four we <U+017F>peak of, he would not I hope, if he were a true <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> be <U+017F>o mad as to thru<U+017F>t at them with the Raw and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118922:33"/>
blunt <hi>Herby</hi> Medicines <U+017F>uch as Dr. <hi>Scarborough,</hi> pre<U+017F>cribe, no nor although they be <U+017F>harpened by <hi>Iacob Heydon,</hi> by plain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tillations: neither would he, I think for pitty, <U+017F>ting the <hi>poor pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieni</hi> with <hi>Eugenius Philalethes</hi> Martyrdome of rude and rank <hi>Minerals,</hi> and unle<U+017F>s they were made into a fine clean natural and temperate quality, which would work mightily, and de<U+017F>troy either of the<U+017F>e four great di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es, <hi>Lepro<U+017F>ie, Gout, Drop<U+017F>ie,</hi> and <hi>Falling <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s:</hi> but feed, Comfort, or at lea<U+017F>t not offend, and hurt his patient; they labour in vain that practi<U+017F>e otherwi<U+017F>e. The<U+017F>e are the <hi>medecines</hi> which I onely u<U+017F>e, and which a good and wi<U+017F>e <hi>Phy<U+017F>ician</hi> ought onely to <U+017F>eek and follow, and if he cannot find it, let him u<U+017F>e the <hi>cure them<U+017F>elves.</hi> But <U+017F>uch a thing as this; I <U+017F>ay, brought to this equality, and finene<U+017F>s of frame and temper, (were it at the fir<U+017F>t, <hi>wight, plant or mineral</hi>) was it which our <hi>father</hi> and <hi>founder Mo<U+017F>es,</hi> (the chief of the Ro<U+017F>ie Cro<U+017F>s) <U+017F>aid is like to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the <U+017F>trength of all <U+017F>trengths piercing and <U+017F>ubduing all things.</p>
               <p>This was it that warranted his <hi>Sons</hi> the <hi>ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> to avow <U+017F>o <U+017F>toutly, that Art was long and Life <U+017F>hort, and all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es <hi>cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> when <hi>Hippocrates the Father of Common Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the infirmity and endle<U+017F>s matter of his weak body, and envious mind tinctured with Covetou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, and fickle Medicines, to cry to <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> but they would not hear <U+017F>uch hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fellows, nor give him <hi>long Life,</hi> he <U+017F>aid therefore that <hi>Art</hi> was <hi>long,</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> was <hi><U+017F>hort.</hi> And whereas he and his off-<U+017F>pring were fain to leave many di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>ed helple<U+017F>s, to the great <U+017F>hame of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Plague</hi> of <hi>mankind,</hi> is it any marvel when as they prick at them (as I <U+017F>aid) with a Butchers-prick? Nay, <U+017F>ee what they do by their practice, they be <U+017F>o far from all help and comfort to the Patient in greate<U+017F>t danger, that they increa<U+017F>e his wi<U+017F>er eys many waies, except the great ea<U+017F>er of all pain, and their common Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine <hi>Death,</hi> be quickly admini<U+017F>tred: Fir<U+017F>t, they make the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <U+017F>uffer the puni<U+017F>hment due to their own <U+017F>lothful Idlene<U+017F>s, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening his <U+017F>tomach with that labour of loo<U+017F>nening and <U+017F>undering the Fine from the Gro<U+017F>s, which they <U+017F>hould before have taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Gla<U+017F><U+017F>es:</hi> and then by doing the<U+017F>e often, they clean tire his feeble Nature (as it would tire a hor<U+017F>e) when as by <U+017F>tripping the foul and gro<U+017F>s <U+017F>tuff, that dulls the working, and reteining the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118922:34"/>
Vertue in a narrow <U+017F>trong body, they might doe as much at one time as they doe now in twenty, and becau<U+017F>e their Medicines applyed are of <U+017F>maller power and weaker than the things that hurt us, they feed nouri<U+017F>h and <U+017F>trengthen the di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e and <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s, but for all this if <U+017F>ome of this company and <U+017F>ide of Leeches have been and are yet <U+017F>ometimes able to heal all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es in our body (though with much ado, as you have heard) <U+017F>ave the four named remedile<U+017F>s, yea and tho<U+017F>e a<U+017F>well in their <U+017F>pring as before their ripene<U+017F>s, as they them<U+017F>elves report. Is there any <hi>Proportion</hi> in <hi>Geometry?</hi> Let the <hi>College of Phy<U+017F>icians</hi> lay mea<U+017F>ures why the <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian mighty Medicines</hi> which I call <hi>Cure-the-greats,</hi> pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ing the<U+017F>e in power, <hi>as much as the ripene<U+017F>s of a di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e is above the Spring,</hi> <U+017F>hall not overmatch the ripe as well as the green Di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<U+017F>es: Wherefore there be no doubts left, but this plainly true, That albeit the <hi>Grecians</hi> is weak and halting in this kind of heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet is the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> or (as now they terme it) the <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ians</hi> and Mineral skill <U+017F>ufficient to cure all di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es: Then I have paid the whole <U+017F>umme of my promi<U+017F>e, touching the <U+017F>econd means and helps to <hi>Bli<U+017F>s</hi> and <hi>Happine<U+017F>s,</hi> which is Life and Health.</p>
               <p>Before I clo<U+017F>e, I think it very meet, while the time and place very fitly <U+017F>erveth, to do a good deed, and this <U+017F>hall be my intent to admoni<U+017F>h and exhort the Grecian Leaches, and their <hi>Scholars</hi> the <hi>English, Spanish, and French Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> whom if they follow <hi>Hippocrates, Plato, Pythagoras,</hi> and his fellows, I love for their Learning, and pitty for their mi<U+017F>leading others (although it be grievous, I know to old Scholars, wone in a kind of Learning, to unlearne all as it were and begin again, for their own Credit and Virtue, yea and profit <U+017F>ake al<U+017F>o, if they e<U+017F>teem that be<U+017F>t, to leave tho<U+017F>e <hi>Gilded Pills and Sugred Baits,</hi> and all other <hi>crafty <U+017F>nares,</hi> wherewith the World hath been <U+017F>o long caught and <U+017F>o long tormented, and to <U+017F>eek this onely heavenly Society; as (to you that are learned) ea<U+017F>ily may temper your <U+017F>elves, and be acquainted with the ready, true, plain and certain way of Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>es. I think in former time they were not greatly to be blamed and accu<U+017F>ed but of dulne<U+017F>s and weakne<U+017F>s of under<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in not applying and <U+017F>eeing this perfection, and <U+017F>upplying of all their wants; but <U+017F>ince they have been <U+017F>o often warned not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118922:34"/>
with words only, but with examples of Learned men, <hi>Matheo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Fernelius, Severinus Danus, Philo Iudaeus, Diodorus Siculus,</hi> and other <U+017F>uch like which have and doe revolt, and flie away from them daily, yea and by the certain deeds of <hi>Paracel<U+017F>e,</hi> it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qity to <U+017F>it <U+017F>till: Well, few words will <U+017F>erve to wi<U+017F>e and vertuous <hi>Phy<U+017F>icians,</hi> <U+017F>uch as are of them<U+017F>elves forward.</p>
               <p>But there is another, and I am afraid, the greater <U+017F>ort, le<U+017F>s ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>t, more Idle and Covetous, full of windy Pride and Words, but empty of all good learning, and they are no friends to <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians,</hi> nor they to them, and the<U+017F>e no gentle warning of any, no though a <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian</hi> him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>hould come and bring <hi>Truth</hi> her <U+017F>elf along with him in per<U+017F>on, would prevail: who care not it <U+017F>eems if half mankind <U+017F>hould peri<U+017F>h for want of help and <U+017F>uccour, rather then lo<U+017F>e their gains; And which not onely <U+017F>peak foully but write fooli<U+017F>hly, again<U+017F>t this overflouri<U+017F>hing vertue, but al<U+017F>o like the giddy people of my time, where they catch the State, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>h the men that hold and po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s it; whereas if it were a good Commonwealth (quoth <hi>Ari<U+017F>totle</hi>) the matter would be <U+017F>o far from <hi>Bani<U+017F>hment</hi> or <hi>Impri<U+017F>onment,</hi> as they would e<U+017F>teem <U+017F>uch a <hi>man</hi> as well as the <hi>Laws</hi> (for he is him<U+017F>elf a Law) exempt from all obedience, and judge him worthy to be followed and obeyed as a <hi>perpetual King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This untowardne<U+017F>s and crookedne<U+017F>s in men <hi>cau<U+017F>od all our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healing Ance<U+017F>tors the Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians</hi> from time to time, never to abide their Sentence, but to the great hurt and lo<U+017F>s of mankind go into willing <hi>Bani<U+017F>hment,</hi> you have e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>hed a kind of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> among you (to pur<U+017F>ue the <U+017F>ame, like a little —) wherein you rule alone over the weak and <U+017F>orry <U+017F>ubjects of mens Bodies, then their health and <U+017F>afety you ought to <U+017F>eek onely, be<U+017F>ides e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to maintain a contented e<U+017F>tate al<U+017F>o, which <hi>Plato</hi> allowes his <hi>Governours,</hi> and not profit only (that were Tyranny) both for humanity and Religion <U+017F>ake, for to omit Religion, which they do lightly omit, if a Phy<U+017F>itian begin once to make a prey of men, he is not onely no man, but a mo<U+017F>t Fierce and cruell Bea<U+017F>t, not fit to be compared and matched and matched any where, if you <U+017F>eek all over the world as with the <hi>mi<U+017F>hapen mon<U+017F>ter</hi> of <hi>India,</hi> which <hi>Ari<U+017F>totle</hi> de<U+017F>cribes, and calls <hi>Martichora,</hi> which being by nature or cu<U+017F>tome, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118922:35"/>
very greedy upon mans fle<U+017F>h, is with manifold and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful helpes furni<U+017F>hed, and armed unto it.</p>
               <p>Fir<U+017F>t with a face like a <hi>Man,</hi> a <hi>voice</hi> like a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> two fit things to allure and call him in) and then if he flye, with the <U+017F>wiftne<U+017F>s of an Hart to overtake him, he darts like a <hi>Porcupine,</hi> to wound him afar of; and with the tail of a <hi>Scorpion,</hi> as it were a poy<U+017F>oned <hi><U+017F>haft,</hi> near hand to <U+017F>ting him: furthermore, le<U+017F>t all this might not <U+017F>erve, by occa<U+017F>ion of <hi>Armour,</hi> he hath feet like a <hi>Lion,</hi> fiercely and cruelly to tear him, and three rowes of teeth, on each Chap for the in devouring. Apply you and the Apothecarries, the re<U+017F>t your <U+017F>elves, in <U+017F>ecret for my part, as I am not a Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian, <U+017F>o I am as well as they, <U+017F>orry to <U+017F>ee evil done. And I am loath to <U+017F>peak evil of it, and <U+017F>ure were not the great grief and envy I do bear; and alwayes did, to <U+017F>ee de<U+017F>ert trodden down by <U+017F>uch unworthine<U+017F>s, and <U+017F>ome little hopes I have to hear of the amendment, and <U+017F>o of the return of the truth, and good men out of bani<U+017F>hment and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>onment, you <U+017F>hould have found me in <hi>We<U+017F>tmin<U+017F>ter-Hall:</hi> as I have been an <hi>Atturny</hi> in Terme time, and mean to continue my practi<U+017F>e there <U+017F>o long as I live, except in the Vacation, which I intend to <U+017F>pend <hi>in Chimical</hi> and <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucian Medicines</hi> for the good of <hi>hone<U+017F>t plain meaning men</hi> and my <U+017F>elf <hi>Eugenius Theodidactus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <U+017F>ome may ask what I mean by <hi>R. C.</hi> the <hi>Ceremonie</hi> is an <hi>Ebony Cro<U+017F>s,</hi> flouri<U+017F>hed and deckt with Ro<U+017F>es of Gold, the <hi>Cro<U+017F>s typi<U+017F>ies Chri<U+017F>ts</hi> <U+017F>ufferings upon the <hi>Cro<U+017F>s</hi> for our <U+017F>ins, the <hi>Ro<U+017F>es of Gold</hi> <U+017F>hew the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> of his <hi>Re<U+017F>urrection</hi> from death to life. And this is carried to <hi>Me<U+017F>que, Ca<U+017F>cle, Apamia, Chaulatean Viri<U+017F><U+017F>a Caunuch, Mount Calvery, Haran</hi> and <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> where they meet when they plea<U+017F>e and make Re<U+017F>olution of all their <hi>Actions,</hi> and then di<U+017F>per<U+017F>e them<U+017F>elves abroad, taking their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure alwayes in one of the<U+017F>e <hi>places,</hi> where they re<U+017F>olve al<U+017F>o all que<U+017F>tions <hi>of what<U+017F>oever hath been done, is done, or <U+017F>hall be done in the world, from the beginning to the end thereof.</hi> And the<U+017F>e are the men are called <hi>Ro<U+017F>ie Crucians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118922:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

